<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<?xml-model href="OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<!--Desire exists within dialogue, so we should add this to the schema-->

<story>
    <title>Iason et Medea. JASON AND MEDEA </title>
    <p>Over the storm-tossed waves, the Argonauts<lb/> had sailed in Argo, their long ship to where<lb/>
        <name>King Phineus</name>, needy in his old age, reigned—<lb/> deprived of sight and feeble.
        When the sons<lb/> of Boreas had landed on the shore,<lb/> and seen the Harpies snatching
        from the king<lb/> his nourishment, befouling it with beaks<lb/> obscene, they drove those
        human-vultures thence.<lb/></p>


    <p>And having suffered hardships and great toils,<lb/> after the day they rescued the sad
        king<lb/> from the vile Harpies, those twin valiant youths,<lb/>
        <name>Zetes</name> and <name>Calais</name> came with their chief,<lb/> the mighty <character
            gender="male" descrip="protector">Jason</character>, where the Phasis flows.<lb/></p>


    <p>From the green margin of that river, all<lb/> the crew of Argonauts, by <character
            gender="male" descrip="protector">Jason</character> led,<lb/> went to the king
            <name>Aeetes</name> and required<lb/> the Golden Fleece, that he received from
            <name>Phryxus</name>.<lb/> When they had bargained with him, full of wiles<lb/> he
        offered to restore the Golden Fleece<lb/> only to those who might to him return,<lb/>
        victorious from hard labors of great risk.<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="virginal">Medea</character>, the king's daughter, near
        his throne,<lb/> saw <character gender="male" descrip="protector">Jason</character>, leader
        of the Argonauts,<lb/> as he was pressing to secure a prize—<lb/> and <desire perp="Medea"
            object="Jason">loved at sight with a consuming flame</desire>.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>Although she struggled to suppress her love,<lb/> unable to restrain herself, she said,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“In vain I've striven to subdue my heart:<lb/> some god
            it must be, which I cannot tell,<lb/> is working to destroy my hapless life;<lb/> or
            else it is the burning flame of love<lb/> that in me rages. If it is not love,<lb/> why
            do the mandates of my father seem<lb/> too harsh? They surely are too harsh. Why do<lb/>
            I fear that he may perish whom I have<lb/> seen only once? What is the secret cause<lb/>
            that I am agitated by such fears?—<lb/> It is no other than the god of
        Love.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Thrust from your virgin breast such burning flames<lb/>
            <desire object="Jason" perp="Medea">but some deluding power is holding me<lb/> helpless
                against my will. Desire persuades<lb/> me one way, but my reason still
                persuades<lb/> another way. I see a better course<lb/> and I approve, but follow its
                defeat.</desire></dia> —<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“O royal maiden, why are you consumed<lb/> with love for
            this strange man, and why are you<lb/> so willing to be carried by the nuptial ties<lb/>
            so far from your own country, where, indeed,<lb/> are many brave men worthy of your
            love?</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>“Whether for life or death his numbered hours<lb/> are in the mercy of the living Gods,<lb/>
        and that he may not suffer risk of death,<lb/> too well foreseen, now let my prayers
        prevail—<lb/> righteously uttered of a generous heart<lb/> without the stress of love. What
        wicked thing<lb/> has <character gender="male">Jason</character> done? His handsome person,
        youth,<lb/> and noble ways, would move a heart of stone.<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Have I a heart of flint, or was I born<lb/> a tigress
            to deny him timely aid?—<lb/> Unless I interpose, he will be slain<lb/> by the hot
            breath of brazen-footed bulls,<lb/> or will be slaughtered by the warriors, sprung<lb/>
            miraculous from earth, or will be given<lb/> to satisfy the ravenous appetite<lb/> of a
            huge dragon.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Let my gloating eyes<lb/> be satiate with his dying
            agonies!<lb/> Let me incite the fury of these bulls!<lb/> Stir to their blood-lust
            mad-born sons of Earth!<lb/> Rouse up the never-sleeping dragon's rage!—<lb/> “Avert it
            Gods!</dia>—<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“But why should I cry out<lb/> upon the Gods to save him
            from such wrong,<lb/> when, by my actions and my power, myself<lb/> may shield him from
            all evils?</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Such a course<lb/> would wreck the kingdom of my
            father—and by me<lb/> the wily stranger would escape from him;<lb/> and spreading to the
            wind his ready sails<lb/> he would forget and leave me to my fate.—<lb/> Oh, if he
            should forget my sacrifice,<lb/> and so prefer those who neglected him,<lb/> let him
            then perish in his treachery.</dia>—<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“But these are idle thoughts: his countenance,<lb/>
            reveals innate nobility and grace,<lb/> that should dispel all fear of treachery,<lb/>
            and guarantee his ever-faithful heart.<lb/> The Gods will witness our united souls,<lb/>
            and he shall pledge his faith. Secure of it<lb/> my fear will be removed. Be ready,
            then—<lb/> and make a virtue of necessity:<lb/> your <character gender="male"
                descrip="matronly">Jason</character> owes himself to you; and he<lb/> must join you
            in true wedlock. Then you shall<lb/> be celebrated through the land of Greece,<lb/> by
            throngs of women, for the man you saved.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Shall I then sail away, and so forsake<lb/> my sister,
            brother, father, Gods, and land<lb/> that gave me birth? My father is indeed<lb/> a
            stern man, and my native land is all<lb/> too barbarous; my brother is a child,—<lb/> my
            sister's goodwill is good help for me;<lb/> and heaven's supreme god is within my
            breast.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“I shall not so be leaving valued hopes,<lb/> but will
            be going surely to great things.<lb/> And I should gain applause from all the
            world,<lb/> as having saved the threatened Argonauts,<lb/> most noble of the Greeks; and
            in their land,<lb/> which certainly is better than my own,<lb/> become the bride of
                <character gender="male" descrip="matronly">Jason</character>, for whose love<lb/> I
            should not hesitate to give the world—<lb/> and in whose love the living Gods
            rejoice<lb/> so greatly; for his sake they would bestow<lb/> their favors on my head,
            and make the stars<lb/> my habitation.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Should I hesitate<lb/> because the wreck-strewn
            mountains bar the way,<lb/> and clash together in the Euxine waves;<lb/> or fear
            Charybdis, fatal to large ships,<lb/> that sucks the deep sea in its whirling gulf<lb/>
            and spouts far upward, with alternate force,<lb/> or Scylla, circled with infuriate
            hounds<lb/> howling in rage from deep Sicilian waves?</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Safe in the shielding arms of him I love,<lb/> on
                <character gender="male">Jason</character>'s bosom leaning, I shall be<lb/> borne
            safely over wide and hostile seas;<lb/> and <desire object="Jason" perp="Medea">in his
                dear embrace forget my fears—<lb/> or if for anything I suffer dread,<lb/> it will
                be only for the one I love.</desire></dia>—<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Medea" gender="female">“Alas, <character gender="female" descrip="matronly"
                >Medea</character>, this vain argument<lb/> has only furnished plausible excuse<lb/>
            for criminal desires, and desecrates<lb/> the marriage rite. It is a wicked thing<lb/>
            to think upon. Before it is too late<lb/> forget your passion and deny this
            guilt.”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>And after she had said these words, her eyes<lb/> were opened to <character gender="female"
            descrip="virginal">the prize of modesty,<lb/> chaste virtue, and a pure
            affection:</character><lb/> and <name>Cupid</name>, vanquished, turned away and
        fled.<lb/></p>


    <p>Then, to an ancient altar of the goddess named<lb/>
        <name>Hecate</name>, <name>Perse</name>'s daughter took her way<lb/> in the deep shadows of
        a forest. She<lb/> was strong of purpose now, and all the flames<lb/> of vanquished passion
        had died down; but when<lb/> she saw the son of Aeson, <desire object="Jason" perp="Medea"
            >dying flames<lb/> leaped up again. Her cheeks grew red, then all<lb/> her face went
            pale again; as a small spark<lb/> when hid beneath the ashes, if fed by<lb/> a breath of
            wind grows and regains its strength,<lb/> as it is fanned to life; so now her love<lb/>
            that had been smoldering, and which you would<lb/> have thought was almost dead, when
            she had see<lb/> again his manly youth, blazed up once more.</desire><lb/></p>


    <p>For on that day his graceful person seemed<lb/> as glorious as a God;—and as she gazed,<lb/>
        and fixed her eyes upon his countenance,<lb/> her frenzy so prevailed, she was
        convinced<lb/> that he was not a mortal. And her eyes<lb/> were fascinated; and she could
        not turn<lb/> away from him. But when he spoke to her,<lb/> and promised marriage, grasping
        her right hand:<lb/> she answered, as her eyes suffused with tears;<lb/>
        <dia speaker="Medea" gender="female" invo="Jason">“I see what I will do, and ignorance<lb/>
            of truth will not be my undoing now,<lb/> but love itself. By my assistance you<lb/>
            shall be preserved; but when preserved fulfill<lb/> your promise.”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>He swore that she could trust in him.<lb/> Then by the goddess of the triple form,<lb/>
        <name>Diana</name>, <name>Trivia</name>, or <name>Luna</name> called,<lb/> and by her sacred
        groves and fanes, he vowed,<lb/> and by the hallowed Sun that sees all things,<lb/> and by
        his own adventures, and his life,—<lb/> on these the youthful <character gender="male"
            descrip="matronly">Jason</character> took his oath.—<lb/> With this she was assured and
        quickly gave<lb/> to him the magic herbs: he learnt their use<lb/> and full of joy withdrew
        into his house.<lb/></p>


    <p>Now when the dawn had dimmed the glittering stars,<lb/> the people hastened to the sacred
        field<lb/> of Mars, and on the hills expectant stood.—<lb/> Arrayed in purple, and in
        majesty<lb/> distinguished by his ivory sceptre, sat<lb/> the king, surrounded by a
        multitude.<lb/> Below them on the visioned Field of Mars,<lb/> huge brazen-footed bulls were
        breathing forth<lb/> from adamantine nostrils living flames,<lb/> blasting the verdant
        herbage in their path!<lb/></p>


    <p>As forges glowing with hot flames resound,<lb/> or as much quick-lime, <character
            gender="male" descrip="rage">burnt in earthen kilns,<lb/> crackles and hisses as if mad
            with rage,<lb/> sprinkled with water, liberating heat;</character><lb/> so their hot
        throats and triple-heated sides,<lb/> resounding told of pent-up fires within.<lb/></p>


    <p>The son of <name>Aeson</name> went to meet them. As<lb/> he came to meet them the fierce
        animals<lb/> turned on him faces terrible, and sharp<lb/> horns tipped with iron, and they
        pawed<lb/> the dusty earth with cloven feet, and filled<lb/> the place with fiery
        bellowings. The Minyans<lb/> were stark with fear; he went up to the bulls<lb/> not feeling
        their hot breath at all, so great<lb/> the power of his charmed drugs; and while he<lb/> was
        stroking their down-hanging dewlaps with<lb/> a fearless hand, he placed the yoke down
        on<lb/> their necks and made them draw the heavy plow,<lb/> and cut through fields that
        never felt the steel<lb/> before. The Colchians were amazed and silent;<lb/> but the loud
        shouting of the Minyans<lb/> increased their hero's courage. Taking then<lb/> the serpent's
        teeth out of a brazen helmet<lb/> he sowed them broadcast in the new-plowed field.<lb/></p>


    <p>The moist earth softened these seeds that were steeped<lb/> in virulent poison and the teeth
        swelled up<lb/> and took new forms. And just as in its mother<lb/> an infant gradually
        assumes the form<lb/> of man, and is perfected through all parts<lb/> within, and does not
        come forth to the light<lb/> till fully formed; so, when the forms of men<lb/> had been
        completed in the womb of earth<lb/> made pregnant, they rose up from it,<lb/> and what is
        yet more wonderful, each one<lb/> clashed weapons that had been brought forth with
        him.<lb/></p>


    <p>When his companions saw the warriors turn<lb/> as if with one accord, to hurl their
        spears,<lb/> sharp-pointed, at the head of <character gender="male" descrip="protected"
            >Jason</character>, fear<lb/> unnerved the boldest and their courage failed.<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="protector">So, too, the maid whose sorcery had
            saved<lb/> him from much danger, when she saw the youth<lb/> encompassed by those raging
            enemies,<lb/> and he alone against so many—struck<lb/> with sudden panic, she turned
            ashen white,<lb/> her bloodless cheeks were blanched; and chilled with fear<lb/> she
            wilted to the ground; and lest the herbs,<lb/> so lately given him, might fail his
            need<lb/> she added incantations and invoked<lb/> mysterious arts. While she protected
            him</character><lb/></p>


    <p>He seized upon a heavy stone, and hurled<lb/> it in the midst of his new enemies—<lb/>
        distracted by this cast, and murderous,<lb/> they turned from him, and clashing their new
        arms,<lb/> those earth-born brothers fought among themselves<lb/> till all were slaughtered
        in blood-thirsty strife.<lb/></p>


    <p>Gladly the Greeks acclaimed him conqueror,<lb/> and pressed around him for the first
        embrace.<lb/> Then, too, <character gender="female" descrip="protector">Medea</character>,
        barbarous Colchian maid,<lb/> although <desire object="Jason" perp="Medea">her modesty
            restrained her heart,<lb/> eagerly longed to fold him in her arms,<lb/> but careful of
            her good name, held aloof,—<lb/> rejoicing in deep, silent love; and she<lb/>
            acknowledged to the Gods her mighty gift<lb/> of incantations.</desire><lb/></p>


    <p>But the dragon, still<lb/> alert,—magnificent and terrible<lb/> with gorgeous crest and
        triple tongue, and fangs<lb/> barbed as a javelin, guards the Golden Fleece:<lb/> and
            <character gender="male" descrip="protected">Jason</character> can obtain that quest
        only<lb/> if slumber may seal up the monster's eyes.—<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="male" descrip="protected">Jason</character>, successful, sprinkled on his
        crest<lb/> Lethean juices of a magic herb,<lb/> and then recited thrice the words which
        bring<lb/> deep slumber, potent words which would becalm<lb/> the storm-tossed ocean, and
        would stop the flow<lb/> of the most rapid rivers of our earth:<lb/> and slowly slumber
        sealed the dragon's eyes.<lb/></p>


    <p>While that great monster slept, the hero took<lb/> the Golden Fleece; and proudly sailed
        away<lb/> bearing his treasure and the willing maid,<lb/> (whose aid had saved him) to his
        native port<lb/> Iolcus—victorious with the Argonauts.<lb/></p>
</story>
