<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <header>Pallas et Arachne.</header>
    <title>ARACHNE AND MINERVA</title>

    <p>All this <character gender="female" descrip="cocky">Minerva heard; and she approved<lb/>
            their songs and their resentment; but her heart</character><lb/> was brooding thus, <dia
            speaker="minerva" gender="female">“It is an easy thing<lb/> to praise another, I should
            do as they:<lb/> no creature of the earth should ever slight<lb/> the majesty that
            dwells in me,—without<lb/> just retribution.”</dia>—So her thought was turned<lb/> upon
        the fortune of <character gender="female" descrip="cocky">Arachne — proud,<lb/> who would
            not ever yield to her the praise<lb/> won by the art of deftly weaving wool,<lb/> a girl
            who had not fame for place of birth,<lb/> nor fame for birth, but only fame for
            skill!</character><lb/></p>


    <p>For it was well known that her father dwelt<lb/> in <place>Colophon</place>; where, at his
        humble trade,<lb/> he dyed in Phocean purples, fleecy wool.<lb/> Her mother, also of the
        lower class,<lb/> had died. <character gender="female">Arachne</character> in a mountain
        town<lb/> by skill had grown so famous in the Land<lb/> of <place>Lydia</place>, that
        unnumbered curious nymphs<lb/> eager to witness her dexterity,<lb/> deserted the lush
        vineyards of <place>Timolus</place>;<lb/> or even left the cool and flowing streams<lb/> of
        bright <place>Pactolus</place>, to admire the cloth,<lb/> or to observe her deftly spinning
        wool.<lb/></p>


    <p>So graceful was her motion then,—if she<lb/> was twisting the coarse wool in little
        balls,<lb/> or if she teased it with her finger-tips,<lb/> or if she softened the fine
        fleece, drawn forth<lb/> in misty films, or if she twirled the smooth<lb/> round spindle
        with her energetic thumb,<lb/> or if with needle she embroidered cloth;—<lb/></p>


    <p>in all her motions one might well perceive<lb/> how much <character gender="female"
            descrip="cocky">Minerva had instructed her:<lb/> but this she ever would deny,
            displeased<lb/> to share her fame;</character> and said, <dia speaker="arachne"
            gender="female">“Let her contend<lb/> in art with me; and if her skill prevails,<lb/> I
            then will forfeit all!”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female">Minerva</character> heard,<lb/> and came to her, disguised with
        long grey hair,<lb/> and with a staff to steady her weak limbs.<lb/> She seemed a feeble
        woman, very old,<lb/> and quavered as she said, <dia speaker="minerva" gender="female" invo="arachne">“Old
            age is not<lb/> the cause of every ill; experience comes<lb/> with lengthened years;
            and, therefore, you should not<lb/> despise my words. It is no harm in you<lb/> to long
            for praise of mortals, when<lb/> your nimble hands are spinning the soft wool,—<lb/> but
            you should not deny Minerva's art—<lb/> and you should pray that she may pardon
            you,<lb/> for she will grant you pardon if you ask.”</dia><lb/>
    </p>

    <p><character gender="female" descrip="rage">Arachne, scowling with an evil face.<lb/> Looked at
            the goddess, as she dropped her thread.<lb/> She hardly could restrain her threatening
            hand,<lb/> and, trembling in her anger,</character>she replied<lb/> to you, disguised
        Minerva:<lb/>
    </p>

    <p><dia gender="female" speaker="arachne" invo="minerva">“Silly fool,—<lb/> worn out and witless in your
            palsied age,<lb/> a great age is your great misfortune!— Let<lb/> your daughter and your
            son's wife—if the Gods<lb/> have blessed you—let them profit by your words;<lb/> within
            myself, my knowledge is contained<lb/> sufficient; you need not believe that your<lb/>
            advice does any good; for I am quite<lb/> unchanged in my opinion. Get you gone,—<lb/>
            advise your goddess to come here herself,<lb/> and not avoid the
        contest!”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>Instantly,<lb/> the goddess said, <dia speaker="minerva" gender="female" invo="arachne"> “Minerva comes to
            you!”</dia><lb/> And with those brief words, put aside the shape<lb/> of the old woman,
        and revealed herself,<lb/> Minerva, goddess.<lb/></p>


    <p>All the other Nymphs<lb/> and matrons of <place>Mygdonia</place> worshiped her;<lb/> but not
            <character gender="female">Arachne</character>, who defiant stood;—<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="joy">although at first she flushed up—then went pale—<lb/> then blushed
            again, reluctant.</character>—So, at first,<lb/> the sky suffuses, as
            <name>Aurora</name> moves,<lb/> and, quickly when the glorious sun comes up,<lb/> pales
        into white.<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="cocky">She even rushed upon<lb/> her own destruction, for
            she would not give<lb/> from her desire to gain the victory.</character><lb/> Nor did
        the daughter of almighty <name>Jove</name><lb/> decline: disdaining to delay with
        words,<lb/> she hesitated not.<lb/></p>


    <p>And both, at once,<lb/> selected their positions, stretched their webs<lb/> with finest warp,
        and separated warp with sley.<lb/> The woof was next inserted in the web<lb/> by means of
        the sharp shuttles, which<lb/> their nimble fingers pushed along, so drawn<lb/> within the
        warp, and so the teeth notched in<lb/> the moving sley might strike them.—Both, in
        haste,<lb/> girded their garments to their breasts and moved<lb/> their skilful arms,
        beguiling their fatigue<lb/> in eager action.<lb/></p>


    <p>Myriad tints appeared<lb/> besides the Tyrian purple—royal dye,<lb/> extracted in brass
        vessels.—As the bow,<lb/> that spans new glory in the curving sky,<lb/> its glittering rays
        reflected in the rain,<lb/> spreads out a multitude of blended tints,<lb/> in scintillating
        beauty to the sight<lb/> of all who gaze upon it; — so the threads,<lb/> inwoven, mingled in
        a thousand tints,<lb/> harmonious and contrasting; shot with gold:<lb/> and there, depicted
        in those shining webs,<lb/> were shown the histories of ancient days:—<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female">Minerva</character> worked the Athenian Hill of Mars,<lb/> where
        ancient Cecrops built his citadel,<lb/> and showed the old contention for the name<lb/> it
        should be given.—Twelve celestial Gods<lb/> surrounded <name>Jupiter</name>, on lofty
        thrones;<lb/> and all their features were so nicely drawn,<lb/> that each could be
            distinguished.—<name>Jupiter</name><lb/> appeared as monarch of those judging
        Gods.<lb/></p>


    <p>There <name>Neptune</name>, guardian of the sea, was shown<lb/> contending with <character
            gender="female">Minerva</character>. As he struck<lb/> the Rock with his long trident, a
        wild horse<lb/> sprang forth which he bequeathed to man. He claimed<lb/> his right to name
        the city for that gift.<lb/></p>


    <p>And then she wove a portrait of herself,<lb/> bearing a shield, and in her hand a lance,<lb/>
        sharp-pointed, and a helmet on her head—<lb/> her breast well-guarded by her
            <name>Aegis</name>: there<lb/> she struck her spear into the fertile earth,<lb/> from
        which a branch of olive seemed to sprout,<lb/> pale with new clustered fruits.—And those
        twelve Gods,<lb/> appeared to judge, that olive as a gift<lb/> surpassed the horse which
            <name>Neptune</name> gave to man.<lb/></p>


    <p>And, so <character gender="female">Arachne</character>, rival of her fame,<lb/> might learn
        the folly of her mad attempt,<lb/> from the great deeds of ancient histories,<lb/> and what
        award presumption must expect,<lb/>
        <character gender="female">Minerva</character> wove four corners with life scenes<lb/> of
        contest, brightly colored, but of size<lb/> diminutive.<lb/></p>



    <p>In one of these was shown<lb/> the snow-clad mountains, <name>Rhodope</name>,<lb/> and
            <name>Haemus</name>, <transform type="physical">which for punishment were changed<lb/>
            from human beings to those rigid forms</transform>,<lb/> when they aspired to rival the
        high Gods.<lb/> And in another corner she described<lb/> that <name>Pygmy</name>, whom the
        angry <name>Juno</name> changed<lb/> from <transform type="physical" gender="female"
            >queen-ship to a crane</transform>; because she thought<lb/> herself an equal of the
        living Gods,<lb/> she was commanded to wage cruel wars<lb/> upon her former subjects. In the
        third,<lb/> she wove the story of <name>Antigone</name>,<lb/> who dared compare herself to
            <name>Juno</name>, queen<lb/> of <name>Jupiter</name>, and showed her as she was<lb/>
        <transform type="physical" gender="female">transformed into a silly chattering
            stork</transform>,<lb/> that praised her beauty, with her ugly beak.—<lb/> Despite the
        powers of <name>Ilion</name> and her sire<lb/>
        <name>Laomedon</name>, her shoulders fledged white wings.<lb/> And so, the third part
        finished, there was left<lb/> one corner, where <character gender="female"
            >Minerva</character> deftly worked<lb/> the story of the father,
        <name>Cinyras</name>;—<lb/> as he was weeping on the temple steps,<lb/> which once had been
        his daughter's living limbs.<lb/> And she adorned the border with designs<lb/> of peaceful
        olive—her devoted tree—<lb/> which having shown, she made an end of work.<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female">Arachne</character>, of Maeonia, wove, at first<lb/> the story of
            <name>Europa</name>, as the bull<lb/> deceived her, and so perfect was her art,<lb/> it
        seemed a real bull in real waves.<lb/>
        <name>Europa</name> seemed to look back towards the land<lb/> which she had left; and call
        in her alarm<lb/> to her companions—and as if she feared<lb/> the touch of dashing waters,
        to draw up<lb/> her timid feet, while she was sitting on<lb/> the bull's back.<lb/></p>


    <p>And she wove <name>Asteria</name> seized<lb/> by the assaulting eagle; and beneath the
        swan's<lb/> white wings showed <name>Leda</name> lying by the stream:<lb/></p>


    <p>and showed <name>Jove</name> dancing as a Satyr, when<lb/> he sought the beautiful
            <name>Antiope</name>,<lb/> to whom was given twins; and how he seemed<lb/>
        <name>Amphitryon</name> when he deceived <name>Alcmena</name>;<lb/> and how he courted
        lovely <name>Danae</name><lb/> luring her as a gleaming shower of gold;<lb/> and poor
            <name>Aegina</name>, hidden in his flame,<lb/> jove as a shepherd with
            <name>Mnemosyne</name>;<lb/> and beautiful <name>Proserpina</name>, involved<lb/> by
        him, apparent as a spotted snake.<lb/></p>


    <p>And in her web, <character gender="female">Arachne</character> wove the scenes<lb/> of
            <name>Neptune</name>:—who was shown first as a bull,<lb/> when he was deep in love with
        virgin <name>Arne</name><lb/> then as <name>Enipeus</name> when the giant twins,<lb/>
        <name>Aloidae</name>, were begot; and as the ram<lb/> that gambolled with
            <name>Bisaltis</name>; as a horse<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="matronly">loved by the fruitful <name>Ceres</name>,
            golden haired,<lb/> all-bounteous mother of the yellow grain</character>;<lb/> and as
        the bird that hovered round snake-haired<lb/>
        <name>Medusa</name>, mother of the winged horse;<lb/> and as the dolphin, sporting with the Nymph,<lb/>
        <name>Melantho</name>.—All of these were woven true<lb/> to life, in proper shades.<lb/></p>


    <p>And there she showed<lb/>
        <name>Apollo</name>, when disguised in various forms:<lb/> as when he seemed a rustic; and
        as when<lb/> he wore hawk-wings, and then the tawny skin<lb/> of a great lion; and once more
        when he<lb/> deluded <name>Isse</name>, as a shepherd lad.<lb/></p>


    <p>And there was <name>Bacchus</name>, when he was disguised<lb/> as a large cluster of
        fictitious grapes;<lb/> deluding by that wile the beautiful<lb/>
        <name>Erigone</name>;—and <name>Saturn</name>, as a steed,<lb/> begetter of the dual-natured
            <name>Chiron</name>.<lb/></p>


    <p>And then <character gender="female">Arachne</character>, to complete her work,<lb/> wove all
        around the web a patterned edge<lb/> of interlacing flowers and ivy leaves.<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="jealous">Minerva could not find a fleck or flaw—<lb/>
            even Envy can not censure perfect art—<lb/> enraged</character> because <character
            gender="female">Arachne</character> had such skill<lb/> she ripped the web, and ruined
        all the scenes<lb/> that showed those wicked actions of the Gods;<lb/> and with her boxwood
        shuttle in her hand,<lb/> struck the unhappy mortal on her head,—<lb/> struck sharply
        thrice, and even once again.<lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="rage">Arachne's spirit, deigning not to brook<lb/> such
            insult, brooded on it, till she tied<lb/> a cord around her neck, and hung
            herself.</character><lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="rage">Minerva, moved to pity at the sight,<lb/> sustained
            and saved her from that bitter death;<lb/> but, angry still, pronounced another
            doom:</character><lb/>
        <dia speaker="minerva" gender="female">“Although I grant you life, most wicked one,<lb/>
            your fate shall be to dangle on a cord,<lb/> and your posterity forever shall<lb/> take
            your example, that your punishment<lb/> may last forever!”</dia> Even as she spoke,<lb/>
        before withdrawing from her victim's sight,<lb/> she sprinkled her with juice—extract of
        herbs<lb/> of <name>Hecate</name>.<lb/></p>


    <p><transform gender="female" type="physical">At once all hair fell off,<lb/> her nose and ears remained not,
            and her head<lb/> shrunk rapidly in size, as well as all<lb/> her body, leaving her
            diminutive.—<lb/> Her slender fingers gathered to her sides<lb/> as long thin legs; and
            all her other parts<lb/> were fast absorbed in her abdomen—whence<lb/> she vented a fine
            thread;—and ever since,<lb/> Arachne as a spider, weaves her web.</transform><lb/></p>
</story>
