<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../ovid-schematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<story>
    <header>Caeneus.</header>
    <title>CAENEUS TRANSFORMED INTO A BIRD</title>

    <p>There was a truce<lb/> for many days after this opening fight<lb/> while both sides resting,
        laid aside their arms.<lb/> A watchful guard patroled the Phrygian walls;<lb/> the Grecian
        trenches had their watchful guard.<lb/> Then, on a festal day, <character gender="male"
            >Achilles</character> gave<lb/> the blood of a slain heifer to obtain<lb/> the favor of
            <character gender="female">Athena</character> for their cause.<lb/> The entrails burned
        upon the altar, while<lb/> the odor, grateful to the deities,<lb/> was mounting to the
        skies. When sacred rites<lb/> were done, a banquet for the heroes was<lb/> served on their
        tables. There the Grecian chiefs<lb/> reclined on couches; while they satisfied<lb/>
        themselves with roasted flesh, and banished cares:<lb/> and thirst with wine. Nor harp nor
        singing voice<lb/> nor long pipe made of boxwood pierced with holes,<lb/> delighted them.
        They talked of their own deeds<lb/> and valor, all that thrilling night: and even<lb/> the
        strength of enemies whom they had met<lb/> and overcome. What else could they admit<lb/> or
        think of, while the great <character gender="male">Achilles</character> spoke<lb/> or
        listened to them? But especially<lb/> the recent victory over <character gender="male"
            >Cygnus</character> held<lb/> them ardent. Wonderful it seemed to them<lb/> that such a
        youth could be composed of flesh<lb/> not penetrable by the sharpest spear;<lb/> of flesh
        which blunted even hardened steel,<lb/> and never could be wounded. All the Greeks,<lb/> and
        even <character gender="male">Achilles</character> wondered at the thought.<lb/></p>


    <p>Then <character gender="male">Nestor</character> said to them:<dia speaker="nestor"
            gender="male"> “During your time,<lb/>
            <character gender="male">Cygnus</character> has been the only man you knew<lb/> who
            could despise all weapons and whose flesh<lb/> could not be pierced by thrust of sword
            or spear.<lb/> But long ago I saw another man<lb/> able to bear unharmed a thousand strokes,<lb/>
            <character gender="male">Caeneus</character> of <place>Thessaly</place>, <character
                gender="male">Caeneus</character> who lived<lb/> upon <place>Mt. Othrys</place>. He
            was famed in war<lb/> yet, strange to say, by birth he was a woman!”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>Then all expressed the greatest wonderment,<lb/> and begged to hear the story of his life.<lb/>
        <character gender="male">Achilles</character> cried, <dia speaker="achilles" gender="male"
            invo="nestor">“O eloquent old man!<lb/> The wisdom of our age! All of us wish<lb/> to
            hear, who was this <character gender="male">Caeneus</character>? Why was he<lb/> changed
            to the other sex? in what campaigns,<lb/> and in what wars was he so known to you?<lb/>
            Who conquered him, if any ever did?”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>The aged man replied to them with care:<dia speaker="nestor" gender="male">—<lb/> “Although
            my great age is a harm to me,<lb/> and many actions of my early days<lb/> escape my
            memory; yet, most of them<lb/> are well remembered. Nothing of old days,<lb/> amid so
            many deeds of war and peace,<lb/> can be more firmly fixed upon my mind<lb/> than the
            strange story I shall tell of him.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="nestor" gender="male">“If long extent of years made anyone<lb/> a witness of
            most wonderful events<lb/> and many, truly I may say to you<lb/> that I have lived two
            hundred years; and now<lb/> have entered my third century.<lb/> The daughter of
                <name>Elatus</name>, <character gender="female">Caenis</character>, was<lb/>
            remarkable for charm—most beautiful<lb/> of all <place>Thessalian</place> maidens—many
            sighed<lb/> for her in vain through all the neighboring towns<lb/> and yours, <character
                gender="male">Achilles</character>, for that was her home.<lb/> But
                <name>Peleus</name> did not try to win her love,<lb/> for he was either married at
            that time<lb/> to your dear mother, or was pledged to her.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="nestor" gender="male"><character gender="female">“Caenis</character> never
            became the willing bride<lb/> of any suitor; but report declares,<lb/> while she was
            walking on a lonely shore,<lb/>
            <desire perp="neptune" object="caeneus">the god of ocean saw and ravished her.<lb/> And
                in the joy of that love</desire>
            <character gender="male">Neptune</character> said,<lb/>
            <dia speaker="neptune" gender="male" invo="caeneus">‘Request of me whatever you
                desire,<lb/> and nothing shall deny your dearest wish!’</dia>—<lb/> the story tells
            us that he made this pledge.<lb/> And <character gender="female">Caenis</character> said
            to <character gender="male">Neptune</character>, <dia speaker="caeneus" gender="female"
                >‘The great wrong,<lb/> which I have suffered from you justifies<lb/> the wonderful
                request that I must make;<lb/> I ask that I may never suffer such<lb/> an injury
                again. Grant I may be<lb/> no longer woman, and I'll ask no
        more.’</dia></dia><lb/></p>


    <p>while she was speaking to him, the last words<lb/> of her strange prayer were uttered in so
        deep,<lb/> in such a manly tone, it seemed indeed<lb/> they must be from a man.—That was a fact:<lb/>
        <character gender="male">Neptune</character> not only had allowed her prayer<lb/> but made
        the new man proof against all wounds<lb/> of spear or sword. Rejoicing in the gift<lb/> he
        went his way as <character gender="male">Caeneus</character> Atracides,<lb/> spent years in
        every manful exercise,<lb/> and roamed the plains of northern
        <place>Thessaly</place>.<lb/></p>
</story>
