<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <title>Ceres et Proserpina CALLIOPE SINGS OF CERES, PLUTO AND PROSERPINE</title>

    <p>First <character descrip="matronly" gender="female">Ceres broke with crooked plow the
            glebe;<lb/> first gave to earth its fruit and wholesome food;<lb/> first gave the
            laws;—all things of <name>Ceres</name> came;<lb/> of her I sing; and oh, that I could
            tell<lb/> her worth in verse; in verse her worth is due.</character><lb/></p>


    <p>Because he dared to covet heavenly thrones<lb/>
        <name>Typhoeus</name>, giant limbs are weighted down<lb/> beneath <place>Sicilia's
            Isle</place>—vast in extent—<lb/> how often thence he strains and strives to rise?<lb/>
        But his right hand <name>Pachynus</name> holds; his legs are pressed<lb/> by
            <place>Lilybaeus</place>, <name>Aetna</name> weights his head.<lb/>
        <character descrip="rage" gender="male">Beneath that ponderous mass <name>Typhoeus</name>
            lies,<lb/> flat on his back; and spues the sands on high;<lb/> and vomits flames from
            his ferocious mouth.<lb/> He often strives to push the earth away,<lb/> the cities and
            the mountains from his limbs—<lb/> by which the lands are shaken. Even the king,<lb/>
            that rules the silent shades is made to quake,<lb/> for fear the earth may open and the
            ground,<lb/> cleft in wide chasms, letting in the day,<lb/> may terrify the trembling
            ghosts.</character> Afraid<lb/> of this disaster, that dark despot left<lb/> his gloomy
        habitation; carried forth<lb/> by soot-black horses, in his gloomy car.<lb/></p>


    <p>He circumspectly viewed <place>Sicilia</place>'s vast<lb/> foundations.—Having well explored
        and proved<lb/> no part was shattered; having laid aside<lb/> his careful fears, he wandered
        in those parts.<lb/></p>


    <p>Him, <name>Venus</name>, <name>Erycina</name>, in her mount<lb/> thus witnessed, and embraced
        her winged son,<lb/> and said, <dia speaker="Venus" gender="female" invo="Cupid">‘O
                <name>Cupid</name>! thou who art my son—<lb/> my arms, my hand, my strength; take up
            those arms,<lb/> by which thou art victorious over all,<lb/> and aim thy keenest arrow
            at the heart<lb/> of that divinity whom fortune gave<lb/> the last award, what time the
            triple realm,<lb/> by lot was portioned out.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Venus" gender="female" invo="Cupid">‘The Gods of Heaven<lb/> are overcome by
            thee; and <name>Jupiter</name>,<lb/> and all the Deities that swim the deep,<lb/> and
            the great ruler of the Water-Gods:<lb/> why, then, should <name>Tartarus</name> escape
            our sway—<lb/> the third part of the universe at stake—<lb/> by which thy mother's
            empire and thy own<lb/> may be enlarged according to great need.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Venus" gender="female" invo="Cupid">‘How shameful is our present lot in
            Heaven,<lb/> the powers of love and I alike despised;<lb/> for, mark how
                <name>Pallas</name> has renounced my sway,<lb/> besides <name>Diana</name>, javelin-hurler—so<lb/>
            <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">will <name>Ceres</name>' daughter choose
                virginity,<lb/> if we permit,—that way her hopes incline.<lb/> Do thou this goddess
                Proserpine</character>, unite<lb/> in marriage to her uncle.
            </dia><name>Venus</name> spoke;—<lb/></p>


    <p><name>Cupid</name> then loosed his quiver, and of all<lb/> its many arrows, by his mother's
        aid,<lb/> selected one; the keenest of them all;<lb/> the least uncertain, surest from the
        string:<lb/> and having fixed his knee against the bow,<lb/> bent back the flexile horn.—The
        flying shaft<lb/> struck <name>Pluto</name> in the breast.<lb/></p>


    <p>There is a lake<lb/> of greatest depth, not far from <place>Henna</place>'s walls,<lb/> long
        since called <place>Pergus</place>; and the songs of swans,<lb/> that wake
            <place>Cayster</place>, rival not the notes<lb/> of swans melodious on its gliding
        waves:<lb/> a fringe of trees, encircling as a wreath<lb/> its compassed waters, with a
        leafy veil<lb/> denies the heat of noon; cool breezes blow<lb/> beneath the boughs; the
        humid ground is sprent<lb/> with purpling flowers, and spring eternal reigns.<lb/></p>


    <p>While <character gender="female" descrip="joy">Proserpine once dallied in that grove,<lb/>
            plucking white lilies and sweet violets,<lb/> and while she heaped her basket, while she
            filled<lb/> her bosom, in a pretty zeal to strive<lb/> beyond all others</character>;
            <desire object="Proserpine" perp="Pluto">she was seen, beloved,<lb/> and carried off by
            Pluto—such the haste<lb/> of sudden love.</desire>
        <lb/></p>

    <p>The goddess, in great fear,<lb/> called on her mother and on all her friends;<lb/> and, in
        her frenzy, as her robe was rent,<lb/> down from the upper edge, her gathered flowers<lb/>
        fell from her loosened tunic.—<character gender="female" descrip="virginal">This
            mishap,<lb/> so perfect was her childish innocence,<lb/> increased her virgin
            grief.</character>—<lb/></p>


    <p>The ravisher<lb/> urged on his chariot, and inspired his steeds;<lb/> called each by name,
        and on their necks and manes<lb/> shook the black-rusted reins. They hastened through<lb/>
        deep lakes, and through the pools of <place>Palici</place>,<lb/> which boiling upward from
        the ruptured earth<lb/> smell of strong sulphur. And they bore him thence<lb/> to where the
        sons of <name>Bacchus</name>, who had sailed<lb/> from twin-sea <place>Corinth</place>, long
        ago had built<lb/> a city's walls between unequal ports.<lb/></p>



    <p>Midway between the streams of <place>Cyane</place><lb/> and <place>Arethusa</place> lies a
        moon-like pool,<lb/> of silvered narrow horns. There stood the Nymph,<lb/> revered above all
        others in that land,<lb/> whose name was <name>Cyane</name>. From her that pond<lb/> was
        always called. And as she stood, concealed<lb/> in middle waves that circled her white
        thighs,<lb/> she recognized the God, and said; <dia speaker="Cyane" gender="female"
            invo="Pluto">‘O thou<lb/> shalt go no further, <name>Pluto</name>, thou shalt not<lb/>
            by force alone become the son-in-law<lb/> of <character descrip="matronly"
                gender="female">Ceres. It is better to beseech<lb/> a mother's aid than drag her
                child away!</character><lb/> And this sustains my word, if I may thus<lb/> compare
            great things with small, <name>Anapis</name> loved<lb/> me also; but he wooed and
            married me<lb/> by kind endearments; not by fear, as thou<lb/> hast terrified this
            girl.’</dia> So did she speak;<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="protector">and stretching out her arms on either
            side<lb/> opposed his way.</character><lb/></p>


    <p>The son of <name>Saturn</name> blazed<lb/>
        <character gender="male" descrip="rage">with uncontrolled rage; and urged his steeds,<lb/>
            and hurled his royal scepter in the pool.<lb/> Cast with a mighty arm it pierced the
            deeps.<lb/></character> The smitten earth made way to <place>Tartarus</place>;—<lb/> it
        opened a wide basin and received<lb/> the plunging chariot in the midst.—But now<lb/> the
        mournful <name>Cyane</name> began to grieve,<lb/> because from her against her
        fountain-rights<lb/> the goddess had been torn. <transform type="physical" gender="female"
            >The deepening wound<lb/> still rankled in her breast, and she dissolved<lb/> in many
            tears, and wasted in those waves<lb/> which lately were submissive to her
            rule.</transform><lb/></p>


    <p><transform type="physical" gender="female">So you could see her members waste away:<lb/> her
            hones begin to bend; her nails get soft;<lb/> her azure hair, her fingers, legs and
            feet,<lb/> and every slender part melt in the pool:<lb/> so brief the time in which her
            tender limbs<lb/> were changed to flowing waves; and after them<lb/> her back and
            shoulders, and her sides and breasts<lb/> dissolved and vanished into rivulets:<lb/> and
            while she changed, the water slowly filled<lb/> her faulty veins instead of living
            blood—<lb/> and nothing that a hand could hold remained.</transform><lb/></p>


    <p>Now it befell when <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">Proserpine was lost,<lb/>
            her anxious mother sought through every land<lb/> and every sea in vain. She rested
            not.</character>lb/> <name>Aurora</name>, when she came with ruddy locks,<lb/> might
        never know, nor even <name>Hesperus</name>,<lb/> if she might deign to rest.—She lit two
        pines<lb/> from <name>Aetna</name>'s flames and held one in each hand,<lb/> and restless
        bore them through the frosty glooms:<lb/> and when serene the day had dimmed the stars<lb/>
        she sought her daughter by the rising sun;<lb/> and when the sun declined she rested
        not.<lb/></p>


    <p>Wearied with labour she began to thirst,<lb/> for all this while no streams had cooled her
        lips;<lb/> when, as by chance, a cottage thatched with straw<lb/> gladdened her sight.
        Thither the goddess went,<lb/> and, after knocking at the humble door,<lb/> waited until an
        ancient woman came;<lb/> who, when she saw the goddess and had heard<lb/> her plea for
        water, gave her a sweet drink,<lb/> but lately brewed of parched barley-meal;<lb/> and while
        the goddess quaffed this drink a boy,<lb/> of bold and hard appearance, stood before<lb/>
        and laughed and called her greedy. <character gender="female" descrip="rage">While he
            spoke<lb/> the angry goddess sprinkled him with meal,<lb/> mixed with the liquid which
            had not been drunk.</character><lb/></p>


    <p><transform type="physical" gender="male">His face grew spotted where the mixture struck,<lb/>
            and legs appeared where he had arms before,<lb/> a tail was added to his changing
            trunk;<lb/> and lest his former strength might cause great harm,<lb/> all parts
            contracted till he measured less<lb/> than common lizards.</transform> While the ancient
        dame<lb/> wondered and wept and strove for one caress,<lb/> the reptile fled and sought a
        lurking place.—<lb/> His very name describes him to the eye,<lb/> a body starred with many
        coloured spots.<lb/></p>


    <p>What lands, what oceans <character descrip="matronly" gender="female">Ceres wandered
            then,<lb/> would weary to relate. The bounded world<lb/> was narrow for the search.
            Again she passed<lb/> through <place>Sicily</place>; again observed all signs;<lb/> and
            as she wandered came to <name>Cyane</name>,<lb/> who strove to tell where Proserpine had
            gone,<lb/> but since her change, had neither mouth nor tongue,<lb/> and so was
            mute.</character> And yet the Nymph made plain<lb/> by certain signs what she desired to
        say:<lb/> for on the surface of the waves she showed<lb/> a well-known girdle <character
            gender="female" descrip="virginal">Proserpine had lost,<lb/> by chance had dropped it in
            that sacred pool;<lb/> which when the goddess recognized, at last,<lb/> convinced her
            daughter had been forced from her,</character><lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="rage">she tore her streaming locks, and frenzied
            struck<lb/> her bosom with her palms. And in her rage,<lb/> although she wist not where
            her daughter was,<lb/> she blamed all countries and cried out against<lb/> their base
            ingratitude; and she declared<lb/> the world unworthy of the gift of corn:<lb/> but
            Sicily before all other lands,<lb/> for there was found the token of her
            loss.</character><lb/></p>


    <p><character gender="female" descrip="rage">For that she broke with savage hand the plows,<lb/>
            which there had turned the soil, and full of wrath<lb/> leveled in equal death the
            peasant and his ox—<lb/> both tillers of the soil—and made decree<lb/> that land should
            prove deceptive to the seed,<lb/> and rot all planted germs.—That fertile isle,<lb/> so
            noted through the world, becomes a waste;<lb/> the corn is blighted in the early
            blade;<lb/> excessive heat, excessive rain destroys;<lb/> the winds destroy, the
            constellations harm;<lb/> the greedy birds devour the scattered seeds;<lb/> thistles and
            tares and tough weeds choke the wheat.</character><lb/></p>



    <p>“For this the <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">Nymph, <name>Alpheian</name>,
            raised her head<lb/> above Elean waves; and having first<lb/> pushed back her dripping
            tresses from her brows,<lb/> back to her ears, she thus began to speak;<lb/></character>
        <dia speaker="Arethusa" gender="female" invo="Ceres">‘O mother of the virgin, sought
            throughout<lb/> the globe! O mother of nutritious fruits!<lb/> Let these tremendous
            labours have an end;<lb/> do not increase the violence of thy wrath<lb/> against the
            Earth, devoted to thy sway,<lb/> and not deserving blame; for only force<lb/> compelled
            the Earth to open for that wrong.<lb/> Think not my supplication is to aid<lb/> my
            native country; hither I am come<lb/> an alien: Pisa is my native land,<lb/> and Elis
            gave me birth. Though I sojourn<lb/> a stranger in this isle of Sicily<lb/> it yet
            delights me more than all the world.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Arethusa" gender="female" invo="Ceres">‘I, <name>Arethusa</name>, claim this
            isle my home,<lb/> and do implore thee keep my throne secure,<lb/> O greatest of the
            Gods! A better hour,<lb/> when thou art lightened of thy cares, will come,<lb/> and when
            thy countenance again is kind;<lb/> and then may I declare what cause removed<lb/> me
            from my native place—and through the waves<lb/> of such a mighty ocean guided me<lb/> to
            find Ortygia.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Arethusa" gender="female" invo="Ceres">‘Through the porous earth<lb/> by
            deepest caverns, I uplift my head<lb/> and see unwonted stars. Now it befell,<lb/> as I
            was gliding far beneath the world,<lb/> where flow dark Stygian streams, I saw<lb/> thy
                <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">Proserpine. Although her
                countenance<lb/> betrayed anxiety and grief, a queen She reigned<lb/> supremely
                great in that opacous world<lb/> queen consort mighty to the King of
                Hell.’</character></dia><lb/></p>

    <p>Astonished and amazed, as thunderstruck,<lb/> when <character gender="female" descrip="rage"
            >Proserpina's mother heard these words,<lb/> long while she stood till great
            bewilderment<lb/> gave way to heavy grief. Then to the skies,<lb/> ethereal, she mounted
            in her car<lb/> and with beclouded face and streaming hair<lb/> stood fronting
                <name>Jove</name>, opprobrious.</character>
        <dia speaker="Ceres" gender="female">‘I have come<lb/> O <name>Jupiter</name>, a suppliant
            to thee,<lb/> both for my own offspring as well as thine.<lb/> If thy hard heart deny a
            mother grace,<lb/> yet haply as a father thou canst feel<lb/> some pity for thy
            daughter; and I pray<lb/> thy care for her may not be valued less<lb/> because my
            groaning travail brought her forth.—<lb/> My long-sought daughter has at last been
            found,<lb/> if one can call it, found, when certain loss<lb/> more certain has been
            proved; or so may deem<lb/> the knowledge of her state.—But I may bear<lb/> his rude
            ways, if again he bring her back.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Ceres" gender="female" invo="Jupiter">‘Thy worthy child should not be forced to
            wed<lb/> a bandit-chief, nor should my daughter's charms<lb/> reward his crime.’</dia>
        She spoke;—and <name>Jupiter</name><lb/> took up the word; <dia speaker="Jupiter"
            gender="male">‘This daughter is a care,<lb/> a sacred pledge to me as well as thee;<lb/>
            but if it please us to acknowledge truth,<lb/> this is a deed of love and injures
            not.<lb/> And if, O goddess, thou wilt not oppose,<lb/> such law-son cannot compass our
            disgrace:<lb/> for though all else were wanting, naught can need<lb/>
            <name>Jove</name>'s brother, who in fortune yields to none<lb/> save me. But if thy
            fixed desire compel<lb/> dissent, let <character gender="female" descrip="virginal"
                >Proserpine return to Heaven;<lb/> however, subject to the binding law,<lb/> if
                there her tongue have never tasted food—<lb/> a sure condition, by the Fates
                decreed.’</character></dia><lb/> he spoke; but <character descrip="protector"
            gender="female">Ceres was no less resolved<lb/> to lead her daughter
        thence.</character><lb/></p>


    <p>“Not so the Fates<lb/> permit.—<character gender="female" descrip="virginal">The virgin,
            thoughtless while she strayed</character><lb/> among the cultivated
            <place>Stygian</place> fields,<lb/> had broken fast. While there she plucked the
        fruit<lb/> by bending a pomegranate tree, and plucked,<lb/> and chewed seven grains, picked
        from the pallid rind;<lb/> and none had seen except <name>Ascalaphus</name>—<lb/> him
            <name>Orphne</name>, famed of all Avernian Nymphs,<lb/> had brought to birth in some
        infernal cave,<lb/> days long ago, from <name>Acheron</name>'s embrace—<lb/> he saw it,
            <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">and with cruel lips debarred<lb/> young
            Proserpine's return. Heaving a sigh,<lb/> the <name>Queen of Erebus</name>, indignant
            changed<lb/> that witness to an evil bird: she turned<lb/> his head, with sprinkled
                <name>Phlegethonian</name> lymph,<lb/></character>
        <transform type="physical" gender="male">into a beak, and feathers, and great eyes;<lb/> his
            head grew larger and his shape, deformed,<lb/> was cased in tawny wings; his lengthened
            nails<lb/> bent inward;—and his sluggish arms<lb/> as wings can hardly move. So he
            became<lb/> the vilest bird; a messenger of grief;<lb/> the lazy owl; sad omen to
            mankind.</transform><lb/></p>


    <p>The telltale's punishment was only just;<lb/> O <character gender="female" descrip="virginal"
            >Siren Maids but wherefore thus have ye<lb/> the feet and plumes of birds, although
            remain<lb/> your virgin features?</character>Is it from the day<lb/> when <character
            gender="female" descrip="virginal">Proserpina gathered vernal flowers;<lb/> because ye
            mingled with her chosen friends?<lb/> And after she was lost, in vain ye sought<lb/>
            through all the world; and wished for wings to waft<lb/> you over the great deep, that
            soon the sea<lb/> might feel your great concern.—The Gods were kind:</character><lb/>
        <transform type="physical" gender="male">ye saw your limbs grow yellow, with a growth<lb/>
            of sudden-sprouting feathers</transform>; but because<lb/> your melodies that gently
        charm the ear,<lb/> besides the <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">glory of your
            speech, might lose<lb/> the blessing, of a tongue, your virgin face<lb/> and human voice
            remained.</character><lb/></p>


    <p>“But <name>Jupiter</name>,<lb/> the mediator of these rival claims,<lb/> urged by his brother
        and his grieving sister,<lb/> divided the long year in equal parts.<lb/> Now <character
            gender="female">Proserpina</character>, <transform type="social" gender="female">as a
            Deity</transform>,<lb/> of equal merit, in two kingdoms reigns:—<lb/> for six months
        with her mother she abides,<lb/> and six months with her husband.—<transform type="physical"
            >Both her mind<lb/> and her appearance quickly were transformed</transform>;<lb/>
        <character descrip="joy">for she who seemed so sad in <name>Pluto</name>'s eyes,<lb/> now as
            a goddess beams in joyful smiles;<lb/> so, when the sun obscured by watery mist<lb/>
            conquers the clouds, it shines in splendour forth.<lb/></character></p>
</story>
