<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <title>DRYOPE</title>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“O my dear mother, <transform type="physical"
                gender="female">if you weep because<lb/> of her who was your servant, now
                transformed<lb/> into a weasel,</transform> how can you support<lb/> the true
            narration of my sister's fate;<lb/> which I must tell to you, although <character
                gender="female" descrip="despair">my tears<lb/> and sorrows hinder and forbid my
                speech</character>?</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“Most beautiful of all Oechalian maids,<lb/> was
                <character gender="female">Dryope</character>, her mother's only child,<lb/> for you
            must know I am the daughter of<lb/> my father's second wife. She is not now<lb/> a maid;
            because, through violence of him<lb/> who rules at <place>Delphi</place> and at
                <place>Delos</place>, she<lb/> was taken by <name>Andraemon,</name> who since
            then<lb/> has been accounted happy in his wife.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“There is a lake surrounded by sweet lawns,<lb/>
            encircling beauties, where the upper slope<lb/> is crowned with myrtles in fair sunny
            groves.<lb/> Without a thought of danger <character gender="female"
            >Dryope</character><lb/> in worship one day went to gather flowers,<lb/> (who hears, has
            greater cause to be indignant)<lb/> delightful garlands, for the <character
                gender="female" descrip="virginal">water-nymphs</character>,<lb/> and, <character
                gender="female" descrip="matronly">in her bosom, carried her dear son,<lb/> not yet
                a year old, whom she fed for love</character>.<lb/> Not far from that dream-lake, in
            moisture grew<lb/> a lotus, beautiful in purple bloom,<lb/> the blossoms promising its
            fruit was near.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“At play with her sweet infant, <character
                gender="female">Dryope</character><lb/> plucked them as toys for him. I, too, was
            there,<lb/> eagerly, also, I put forth my hand,<lb/> and was just ready to secure a
            spray,<lb/> when I was startled by some drops of blood<lb/> down-falling from the
            blossoms which were plucked;<lb/> and even the trembling branches shook in
        dread.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“Who wills, the truth of this may learn from all<lb/>
            quaint people of that land, who still relate<lb/> the <name>Story of Nymph Lotis</name>.
                <desire object="dryope" perp="priapus">She, they say,<lb/> while flying from the
                lust of <character gender="male">Priapus</character>,<lb/>
                <transform type="physical" gender="female">was transformed quickly from her human
                    shape,<lb/> into this tree,</transform> though she has kept her
            name.</desire></dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="Iole" gender="female">“But ignorant of all this, <character gender="female"
                >Dryope</character>,<lb/> alarmed, decided she must now return;<lb/> so, having
            first adored the <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">hallowed
                nymphs</character>,<lb/> upright she stood, and would have moved away,<lb/> but both
            her feet were tangled in a root.<lb/> There, as she struggled in its tightening
            hold,<lb/> she could move nothing save her upper parts;<lb/> and growing from that root,
            live bark began<lb/> to gather slowly upward from the ground,<lb/> spreading around her,
            till it touched her loins:<lb/> in terror when she saw the clinging growth,<lb/> she
            would have torn her hair out by the roots,<lb/> but, when she clutched at it, her hands
            were filled<lb/> with lotus leaves grown up from her changed head.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“Alas, her little son, <character gender="male"
                >Amphissos</character>, felt<lb/> his mother's bosom harden to his touch,<lb/> and
            no life-stream refreshed his eager lips.<lb/>
            <character descrip="despair" gender="female">And while I saw your cruel destiny,<lb/> O
                my dear sister! and could give no help,<lb/> I clung to your loved body and
                around<lb/> the growing trunk and branches, hoping so<lb/> to stop their evil
                growth; and I confess,<lb/> endeavored there to hide beneath the
            bark.</character></dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female">“And, oh! <character gender="male">Andraemon</character>
            and her father, then<lb/> appeared to me while they were sadly seeking<lb/> for
                <character gender="female">Dryope</character>: so there I had to show<lb/>
            <transform type="physical" gender="female">the lotus as it covered her, and they<lb/>
                gave kisses to the warm wood, and prostrate fell<lb/> upon the ground, and clung to
                growing roots<lb/> of their new darling tree, transformed from
            her</transform>.—<lb/> Dear sister, there was nothing of yourself<lb/> remaining but
            your face; and I could see<lb/> your tears drop slowly on the trembling leaves<lb/>
            which had so marvellously grown on you;<lb/> and while your lips remained uncovered,
            all<lb/> the air surrounding, echoed your complaint:—</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="iole" gender="female"><dia speaker="dryope" gender="female">“If oaths of
                wretched women can have force,<lb/> I swear I have not merited this fate!<lb/>
                Though innocent, to suffer punishment!<lb/> And if one word of my complaint is
                false,<lb/> I pray I may soon wither, and my leaves<lb/> fall from me as in blight,
                and let the axe<lb/> devote me, wretched to the flames. But take<lb/> this infant
                from my branches to a nurse;<lb/> and let him often play beneath his tree,—<lb/> his
                mother always. Let him drink his milk<lb/> beneath my shade. When he has learned to
                talk<lb/> let him salute me, and in sorrow say<lb/>
                <dia speaker="andraemon" gender="female">“In this tree-trunk my mother is
                    concealed.”</dia><lb/> O, let him dread the fate that lurks in ponds,<lb/> and
                let him often play beneath his tree,—<lb/> and let him be persuaded every shrub<lb/>
                contains the body of a goddess. — Ah!<lb/> Farewell my husband,—sister, — and
                farewell<lb/> my father! If my love remain in you<lb/> remember to protect my life
                from harm,<lb/> so that the pruning-knife may never clip<lb/> my branches, and
                protect my foliage from<lb/> the browsing sheep.</dia></dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia gender="female" speaker="iole"><dia speaker="dryope" gender="female">“<character
                    gender="female" descrip="matronly">I cannot stoop to you;<lb/> 0h, if you love
                    me, lift your lips to mine,<lb/> and let me kiss you, if but once again,<lb/>
                    before this growing lotus covers me.<lb/> Lift up my darling infant to my
                    lips.</character><lb/>
                <character gender="female" descrip="despair">How can I hope to say much more to
                    you?<lb/> The new bark now is creeping up my neck,<lb/> and creeping downward
                    from my covered brow!<lb/> Ah, do not close my live eyes with your hands;<lb/>
                    there is no need of it, for growing bark<lb/> will spread and darken them before
                    I die</character>!’</dia><lb/> Such were the last words her poor smothered
            lips<lb/> could utter; <transform type="physical" gender="female">for she was so quickly
                changed;<lb/> and long thereafter the new branches kept<lb/> the warmth of her lost
                body, so transformed</transform>.”</dia><lb/></p>
</story>
