<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../ovid-schematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<story>
    <title>NARCISSUS AND ECHOTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS</title>

    <p><name>Tiresias</name>' fame of prophecy was spread<lb/> through all the cities of
            <place>Aonia</place>,<lb/> for his unerring answers unto all<lb/> who listened to his
        words. And first of those<lb/> that harkened to his fateful prophecies,<lb/> a lovely Nymph,
        named <name>Liriope</name>, came<lb/> with her dear son, who then fifteen, might seem<lb/> a
        man or boy—he who was born to her<lb/> upon the green merge of <name>Cephissus</name>'
        stream—<lb/> that mighty River-God whom she declared<lb/> the father of her boy.—<lb/></p>


    <p>she questioned him.<lb/> Imploring him to tell her if her son,<lb/> unequalled for his
        beauty, whom she called<lb/>
        <character gender="male">Narcissus</character>, might attain a ripe old age.<lb/> To which
        the blind seer answered in these words,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="tiresias" gender="male">“If he but fail to recognize himself,<lb/> a long life
            he may have, beneath the sun,</dia>”—<lb/> so, frivolous the prophet's words
        appeared;<lb/> and yet the event, the manner of his death,<lb/> the strange delusion of his
        frenzied love, confirmed it.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>Three times five years so were passed.<lb/> Another five-years, and the lad might seem<lb/> a
        young man or a boy. <desire object="narcissus">And many a youth,<lb/> and many a damsel
            sought to gain his love;<lb/> but such his mood and spirit and his pride,<lb/> none
            gained his favour.<lb/></desire></p>


    <p>Once a noisy <character gender="female" descrip="cocky">Nymph,<lb/> (who never held her
            tongue when others spoke,<lb/> who never spoke till others had begun)<lb/> mocking Echo,
            spied him as he drove,<lb/> in his delusive nets, some timid
        stags.—</character><lb/></p>


    <p>for <character>Echo</character> was a Nymph, in olden time,—<lb/> and, more than vapid
        sound,—possessed a form:<lb/> and she was then deprived the use of speech,<lb/> except to
        babble and repeat the words,<lb/> once spoken, over and over.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p><character gender="female" descrip="jealous">Juno confused<lb/> her silly tongue, because she
            often held<lb/> that glorious goddess with her endless tales,<lb/> till many a hapless
            Nymph, from Jove's embrace,<lb/> had made escape adown a mountain.</character> But<lb/>
        for this, the goddess might have caught them. Thus<lb/> the glorious Juno, when she knew her
        guile;<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="juno" gender="female">“Your tongue, so freely wagged at my expense,<lb/> shall
            be of little use; your endless voice,<lb/> much shorter than your tongue.”</dia> At once
        the Nymph<lb/> was stricken as the goddess had decreed;—<lb/> and, ever since, she only
        mocks the sounds<lb/> of others' voices, or, perchance, returns<lb/> their final words.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>One day, when she observed<lb/>
        <character>Narcissus</character> wandering in the pathless woods,<lb/>
        <desire object="narcissus" perp="echo">she loved him and she followed him, with soft<lb/>
            and stealthy tread.—The more she followed him<lb/> the hotter did she burn, as when the
            flame<lb/> flares upward from the sulphur on the torch.<lb/></desire></p>


    <p><desire object="narcissus" perp="echo">Oh, how she longed to make her passion known!<lb/> To
            plead in soft entreaty! to implore his love!</desire><lb/> But now, till others have
        begun, a mute<lb/> of Nature she must be. She cannot choose<lb/> but wait the moment when
        his voice may give<lb/> to her an answer.<lb/></p>


    <p>Presently the youth,<lb/> by chance divided from his trusted friends,<lb/> cries loudly, <dia
            speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Who is here?”</dia> and Echo, <dia speaker="echo" gender="female"
        >“Here!”</dia><lb/> Replies. Amazed, he casts his eyes around,<lb/> and calls with louder
        voice, <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Come here!”</dia>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Come here!”</dia><lb/> She calls the youth who calls.—He turns to
        see<lb/> who calls him and, beholding naught exclaims,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Avoid me not!”</dia>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Avoid me not!”</dia> returns.<lb/></p>


    <p>He tries again, again, and is deceived<lb/> by this alternate voice, and calls aloud;<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Oh let us come together!”</dia> Echo cries,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Oh let us come together!”</dia>
        <desire object="narcissus" perp="echo">Never sound<lb/> seemed sweeter to the Nymph, and
            from the woods<lb/> she hastens in accordance with her words,<lb/> and strives to wind
            her arms around his neck.</desire><lb/> He flies from her and as he leaves her says,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Take off your hands! you shall not fold your
            arms<lb/> around me. Better death than such a one<lb/> should ever caress me!”</dia>
        Naught she answers save,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Caress me!”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>Thus rejected she lies hid<lb/> in the deep woods, hiding her blushing face<lb/> with the
        green leaves; and ever after lives<lb/> concealed in lonely caverns in the hills.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>But her great love increases with neglect;<lb/> her miserable body wastes away,<lb/> wakeful
        with sorrows; leanness shrivels up<lb/> her skin, and all her lovely features melt,<lb/> as
        if dissolved upon the wafting winds—<lb/> nothing remains except her bones and voice—<lb/>
        her voice continues, in the wilderness;<lb/> her bones have turned to stone. She lies
        concealed<lb/> in the wild woods, nor is she ever seen<lb/> on lonely mountain range; for,
        though we hear<lb/> her calling in the hills, 'tis but a voice,<lb/> a voice that lives,
        that lives among the hills.<lb/></p>


    <p>Thus he deceived the Nymph and many more,<lb/> sprung from the mountains or the sparkling
        waves;<lb/> and thus he slighted many an amorous youth.—<lb/> and therefore, some one whom
        he once despised,<lb/> lifting his hands to Heaven, implored the Gods,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" invo="nemesis" gender="male">“If he should love deny him what he
        loves!”</dia><lb/> and as the prayer was uttered it was heard<lb/> by
            <character>Nemesis</character>, who granted her assent.<lb/>
    </p>

    <header>NARCISSUS</header>

    <p>There was a fountain silver-clear and bright,<lb/> which neither shepherds nor the wild
        she-goats,<lb/> that range the hills, nor any cattle's mouth<lb/> had touched—its waters
        were unsullied—birds<lb/> disturbed it not; nor animals, nor boughs<lb/> that fall so often
        from the trees. Around<lb/> sweet grasses nourished by the stream grew; trees<lb/> that
        shaded from the sun let balmy airs<lb/> temper its waters. Here Narcissus, tired<lb/> of
        hunting and the heated noon, lay down,<lb/> attracted by the peaceful solitudes<lb/> and by
        the glassy spring. There as he stooped<lb/> to quench his thirst another thirst
        increased.<lb/></p>


    <p><desire object="narcissus" perp="narcissus">While he is drinking he beholds himself<lb/>
            reflected in the mirrored pool—and loves;<lb/> loves an imagined body which
            contains<lb/> no substance, for he deems the mirrored shade<lb/> a thing of life to
            love. He cannot move,<lb/> for so he marvels at himself, and lies<lb/> with countenance
            unchanged, as if indeed<lb/> a statue carved of Parian marble. Long,<lb/> supine upon
            the bank, his gaze is fixed<lb/> on his own eyes, twin stars; his fingers shaped<lb/> as
            Bacchus might desire, his flowing hair<lb/> as glorious as <name>Apollo</name>'s, and
            his cheeks<lb/> youthful and smooth; his ivory neck, his mouth<lb/> dreaming in
            sweetness, his complexion fair<lb/> and blushing as the rose in snow-drift white.<lb/>
            All that is lovely in himself he loves,<lb/> and in his witless way he wants
            himself:—<lb/> he who approves is equally approved;<lb/> he seeks, is sought, he burns
            and he is burnt.</desire><lb/></p>


    <p>And how he kisses the deceitful fount;<lb/> and how he thrusts his arms to catch the
        neck<lb/> that's pictured in the middle of the stream!<lb/> Yet never may he wreathe his
        arms around<lb/> that image of himself. He knows not what<lb/> he there beholds, but what he
        sees inflames<lb/> his longing, and the error that deceives<lb/> allures his eyes. But why,
        O foolish boy,<lb/> so vainly catching at this flitting form?<lb/> The cheat that you are
        seeking has no place.<lb/> Avert your gaze and you will lose your love,<lb/> for this that
        holds your eyes is nothing save<lb/> the image of yourself reflected back to you.<lb/> It
        comes and waits with you; it has no life;<lb/> it will depart if you will only go.<lb/></p>



    <p>Nor food nor rest can draw him thence—outstretched<lb/> upon the overshadowed green, his
        eyes<lb/> fixed on the mirrored image never may know<lb/> their longings satisfied, and by
        their sight<lb/> he is himself undone. Raising himself<lb/> a moment, he extends his arms
        around,<lb/> and, beckoning to the murmuring forest;<dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">
            “Oh,<lb/> ye aisled wood was ever man in love<lb/> more fatally than I? Your silent
            paths<lb/> have sheltered many a one whose love was told,<lb/> and ye have heard their
            voices. Ages vast<lb/> have rolled away since your forgotten birth,<lb/> but who is he
            through all those weary years<lb/> that ever pined away as I? Alas,<lb/> this fatal
            image wins my love, as I<lb/> behold it. But I cannot press my arms<lb/> around the form
            I see, the form that gives<lb/> me joy. What strange mistake has intervened<lb/> betwixt
            us and our love? It grieves me more<lb/> that neither lands nor seas nor mountains,
            no,<lb/> nor walls with closed gates deny our loves,<lb/> but only a little water keeps
            us far<lb/> asunder. Surely he desires my love<lb/> and my embraces, for as oft I
            strive<lb/> to kiss him, bending to the limpid stream<lb/> my lips, so often does he
            hold his face<lb/> fondly to me, and vainly struggles up.<lb/> It seems that I could
            touch him. 'Tis a strange<lb/> delusion that is keeping us apart.<lb/></dia></p>

    <p><dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Whoever thou art, Come up! Deceive me not!<lb/> Oh,
            whither when I fain pursue art thou?<lb/> Ah, surely I am young and fair, the
            Nymphs<lb/> have loved me; and when I behold thy smiles<lb/> I cannot tell thee what
            sweet hopes arise.<lb/> When I extend my loving arms to thee<lb/> thine also are
            extended me — thy smiles<lb/> return my own. When I was weeping, I<lb/> have seen thy
            tears, and every sign I make<lb/> thou cost return; and often thy sweet lips<lb/> have
            seemed to move, that, peradventure words,<lb/> which I have never heard, thou hast
            returned.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“No more my shade deceives me, I perceive<lb/> 'Tis I
            in thee—I love myself—the flame<lb/> arises in my breast and burns my heart—<lb/> what
            shall I do? Shall I at once implore?<lb/> Or should I linger till my love is
            sought?<lb/> What is it I implore? The thing that I<lb/> desire is mine—abundance makes
            me poor.<lb/> Oh, I am tortured by a strange desire<lb/> unknown to me before, for I
            would fain<lb/> put off this mortal form; which only means<lb/> I wish the object of my
            love away.<lb/> Grief saps my strength, the sands of life are run,<lb/> and in my early
            youth am I cut off;<lb/> but death is not my bane—it ends my woe.—<lb/> I would not
            death for this that is my love,<lb/> as two united in a single soul<lb/> would die as
            one.”<lb/></dia></p>


    <p>He spoke; and crazed with love,<lb/> returned to view the same face in the pool;<lb/> and as
        he grieved his tears disturbed the stream,<lb/> and ripples on the surface, glassy
        clear,<lb/> defaced his mirrored form. And thus the youth,<lb/> when he beheld that lovely
        shadow go;<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Ah whither cost thou fly? Oh, I entreat<lb/> thee
            leave me not. Alas, thou cruel boy<lb/> thus to forsake thy lover. Stay with me<lb/>
            that I may see thy lovely form, for though<lb/> I may not touch thee I shall feed my
            eyes<lb/> and soothe my wretched pains.”</dia> And while he spoke<lb/> he rent his
        garment from the upper edge,<lb/> and beating on his naked breast, all white<lb/> as marble,
        every stroke produced a tint<lb/> as lovely as the apple streaked with red,<lb/> or as the
        glowing grape when purple bloom<lb/> touches the ripening clusters.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>When as glass<lb/> again the rippling waters smoothed, and when<lb/> such beauty in the
        stream the youth observed,<lb/> no more could he endure. As in the flame<lb/> the yellow
        wax, or as the hoar-frost melts<lb/> in early morning 'neath the genial sun;<lb/> so did he
        pine away, by love consumed,<lb/> and slowly wasted by a hidden flame.<lb/> No vermeil bloom
        now mingled in the white<lb/> of his complexion fair; no strength has he,<lb/> no vigor, nor
        the comeliness that wrought<lb/> for love so long: alas, that handsome form<lb/> by Echo
        fondly loved may please no more.<lb/></p>


    <p>But when she saw him in his hapless plight,<lb/> though angry at his scorn, she only
        grieved.<lb/> As often as the love-lore boy complained,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Alas!”</dia>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Alas!”</dia> her echoing voice returned;<lb/> and as he struck his
        hands against his arms,<lb/> she ever answered with her echoing sounds.<lb/> And as he gazed
        upon the mirrored pool<lb/> he said at last, <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“Ah, youth beloved in
            vain!”</dia><lb/>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“In vain, in vain!”</dia> the spot returned his words;<lb/> and when he
        breathed a sad <dia speaker="narcissus" gender="male">“farewell!”</dia>
        <dia speaker="echo" gender="female">“Farewell!”</dia><lb/> sighed <character>Echo</character> too. He laid
        his wearied head,<lb/> and rested on the verdant grass; and those<lb/> bright eyes, which
        had so loved to gaze, entranced,<lb/> on their own master's beauty, sad Night closed.<lb/>
        And now although among the nether shades<lb/> his sad sprite roams, he ever loves to
        gaze<lb/> on his reflection in the Stygian wave.<lb/></p>


    <p>His Naiad sisters mourned, and having clipped<lb/> their shining tresses laid them on his
        corpse:<lb/> and all the Dryads mourned: and Echo made<lb/> lament anew. And these would
        have upraised<lb/> his funeral pyre, and waved the flaming torch,<lb/> and made his bier;
        but as they turned their eyes<lb/> where he had been, <transform type="physical">alas he was
            not there!<lb/> And in his body's place a sweet flower grew,<lb/> golden and white, the
            white around the gold.</transform><lb/></p>

</story>
