<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <header>Achelous et Hercules.</header>
    <title>HERCULES AND ACHELOUS</title>

    <p>To him the hero, who proclaimed himself<lb/> a favored son of <name>Neptune</name>, answered now;<lb/>
        <dia gender="male">“Declare the reason of your heavy sighs,<lb/> and how your horn was
            broken?”</dia> And at once<lb/> the Calydonian River-God replied,<lb/> binding with
        reeds his unadorned rough locks:<lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“It is a mournful task you have required,<lb/> for who
            can wish to tell his own disgrace?<lb/> But truly I shall speak without disguise,<lb/>
            for my defeat, if rightly understood,<lb/> should be my glory.—Even to have fought<lb/>
            in battle with a hero of such might,<lb/> affords me consolation.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“<name>Deianira</name><lb/> (you may have heard some
            tales of her) was once<lb/> the envied hope of many. She was then<lb/>
            <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">a lovely virgin</character>.—<desire
                object="Deianira" perp="Achelous">I, among the rest<lb/> who loved this
                maiden</desire>, entered the fair home<lb/> of her great father <name>Oeneus</name>,
            and I said;</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“ <dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">‘Consider all
                my claims, <name>Parthaon</name>'s son,<lb/> for I am come to plead your daughter's
                cause<lb/> and mine—So you may make me son-in-law.,—’</dia><lb/> no sooner was it
            said, than <character gender="male">Hercules</character><lb/> in such words also claimed
                <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">the virgin's hand</character>:<lb/>
            all others quickly yielded to our claims.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“He boasted his descent from <name>Jupiter</name>;<lb/>
            the glory of his labors and great deeds<lb/> performed at his unjust stepmother's
            wish.</dia><lb/>
    </p>

    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“But as he was not then a God, it seemed<lb/>
            disgraceful if my state should yield my right;<lb/> so I contended with these haughty words,<lb/>
            <dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male" invo="Hercules">‘<character gender="male"
                    descrip="cocky">Why should this alien of a foreign land,<lb/> contending for
                    your daughter, match himself<lb/> to me! king of the waters in this
                    realm!</character><lb/> For as I wind around, across your lands,<lb/> I must be
                of your people, and a part<lb/> of your great state. Oh, let it not be said,<lb/>
                because the jealous <name>Juno</name> had no thought<lb/> to punish me by labors, my
                descent<lb/> is not so regal! This tremendous boast,<lb/> that you,
                    <name>Alcmena</name>'s son, are sprung from <name>Jove</name>,<lb/> falls at the
                touch of truth;—or it reveals<lb/> the shame of a weak mother, who so gained<lb/>
                your doubtful glory of descent from Heaven!<lb/> Prove your descent from
                    <name>Jupiter</name> is false,<lb/> or else confess you are the son of
                shame!’</dia></dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“But <character gender="male">Hercules</character>,
                <character gender="male" descrip="rage">unable to control<lb/> the flame of his
                great wrath, scowled as I spoke</character>.<lb/> He briefly answered me, <dia
                speaker="Hercules" gender="male">‘My hand excels<lb/> my tongue; let me now overcome
                in fight,<lb/> and I may suffer your offence of words.’</dia></dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“Full of unvented rage he rushed on me,<lb/> but firm I
            stood, ashamed to yield a foot—<lb/> I had so largely boasted, no retreat was left,<lb/>
            and so I doffed my green robe—Striking guard,<lb/> with clenched hands doubled at my
            breast,<lb/> I stood my ground. He scooped up in his hand<lb/> fine, yellow dust; and
            tossed it on the air<lb/> so that the tawny powder sprinkled us;<lb/> quick-shifting
            then he sought to strike my neck,<lb/> or feint at my quick-moving legs, and turn<lb/>
            swift moving to attack me at all points.<lb/> But as a huge cliff in the sea
            remains<lb/> unmoved, unshaken by the sounding waves,<lb/> so my great size, against his
            vain attacks,<lb/> defended me securely—Back we went;<lb/> retiring for a space; then
            rushed again<lb/> together, furious, and with foot to foot,<lb/> determined not to
            yield, defiant stood,<lb/> till, forward-bending from my waist and hips,<lb/> I pressed
            my forehead against his and locked<lb/> his fingers into mine: so, have I seen<lb/> two
            strong bulls rush in combat for the good<lb/> of some smooth heifer in the
            pasture—while<lb/> the herd a-tremble and uncertain, wait;<lb/> ready to give allegiance
            to the one<lb/> most worthy of dominion.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia gender="male" speaker="Achelous">“Thrice in vain<lb/>
            <character gender="male">Hercules</character> strove to push my breast from his,<lb/>
            but I pressed ever closer—till, the fourth<lb/> attempt succeeding, he unloosed my
            grip,<lb/> and breaking from my circling arms drew back,<lb/> and struck me such a
            buffet with his hand,<lb/> it twisted me about, and instantly<lb/> he clung with all his
            weight upon my back—</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“Believe me I have not suppressed the truth.<lb/> Nor
            shall I try to gain applause not due:<lb/> I seemed to bear a mountain on my back.
            —<lb/> straining and dripping sweat, I broke his hold,—<lb/> with great exertion I
            unlocked his grip.<lb/> He pressed upon me, as I strained for breath,<lb/> preventing a
            renewal of my strength,<lb/> and seized upon my neck. Then at the last,<lb/> my bent
            knee went down on the gritty earth,<lb/> I bit the sand. So, worsted in my strength,<lb/>
            <transform type="physical" gender="male">I sought diversion by an artifice,<lb/> and
                changed me to a serpent.—I then slipped<lb/> from his tight clutches my great
                length, and coiled<lb/> my body now transformed to snaky folds—<lb/> hissing I
                darted my divided tongue.</transform></dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“But <character gender="male">Hercules</character>,
                <name>Alcides</name>, only laughed<lb/> and in derision of my scheming, said,<lb/>
            <dia speaker="Hercules" gender="male" invo="Achelous">‘It was the pastime of my cradle
                days<lb/> to strangle better snakes than you—and though<lb/> your great length may
                excel all of your kind,<lb/> how small a part of that Lernaean snake<lb/> would
                you—one serpent be? It grew from wounds<lb/> I gave (at first it had one hundred
                heads)<lb/> and every time I severed one head from<lb/> its neck two grew there in
                the place of one,<lb/> by which its strength increased. This creature then<lb/>
                outbranching with strong serpents, sprung from death<lb/> and thriving on
                destruction, I destroyed.—<lb/> What do you think will then become of you,<lb/>
                disguised so in deceitful serpent-form,<lb/> wielding a borrowed weapon not your
                own</dia></dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“And after he had ridiculed me thus,<lb/> he gouged his
            fingers underneath my jaws,<lb/> so that my throat was tortured, as if squeezed<lb/>
            with forceps, while I struggled in his grip.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia speaker="Achelous" gender="male">“Twice was I vanquished, there remained to me<lb/>
            <transform type="physical" gender="male">a third form so again I changed to seem<lb/> a
                savage bull, and with my limbs renewed<lb/> in that form fought once
                more.</transform> He threw his arms<lb/> about the left side of my ponderous
            neck,<lb/> and dragging on me followed as I ran.<lb/> He seized on my hard horns, and,
            tugging turned<lb/> and twisted me, until he fastened them<lb/> firm in the surface of
            the earth; and pushed<lb/> me, helpless, to the shifting sand beneath.<lb/> Not yet
            content he laid his fierce right hand<lb/> on my tough horn, and broke and tore it
            from<lb/> my mutilated head.—This horn, now heaped<lb/> with fruits delicious and
            sweet-smelling flowers,<lb/> the Naiads have held sacred from that hour,<lb/> devoted to
            the bounteous goddess <name>Plenty</name>.’</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>All this the <character gender="male">River-god</character> said; <character gender="female"
            descrip="virginal">then a nymph,<lb/> a lovely nymph</character> like fair
            <name>Diana</name> dressed,<lb/> whose locks were flowing down on either side,<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="matronly">came graceful to the board, and brought to
            them<lb/> of Autumn's plenty in an ample horn,<lb/> and gave to them selected apples
            for<lb/> a second course.</character><lb/></p>


    <p>And now, as early dawn<lb/> appeared, and as the rising sunlight flashed<lb/> on golden
        summits of surrounding hills,<lb/> the young men waited not until the stream<lb/> subsiding,
        had resumed its peaceful way,<lb/> but all arose, reluctant, and went forth.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p>Then <character gender="male">Achelous</character>, in his moving waves,<lb/> hid his fine
        rustic features and his head,<lb/> scarred by the wound which gave the <name>Horn of
            Plenty</name>.<lb/></p>
</story>
