<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../ovid-schematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<story>
    <header>Nisus et Scylla. </header>
    <title>KING MINOS AND SCYLLA</title>

    <p>Now <character gender="male">Lucifer</character> unveiled the glorious day,<lb/> and as the
        session of the night dissolved,<lb/> the cool east wind declined, and vapors wreathed<lb/>
        the moistened valleys. Veering to the south<lb/> the welcome wind gave passage to the
        sons<lb/> of <name>Aeacus</name>, and wafted <name>Cephalus</name><lb/> on his returning
        way, propitious; where<lb/> before the wonted hour, they entered port.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> King <character gender="male">Minos</character>, while the fair wind moved their ship,<lb/>
        was laying waste the land of <place>Megara</place>.<lb/> He gathered a great army round the
        walls<lb/> built by <name>Alcathous</name>, where reigned in splendor<lb/>
        King <character gender="male" descrip="protector">Nisus—mighty and renowned in war—<lb/> upon the
        center of whose hoary head<lb/> a lock of purple hair was growing.
            —Its<lb/> proved virtue gave protection to his
        throne.</character><lb/></p>

    <p>Six times the horns of rising <name>Phoebe</name> grew,<lb/> and still the changing fortune
        of the war<lb/> was in suspense; so, <name>Victory</name> day by day<lb/> between them
        hovered on uncertain wings.<lb/></p>

    <p>Within that city was a regal tower<lb/> on tuneful walls; where once <name>Apollo</name>
        laid<lb/> his golden harp; and in the throbbing stone<lb/> the sounds remained. And there,
        in times of peace<lb/> the daughter of King <character gender="male">Nisus</character> loved
        to mount<lb/> the walls and strike the sounding stone with pebbles:<lb/> so, when the war
        began, she often viewed<lb/> the dreadful contest from that height;<lb/> until, so long the
        hostile camp remained,<lb/> she had become acquainted with the names,<lb/> and knew the
        habits, horses and the arms<lb/> of many a chief, and could discern the signs<lb/> of their
            <name>Cydonean</name> quivers.<lb/></p>

    <p>More than all,<lb/> the features of King <character gender="male">Minos</character> were
        engraved<lb/> upon the tablets of her mind. <desire object="minos" perp="scylla">And
            when<lb/> he wore his helmet, crested with gay plumes,<lb/> she deemed it glorious; when
            he held his shield<lb/> shining with gold, no other seemed so grand;<lb/> and when he
            poised to hurl the tough spear home,<lb/> she praised his skill and strength; and when
            he bent<lb/> his curving bow with arrow on the cord,<lb/> she pictured him as
                <name>Phoebus</name> taking aim,—<lb/> but when, arrayed in purple, and upon<lb/>
            the back of his white war horse, proudly decked<lb/> with richly broidered housings, he
            reined in<lb/> the nervous steed, and took his helmet off,<lb/> showing his fearless
            features, then the maid,<lb/> daughter of <name>Nisus</name>, could control herself<lb/>
            no longer; and a frenzy seized her mind.</desire><lb/></p>

    <p>She called the javelin happy which he touched,<lb/> and blessed were the reins within his
        hand.<lb/></p>

    <p>She had an impulse to direct her steps,<lb/>
        <character gender="female" descrip="virginal">a tender virgin</character>, through the
        hostile ranks,<lb/> or cast her body from the topmost towers<lb/> into the Gnossian
            camp.<desire object="minos" perp="scylla"> She had a wild<lb/> desire to open to the
            enemy<lb/> the heavy brass-bound gates, or anything<lb/> that <character gender="male"
                >Minos</character> could desire.</desire><lb/></p>

    <p>And as she sat<lb/> beholding the white tents, <character gender="female" descrip="despair"
            >she cried, <dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“Alas!<lb/> Should I rejoice or grieve
                to see this war?<lb/> I grieve that <name>Minos</name> is the enemy<lb/> of her who
                loves him; but unless the war<lb/> had brought him, how could he be known to
                me?<lb/> But should he take me for a hostage? That<lb/> might end the war—a pledge
                of peace, he might<lb/> keep me for his companion.</dia></character><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“O, supreme<lb/> of mankind! she who bore you must have
            been<lb/> as beautiful as you are; ample cause<lb/> for <name>Jove</name> to lose his
            heart.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“O, happy hour!<lb/> If moving upon wings through
            yielding air,<lb/> I could alight within the hostile camp<lb/> in front of
                <name>Minos</name>, and declare to him<lb/> my name and passion!</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“Then would I implore<lb/> what dowry he could wish,
            and would provide<lb/> whatever he might ask, except alone<lb/> the city of my father.
            Perish all<lb/> my secret hopes before one act of mine<lb/> should offer treason to
            accomplish it.<lb/> And yet, the kindness of a conqueror<lb/> has often proved a
            blessing, manifest<lb/> to those who were defeated. Certainly<lb/> the war he carries on
            is justified<lb/> by his slain son.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“He is a mighty king,<lb/> thrice strengthened in his
            cause. Undoubtedly<lb/> we shall be conquered, and, if such a fate<lb/> awaits our city,
                <desire object="minos" perp="scylla">why should he by force<lb/> instead of my
                consuming love, prevail<lb/> to open the strong gates?</desire> Without delay<lb/>
            and dreadful slaughter, it is best for him<lb/> to conquer and decide this savage
            war.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“Ah, <character gender="male">Minos</character>, how I
            fear the bitter fate<lb/> should any warrior hurl his cruel spear<lb/> and pierce you by
            mischance, for surely none<lb/> can be so hardened to transfix your breast<lb/> with
            purpose known.”</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><desire object="minos" perp="scylla">Oh, let her love prevail<lb/> to open for his army the
            great gates.<lb/> Only the thought of it, has filled her soul;</desire><lb/> she is
        determined to deliver up<lb/> her country as a dowry with herself,<lb/> and so decide the
        war! But what avails<lb/> this idle talk.<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“A guard surrounds the gates,<lb/> my father keeps the
            keys, and <character gender="female" descrip="despair">he alone<lb/> is my obstruction,
                and the innocent<lb/> account of my despair.</character> Would to the Gods<lb/> I
            had no father! Is not man the God<lb/> of his own fortune, though his idle prayers<lb/>
            avail not to compel his destiny?</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female"><desire object="minos" perp="scylla">“Another woman
                crazed with passionate desires,<lb/> which now inflame me, would not hesitate,<lb/>
                but with a fierce abandon would destroy<lb/> whatever checked her passion. Who is
                there<lb/> with love to equal mine? I dare to go<lb/> through flames and swords; but
                swords and flames<lb/> are not now needed, for I only need<lb/> my royal father's
                lock of purple hair.<lb/> More precious than fine gold, it has a power<lb/> to give
                my heart all that it may desire.”</desire></dia><lb/></p>

    <p>While <character gender="female">Scylla</character> said this, night that heals our
        cares<lb/> came on, and she grew bolder in the dark.<lb/> And now it is the late and silent
        hour<lb/> when slumber takes possession of the breast.<lb/> Outwearied with the cares of
        busy day;<lb/> then as her father slept, with stealthy tread<lb/> she entered his abode, and
        there despoiled,<lb/> and clipped his fatal lock of purple hair.<lb/></p>

    <p>Concealing in her bosom the sad prize<lb/> of crime degenerate, she at once went forth<lb/> a
        gate unguarded, and with shameless haste<lb/> sped through the hostile army to the tent<lb/>
        of <name>Minos</name>, whom, astonished, she addressed:<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female">“Only my love has led me to this deed.<lb/> The
            daughter of <name>King Nisus</name>, I am called<lb/> the maiden <character
                gender="female">Scylla</character>. Unto you I come<lb/> and offer up a power that
            will prevail<lb/> against my country, and I stipulate<lb/> no recompense except
            yourself. Take then<lb/> this purple hair, a token of my love.—<lb/> Deem it not lightly
            as a lock of hair<lb/> held idly forth to you; it is in truth<lb/> my father's
            life.”</dia><desire object="minos" perp="scylla">And as she spoke<lb/> she held out in
            her guilty hand the prize,<lb/> and begged him to accept it with her
        love.</desire><lb/></p>

    <p>Shocked at the thought of such a heinous crime,<lb/>
        <name>Minos</name> refused, and said, <dia speaker="minos" gender="male" invo="scylla">“O
            execrable thing!<lb/>
            <character gender="male" descrip="rage">Despised abomination of our time!<lb/> May all
                the Gods forever banish you<lb/> from their wide universe, and may the earth<lb/>
                and the deep ocean be denied to you!</character><lb/> So great a monster shall not
            be allowed<lb/> to desecrate the sacred <place>Isle of Crete</place>,<lb/> where
                <name>Jupiter</name> was born.”</dia>So <character gender="male">Minos</character>
        spoke.<lb/></p>

    <p>Nevertheless he conquered <name>Megara</name>,<lb/> (so aided by the damsel's wicked
        deed)<lb/> and as a just and mighty king imposed<lb/> his own conditions on the vanquished
        land.<lb/></p>

    <p>He ordered his great fleet to tarry not;<lb/> the hawsers were let loose, and the long
        oars<lb/> quickly propelled his brazen-pointed ships.—<lb/></p>

    <p>When <character gender="female">Scylla</character>saw them launching forth,<lb/> observed
        them sailing on the mighty deep,<lb/> she called with vain entreaties; <character
            gender="female" descrip="rage">but at last,<lb/> aware the prince ignored her and
            refused<lb/> to recompense her wickedness, enraged,<lb/> and raving, she held up her
            impious hands,<lb/> her long hair streaming on the wind,</character> — and
        said:<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“Oh, wherefore have you flown, and left
            behind<lb/> the author of your glory. Oh, wretch! wretch<lb/> to whom I offered up my
            native land,<lb/> and sacrificed my father! Where have you<lb/> now flown, ungrateful
            man whose victory<lb/> is both my crime and virtue? And the gift<lb/> presented to you,
            and my passion,<lb/> have these not moved you? All my love and hope<lb/> in you
            alone!</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“Forsaken by my prince,<lb/> shall I
            return to my defeated land?<lb/> If never ruined it would shut its walls<lb/> against
            me.—Shall I seek my father's face<lb/> whom I delivered to all-conquering arms?<lb/> My
            fellow-citizens despise my name;<lb/> my friends and neighbors hate me; I have shut<lb/>
            the world against me, only in the hope<lb/> that <name>Crete</name> would surely welcome
            me;—and now,<lb/> he has forbidden me.</dia><lb/>
    </p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“And is it so<lb/> I am requited by this
            thankless wretch!<lb/>
            <name>Europa</name> could not be your mother! Spawn<lb/> of cruel <name>Syrtis</name>!
            Savage cub of fierce<lb/> Armenian tigress;—or <name>Charybdis</name>, tossed<lb/> by
            the wild South-wind begot you! Can you be<lb/> the son of <name>Jupiter</name>? Your
            mother was<lb/> not ever tricked by the false semblance<lb/> of a bull. <character
                gender="female" descrip="rage">All that story of your birth<lb/> is false! You are
                the offspring of a bull<lb/> as fierce as you are!</character></dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“<character gender="female"
                descrip="despair">Let your vengeance fall<lb/> upon me, O my father
                    <name>Nisus</name>, let<lb/> the ruined city I betrayed rejoice<lb/> at my
                misfortunes—richly merited—<lb/> destroy me, you whom I have ruined;—I<lb/> should
                perish for my crimes!</character> But why should you,<lb/> who conquered by my
            crime, abandon me?<lb/> The treason to my father and my land<lb/> becomes an act of
            kindness in your cause.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“That woman is a worthy mate for you<lb/>
            who hid in wood deceived the raging bull,<lb/> and bore to him the infamy of
                <name>Crete</name>.<lb/> I do not wonder that <name>Pasiphae</name><lb/> preferred
            the bull to you, more savage than<lb/> the wildest beast. Alas, alas for
        me!</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“Do my complaints reach your unwilling
            ears?<lb/> Or do the same winds waft away my words<lb/> that blow upon your ships,
            ungrateful man?—<lb/> Ah, wretched that I am, he takes delight<lb/> in hastening from
            me. The deep waves resound<lb/> as smitten by the oars, his ship departs;<lb/> and I am
            lost and even my native land<lb/> is fading from his sight.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="scylla" gender="female" invo="minos">“Oh heart of flint!<lb/> you shall not
            prosper in your cruelty,<lb/> and you shall not forget my sacrifice;<lb/> in spite of
            everything I follow you!<lb/> I'll grasp the curving stern of your swift ship,<lb/> and
            I will follow through unending seas.”</dia><lb/></p>

    <p>And as she spoke, she leaped into the waves,<lb/> and followed the receding ships—for
        strength<lb/> from passion came to her. And soon she clung<lb/> unwelcome, to the sailing
        Gnossian ship.<lb/></p>

    <p><transform type="physical" gender="male">Meanwhile, the Gods had changed her father's
            form<lb/> and now he hovered over the salt deep,<lb/> a hawk with tawny
            wings.</transform> So when he saw<lb/> his daughter clinging to the hostile ship<lb/> he
        would have torn her with his rending beak;—<lb/> he darted towards her through the yielding
        air.<lb/> In terror she let go, but as she fell<lb/> the light air held her from the ocean
        spray;<lb/> her feather-weight supported by the breeze;<lb/>
        <transform type="physical" gender="female">she spread her wings, and changed into a
            bird.</transform><lb/> They called her “<name>Ciris</name>” when she cut the wind,<lb/>
        and “<name>Ciris</name>”—cut-the-lock—remains her name.<lb/></p>
</story>
