<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <header> Scylla et Circe. </header>
    <title>SCYLLA TRANSFORMED TO A ROCK</title>

    <p>Now the <place>Euboean</place> dweller in great waves,<lb/>
        <character gender="male">Glaucus</character>, had left behind the crest of
            <place>Aetna</place>,<lb/> raised upward from a giant's head; and left<lb/> the
            <character gender="male">Cyclops</character>' fields, that never had been torn<lb/> by
        harrow or by plough and never were<lb/> indebted to the toil of oxen yoked;<lb/> left
            <place>Zancle</place>, also, and the opposite walls<lb/> of <place>Rhegium</place>, and
        the sea, abundant cause<lb/> of shipwreck, which confined with double shores<lb/> bounds the
        Ausonian and Sicilian lands.<lb/></p>

    <p>All these behind him, <character gender="male">Glaucus</character>, swimming on<lb/> with his
        huge hands through those Tyrrhenian seas,<lb/> drew near the hills so rich in magic
        herbs<lb/> and halls of <character gender="female">Circe</character>, daughter of the
        Sun,—<lb/> halls filled with men in guise of animals.<lb/> After due salutations had been
        given—<lb/> received by her as kindly—,<character gender="male">Glaucus</character>
        said,<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="glaucus" gender="male" invo="circe">“You as a goddess, certainly should
            have<lb/> compassion upon me, a god; for you<lb/> alone (if I am worthy of it) can<lb/>
            relieve my passion. What the power of herbs<lb/> can be, <character gender="female"
                >Titania</character>, none knows more than I,<lb/> for by their power I was myself
            transformed.<lb/> To make the cause of my strange madness known,<lb/> I have found
                <character gender="female">Scylla</character> on Italian shores,<lb/> directly
            opposite Messenian walls.</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="glaucus" gender="male" invo="circe">“It shames me to recount my promises,<lb/>
            entreaties, and caresses, and at last<lb/> rejection of my suit. If you have known<lb/>
            a power of incantation, I implore<lb/> you now repeat that incantation here,<lb/> with
            sacred lips—If herbs have greater power,<lb/> use the tried power of herbs. But I would
            not<lb/> request a cure—the healing of this wound.<lb/> Much better than an end of pain,
            let her<lb/> share, and feel with me my impassioned flame.”</dia><lb/></p>

    <p>But <character gender="female">Circe</character> was more quick than any other<lb/> to burn
        with passion's flame. It may have been<lb/> her nature or it may have been the work<lb/> of
            <name>Venus</name>, angry at her tattling sire.<lb/></p>

    <p><dia speaker="circe" gender="female" invo="glaucus">“You might do better,” she replied,
                <desire object="glaucus" perp="circe">“to court<lb/> one who is willing, one who
                wants your love,<lb/> and feels a like desire. You did deserve<lb/> to win her love,
                yes, to be wooed yourself.<lb/> In fact you might be. <character gender="female"
                    descrip="cocky">If you give some hope,<lb/> you have my word, you shall indeed
                    be wooed.<lb/> That you may have no doubt, and so retain<lb/> all confidence in
                    your attraction's power—<lb/> behold! I am a goddess, and I am<lb/> the daughter
                    also, of the radiant Sun!<lb/> And I who am so potent with my charms,<lb/> and I
                    who am so potent with my herbs,<lb/> wish only to be yours.</character> Despise
                her who<lb/> despises you, and her who is attached<lb/> by one act offer each her
                just reward</desire>.”</dia><lb/></p>

    <p>But <character gender="male">Glaucus</character> answered her attempt of love,<lb/>
        <dia speaker="glaucus" gender="male">“The trees will sooner grow in ocean waves,<lb/> than I
            shall change my love for graceful! <character gender="female"
        >Scylla</character>.”</dia><lb/></p>

    <p><character gender="female" descrip="jealous">The goddess in her jealous rage could not<lb/>
            and would not injure him, whom she still loved,<lb/> but turned her wrath upon the one
            preferred.</character><lb/> She bruised immediately the many herbs<lb/> most infamous
        for horrid juices, which,<lb/> when bruised, she mingled with most artful care<lb/> and
        incantations given by <character gender="female">Hecate</character>.<lb/> Then, clothed in
        azure vestments, she passed through<lb/> her troop of fawning savage animals,<lb/> and
        issued from the center of her hall.<lb/> Pacing from there to <place>Rhegium</place>,
        opposite<lb/> the dangerous rocks of <place>Zancle</place>, she at once<lb/> entered the
        tossed waves boiling up with tides:<lb/> on these as if she walked on the firm shore,<lb/>
        she set her feet and, hastening on dry shod,<lb/> she skimmed along the surface of the
        deep.<lb/></p>

    <p>Not far away there was an inlet curved,<lb/> round as a bent bow, which was often used<lb/>
        by <character gender="female">Scylla</character> as a favorite retreat.<lb/> There, she
        withdrew from heat of sea and sky<lb/> when in the zenith blazed the unclouded sun<lb/> and
        cast the shortest shadows on the ground.<lb/>
        <character gender="female">Circe</character> infected it before that hour,<lb/></p>

    <p>polluting it with monster-breeding drugs.<lb/> She sprinkled juices over it, distilled<lb/>
        from an obnoxious root, and thrice times nine<lb/> she muttered over it with magic
        lips,<lb/> her most mysterious charm involved in words<lb/> of strangest import and of
        dubious thought.<lb/></p>

    <p><character gender="female">Scylla</character> came there and waded in waist deep,<lb/> then
        saw her loins defiled with barking shapes.<lb/> Believing they could be no part of her,<lb/>
        she ran and tried to drive them back and feared<lb/> the boisterous canine jaws. But what
        she fled<lb/> she carried with her. And, feeling for her thighs,<lb/> her legs, and feet,
        she found Cerberian jaws<lb/> instead. She rises from a rage of dogs,<lb/> and shaggy backs
        encircle her shortened loins.<lb/></p>

    <p>The lover <character gender="male">Glaucus</character> wept. He fled the embrace<lb/> of
            <character gender="female">Circe</character> and her hostile power of herbs<lb/> and
        magic spells. But <character gender="female">Scylla</character> did not leave<lb/> the place
        of her disaster; and, as soon<lb/> as she had opportunity, for hate<lb/> of <character
            gender="female">Circe</character>, she robbed <name>Ulysses</name> of his men.<lb/>
        <transform type="physical" gender="female">She would have wrecked the Trojan ships, if
            she<lb/> had not been changed beforehand to a rock</transform><lb/> which to this day
        reveals a craggy rim.<lb/> And even the rock awakes the sailors' dread.<lb/></p>
</story>
