<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../important-stuff/OVID-SCHEMA-DRAFT1.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <header>Minyeides</header>
    <title>THE DAUGHTERS OF KING MINYAS TRANSFORMED TO BATS</title>
    <p>
        <character gender="female">Alcithoe</character>, daughter of 
        King <character gender="male">Minyas</character>,<lb/> consents not to the orgies of the God;<lb/> denies that
            <name>Bacchus</name> is the son of <name>Jove</name>,<lb/> and her two sisters join her
        in that crime.<lb/></p>


    <p>'Twas festal-day when matrons and their maids,<lb/> keeping it sacred, had forbade all
        toil.—<lb/> And having draped their bosoms with wild skins,<lb/> they loosed their long hair
        for the sacred wreaths,<lb/> and took the leafy thyrsus in their hands;—<lb/> for so the
        priest commanded them. Austere<lb/> the wrath of <name>Bacchus</name> if his power be
        scorned.<lb/></p>


    <p>Mothers and youthful brides obeyed the priest;<lb/> and putting by their wickers and their
        webs,<lb/> dropt their unfinished toils to offer up<lb/> frankincense to the God; invoking
        him<lb/> with many names:—<dia gender="female" invo="bacchus">“O <name>Bacchus</name>! O
            Twice-born!<lb/> O Fire-begot! Thou only child Twice-mothered!<lb/> God of all those who
            plant the luscious grape!<lb/> O <name>Liber</name>!” All these names and many
            more,<lb/> for ages known—throughout the lands of Greece.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia gender="female" invo="bacchus">“Thy youth is not consumed by wasting time;<lb/> and lo,
            thou art an ever-youthful boy,<lb/> most beautiful of all the Gods of Heaven,<lb/>
            <character gender="non-binary" descrip="virginal">smooth as a virgin </character>when
            thy horns are hid.—<lb/> The distant east to tawny India's clime,<lb/> where rolls
            remotest Ganges to the sea,<lb/> was conquered by thy might.—O Most-revered!<lb/> Thou
            didst destroy the doubting <name>Pentheus</name>,<lb/> and hurled the sailors' bodies in
            the deep,<lb/> and smote <name>Lycurgus</name>, wielder of the ax.</dia><lb/></p>


    <p><dia gender="female" invo="bacchus">“And thou dost guide thy lynxes, double-yoked,<lb/> with
            showy harness.—<name>Satyrs</name> follow thee;<lb/> and <name>Bacchanals</name>, and
            old <name>Silenus</name>, drunk,<lb/> unsteady on his staff; jolting so rough<lb/> on
            his small back-bent ass; and all the way<lb/> resounds a youthful clamour; and the
            screams<lb/> of women! and the noise of tambourines!<lb/> And the hollow cymbals! and
            the boxwood flutes,—<lb/> fitted with measured holes.—Thou art implored<lb/> by all
            Ismenian women to appear<lb/> peaceful and mild; and they perform thy
        rites.”</dia><lb/></p>


    <p>Only the daughters of King <character gender="male">Minyas</character><lb/> are carding wool
        within their fastened doors,<lb/> or twisting with their thumbs the fleecy yarn,<lb/> or
        working at the web. So they corrupt<lb/> the sacred festival with needless toil,<lb/>
        keeping their hand-maids busy at the work.<lb/></p>


    <p>And one of them, while drawing out the thread<lb/> with nimble thumb, anon began to speak;<lb/>
        <dia gender="female">“While others loiter and frequent these rites<lb/> fantastic, we the
            wards of <name>Pallas</name>, much<lb/> to be preferred, by speaking novel thoughts<lb/>
            may lighten labour. Let us each in turn,<lb/> relate to an attentive audience,<lb/> a
            novel tale; and so the hours may glide.”</dia><lb/> it pleased her sisters, and they
        ordered her<lb/> to tell the story that she loved the most.<lb/></p>


    <p>So, as she counted in her well-stored mind<lb/> the many tales she knew, first doubted
        she<lb/> whether to tell the tale of <name>Derceto</name>,—<lb/> that Babylonian, who, aver
        the tribes<lb/> of <place>Palestine</place>, in limpid ponds yet lives,—<lb/>
        <transform gender="female" type="physical">her body changed, and scales upon her
            limbs</transform>;<lb/> or how her daughter, <transform gender="female" type="physical"
            >having taken wings</transform>,<lb/> passed her declining years in whitened
        towers.<lb/> Or should she tell of <name>Nais</name>, who with herbs,<lb/> too potent, into
        fishes had transformed<lb/> the bodies of her lovers, till she met<lb/> herself the same sad
        fate; or of that tree<lb/> which sometime bore white fruit, but now is changed<lb/> and
        darkened by the blood that stained its roots.—<lb/> Pleased with the novelty of this, at
        once<lb/> she tells the tale of <name>Pyramus</name> and <name>Thisbe</name>;—<lb/> and
        swiftly as she told it unto them,<lb/> the fleecy wool was twisted into threads.<lb/></p>
</story>
