<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>BOOK 1

Invocatio.
INVOCATION
<l>My soul is wrought to sing of forms transformed</l>
<l>to bodies new and strange! Immortal Gods</l>
<l>inspire my heart, for ye have changed yourselves</l>
<l>and all things you have changed! Oh lead my song</l>
<l>in smooth and measured strains, from olden days</l>
<l>when earth began to this completed time!</l>


THE CREATION
Mundi origo.
<l>Before the ocean and the earth appeared—</l>
<l>before the skies had overspread them all—</l>
<l>the face of Nature in a vast expanse</l>
<l>was naught but Chaos uniformly waste.</l>
<l>It was a rude and undeveloped mass,</l>
<l>that nothing made except a ponderous weight;</l>
<l>and all discordant elements confused,</l>
<l>were there congested in a shapeless heap.</l>

    
<l>As yet the sun afforded earth no light,</l>
<l>nor did the moon renew her crescent horns;</l>
<l>the earth was not suspended in the air</l>
<l>exactly balanced by her heavy weight.</l>
<l>Not far along the margin of the shores</l>
<l>had Amphitrite stretched her lengthened arms,—</l>
<l>for all the land was mixed with sea and air.</l>
<l>The land was soft, the sea unfit to sail,</l>
<l>the atmosphere opaque, to naught was given</l>
<l>a proper form, in everything was strife,</l>
<l>and all was mingled in a seething mass—</l>
<l>with hot the cold parts strove, and wet with dry</l>
<l>and soft with hard, and weight with empty void.</l>

    
<l>But God, or kindly Nature, ended strife—</l>
<l>he cut the land from skies, the sea from land,</l>
<l>the heavens ethereal from material air;</l>
<l>and when were all evolved from that dark mass</l>
<l>he bound the fractious parts in tranquil peace.</l>
<l>The fiery element of convex heaven</l>
<l>leaped from the mass devoid of dragging weight,</l>
<l>and chose the summit arch to which the air</l>
<l>as next in quality was next in place.</l>
<l>The earth more dense attracted grosser parts</l>
<l>and moved by gravity sank underneath;</l>
<l>and last of all the wide surrounding waves</l>
<l>in deeper channels rolled around the globe.</l>

    
<l>And when this God —which one is yet unknown—</l>
<l>had carved asunder that discordant mass,</l>
<l>had thus reduced it to its elements,</l>
<l>that every part should equally combine,</l>
<l>when time began He rounded out the earth</l>
<l>and moulded it to form a mighty globe.</l>
<l>Then poured He forth the deeps and gave command</l>
<l>that they should billow in the rapid winds,</l>
<l>that they should compass every shore of earth. </l>
<l>he also added fountains, pools and lakes,</l>
<l>and bound with shelving banks the slanting streams,</l>
<l>which partly are absorbed and partly join</l>
<l>the boundless ocean. Thus received amid</l>
<l>the wide expanse of uncontrolled waves,</l>
<l>they beat the shores instead of crooked banks.</l>

    
<l>At His command the boundless plains extend,</l>
<l>the valleys are depressed, the woods are clothed</l>
<l>in green, the stony mountains rise. And as</l>
<l>the heavens are intersected on the right</l>
<l>by two broad zones, by two that cut the left,</l>
<l>and by a fifth consumed with ardent heat,</l>
<l>with such a number did the careful God</l>
<l>mark off the compassed weight, and thus the earth</l>
<l>received as many climes.—Such heat consumes</l>
<l>the middle zone that none may dwell therein;</l>
<l>and two extremes are covered with deep snow;</l>
<l>and two are placed betwixt the hot and cold,</l>
<l>which mixed together give a temperate clime;</l>
<l>and over all the atmosphere suspends</l>
<l>with weight proportioned to the fiery sky,</l>
<l>exactly as the weight of earth compares</l>
<l>with weight of water.</l>

    
<l>And He ordered mist</l>
<l>to gather in the air and spread the clouds.</l>
<l>He fixed the thunders that disturb our souls,</l>
<l>and brought the lightning on destructive winds</l>
<l>that also waft the cold. Nor did the great</l>
<l>Artificer permit these mighty winds</l>
<l>to blow unbounded in the pathless skies,</l>
<l>but each discordant brother fixed in space,</l>
<l>although His power can scarce restrain their rage</l>
<l>to rend the universe. At His command</l>
<l>to far Aurora, Eurus took his way,</l>
<l>to Nabath, Persia, and that mountain range</l>
<l>first gilded by the dawn; and Zephyr's flight</l>
<l>was towards the evening star and peaceful shores,</l>
<l>warm with the setting sun; and Boreas</l>
<l>invaded Scythia and the northern snows;</l>
<l>and Auster wafted to the distant south</l>
<l>where clouds and rain encompass his abode.—</l>
<l>and over these He fixed the liquid sky,</l>
<l>devoid of weight and free from earthly dross.</l>

    
<l>And scarcely had He separated these</l>
<l>and fixed their certain bounds, when all the stars,</l>
<l>which long were pressed and hidden in the mass,</l>
<l>began to gleam out from the plains of heaven,</l>
<l>and traversed, with the Gods, bright ether fields:</l>
<l>and lest some part might be bereft of life</l>
<l>the gleaming waves were filled with twinkling fish;</l>
<l>the earth was covered with wild animals;</l>
<l>the agitated air was filled with birds. </l>

    
<l>But one more perfect and more sanctified,</l>
<l>a being capable of lofty thought,</l>
<l>intelligent to rule, was wanting still</l>
<l>man was created! Did the Unknown God</l>
<l>designing then a better world make man</l>
<l>of seed divine? or did Prometheus</l>
<l>take the new soil of earth (that still contained</l>
<l>some godly element of Heaven's Life)</l>
<l>and use it to create the race of man;</l>
<l>first mingling it with water of new streams;</l>
<l>so that his new creation, upright man,</l>
<l>was made in image of commanding Gods?</l>
<l>On earth the brute creation bends its gaze,</l>
<l>but man was given a lofty countenance</l>
<l>and was commanded to behold the skies;</l>
<l>and with an upright face may view the stars:—</l>
<l>and so it was that shapeless clay put on</l>
<l>the form of man till then unknown to earth.</l>


Quattuor aetates. Gigantes.
THE FOUR AGES

<l>First was the Golden Age. Then rectitude</l>
<l>spontaneous in the heart prevailed, and faith.</l>
<l>Avengers were not seen, for laws unframed</l>
<l>were all unknown and needless. Punishment</l>
<l>and fear of penalties existed not.</l>
<l>No harsh decrees were fixed on brazen plates.</l>
<l>No suppliant multitude the countenance</l>
<l>of Justice feared, averting, for they dwelt</l>
<l>without a judge in peace. Descended not</l>
<l>the steeps, shorn from its height, the lofty pine,</l>
<l>cleaving the trackless waves of alien shores,</l>
<l>nor distant realms were known to wandering men.</l>
<l>The towns were not entrenched for time of war;</l>
<l>they had no brazen trumpets, straight, nor horns</l>
<l>of curving brass, nor helmets, shields nor swords.</l>
<l>There was no thought of martial pomp —secure</l>
<l>a happy multitude enjoyed repose.</l>

    
<l>Then of her own accord the earth produced</l>
<l>a store of every fruit. The harrow touched</l>
<l>her not, nor did the plowshare wound</l>
<l>her fields. And man content with given food,</l>
<l>and none compelling, gathered arbute fruits</l>
<l>and wild strawberries on the mountain sides,</l>
<l>and ripe blackberries clinging to the bush,</l>
<l>and corners and sweet acorns on the ground,</l>
<l>down fallen from the spreading tree of Jove.</l>
<l>Eternal Spring! Soft breathing zephyrs soothed</l>
<l>and warmly cherished buds and blooms, produced</l>
<l>without a seed. The valleys though unplowed</l>
<l>gave many fruits; the fields though not renewed</l>
<l>white glistened with the heavy bearded wheat:</l>
<l>rivers flowed milk and nectar, and the trees,</l>
<l>the very oak trees, then gave honey of themselves.</l>

    
<l>When Saturn had been banished into night</l>
<l>and all the world was ruled by Jove supreme,</l>
<l>the Silver Age, though not so good as gold</l>
<l>but still surpassing yellow brass, prevailed.</l>

    
<l>Jove first reduced to years the Primal Spring,</l>
<l>by him divided into periods four,</l>
<l>unequal,—summer, autumn, winter, spring.—</l>
<l>then glowed with tawny heat the parched air,</l>
<l>or pendent icicles in winter froze</l>
<l>and man stopped crouching in crude caverns, while</l>
<l>he built his homes of tree rods, bark entwined.</l>
<l>Then were the cereals planted in long rows,</l>
<l>and bullocks groaned beneath the heavy yoke.</l>

    
<l>The third Age followed, called The Age of Bronze,</l>
<l>when cruel people were inclined to arms</l>
<l>but not to impious crimes. And last of all</l>
<l>the ruthless and hard Age of Iron prevailed,</l>
<l>from which malignant vein great evil sprung;</l>
<l>and modesty and faith and truth took flight,</l>
<l>and in their stead deceits and snares and frauds</l>
<l>and violence and wicked love of gain,</l>
<l>succeeded.—Then the sailor spread his sails</l>
<l>to winds unknown, and keels that long had stood</l>
<l>on lofty mountains pierced uncharted waves.</l>
<l>Surveyors anxious marked with metes and bounds</l>
<l>the lands, created free as light and air:</l>
<l>nor need the rich ground furnish only crops,</l>
<l>and give due nourishment by right required,—</l>
<l>they penetrated to the bowels of earth</l>
<l>and dug up wealth, bad cause of all our ills,—</l>
<l>rich ores which long ago the earth had hid</l>
<l>and deep removed to gloomy Stygian caves:</l>
<l>and soon destructive iron and harmful gold</l>
<l>were brought to light; and War, which uses both,</l>
<l>came forth and shook with sanguinary grip</l>
<l>his clashing arms. Rapacity broke forth—</l>
<l>the guest was not protected from his host,</l>
<l>the father in law from his own son in law;</l>
<l>even brothers seldom could abide in peace.</l>
<l>The husband threatened to destroy his wife,</l>
<l>and she her husband: horrid step dames mixed</l>
<l>the deadly henbane: eager sons inquired</l>
<l>their fathers, ages. Piety was slain:</l>
<l>and last of all the virgin deity,</l>
<l>Astraea vanished from the blood-stained earth.</l>

GIANTS
<l>And lest ethereal heights should long remain</l>
<l>less troubled than the earth, the throne of Heaven</l>
<l>was threatened by the Giants;   and they piled</l>
<l>mountain on mountain to the lofty stars.</l>
<l>But Jove, omnipotent, shot thunderbolts</l>
<l>through Mount Olympus, and he overturned</l>
<l>from Ossa huge, enormous Pelion.</l>
<l>And while these dreadful bodies lay overwhelmed</l>
<l>in their tremendous bulk, (so fame reports)</l>
<l>the Earth was reeking with the copious blood</l>
<l>of her gigantic sons; and thus replete</l>
<l>with moisture she infused the steaming gore</l>
<l>with life renewed. So that a monument</l>
<l>of such ferocious stock should be retained,</l>
<l>she made that offspring in the shape of man;  </l>
<l>but this new race alike despised the Gods,</l>
<l>and by the greed of savage slaughter proved</l>
<l>a sanguinary birth.</l>


Lycaon.
LYCAON CHANGED TO A WOLF

<l>When, from his throne</l>
<l>supreme, the Son of Saturn viewed their deeds,</l>
<l>he deeply groaned: and calling to his mind</l>
<l>the loathsome feast Lycaon had prepared,</l>
<l>a recent deed not common to report,</l>
<l>his soul conceived great anger —worthy Jove— </l>
<l>and he convened a council. No delay</l>
<l>detained the chosen Gods.</l>

    
<l>When skies are clear</l>
<l>a path is well defined on high, which men,</l>
<l>because so white, have named the Milky Way.</l>
<l>It makes a passage for the deities</l>
<l>and leads to mansions of the Thunder God,</l>
<l>to Jove's imperial home. On either side</l>
<l>of its wide way the noble Gods are seen,</l>

    
<l>inferior Gods in other parts abide,</l>
<l>but there the potent and renowned of Heaven</l>
<l>have fixed their homes.—It is a glorious place,</l>
<l>our most audacious verse might designate</l>
<l>the “Palace of High Heaven.” When the Gods</l>
<l>were seated, therefore, in its marble halls</l>
<l>the King of all above the throng sat high,</l>
<l>and leaning on his ivory scepter, thrice,</l>
<l>and once again he shook his awful locks,</l>
<l>wherewith he moved the earth, and seas and stars,—</l>
<l>and thus indignantly began to speak;</l>

<l>“The time when serpent footed giants strove</l>
<l>to fix their hundred arms on captive Heaven,</l>
<l>not more than this event could cause alarm</l>
<l>for my dominion of the universe.</l>
<l>Although it was a savage enemy,</l>
<l>yet warred we with a single source derived</l>
<l>of one. Now must I utterly destroy</l>
<l>this mortal race wherever Nereus roars</l>
<l>around the world. Yea, by the Infernal Streams</l>
<l>that glide through Stygian groves beneath the world,</l>
<l>I swear it. Every method has been tried.</l>
<l>The knife must cut immedicable wounds,</l>
<l>lest maladies infect untainted parts.</l>

<l>“Beneath my sway are demi gods and fauns,</l>
<l>nymphs, rustic deities, sylvans of the hills,</l>
<l>satyrs;—all these, unworthy Heaven's abodes,</l>
<l>we should at least permit to dwell on earth</l>
<l>which we to them bequeathed. What think ye, Gods,</l>
<l>is safety theirs when I, your sovereign lord,</l>
<l>the Thunder-bolt Controller, am ensnared</l>
<l>by fierce Lycaon?” Ardent in their wrath,</l>
<l>the astonished Gods demand revenge overtake</l>
<l>this miscreant; he who dared commit such crimes.</l>
<l>'Twas even thus when raged that impious band</l>
<l>to blot the Roman name in sacred blood</l>
<l>of Caesar, sudden apprehensive fears</l>
<l>of ruin absolute astonished man,</l>
<l>and all the world convulsed. Nor is the love</l>
<l>thy people bear to thee, Augustus, less</l>
<l>than these displayed to Jupiter whose voice</l>
<l>and gesture all the murmuring host restrained:</l>
<l>and as indignant clamour ceased, suppressed</l>
<l>by regnant majesty, Jove once again</l>
<l>broke the deep silence with imperial words;</l>

<l>“Dismiss your cares; he paid the penalty</l>
<l>however all the crime and punishment</l>
<l>now learn from this:—An infamous report</l>
<l>of this unholy age had reached my ears,</l>
<l>and wishing it were false, I sloped my course</l>
<l>from high Olympus, and—although a God—</l>
<l>disguised in human form I viewed the world.</l>
<l>It would delay us to recount the crimes</l>
<l>unnumbered, for reports were less than truth.</l>

<l>“I traversed Maenalus where fearful dens</l>
<l>abound, over Lycaeus, wintry slopes</l>
<l>of pine tree groves, across Cyllene steep;</l>
<l>and as the twilight warned of night's approach,</l>
<l>I stopped in that Arcadian tyrant's realms</l>
<l>and entered his inhospitable home:—</l>
<l>and when I showed his people that a God</l>
<l>had come, the lowly prayed and worshiped me,</l>
<l>but this Lycaon mocked their pious vows</l>
<l>and scoffing said; ‘A fair experiment</l>
<l>will prove the truth if this be god or man.’</l>
<l>and he prepared to slay me in the night,—</l>
<l>to end my slumbers in the sleep of death.</l>
<l>So made he merry with his impious proof;</l>
<l>but not content with this he cut the throat</l>
<l>of a Molossian hostage sent to him,</l>
<l>and partly softened his still quivering limbs</l>
<l>in boiling water, partly roasted them</l>
<l>on fires that burned beneath. And when this flesh</l>
<l>was served to me on tables, I destroyed</l>
<l>his dwelling and his worthless Household Gods,</l>
<l>with thunder bolts avenging. Terror struck</l>
<l>he took to flight, and on the silent plains</l>
<l>is howling in his vain attempts to speak;</l>
<l>he raves and rages and his greedy jaws,</l>
<l>desiring their accustomed slaughter, turn</l>
<l>against the sheep—still eager for their blood.</l>
<l>His vesture separates in shaggy hair,</l>
<l>his arms are changed to legs; and as a wolf</l>
<l>he has the same grey locks, the same hard face,</l>
<l>the same bright eyes, the same ferocious look.</l>

THE DELUGE

<l>“Thus fell one house, but not one house alone</l>
<l>deserved to perish; over all the earth</l>
<l>ferocious deeds prevail,—all men conspire</l>
<l>in evil. Let them therefore feel the weight</l>
<l>of dreadful penalties so justly earned,</l>
<l>for such hath my unchanging will ordained.”</l>

    
<l>with exclamations some approved the words</l>
<l>of Jove and added fuel to his wrath,</l>
<l>while others gave assent: but all deplored</l>
<l>and questioned the estate of earth deprived</l>
<l>of mortals. Who could offer frankincense</l>
<l>upon the altars? Would he suffer earth</l>
<l>to be despoiled by hungry beasts of prey?</l>
<l>Such idle questions of the state of man</l>
<l>the King of Gods forbade, but granted soon</l>
<l>to people earth with race miraculous,</l>
<l>unlike the first. </l>


Diluvium. Deucalion et Pyrrha.

<l>And now his thunder bolts</l>
<l>would Jove wide scatter, but he feared the flames,</l>
<l>unnumbered, sacred ether might ignite</l>
<l>and burn the axle of the universe:</l>
<l>and he remembered in the scroll of fate,</l>
<l>there is a time appointed when the sea</l>
<l>and earth and Heavens shall melt, and fire destroy</l>
<l>the universe of mighty labour wrought.</l>
<l>Such weapons by the skill of Cyclops forged,</l>
<l>for different punishment he laid aside—</l>
<l>for straightway he preferred to overwhelm</l>
<l>the mortal race beneath deep waves and storms</l>
<l>from every raining sky. And instantly</l>
<l>he shut the Northwind in Aeolian caves,</l>
<l>and every other wind that might dispel</l>
<l>the gathering clouds. He bade the Southwind blow:—</l>

    
<l>the Southwind flies abroad with dripping wings,</l>
<l>concealing in the gloom his awful face:</l>
<l>the drenching rain descends from his wet beard</l>
<l>and hoary locks; dark clouds are on his brows</l>
<l>and from his wings and garments drip the dews:</l>
<l>his great hands press the overhanging clouds;</l>
<l>loudly the thunders roll; the torrents pour;</l>
<l>Iris, the messenger of Juno, clad</l>
<l>in many coloured raiment, upward draws</l>
<l>the steaming moisture to renew the clouds.</l>

    
<l>The standing grain is beaten to the ground,</l>
<l>the rustic's crops are scattered in the mire,</l>
<l>and he bewails the long year's fruitless toil.</l>

    
<l>The wrath of Jove was not content with powers</l>
<l>that emanate from Heaven; he brought to aid</l>
<l>his azure brother, lord of flowing waves,</l>
<l>who called upon the Rivers and the Streams:</l>
<l>and when they entered his impearled abode,</l>
<l>Neptune, their ancient ruler, thus began;</l>
<l>“A long appeal is needless; pour ye forth</l>
<l>in rage of power; open up your fountains;</l>
<l>rush over obstacles;   let every stream</l>
<l>pour forth in boundless floods.” Thus he commands,</l>
<l>and none dissenting all the River Gods</l>
<l>return, and opening up their fountains roll</l>
<l>tumultuous to the deep unfruitful sea.</l>

    
<l>And Neptune with his trident smote the Earth,</l>
<l>which trembling with unwonted throes heaved up</l>
<l>the sources of her waters bare; and through</l>
<l>her open plains the rapid rivers rushed</l>
<l>resistless, onward bearing the waving grain,</l>

    
<l>the budding groves, the houses, sheep and men,—</l>
<l>and holy temples, and their sacred urns.</l>
<l>The mansions that remained, resisting vast</l>
<l>and total ruin, deepening waves concealed</l>
<l>and whelmed their tottering turrets in the flood</l>
<l>and whirling gulf. And now one vast expanse,</l>
<l>the land and sea were mingled in the waste</l>
<l>of endless waves—a sea without a shore.</l>

    
<l>One desperate man seized on the nearest hill;</l>
<l>another sitting in his curved boat,</l>
<l>plied the long oar where he was wont to plow;</l>
<l>another sailed above his grain, above</l>
<l>his hidden dwelling; and another hooked</l>
<l>a fish that sported in a leafy elm.</l>
<l>Perchance an anchor dropped in verdant fields,</l>
<l>or curving keels were pushed through tangled vines;</l>
<l>and where the gracile goat enjoyed the green,</l>
<l>unsightly seals reposed. Beneath the waves</l>
<l>were wondering Nereids, viewing cities, groves</l>
<l>and houses. Dolphins darting mid the trees,</l>
<l>meshed in the twisted branches, beat against</l>
<l>the shaken oak trees. There the sheep, affrayed,</l>
<l>swim with the frightened wolf, the surging waves</l>
<l>float tigers and lions: availeth naught</l>
<l>his lightning shock the wild boar, nor avails</l>
<l>the stag's fleet footed speed. The wandering bird,</l>
<l>seeking umbrageous groves and hidden vales,</l>
<l>with wearied pinion droops into the sea.</l>
<l>The waves increasing surge above the hills,</l>
<l>and rising waters dash on mountain tops.</l>
<l>Myriads by the waves are swept away,</l>
<l>and those the waters spare, for lack of food,</l>
<l>starvation slowly overcomes at last.</l>

    
<l>A fruitful land and fair but now submerged</l>
<l>beneath a wilderness of rising waves,</l>
<l>'Twixt Oeta and Aonia, Phocis lies,</l>
<l>where through the clouds Parnassus' summits twain</l>
<l>point upward to the stars, unmeasured height,</l>
<l>save which the rolling billows covered all:</l>
<l>there in a small and fragile boat, arrived,</l>
<l>Deucalion and the consort of his couch,</l>
<l>prepared to worship the Corycian Nymphs,</l>
<l>the mountain deities, and Themis kind,</l>
<l>who in that age revealed in oracles</l>
<l>the voice of fate. As he no other lived</l>
<l>so good and just, as she no other feared</l>
<l>the Gods.</l>

    
<l>When Jupiter beheld the globe</l>
<l>in ruin covered, swept with wasting waves,</l>
<l>and when he saw one man of myriads left,</l>
<l>one helpless woman left of myriads lone,</l>
<l>both innocent and worshiping the Gods,</l>
<l>he scattered all the clouds; he blew away</l>
<l>the great storms by the cold northwind.</l>


    
<l>Once more</l>
<l>the earth appeared to heaven and the skies</l>
<l>appeared to earth. The fury of the main</l>
<l>abated, for the Ocean ruler laid</l>
<l>his trident down and pacified the waves,</l>
<l>and called on azure Triton.—Triton arose</l>
<l>above the waving seas, his shoulders mailed</l>
<l>in purple shells.—He bade the Triton blow,</l>
<l>blow in his sounding shell, the wandering streams</l>
<l>and rivers to recall with signal known:</l>
<l>a hollow wreathed trumpet, tapering wide</l>
<l>and slender stemmed, the Triton took amain</l>
<l>and wound the pearly shell at midmost sea.</l>
<l>Betwixt the rising and the setting suns</l>
<l>the wildered notes resounded shore to shore,</l>
<l>and as it touched his lips, wet with the brine</l>
<l>beneath his dripping beard, sounded retreat:</l>
<l>and all the waters of the land and sea</l>
<l>obeyed. Their fountains heard and ceased to flow;</l>
<l>their waves subsided; hidden hills uprose;</l>
<l>emerged the shores of ocean; channels filled</l>
<l>with flowing streams; the soil appeared; the land</l>
<l>increased its surface as the waves decreased:</l>
<l>and after length of days the trees put forth,</l>
<l>with ooze on bending boughs, their naked tops.</l>

    
<l>And all the wasted globe was now restored,</l>
<l>but as he viewed the vast and silent world</l>
<l>Deucalion wept and thus to Pyrrha spoke;</l>
<l>“O sister! wife! alone of woman left!</l>
<l>My kindred in descent and origin!</l>
<l>Dearest companion of my marriage bed,</l>
<l>doubly endeared by deepening dangers borne,—</l>
<l>of all the dawn and eve behold of earth,</l>
<l>but you and I are left—for the deep sea</l>
<l>has kept the rest! And what prevents the tide</l>
<l>from overwhelming us? Remaining clouds</l>
<l>affright us. How could you endure your fears</l>
<l>if you alone were rescued by this fate,</l>
<l>and who would then console your bitter grief?</l>
<l>Oh be assured, if you were buried in the waves,</l>
<l>that I would follow you and be with you!</l>
<l>Oh would that by my father's art I might</l>
<l>restore the people, and inspire this clay</l>
<l>to take the form of man. Alas, the Gods</l>
<l>decreed and only we are living!”, Thus</l>
<l>Deucalion's plaint to Pyrrha;—and they wept.</l>

    
<l>And after he had spoken, they resolved</l>
<l>to ask the aid of sacred oracles,—</l>
<l>and so they hastened to Cephissian waves</l>
<l>which rolled a turbid flood in channels known.</l>
<l>Thence when their robes and brows were sprinkled well,</l>
<l>they turned their footsteps to the goddess' fane:</l>
<l>its gables were befouled with reeking moss</l>
<l>and on its altars every fire was cold.</l>
<l>But when the twain had reached the temple steps</l>
<l>they fell upon the earth, inspired with awe,</l>
<l>and kissed the cold stone with their trembling lips,</l>
<l>and said; “If righteous prayers appease the Gods,</l>
<l>and if the wrath of high celestial powers</l>
<l>may thus be turned, declare, O Themis! whence</l>
<l>and what the art may raise humanity?</l>
<l>O gentle goddess help the dying world!”</l>

    
<l>Moved by their supplications, she replied;</l>
<l>“Depart from me and veil your brows; ungird</l>
<l>your robes, and cast behind you as you go,</l>
<l>the bones of your great mother.” Long they stood</l>
<l>in dumb amazement: Pyrrha, first of voice,</l>
<l>refused the mandate and with trembling lips</l>
<l>implored the goddess to forgive—she feared</l>
<l>to violate her mother's bones and vex</l>
<l>her sacred spirit. Often pondered they</l>
<l>the words involved in such obscurity,</l>
<l>repeating oft: and thus Deucalion</l>
<l>to Epimetheus' daughter uttered speech</l>
<l>of soothing import; “ Oracles are just</l>
<l>and urge not evil deeds, or naught avails</l>
<l>the skill of thought. Our mother is the Earth,</l>
<l>and I may judge the stones of earth are bones</l>
<l>that we should cast behind us as we go.”</l>

    
<l>And although Pyrrha by his words was moved</l>
<l>she hesitated to comply; and both amazed</l>
<l>doubted the purpose of the oracle,</l>
<l>but deemed no harm to come of trial. They,</l>
<l>descending from the temple, veiled their heads</l>
<l>and loosed their robes and threw some stones</l>
<l>behind them. It is much beyond belief,</l>
<l>were not receding ages witness, hard</l>
<l>and rigid stones assumed a softer form,</l>
<l>enlarging as their brittle nature changed</l>
<l>to milder substance,—till the shape of man</l>
<l>appeared, imperfect, faintly outlined first,</l>
<l>as marble statue chiseled in the rough.</l>
<l>The soft moist parts were changed to softer flesh,</l>
<l>the hard and brittle substance into bones,</l>
<l>the veins retained their ancient name. And now</l>
<l>the Gods supreme ordained that every stone</l>
<l>Deucalion threw should take the form of man,</l>
<l>and those by Pyrrha cast should woman's form</l>
<l>assume: so are we hardy to endure</l>
<l>and prove by toil and deeds from what we sprung.</l>


Python.
THE PYTHIAN GAMES

<l>And after this the Earth spontaneous</l>
<l>produced the world of animals, when all</l>
<l>remaining moistures of the mirey fens</l>
<l>fermented in the sun, and fruitful seeds</l>
<l>in soils nutritious grew to shapes ordained.</l>
<l>So when the seven streamed Nile from oozy fields</l>
<l>returneth duly to her ancient bed,</l>
<l>the sun's ethereal rays impregn the slime,</l>
<l>that haply as the peasants turn the soil</l>
<l>they find strange animals unknown before:</l>
<l>some in the moment of their birth, and some</l>
<l>deprived of limbs, imperfect; often part</l>
<l>alive and part of slime inanimate</l>
<l>are fashioned in one body. Heat combined</l>
<l>with moisture so conceives and life results</l>
<l>from these two things. For though the flames may be</l>
<l>the foes of water, everything that lives</l>
<l>begins in humid vapour, and it seems</l>
<l>discordant concord is the means of life.</l>

    
<l>When Earth, spread over with diluvian ooze,</l>
<l>felt heat ethereal from the glowing sun,</l>
<l>unnumbered species to the light she gave,</l>
<l>and gave to being many an ancient form,</l>
<l>or monster new created. Unwilling she</l>
<l>created thus enormous Python.—Thou</l>
<l>unheard of serpent spread so far athwart</l>
<l>the side of a vast mountain, didst fill with fear</l>
<l>the race of new created man. The God</l>
<l>that bears the bow (a weapon used till then</l>
<l>only to hunt the deer and agile goat)</l>
<l>destroyed the monster with a myriad darts,</l>
<l>and almost emptied all his quiver, till</l>
<l>envenomed gore oozed forth from livid wounds.</l>

    
<l>Lest in a dark oblivion time should hide</l>
<l>the fame of this achievement, sacred sports</l>
<l>he instituted, from the Python called</l>
<l>“The Pythian Games.” In these the happy youth</l>
<l>who proved victorious in the chariot race,</l>
<l>running and boxing, with an honoured crown</l>
<l>of oak leaves was enwreathed. The laurel then</l>
<l>was not created, wherefore Phoebus, bright</l>
<l>and godlike, beauteous with his flowing hair,</l>
<l>was wont to wreathe his brows with various leaves.</l>


Daphne.
DAPHNE AND PHOEBUS

<l>Daphne, the daughter of a River God</l>
<l>was first beloved by Phoebus, the great God</l>
<l>of glorious light. 'Twas not a cause of chance</l>
<l>but out of Cupid's vengeful spite that she</l>
<l>was fated to torment the lord of light.</l>
<l>For Phoebus, proud of Python's death, beheld</l>
<l>that impish god of Love upon a time</l>
<l>when he was bending his diminished bow,</l>
<l>and voicing his contempt in anger said;</l>

<l>“What, wanton boy, are mighty arms to thee,</l>
<l>great weapons suited to the needs of war?</l>
<l>The bow is only for the use of those</l>
<l>large deities of heaven whose strength may deal</l>
<l>wounds, mortal, to the savage beasts of prey;</l>
<l>and who courageous overcome their foes.—</l>
<l>it is a proper weapon to the use</l>
<l>of such as slew with arrows Python, huge,</l>
<l>whose pestilential carcase vast extent</l>
<l>covered. Content thee with the flames thy torch</l>
<l>enkindles (fires too subtle for my thought)</l>
<l>and leave to me the glory that is mine.”</l>

    
<l>to him, undaunted, Venus, son replied;</l>
<l>“O Phoebus, thou canst conquer all the world</l>
<l>with thy strong bow and arrows, but with this</l>
<l>small arrow I shall pierce thy vaunting breast!</l>
<l>And by the measure that thy might exceeds</l>
<l>the broken powers of thy defeated foes,</l>
<l>so is thy glory less than mine.” No more</l>
<l>he said, but with his wings expanded thence</l>
<l>flew lightly to Parnassus, lofty peak.</l>
<l>There, from his quiver he plucked arrows twain,</l>
<l>most curiously wrought of different art;</l>
<l>one love exciting, one repelling love.</l>
<l>The dart of love was glittering, gold and sharp,</l>
<l>the other had a blunted tip of lead;</l>
<l>and with that dull lead dart he shot the Nymph,</l>
<l>but with the keen point of the golden dart</l>
<l>he pierced the bone and marrow of the God.</l>

    
<l>Immediately the one with love was filled,</l>
<l>the other, scouting at the thought of love,</l>
<l>rejoiced in the deep shadow of the woods,</l>
<l>and as the virgin Phoebe (who denies</l>
<l>the joys of love and loves the joys of chase)</l>
<l>a maiden's fillet bound her flowing hair,—</l>
<l>and her pure mind denied the love of man.</l>
<l>Beloved and wooed she wandered silent paths,</l>
<l>for never could her modesty endure</l>
<l>the glance of man or listen to his love.</l>

    
<l>Her grieving father spoke to her, “Alas,</l>
<l>my daughter, I have wished a son in law,</l>
<l>and now you owe a grandchild to the joy</l>
<l>of my old age.” But Daphne only hung</l>
<l>her head to hide her shame. The nuptial torch</l>
<l>seemed criminal to her. She even clung,</l>
<l>caressing, with her arms around his neck,</l>
<l>and pled, “My dearest father let me live</l>
<l>a virgin always, for remember Jove</l>
<l>did grant it to Diana at her birth.”</l>

    
<l>But though her father promised her desire,</l>
<l>her loveliness prevailed against their will;</l>
<l>for, Phoebus when he saw her waxed distraught,</l>
<l>and filled with wonder his sick fancy raised</l>
<l>delusive hopes, and his own oracles</l>
<l>deceived him.—As the stubble in the field</l>
<l>flares up, or as the stacked wheat is consumed</l>
<l>by flames, enkindled from a spark or torch</l>
<l>the chance pedestrian may neglect at dawn;</l>
<l>so was the bosom of the god consumed,</l>
<l>and so desire flamed in his stricken heart.</l>

    
<l>He saw her bright hair waving on her neck;—</l>
<l>“How beautiful if properly arranged! ”</l>
<l>He saw her eyes like stars of sparkling fire,</l>
<l>her lips for kissing sweetest, and her hands</l>
<l>and fingers and her arms; her shoulders white</l>
<l>as ivory;—and whatever was not seen</l>
<l>more beautiful must be.</l>

    
<l>Swift as the wind</l>
<l>from his pursuing feet the virgin fled,</l>
<l>and neither stopped nor heeded as he called;</l>
<l>“O Nymph! O Daphne! I entreat thee stay,</l>
<l>it is no enemy that follows thee—</l>
<l>why, so the lamb leaps from the raging wolf,</l>
<l>and from the lion runs the timid faun,</l>
<l>and from the eagle flies the trembling dove,</l>
<l>all hasten from their natural enemy</l>
<l>but I alone pursue for my dear love.</l>
<l>Alas, if thou shouldst fall and mar thy face,</l>
<l>or tear upon the bramble thy soft thighs,</l>
<l>or should I prove unwilling cause of pain!</l>

<l>“The wilderness is rough and dangerous,</l>
<l>and I beseech thee be more careful—I</l>
<l>will follow slowly.—Ask of whom thou wilt,</l>
<l>and thou shalt learn that I am not a churl—</l>
<l>I am no mountain dweller of rude caves,</l>
<l>nor clown compelled to watch the sheep and goats;</l>
<l>and neither canst thou know from whom thy feet</l>
<l>fly fearful, or thou wouldst not leave me thus.</l>

<l>“The Delphic Land, the Pataraean Realm,</l>
<l>Claros and Tenedos revere my name,</l>
<l>and my immortal sire is Jupiter.</l>
<l>The present, past and future are through me</l>
<l>in sacred oracles revealed to man,</l>
<l>and from my harp the harmonies of sound</l>
<l>are borrowed by their bards to praise the Gods.</l>
<l>My bow is certain, but a flaming shaft</l>
<l>surpassing mine has pierced my heart—</l>
<l>untouched before. The art of medicine</l>
<l>is my invention, and the power of herbs;</l>
<l>but though the world declare my useful works</l>
<l>there is no herb to medicate my wound,</l>
<l>and all the arts that save have failed their lord.,”</l>


    
<l>But even as he made his plaint, the Nymph</l>
<l>with timid footsteps fled from his approach,</l>
<l>and left him to his murmurs and his pain.</l>

    
<l>Lovely the virgin seemed as the soft wind</l>
<l>exposed her limbs, and as the zephyrs fond</l>
<l>fluttered amid her garments, and the breeze</l>
<l>fanned lightly in her flowing hair. She seemed</l>
<l>most lovely to his fancy in her flight;</l>
<l>and mad with love he followed in her steps,</l>
<l>and silent hastened his increasing speed.</l>

    
<l>As when the greyhound sees the frightened hare</l>
<l>flit over the plain:—With eager nose outstretched,</l>
<l>impetuous, he rushes on his prey,</l>
<l>and gains upon her till he treads her feet,</l>
<l>and almost fastens in her side his fangs;</l>

    
<l>but she, whilst dreading that her end is near,</l>
<l>is suddenly delivered from her fright;</l>
<l>so was it with the god and virgin: one</l>
<l>with hope pursued, the other fled in fear;</l>
<l>and he who followed, borne on wings of love,</l>
<l>permitted her no rest and gained on her,</l>
<l>until his warm breath mingled in her hair.</l>

    
<l>Her strength spent, pale and faint, with pleading eyes</l>
<l>she gazed upon her father's waves and prayed,</l>
<l>“Help me my father, if thy flowing streams</l>
<l>have virtue! Cover me, O mother Earth!</l>
<l>Destroy the beauty that has injured me,</l>
<l>or change the body that destroys my life.”</l>

    
<l>Before her prayer was ended, torpor seized</l>
<l>on all her body, and a thin bark closed</l>
<l>around her gentle bosom, and her hair</l>
<l>became as moving leaves; her arms were changed</l>
<l>to waving branches, and her active feet</l>
<l>as clinging roots were fastened to the ground—</l>
<l>her face was hidden with encircling leaves.—</l>

    
<l>Phoebus admired and loved the graceful tree,</l>
<l>(For still, though changed, her slender form remained)</l>
<l>and with his right hand lingering on the trunk</l>
<l>he felt her bosom throbbing in the bark.</l>
<l>He clung to trunk and branch as though to twine.</l>
<l>His form with hers, and fondly kissed the wood</l>
<l>that shrank from every kiss.</l>

    
<l>And thus the God;</l>
<l>“Although thou canst not be my bride, thou shalt</l>
<l>be called my chosen tree, and thy green leaves,</l>
<l>O Laurel! shall forever crown my brows,</l>
<l>be wreathed around my quiver and my lyre;</l>
<l>the Roman heroes shall be crowned with thee,</l>
<l>as long processions climb the Capitol</l>
<l>and chanting throngs proclaim their victories;</l>
<l>and as a faithful warden thou shalt guard</l>
<l>the civic crown of oak leaves fixed between</l>
<l>thy branches, and before Augustan gates.</l>
<l>And as my youthful head is never shorn,</l>
<l>so, also, shalt thou ever bear thy leaves</l>
<l>unchanging to thy glory.,”</l>

    
<l>Here the God,</l>
<l>Phoebus Apollo, ended his lament,</l>
<l>and unto him the Laurel bent her boughs,</l>
<l>so lately fashioned; and it seemed to him</l>
<l>her graceful nod gave answer to his love.</l>


Io. Argus. Syrinx.
IO AND JUPITER	

<l>There is a grove in Thessaly, enclosed</l>
<l>on every side with crags, precipitous,—</l>
<l>on which a forest grows—and this is called</l>
<l>the Vale of Tempe—through this valley flows</l>
<l>the River Peneus, white with foaming waves,</l>
<l>that issue from the foot of Pindus, whence</l>
<l>with sudden fall up gather steamy clouds</l>
<l>that sprinkle mist upon the circling trees,</l>
<l>and far away with mighty roar resound.</l>
<l>It is the abode, the solitary home,</l>
<l>that mighty River loves, where deep in gloom</l>
<l>of rocky cavern, he resides and rules</l>
<l>the flowing waters and the water nymphs</l>
<l>abiding there. All rivers of that land</l>
<l>now hasten thither, doubtful to console</l>
<l>or flatter Daphne's parent: poplar crowned</l>
<l>Sperchios, swift Enipeus and the wild</l>
<l>Amphrysos, old Apidanus and Aeas,</l>
<l>with all their kindred streams that wandering maze</l>
<l>and wearied seek the ocean. Inachus</l>
<l>alone is absent, hidden in his cave</l>
<l>obscure, deepening his waters with his tears—</l>
<l>most wretchedly bewailing, for he deems</l>
<l>his daughter Io lost. If she may live</l>
<l>or roam a spirit in the nether shades</l>
<l>he dares not even guess but dreads</l>

    
<l>for Jove not long before had seen her while</l>
<l>returning from her father's stream, and said;</l>
<l>“O virgin, worthy of immortal Jove,</l>
<l>although some happy mortal's chosen bride,—</l>
<l>behold these shades of overhanging trees,</l>
<l>and seek their cool recesses while the sun</l>
<l>is glowing in the height of middle skies—”</l>
<l>and as he spoke he pointed out the groves—</l>
<l>“But should the dens of wild beasts frighten you,</l>
<l>with safety you may enter the deep woods,</l>
<l>conducted by a God—not with a God</l>
<l>of small repute, but in the care of him</l>
<l>who holds the heavenly scepter in his hand</l>
<l>and fulminates the trackless thunder bolts.—</l>
<l>forsake me not! ” For while he spoke she fled,</l>
<l>and swiftly left behind the pasture fields</l>
<l>of Lerna, and Lyrcea's arbours, where</l>
<l>the trees are planted thickly. But the God</l>
<l>called forth a heavy shadow which involved</l>
<l>the wide extended earth, and stopped her flight</l>
<l>and ravished in that cloud her chastity.</l>

    
<l>Meanwhile, the goddess Juno gazing down</l>
<l>on earth's expanse, with wonder saw the clouds</l>
<l>as dark as night enfold those middle fields</l>
<l>while day was bright above. She was convinced</l>
<l>the clouds were none composed of river mist</l>
<l>nor raised from marshy fens. Suspicious now,</l>
<l>from oft detected amours of her spouse,</l>
<l>she glanced around to find her absent lord,</l>
<l>and quite convinced that he was far from heaven,</l>
<l>she thus exclaimed; “This cloud deceives my mind,</l>
<l>or Jove has wronged me.” From the dome of heaven</l>
<l>she glided down and stood upon the earth,</l>
<l>and bade the clouds recede. But Jove had known</l>
<l>the coming of his queen. He had transformed</l>
<l>the lovely Io, so that she appeared</l>
<l>a milk white heifer—formed so beautiful</l>
<l>and fair that envious Juno gazed on her.</l>
<l>She queried: “Whose? what herd? what pasture fields?”</l>
<l>As if she guessed no knowledge of the truth.</l>
<l>And Jupiter, false hearted, said the cow</l>
<l>was earth begotten, for he feared his queen</l>
<l>might make inquiry of the owner's name.</l>
<l>Juno implored the heifer as a gift.—</l>
<l>what then was left the Father of the Gods?</l>
<l>'Twould be a cruel thing to sacrifice</l>
<l>his own beloved to a rival's wrath.</l>
<l>Although refusal must imply his guilt</l>
<l>the shame and love of her almost prevailed;</l>
<l>but if a present of such little worth</l>
<l>were now denied the sharer of his couch,</l>
<l>the partner of his birth, 'twould prove indeed</l>
<l>the earth born heifer other than she seemed—</l>
<l>and so he gave his mistress up to her.</l>

    
<l>Juno regardful of Jove's cunning art,</l>
<l>lest he might change her to her human form,</l>
<l>gave the unhappy heifer to the charge</l>
<l>of Argus, Aristorides, whose head</l>
<l>was circled with a hundred glowing eyes;</l>
<l>of which but two did slumber in their turn</l>
<l>whilst all the others kept on watch and guard.</l>

    
<l>Whichever way he stood his gaze was fixed</l>
<l>on Io—even if he turned away</l>
<l>his watchful eyes on Io still remained.</l>
<l>He let her feed by day; but when the sun</l>
<l>was under the deep world he shut her up,</l>
<l>and tied a rope around her tender neck.</l>

    
<l>She fed upon green leaves and bitter herbs </l>
<l>and on the cold ground slept—too often bare,</l>
<l>she could not rest upon a cushioned couch.</l>
<l>She drank the troubled waters. Hoping aid</l>
<l>she tried to stretch imploring arms to Argus,</l>
<l>but all in vain for now no arms remained;</l>
<l>the sound of bellowing was all she heard,</l>
<l>and she was frightened with her proper voice.</l>

    
<l>Where former days she loved to roam and sport,</l>
<l>she wandered by the banks of Inachus:</l>
<l>there imaged in the stream she saw her horns</l>
<l>and, startled, turned and fled. And Inachus</l>
<l>and all her sister Naiads knew her not,</l>
<l>although she followed them, they knew her not,</l>
<l>although she suffered them to touch her sides</l>
<l>and praise her.</l>

    
<l>When the ancient Inachus</l>
<l>gathered sweet herbs and offered them to her,</l>
<l>she licked his hands, kissing her father's palms,</l>
<l>nor could she more restrain her falling tears.</l>
<l>If only words as well as tears would flow,</l>
<l>she might implore his aid and tell her name</l>
<l>and all her sad misfortune; but, instead,</l>
<l>she traced in dust the letters of her name</l>
<l>with cloven hoof; and thus her sad estate</l>
<l>was known.</l>


<l>“Ah wretched me! ” her father cried;</l>
<l>and as he clung around her horns and neck</l>
<l>repeated while she groaned, “Ah wretched me!</l>
<l>Art thou my daughter sought in every clime?</l>
<l>When lost I could not grieve for thee as now</l>
<l>that thou art found; thy sighs instead of words</l>
<l>heave up from thy deep breast, thy longings give</l>
<l>me answer. I prepared the nuptial torch</l>
<l>and bridal chamber, in my ignorance,</l>
<l>since my first hope was for a son in law;</l>
<l>and then I dreamed of children from the match:</l>
<l>but now the herd may furnish thee a mate,</l>
<l>and all thy issue of the herd must be.</l>
<l>Oh that a righteous death would end my grief!—</l>
<l>it is a dreadful thing to be a God!</l>
<l>Behold the lethal gate of death is shut</l>
<l>against me, and my growing grief must last</l>
<l>throughout eternity.”</l>

    
<l>While thus he moaned</l>
<l>came starry Argus there, and Io bore</l>
<l>from her lamenting father. Thence he led</l>
<l>his charge to other pastures; and removed</l>
<l>from her, upon a lofty mountain sat,</l>
<l>whence he could always watch her, undisturbed.</l>

    
<l>The sovereign god no longer could endure</l>
<l>to witness Io's woes. He called his son,</l>
<l>whom Maia brightest of the Pleiades</l>
<l>brought forth, and bade him slay the star eyed guard,</l>
<l>argus. He seized his sleep compelling wand</l>
<l>and fastened waving wings on his swift feet,</l>
<l>and deftly fixed his brimmed hat on his head:—</l>
<l>lo, Mercury, the favoured son of Jove,</l>
<l>descending to the earth from heaven's plains,</l>
<l>put off his cap and wings,— though still retained</l>
<l>his wand with which he drove through pathless wilds</l>
<l>some stray she goats, and as a shepherd fared,</l>
<l>piping on oaten reeds melodious tunes.</l>

    
<l>Argus, delighted with the charming sound</l>
<l>of this new art began; “Whoever thou art,</l>
<l>sit with me on this stone beneath the trees</l>
<l>in cooling shade, whilst browse the tended flock</l>
<l>abundant herbs; for thou canst see the shade</l>
<l>is fit for shepherds.” Wherefore, Mercury</l>
<l>sat down beside the keeper and conversed</l>
<l>of various things—passing the laggard hours.—</l>

    
<l>then soothly piped he on the joined reeds</l>
<l>to lull those ever watchful eyes asleep;</l>
<l>but Argus strove his languor to subdue,</l>
<l>and though some drowsy eyes might slumber, still</l>
<l>were some that vigil kept. Again he spoke,</l>
<l>(for the pipes were yet a recent art)</l>
<l>“I pray thee tell what chance discovered these.”</l>

    
<l>To him the God, “ A famous Naiad dwelt</l>
<l>among the Hamadryads, on the cold</l>
<l>Arcadian summit Nonacris, whose name</l>
<l>was Syrinx. Often she escaped the Gods,</l>
<l>that wandered in the groves of sylvan shades,</l>
<l>and often fled from Satyrs that pursued.</l>
<l>Vowing virginity, in all pursuits</l>
<l>she strove to emulate Diana's ways:</l>
<l>and as that graceful goddess wears her robe,</l>
<l>so Syrinx girded hers that one might well</l>
<l>believe Diana there. Even though her bow</l>
<l>were made of horn, Diana's wrought of gold,</l>
<l>vet might she well deceive.</l>

<l>“Now chanced it Pan.</l>
<l>Whose head was girt with prickly pines, espied</l>
<l>the Nymph returning from the Lycian Hill,</l>
<l>and these words uttered he: ”—But Mercury</l>
<l>refrained from further speech, and Pan's appeal</l>
<l>remains untold. If he had told it all,</l>
<l>the tale of Syrinx would have followed thus:—</l>

    
<l>but she despised the prayers of Pan, and fled</l>
<l>through pathless wilds until she had arrived</l>
<l>the placid Ladon's sandy stream, whose waves</l>
<l>prevented her escape. There she implored</l>
<l>her sister Nymphs to change her form: and Pan,</l>
<l>believing he had caught her, held instead</l>
<l>some marsh reeds for the body of the Nymph;</l>
<l>and while he sighed the moving winds began</l>
<l>to utter plaintive music in the reeds,</l>
<l>so sweet and voice like that poor Pan exclaimed;</l>
<l>“Forever this discovery shall remain</l>
<l>a sweet communion binding thee to me.”—</l>
<l>and this explains why reeds of different length,</l>
<l>when joined together by cementing wax,</l>
<l>derive the name of Syrinx from the maid.</l>


    
<l>Such words the bright god Mercury would say;</l>
<l>but now perceiving Argus' eyes were dimmed</l>
<l>in languorous doze, he hushed his voice and touched</l>
<l>the drooping eyelids with his magic wand,</l>
<l>compelling slumber. Then without delay</l>
<l>he struck the sleeper with his crescent sword,</l>
<l>where neck and head unite, and hurled his head,</l>
<l>blood dripping, down the rocks and rugged cliff.</l>

    
<l>Low lies Argus: dark is the light of all</l>
<l>his hundred eyes, his many orbed lights</l>
<l>extinguished in the universal gloom</l>
<l>that night surrounds; but Saturn's daughter spread</l>
<l>their glister on the feathers of her bird,</l>
<l>emblazoning its tail with starry gems.</l>

    
<l>Juno made haste, inflamed with towering rage,</l>
<l>to vent her wrath on Io; and she raised</l>
<l>in thought and vision of the Grecian girl</l>
<l>a dreadful Fury. Stings invisible,</l>
<l>and pitiless, she planted in her breast,</l>
<l>and drove her wandering throughout the globe.</l>

    
<l>The utmost limit of her laboured way,</l>
<l>O Nile, thou didst remain. Which, having reached,</l>
<l>and placed her tired knees on that river's edge,</l>
<l>she laid her there, and as she raised her neck</l>
<l>looked upward to the stars, and groaned and wept</l>
<l>and mournfully bellowed: trying thus to plead,</l>
<l>by all the means she had, that Jupiter</l>
<l>might end her miseries. Repentant Jove</l>
<l>embraced his consort, and entreated her</l>
<l>to end the punishment: “Fear not,” he said,</l>
<l>“For she shall trouble thee no more.” He spoke,</l>
<l>and called on bitter Styx to hear his oath.</l>

    
<l>And now imperial Juno, pacified,</l>
<l>permitted Io to resume her form,—</l>
<l>at once the hair fell from her snowy sides;</l>
<l>the horns absorbed, her dilate orbs decreased;</l>
<l>the opening of her jaws contracted; hands</l>
<l>appeared and shoulders; and each transformed hoof</l>
<l>became five nails. And every mark or form</l>
<l>that gave the semblance of a heifer changed,</l>
<l>except her fair white skin; and the glad Nymph</l>
<l>was raised erect and stood upon her feet.</l>
<l>But long the very thought of speech, that she</l>
<l>might bellow as a heifer, filled her mind</l>
<l>with terror, till the words so long forgot</l>
<l>for some sufficient cause were tried once more.</l>


Phaethon.
<l>and since that time, the linen wearing throng</l>
<l>of Egypt have adored her as a God;</l>
<l>for they believe the seed of Jove prevailed;</l>
<l>and when her time was due she bore to him</l>
<l>a son called Epaphus; who also dwells</l>
<l>in temples with his mother in that land.</l>

    
<l>Now Phaethon, whose father was the Sun,</l>
<l>was equal to his rival, Epaphus,</l>
<l>in mind and years; and he was glad to boast</l>
<l>of wonders, nor would yield to Epaphus</l>
<l>for pride of Phoebus, his reputed sire.</l>
<l>Unable to endure it, Io's son</l>
<l>thus mocked him; “Poor, demented fellow, what</l>
<l>will you not credit if your mother speaks,</l>
<l>you are so puffed up with the fond conceit</l>
<l>of your imagined sire, the Lord of Day.”</l>

    
<l>shame crimsoned in his cheeks, but Phaethon</l>
<l>withholding rage, reported all the taunts</l>
<l>of Epaphus to Clymene his mother:</l>
<l>“'Twill grieve you, mother, I, the bold and free,</l>
<l>was silent; and it shames me to report</l>
<l>this dark reproach remains unchallenged. Oh,</l>
<l>if I am born of race divine, give proof</l>
<l>of that illustrious descent and claim</l>
<l>my right to Heaven.” Around his mother's neck</l>
<l>he drew his arms, and by the head of Merops,</l>
<l>and by his own, and by the nuptial torch</l>
<l>of his beloved sisters, he implored</l>
<l>for some true token of his origin.</l>

    
<l>Or moved by Phaethon's importuned words,</l>
<l>or by the grievous charge, who might declare?</l>
<l>She raised her arms to Heaven, and gazing full</l>
<l>upon the broad sun said; “I swear to you</l>
<l>by yonder orb, so radiant and bright,</l>
<l>which both beholds and hears us while we speak,</l>
<l>that you are his begotten son.—You are</l>
<l>the child of that great light which sways the world:</l>
<l>and if I have not spoken what is true,</l>
<l>let not mine eyes behold his countenance,</l>
<l>and let this fatal moment be the last</l>
<l>that I shall look upon the light of day!</l>
<l>Nor will it weary you, my son, to reach</l>
<l>your father's dwelling; for the very place</l>
<l>where he appears at dawn is near our land.</l>
<l>Go, if it please you, and the very truth</l>
<l>learn from your father.” Instantly sprang forth</l>
<l>exultant Phaethon. Overjoyed with words</l>
<l>so welcome, he imagined he could leap</l>
<l>and touch the skies. And so he passed his land</l>
<l>of Ethiopia, and the Indies, hot</l>
<l>beneath the tawny sun, and there he turned</l>
<l>his footsteps to his father's Land of Dawn.</l>