<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 5


BATTLE OF THE WEDDING FEASTPERSEUS AND ANDROMEDA

<l>While Perseus, the brave son of Jupiter,</l>
<l>surrounded at the feast by Cepheus' lords,</l>
<l>narrated this, a raging multitude</l>
<l>with sudden outcry filled the royal courts—</l>
<l>not with the clamours of a wedding feast</l>
<l>but boisterous rage, portentous of dread war.</l>

    
<l>As when the fury of a great wind strikes</l>
<l>a tranquil sea, tempestuous billows roll</l>
<l>across the peaceful bosom of the deep;</l>
<l>so were the pleasures at the banquet changed</l>
<l>to sudden tumult.</l>

    
<l>Foremost of that throng,</l>
<l>the rash ring-leader, Phineus, shook his spear,</l>
<l>brass-tipped of ash, and shouted, “Ha, 'tis I!</l>
<l>I come avenger of my ravished bride!</l>
<l>Let now your flittering wings deliver you,</l>
<l>or even Jupiter, dissolved in showers</l>
<l>of imitation gold.” So boasted he,</l>
<l>aiming his spear at Perseus.</l>

    
<l>Thus to him</l>
<l>cried Cepheus: “Hold your hand, and strike him not!</l>
<l>What strange delusions, O my brother, have</l>
<l>compelled you to this crime? Is it the just</l>
<l>requital of heroic worth? A fair</l>
<l>reguerdon for the life of her you loved?</l>

    
<l>“If truth were known, not Perseus ravished her</l>
<l>from you; but, either 'twas the awful God</l>
<l>that rules the Nereides; or Ammon, crowned</l>
<l>with crescent horns; or that monstrosity</l>
<l>of Ocean's vast abyss, which came to glut</l>
<l>his famine on the issue of my loins.</l>
<l>Nor was your suit abandoned till the time</l>
<l>when she must perish and be lost to you.</l>
<l>So cruel are you, seeking my daughter's death,</l>
<l>rejoicing lightly in our deep despair.—</l>

    
<l>“And was it not enough for you to stand</l>
<l>supinely by, while she was bound in chains,</l>
<l>and offer no assistance, though you were</l>
<l>her lover and betrothed? And will you grieve</l>
<l>that she was rescued from a dreadful fate,</l>
<l>and spoil her champion of his just rewards?</l>
<l>Rewards that now may seem magnificent,</l>
<l>but not denied to you if you had won</l>
<l>and saved, when she was fettered to the rock.</l>

    
<l>“Let him, whose strength to my declining years</l>
<l>restored my child, receive the merit due</l>
<l>his words and deeds; and know his suit was not</l>
<l>preferred to yours, but granted to prevent</l>
<l>her certain death.”</l>

    
<l>not deigning to reply,</l>
<l>against them Phineus stood; and glancing back</l>
<l>from him to Perseus, with alternate looks,</l>
<l>as doubtful which should feel his first attack,</l>
<l>made brief delay. Then vain at Perseus hurled</l>
<l>his spear, with all the force that rage inspired,</l>
<l>but, missing him it quivered in a couch.</l>

    
<l>Provoked beyond endurance Perseus leaped</l>
<l>forth from the cushioned seats, and fiercely sent</l>
<l>that outwrenched weapon back. It would have pierced</l>
<l>his hostile breast had not the miscreant crouched</l>
<l>behind the altars. Oh perverted good,</l>
<l>that thus an altar should abet the wrong!</l>

    
<l>But, though the craven Phineus escaped,</l>
<l>not vainly flew the whizzing point, but struck</l>
<l>in Rhoetus' forehead. As the barb was torn</l>
<l>out of the bone, the victim's heels began</l>
<l>to kick upon the floor, and spouting blood</l>
<l>defiled the festal board. Then truly flame</l>
<l>in uncontrolled rage the vulgar crowd,</l>
<l>and hurl their harmful darts.</l>

    
<l>And there are some</l>
<l>who hold that Cepheus and his son-in-law</l>
<l>deserved to die; but Cepheus had passed forth</l>
<l>the threshold of his palace: having called</l>
<l>on all the Gods of Hospitality</l>
<l>and Truth and Justice to attest, he gave</l>
<l>no comfort to the enemies of Peace.</l>

    
<l>Unconquered Pallas is at hand and holds</l>
<l>her Aegis to protect her brother's life;</l>
<l>she lends him dauntless courage. At the feast</l>
<l>was one from India's distant shores, whose name</l>
<l>was Athis. It was said that Limnate,</l>
<l>the daughter of the River Ganges, him</l>
<l>in vitreous caverns bright had brought to birth;</l>
<l>and now at sixteen summers in his prime,</l>
<l>the handsome youth was clad in costly robes.</l>

    
<l>A purple mantle with a golden fringe</l>
<l>covered his shoulders, and a necklace, carved</l>
<l>of gold, enhanced the beauty of his throat.</l>
<l>His hair encompassed with a coronal,</l>
<l>delighted with sweet myrrh. Well taught was he</l>
<l>to hurl the javelin at a distant mark,</l>
<l>and none with better skill could stretch the bow.</l>

    
<l>No sooner had he bent the pliant horns</l>
<l>than Perseus, with a smoking billet, seized</l>
<l>from the mid-altar, struck him on the face,</l>
<l>and smashed his features in his broken skull.</l>

    
<l>And when Assyrian Lycabas had seen</l>
<l>his dear companion, whom he truly loved,</l>
<l>beating his handsome countenance in blood.</l>
<l>And when he had bewailed his lost life,</l>
<l>that ebbed away from that unpiteous wound,</l>
<l>he snatched the bow that Athis used, and said;</l>

<l>“Let us in single combat seek revenge;</l>
<l>not long will you rejoice the stripling's fate;</l>
<l>a deed most worthy shame.” So speaking, forth</l>
<l>the piercing arrow bounded from the cord,</l>
<l>which, though avoided, struck the hero's cloak</l>
<l>and fastened in its folds.—</l>

    
<l>Then Perseus turned</l>
<l>upon him, with the trusted curving sword,</l>
<l>cause of Medusa's death, and drove the blade</l>
<l>deep in his breast. The dying victim's eyes,</l>
<l>now swimming in a shadowous night, looked 'round</l>
<l>for Athis, whom, beholding, he reclined</l>
<l>upon, and ushered to the other world,—</l>
<l>sad consolation of united death.</l>


    
<l>And Phorbas the descendant of Methion.</l>
<l>Who hailed from far Syene, with his friend</l>
<l>Amphimedon of Libya, in their haste</l>
<l>to join the battle, slipped up in the blood</l>
<l>and fell together: just as they arose</l>
<l>that glittering sword was driven through the throat</l>
<l>of Phorbas into the ribs of his companion.</l>

    
<l>But Erithus, the son of Actor, swung</l>
<l>a battle-ax, so weighty, Perseus chose</l>
<l>not combat with his curving blade. He seized</l>
<l>in his two hands a huge bowl, wrought around</l>
<l>with large design, outstanding from its mass.</l>

    
<l>This, lifting up, he dashes on his foe,</l>
<l>who vomits crimson blood, and falling back</l>
<l>beats on the hard floor with his dying head.</l>

    
<l>And next he slew Caucasian Abaris,</l>
<l>and Polydaemon—from Semiramis</l>
<l>nobly descended—and Sperchius, son,</l>
<l>Lycetus, long-haired Elyces, unshorn,</l>
<l>Clytus and Phlegias, the hero slew;—</l>
<l>and trampled on the dying heaped around.</l>

    
<l>Not daring to engage his enemy</l>
<l>in open contest, Phineus held aloof,</l>
<l>and hurled his javelin. Badly aimed—by some</l>
<l>mischance or turned—it wounded Idas, who</l>
<l>had followed neither side; vain-hoping thus</l>
<l>to shun the conflict.</l>

    
<l>Idas, filled with rage,</l>
<l>on Phineus gazed with futile hate, and said,</l>
<l>“Since I am forced unwilling to such deeds,</l>
<l>behold, whom you have made your enemy,</l>
<l>O savage Phineus! Let your recompense</l>
<l>be stroke for stroke.” So speaking, from the wound</l>
<l>he drew the steel, but, faint from loss of blood,</l>
<l>before his arm could hurl the weapon back,</l>
<l>he sank upon his knees.</l>

    
<l>Here, also, lies</l>
<l>Odytes,—noblest of the Cephenes,</l>
<l>save Cepheus only,—slaughtered by the sword</l>
<l>of Clymenus. And Prothoenor lies</l>
<l>the victim of Hypseus; by his side</l>
<l>Hypseus slaughtered by Lyncidas falls.</l>

    
<l>And in the midst of this destruction stood</l>
<l>Emathion, now an aged man, revered,</l>
<l>who feared the Gods, and stood for upright deeds.</l>
<l>And, since his years denied him strength for war,</l>
<l>he battled with his tongue, and railed, and cursed</l>
<l>their impious weapons. As that aged man</l>
<l>clings to the altar with his trembling hands,</l>
<l>Chromis with ruthless sword cuts off his head,</l>
<l>which straightway falls upon the altar, whence</l>
<l>his dying tongue denounces them in words</l>
<l>of execration: and his soul expires</l>
<l>amid the altar flames.</l>

    
<l>Then Broteas</l>
<l>and Ammon, his twin brother, who not knew</l>
<l>their equals at the cestus, by the hand</l>
<l>of Phineus fell; for what avails in deed</l>
<l>the cestus as a weapon matched with swords.</l>
<l>Ampycus by the same hand fell,—the priest</l>
<l>of Ceres, with his temples wreathed in white.</l>

    
<l>And O, Iapetides not for this</l>
<l>did you attend the feast! Your voice attuned</l>
<l>melodious to the harp, was in request</l>
<l>to celebrate the wedding-day with song,—</l>
<l>a work of peace; as you did stand aside,</l>
<l>holding the peaceful plectrum in your hand,</l>
<l>the mocking Pettalus in ridicule said,</l>
<l>“Go sing your ditties to the Stygian shades.”</l>
<l>And, mocking thus, he drove his pointed sword</l>
<l>in your right temple. As your limbs gave way,</l>
<l>your dying fingers swept the tuneful strings:</l>
<l>and falling you did chant a mournful dirge.—</l>
<l>You to avenge enraged Lycormas tore</l>
<l>a huge bar from the door-post, on the right,</l>
<l>and dashing it against the mocker crushed</l>
<l>his neck-bones: as a slaughtered bullock falls—</l>
<l>he tumbled to the ground.</l>

    
<l>Then on the left.</l>
<l>Cinyphian Pelates began to wrench</l>
<l>an oak plank from the door-post, but the spear</l>
<l>of Corythus, the son of Marmarus,</l>
<l>pinioned his right hand to the wooden post;</l>
<l>and while he struggled Abas pierced his side.—</l>
<l>He fell not to the floor, but dying hung</l>
<l>suspended from the door-post by his hand.</l>

    
<l>And of the friends of Perseus, Melaneus</l>
<l>was slain, and Dorylas whose wealth was large</l>
<l>in Nasamonian land. No other lord,</l>
<l>as Dorylas, such vast estates possessed;</l>
<l>no other owned so many heaps of corn.</l>
<l>The missile steel stood fastened in his groin,</l>
<l>obliquely fixed,—a fatal spot—and when</l>
<l>the author of his wound, Halcyoneus</l>
<l>the Bactrian, beheld his victim thus,</l>
<l>rolling his eyes and sobbing forth his soul,</l>
<l>he railed; “Keep for yourself of all your lands</l>
<l>as much as you can cover.” And he left</l>
<l>the bleeding corpse.</l>

    
<l>But Perseus in revenge</l>
<l>hurled after him a spear, which, in his need,</l>
<l>he ripped out from the wound, yet warm, and struck</l>
<l>the boaster on the middle of his nose.</l>
<l>The piercing steel, passed through his nose and neck,—</l>
<l>remained projecting from the front and back.</l>

    
<l>And while good fortune helped his hand, he slew</l>
<l>Clanis and Clytius, of one mother born,</l>
<l>but with a different wound he slaughtered each:</l>
<l>for, leveled by a mighty arm, his ashen spear</l>
<l>drove through the thighs of Clytius, right and left,</l>
<l>and Clanis bit the javelin with his teeth.</l>

    
<l>And by his might, Mendesian Celadon</l>
<l>and Atreus fell, his mother of the tribes</l>
<l>of Palestine, his father was unknown.</l>
<l>Aethion, also, who could well foresee</l>
<l>the things to come, but was at last deceived</l>
<l>by some false omen. And Thoactes fell,</l>
<l>the armour-bearer of the king; and, next,</l>
<l>the infamous Agyrtes who had slain</l>
<l>his father. These he slew; and though his strength</l>
<l>was nearly spent, so many more remained:</l>
<l>for now the multitude with one accord</l>
<l>conspired to slaughter him. From every side</l>
<l>the raging troops assailed the better cause.</l>

    
<l>In vain the pious father and the bride,</l>
<l>together with her mother, fill the halls</l>
<l>with lamentations; for the clash of arms,</l>
<l>the groans of fallen heroes drown their cries.—</l>
<l>Bellona in a sea of blood has drenched</l>
<l>their Household Gods, polluted by these deeds,</l>
<l>and she endeavours to renew the strife.</l>

    
<l>Perseus, alone against that raging throng,</l>
<l>is now surrounded by a myriad men,</l>
<l>led on by Phineus; and their flying darts,</l>
<l>as thick as wintry tail, are showered around</l>
<l>on every side, grazing his eyes and ears.—</l>
<l>Quickly he fixed his shoulder firm against</l>
<l>the rock of a great pillar, which secured</l>
<l>his back from danger, and he faced his foes,</l>
<l>and baffled their attack.</l>

    
<l>Upon his left</l>
<l>Chaonian Molpeus pressed, and on his right</l>
<l>a Nabathe an called Ethemon pressed.—</l>

    
<l>As when a tiger from a valley hears</l>
<l>the lowing of two herds, in separate fields,</l>
<l>though hunger urges he not knows on which</l>
<l>to spring, but rages equally for each;</l>
<l>so, Perseus doubtful which may first attack</l>
<l>his left or right, knows not on which to turn,</l>
<l>but stands attentive witness to the flight</l>
<l>of Molpeus, whom he wounded in the leg.</l>

    
<l>Nor could he choose—Ethemon, full of rage,</l>
<l>pressed on him to inflict a fatal wound,</l>
<l>deep in his neck; but with incautious force</l>
<l>struck the stone pillar with his ringing sword</l>
<l>and shattered the metal blade, close to the hilt;</l>
<l>the flying fragment pierced its owner's neck,</l>
<l>but not with mortal wound. In vain he pled</l>
<l>for mercy, stretching forth his helpless arms:</l>
<l>perseus transfixed him with his glittering blade,</l>
<l>Cyllenian.</l>


    
<l>But when he saw his strength</l>
<l>was yielding to the multitude, he said,</l>
<l>“Since you have forced disaster on yourselves,</l>
<l>why should I hesitate to save myself?—</l>
<l>O friends, avert your faces if ye stand</l>
<l>before me!” And he raised Medusa,s head.</l>

    
<l>Thescelus answered him; “Seek other dupes</l>
<l>to chase with wonders!” Just as he prepared</l>
<l>to hurl the deadly javelin from his hand,</l>
<l>he stood, unmoving in that attitude,</l>
<l>a marble statue.</l>

    
<l>Ampyx, close to him,</l>
<l>exulting in a mighty spirit, made</l>
<l>a lunge to pierce Lyncides in the breast;</l>
<l>but, as his sword was flashing in the air,</l>
<l>his right arm grew so rigid, there he stood</l>
<l>unable to draw back or thrust it forth.</l>

    
<l>But Nileus, who had feigned himself begot</l>
<l>by seven-fold Nile, and carved his shield with gold</l>
<l>and silver streams, alternate seven, shouted;</l>
<l>“Look, look! O Perseus, him from whom I sprung!</l>
<l>And you shall carry to the silent shades</l>
<l>a mighty consolation in your death,</l>
<l>that you were slain by such a one as I.”</l>
<l>But in the midst of boasting, the last words</l>
<l>were silenced; and his open mouth, although</l>
<l>incapable of motion, seemed intent</l>
<l>to utter speech.</l>

    
<l>Then Eryx, chiding says;</l>
<l>“Your craven spirits have benumbed you, not</l>
<l>Medusa's poison.—Come with me and strike</l>
<l>this youthful mover of magician charms</l>
<l>down to the ground.”—He started with a rush;</l>
<l>the earth detained his steps; it held him fast;</l>
<l>he could not speak; he stood, complete with arms,</l>
<l>a statue.</l>

    
<l>Such a penalty was theirs,</l>
<l>and justly earned; but near by there was one,</l>
<l>aconteus, who defending Perseus, saw</l>
<l>medusa as he fought; and at the sight</l>
<l>the soldier hardened to an upright stone.—</l>
<l>Assured he was alive, Astyages</l>
<l>now struck him with his long sword, but the blade</l>
<l>resounded with a ringing note; and there,</l>
<l>astonished at the sound, Astyages,</l>
<l>himself, assumed that nature; and remained</l>
<l>with wonder pictured on his marble face.</l>

    
<l>And not to weary with the names of men,</l>
<l>sprung from the middle classes, there remained</l>
<l>two hundred warriors eager for the fight—</l>
<l>as soon as they could see Medusa's face,</l>
<l>two hundred warriors stiffened into stone.</l>

    
<l>At last, repentant, Phineus dreads the war,</l>
<l>unjust, for in a helpless fright he sees</l>
<l>the statues standing in strange attitudes;</l>
<l>and, recognizing his adherents, calls</l>
<l>on each by name to rescue from that death.</l>
<l>Still unbelieving he begins to touch</l>
<l>the bodies, nearest to himself, and all</l>
<l>are hard stone.</l>

    
<l>Having turned his eyes away,</l>
<l>he stretched his hands and arms obliquely back</l>
<l>to Perseus, and confessed his wicked deeds;</l>
<l>and thus imploring spoke;</l>

<l>“Remove, I pray,</l>
<l>O Perseus, thou invincible, remove</l>
<l>from me that dreadful Gorgon: take away</l>
<l>the stone-creating countenance of thy</l>
<l>unspeakable Medusa! For we warred</l>
<l>not out of hatred, nor to gain a throne,</l>
<l>but clashed our weapons for a woman's sake.—</l>

    
<l>“Thy merit proved thy valid claim, and time</l>
<l>gave argument for mine. It grieves me not</l>
<l>to yield, O bravest, only give me life,</l>
<l>and all the rest be thine.” Such words implored</l>
<l>the craven, never daring to address</l>
<l>his eyes to whom he spoke.</l>

    
<l>And thus returned</l>
<l>the valiant Perseus; “I will grant to you,</l>
<l>O timid-hearted Phineus! as behoves</l>
<l>your conduct; and it should appear a gift,</l>
<l>magnanimous, to one who fears to move.—</l>
<l>Take courage, for no steel shall violate</l>
<l>your carcase; and, moreover, you shall be</l>
<l>a monument, that ages may record</l>
<l>your unforgotten name. You shall be seen</l>
<l>thus always, in the palace where resides</l>
<l>my father-in-law, that my surrendered spouse</l>
<l>may soften her great grief when she but sees</l>
<l>the darling image of her first betrothed.”</l>

    
<l>He spoke, and moved Medusa to that side</l>
<l>where Phineus had turned his trembling face:</l>
<l>and as he struggled to avert his gaze</l>
<l>his neck grew stiff; the moisture of his eyes</l>
<l>was hardened into stone.—And since that day</l>
<l>his timid face and coward eyes and hands,</l>
<l>forever shall be guilty as in life.</l>

    
<l>After such deeds, victorious Perseus turned,</l>
<l>and sought the confines of his native land;</l>
<l>together with his bride; which, having reached,</l>
<l>he punished Proetus—who by force of arms</l>
<l>had routed his own brother from the throne</l>
<l>of Argos. By his aid Acrisius,</l>
<l>although his undeserving parent, gained</l>
<l>his citadels once more: for Proetus failed,</l>
<l>with all his arms and towers unjustly held,</l>
<l>to quell the grim-eyed monster, snake-begin.</l>

    
<l>Yet not the valour of the youth, upheld</l>
<l>by many labours, nor his grievous wrongs</l>
<l>have softened you, O Polydectes! king</l>
<l>of Little Seriphus; but bitter hate</l>
<l>ungoverned, rankles in your hardened heart—</l>
<l>there is no limit to your unjust rage.</l>
<l>Even his praises are defamed by you</l>
<l>and all your arguments are given to prove</l>
<l>Medusa's death a fraud.—Perseus rejoined;</l>
<l>“By this we give our true pledge of the truth,</l>
<l>avert your eyes!” And by Medusa's face</l>
<l>he made the features of that impious king</l>
<l>a bloodless stone.</l>


Hippocrene. Pierides.
THE NINE MUSES AND MINERVA

<l>Through all these mighty deeds</l>
<l>Pallas, Minerva, had availed to guide</l>
<l>her gold-begotten brother. Now she sped,</l>
<l>surrounded in a cloud, from Seriphus,</l>
<l>while Cynthus on the right, and Gyarus</l>
<l>far faded from her view. And where a path,</l>
<l>high over the deep sea, leads the near way,</l>
<l>she winged the air for Thebes, and Helicon</l>
<l>haunt of the Virgin Nine.</l>

    
<l>High on that mount</l>
<l>she stayed her flight, and with these words bespoke</l>
<l>those well-taught sisters; “Fame has given to me</l>
<l>the knowledge of a new-made fountain—gift</l>
<l>of Pegasus, that fleet steed, from the blood</l>
<l>of dread Medusa sprung—it opened when</l>
<l>his hard hoof struck the ground.—It is the cause</l>
<l>that brought me.—For my longing to have seen</l>
<l>this fount, miraculous and wonderful,</l>
<l>grows not the less in that myself did see</l>
<l>the swift steed, nascent from maternal blood.”</l>

    
<l>To which Urania thus; “Whatever the cause</l>
<l>that brings thee to our habitation, thou,</l>
<l>O goddess, art to us the greatest joy.</l>
<l>And now, to answer thee, reports are true;</l>
<l>this fountain is the work of Pegasus,”</l>

    
<l>And having said these words, she gladly thence</l>
<l>conducted Pallas to the sacred streams.</l>

    
<l>And Pallas, after she had long admired</l>
<l>that fountain, flowing where the hoof had struck,</l>
<l>turned round to view the groves of ancient trees;</l>
<l>the grottoes and the grass bespangled, rich</l>
<l>with flowers unnumbered—all so beautiful</l>
<l>she deemed the charm of that locality</l>
<l>a fair surrounding for the studious days</l>
<l>of those Mnemonian Maids.</l>

THE NINE MUSES AND PYRENAEUS

<l>But one of them</l>
<l>addressed her thus; “O thou whose valour gave</l>
<l>thy mind to greater deeds! if thou hadst stooped</l>
<l>to us, Minerva, we had welcomed thee</l>
<l>most worthy of our choir! Thy words are true;</l>
<l>and well hast thou approved the joys of art,</l>
<l>and this retreat. Most happy would we be</l>
<l>if only we were safe; but wickedness</l>
<l>admits of no restraint, and everything</l>
<l>affrights our virgin minds; and everywhere</l>
<l>the dreadful Pyrenaeus haunts our sight;—</l>
<l>scarcely have we recovered from the shock.</l>

    
<l>“That savage, with his troops of Thrace. had seized</l>
<l>the lands of Daulis and of Phocis, where</l>
<l>he ruled in tyranny; and when we sought</l>
<l>the Temples of Parnassus, he observed</l>
<l>us on our way;—and knowing our estate,</l>
<l>pretending to revere our sacred lives,</l>
<l>he said; ‘O Muses, I beseech you pause!</l>
<l>Choose now the shelter of my roof and shun</l>
<l>the heavy stars that teem with pouring rain;</l>
<l>nor hesitate, for often the glorious Gods</l>
<l>have entered humbler homes.’</l>

    
<l>“Moved by his words,</l>
<l>and by the growing storm, we gave assent,</l>
<l>and entered his first house. But presently</l>
<l>the storm abated, and the southern wind</l>
<l>was conquered by the north; the black clouds fled,</l>
<l>and soon the skies were clear.</l>

    
<l>“At once we sought</l>
<l>to quit the house, but Pyrenaeus closed</l>
<l>all means of exit,—and prepared to force</l>
<l>our virtue. Instantly we spread our wings,</l>
<l>and so escaped; but on a lofty tower</l>
<l>he stood, as if to follow, and exclaimed;</l>
<l>‘A path for you marks out a way for me.,</l>
<l>and quite insane, he leaped down from the top</l>
<l>of that high tower.—Falling on his face,</l>
<l>the bones were crushed, and as his life ebbed out</l>
<l>the ground was crimsoned with his wicked blood.”</l>

THE NINE MUSES AND THE NINE MAGPIES

<l>So spoke the Muse. And now was heard the sound</l>
<l>of pennons in the air, and voices, too,</l>
<l>gave salutations from the lofty trees.</l>

    
<l>Minerva, thinking they were human tongues,</l>
<l>looked up in question whence the perfect words;</l>
<l>but on the boughs, nine ugly magpies perched,</l>
<l>those mockers of all sounds, which now complained</l>
<l>their hapless fate. And as she wondering stood,</l>
<l>Urania, goddess of the Muse, rejoined;—</l>

    
<l>“Look, those but lately worsted in dispute</l>
<l>augment the number of unnumbered birds.—</l>
<l>Pierus was their father, very rich</l>
<l>in lands of Pella; and their mother (called</l>
<l>Evippe of Paeonia) when she brought</l>
<l>them forth, nine times evoked, in labours nine,</l>
<l>Lucina's aid.—Unduly puffed with pride,</l>
<l>because it chanced their number equalled ours,</l>
<l>these stupid sisters, hither to engage</l>
<l>in wordy contest, fared through many towns;—</l>
<l>through all Haemonia and Achaia came</l>
<l>to us, and said;—</l>

<l>‘Oh, cease your empty songs,</l>
<l>attuned to dulcet numbers, that deceive</l>
<l>the vulgar, untaught throng. If aught is yours</l>
<l>of confidence, O Thespian Deities</l>
<l>contend with us: our number equals yours.</l>
<l>We will not be defeated by your arts;</l>
<l>nor shall your songs prevail.—Then, conquered, give</l>
<l>Hyantean Aganippe; yield to us</l>
<l>the Medusean Fount;—and should we fail,</l>
<l>we grant Emathia's plains, to where uprise</l>
<l>Paeonia's peaks of snow.—Let chosen Nymphs</l>
<l>award the prize—.’ 'Twas shameful to contend;</l>
<l>it seemed more shameful to submit. At once,</l>
<l>the chosen Nymphs swore justice by their streams,</l>
<l>and sat in judgment on their thrones of rock.</l>

    
<l>“At once, although the lot had not been cast,</l>
<l>the leading sister hastened to begin.—</l>
<l>She chanted of celestial wars; she gave</l>
<l>the Giants false renown; she gave the Gods</l>
<l>small credit for great deeds.—She droned out, ‘Forth,</l>
<l>those deepest realms of earth, Typhoeus came,</l>
<l>and filled the Gods with fear. They turned their backs</l>
<l>in flight to Egypt; and the wearied rout,</l>
<l>where Great Nile spreads his seven-channeled mouth,</l>
<l>were there received.—Thither the earth-begot</l>
<l>Typhoeus hastened: but the Gods of Heaven</l>
<l>deceptive shapes assumed.—Lo, Jupiter,</l>
<l>(As Libyan Ammon's crooked horns attest)</l>
<l>was hidden in the leader of a flock;</l>
<l>Apollo in a crow; Bacchus in a goat;</l>
<l>Diana in a cat; Venus in a fish;</l>
<l>Saturnian Juno in a snow-white cow;</l>
<l>Cyllenian Hermes in an Ibis' wings.’—</l>
<l>Such stuff she droned out from her noisy mouth:</l>
<l>and then they summoned us; but, haply, time</l>
<l>permits thee not, nor leisure thee permits,</l>
<l>that thou shouldst hearken to our melodies.”</l>

<l>“Nay doubt it not,” quoth Pallas, “but relate</l>
<l>your melodies in order.” And she sat</l>
<l>beneath the pleasant shadows of the grove.</l>

    
<l>And thus again Urania; “On our side</l>
<l>we trusted all to one.” Which having said,</l>
<l>Calliope arose. Her glorious hair</l>
<l>was bound with ivy. She attuned the chords,</l>
<l>and chanted as she struck the sounding strings:—</l>


Ceres et Proserpina.
CALLIOPE SINGS OF CERES, PLUTO AND PROSERPINE

<l>“First Ceres broke with crooked plow the glebe;</l>
<l>first gave to earth its fruit and wholesome food;</l>
<l>first gave the laws;—all things of Ceres came;</l>
<l>of her I sing; and oh, that I could tell</l>
<l>her worth in verse; in verse her worth is due.</l>

    
<l>“Because he dared to covet heavenly thrones</l>
<l>Typhoeus, giant limbs are weighted down</l>
<l>beneath Sicilia's Isle—vast in extent—</l>
<l>how often thence he strains and strives to rise?</l>
<l>But his right hand Pachynus holds; his legs are pressed</l>
<l>by Lilybaeus, Aetna weights his head.</l>
<l>Beneath that ponderous mass Typhoeus lies,</l>
<l>flat on his back; and spues the sands on high;</l>
<l>and vomits flames from his ferocious mouth.</l>
<l>He often strives to push the earth away,</l>
<l>the cities and the mountains from his limbs—</l>
<l>by which the lands are shaken. Even the king,</l>
<l>that rules the silent shades is made to quake,</l>
<l>for fear the earth may open and the ground,</l>
<l>cleft in wide chasms, letting in the day,</l>
<l>may terrify the trembling ghosts. Afraid</l>
<l>of this disaster, that dark despot left</l>
<l>his gloomy habitation; carried forth</l>
<l>by soot-black horses, in his gloomy car.</l>

    
<l>“He circumspectly viewed Sicilia's vast</l>
<l>foundations.—Having well explored and proved</l>
<l>no part was shattered; having laid aside</l>
<l>his careful fears, he wandered in those parts.</l>

    
<l>“Him, Venus, Erycina, in her mount</l>
<l>thus witnessed, and embraced her winged son,</l>
<l>and said, ‘O Cupid! thou who art my son—</l>
<l>my arms, my hand, my strength; take up those arms,</l>
<l>by which thou art victorious over all,</l>
<l>and aim thy keenest arrow at the heart</l>
<l>of that divinity whom fortune gave</l>
<l>the last award, what time the triple realm,</l>
<l>by lot was portioned out.</l>

    
<l>‘The Gods of Heaven</l>
<l>are overcome by thee; and Jupiter,</l>
<l>and all the Deities that swim the deep,</l>
<l>and the great ruler of the Water-Gods:</l>
<l>why, then, should Tartarus escape our sway—</l>
<l>the third part of the universe at stake—</l>
<l>by which thy mother's empire and thy own</l>
<l>may be enlarged according to great need.</l>

    
<l>‘How shameful is our present lot in Heaven,</l>
<l>the powers of love and I alike despised;</l>
<l>for, mark how Pallas has renounced my sway,</l>
<l>besides Diana, javelin-hurler—so</l>
<l>will Ceres' daughter choose virginity,</l>
<l>if we permit,—that way her hopes incline.</l>
<l>Do thou this goddess Proserpine, unite</l>
<l>in marriage to her uncle. Venus spoke;—</l>

    
<l>“Cupid then loosed his quiver, and of all</l>
<l>its many arrows, by his mother's aid,</l>
<l>selected one; the keenest of them all;</l>
<l>the least uncertain, surest from the string:</l>
<l>and having fixed his knee against the bow,</l>
<l>bent back the flexile horn.—The flying shaft</l>
<l>struck Pluto in the breast.</l>

    
<l>“There is a lake</l>
<l>of greatest depth, not far from Henna's walls,</l>
<l>long since called Pergus; and the songs of swans,</l>
<l>that wake Cayster, rival not the notes</l>
<l>of swans melodious on its gliding waves:</l>
<l>a fringe of trees, encircling as a wreath</l>
<l>its compassed waters, with a leafy veil</l>
<l>denies the heat of noon; cool breezes blow</l>
<l>beneath the boughs; the humid ground is sprent</l>
<l>with purpling flowers, and spring eternal reigns.</l>

    
<l>“While Proserpine once dallied in that grove,</l>
<l>plucking white lilies and sweet violets,</l>
<l>and while she heaped her basket, while she filled</l>
<l>her bosom, in a pretty zeal to strive</l>
<l>beyond all others; she was seen, beloved,</l>
<l>and carried off by Pluto—such the haste</l>
<l>of sudden love. </l>

<l>“The goddess, in great fear,</l>
<l>called on her mother and on all her friends;</l>
<l>and, in her frenzy, as her robe was rent,</l>
<l>down from the upper edge, her gathered flowers</l>
<l>fell from her loosened tunic.—This mishap,</l>
<l>so perfect was her childish innocence,</l>
<l>increased her virgin grief.—</l>

    
<l>“The ravisher</l>
<l>urged on his chariot, and inspired his steeds;</l>
<l>called each by name, and on their necks and manes</l>
<l>shook the black-rusted reins. They hastened through</l>
<l>deep lakes, and through the pools of Palici,</l>
<l>which boiling upward from the ruptured earth</l>
<l>smell of strong sulphur. And they bore him thence</l>
<l>to where the sons of Bacchus, who had sailed</l>
<l>from twin-sea Corinth, long ago had built</l>
<l>a city's walls between unequal ports.</l>


    
<l>“Midway between the streams of Cyane</l>
<l>and Arethusa lies a moon-like pool,</l>
<l>of silvered narrow horns. There stood the Nymph,</l>
<l>revered above all others in that land,</l>
<l>whose name was Cyane. From her that pond</l>
<l>was always called. And as she stood, concealed</l>
<l>in middle waves that circled her white thighs,</l>
<l>she recognized the God, and said; ‘O thou</l>
<l>shalt go no further, Pluto, thou shalt not</l>
<l>by force alone become the son-in-law</l>
<l>of Ceres. It is better to beseech</l>
<l>a mother's aid than drag her child away!</l>
<l>And this sustains my word, if I may thus</l>
<l>compare great things with small, Anapis loved</l>
<l>me also; but he wooed and married me</l>
<l>by kind endearments; not by fear, as thou</l>
<l>hast terrified this girl.’ So did she speak;</l>
<l>and stretching out her arms on either side</l>
<l>opposed his way.</l>

    
<l>“The son of Saturn blazed</l>
<l>with uncontrolled rage; and urged his steeds,</l>
<l>and hurled his royal scepter in the pool.</l>
<l>Cast with a mighty arm it pierced the deeps.</l>
<l>The smitten earth made way to Tartarus;—</l>
<l>it opened a wide basin and received</l>
<l>the plunging chariot in the midst.—But now</l>
<l>the mournful Cyane began to grieve,</l>
<l>because from her against her fountain-rights</l>
<l>the goddess had been torn. The deepening wound</l>
<l>still rankled in her breast, and she dissolved</l>
<l>in many tears, and wasted in those waves</l>
<l>which lately were submissive to her rule.</l>

    
<l>“So you could see her members waste away:</l>
<l>her hones begin to bend; her nails get soft;</l>
<l>her azure hair, her fingers, legs and feet,</l>
<l>and every slender part melt in the pool:</l>
<l>so brief the time in which her tender limbs</l>
<l>were changed to flowing waves; and after them</l>
<l>her back and shoulders, and her sides and breasts</l>
<l>dissolved and vanished into rivulets:</l>
<l>and while she changed, the water slowly filled</l>
<l>her faulty veins instead of living blood—</l>
<l>and nothing that a hand could hold remained.</l>

    
<l>“Now it befell when Proserpine was lost,</l>
<l>her anxious mother sought through every land</l>
<l>and every sea in vain. She rested not.</l>
<l>Aurora, when she came with ruddy locks,</l>
<l>might never know, nor even Hesperus,</l>
<l>if she might deign to rest.—She lit two pines</l>
<l>from Aetna's flames and held one in each hand,</l>
<l>and restless bore them through the frosty glooms:</l>
<l>and when serene the day had dimmed the stars</l>
<l>she sought her daughter by the rising sun;</l>
<l>and when the sun declined she rested not.</l>

    
<l>“Wearied with labour she began to thirst,</l>
<l>for all this while no streams had cooled her lips;</l>
<l>when, as by chance, a cottage thatched with straw</l>
<l>gladdened her sight. Thither the goddess went,</l>
<l>and, after knocking at the humble door,</l>
<l>waited until an ancient woman came;</l>
<l>who, when she saw the goddess and had heard</l>
<l>her plea for water, gave her a sweet drink,</l>
<l>but lately brewed of parched barley-meal;</l>
<l>and while the goddess quaffed this drink a boy,</l>
<l>of bold and hard appearance, stood before</l>
<l>and laughed and called her greedy. While he spoke</l>
<l>the angry goddess sprinkled him with meal,</l>
<l>mixed with the liquid which had not been drunk.</l>

    
<l>“His face grew spotted where the mixture struck,</l>
<l>and legs appeared where he had arms before,</l>
<l>a tail was added to his changing trunk;</l>
<l>and lest his former strength might cause great harm,</l>
<l>all parts contracted till he measured less</l>
<l>than common lizards. While the ancient dame</l>
<l>wondered and wept and strove for one caress,</l>
<l>the reptile fled and sought a lurking place.—</l>
<l>His very name describes him to the eye,</l>
<l>a body starred with many coloured spots.</l>

    
<l>“What lands, what oceans Ceres wandered then,</l>
<l>would weary to relate. The bounded world</l>
<l>was narrow for the search. Again she passed</l>
<l>through Sicily; again observed all signs;</l>
<l>and as she wandered came to Cyane,</l>
<l>who strove to tell where Proserpine had gone,</l>
<l>but since her change, had neither mouth nor tongue,</l>
<l>and so was mute. And yet the Nymph made plain</l>
<l>by certain signs what she desired to say:</l>
<l>for on the surface of the waves she showed</l>
<l>a well-known girdle Proserpine had lost,</l>
<l>by chance had dropped it in that sacred pool;</l>
<l>which when the goddess recognized, at last,</l>
<l>convinced her daughter had been forced from her,</l>
<l>she tore her streaming locks, and frenzied struck</l>
<l>her bosom with her palms. And in her rage,</l>
<l>although she wist not where her daughter was,</l>
<l>she blamed all countries and cried out against</l>
<l>their base ingratitude; and she declared</l>
<l>the world unworthy of the gift of corn:</l>
<l>but Sicily before all other lands,</l>
<l>for there was found the token of her loss.</l>

    
<l>“For that she broke with savage hand the plows,</l>
<l>which there had turned the soil, and full of wrath</l>
<l>leveled in equal death the peasant and his ox—</l>
<l>both tillers of the soil—and made decree</l>
<l>that land should prove deceptive to the seed,</l>
<l>and rot all planted germs.—That fertile isle,</l>
<l>so noted through the world, becomes a waste;</l>
<l>the corn is blighted in the early blade;</l>
<l>excessive heat, excessive rain destroys;</l>
<l>the winds destroy, the constellations harm;</l>
<l>the greedy birds devour the scattered seeds;</l>
<l>thistles and tares and tough weeds choke the wheat.</l>


    
<l>“For this the Nymph, Alpheian, raised her head</l>
<l>above Elean waves; and having first</l>
<l>pushed back her dripping tresses from her brows,</l>
<l>back to her ears, she thus began to speak;</l>
<l>‘O mother of the virgin, sought throughout</l>
<l>the globe! O mother of nutritious fruits!</l>
<l>Let these tremendous labours have an end;</l>
<l>do not increase the violence of thy wrath</l>
<l>against the Earth, devoted to thy sway,</l>
<l>and not deserving blame; for only force</l>
<l>compelled the Earth to open for that wrong.</l>
<l>Think not my supplication is to aid</l>
<l>my native country; hither I am come</l>
<l>an alien: Pisa is my native land,</l>
<l>and Elis gave me birth. Though I sojourn</l>
<l>a stranger in this isle of Sicily</l>
<l>it yet delights me more than all the world.</l>

    
<l>‘I, Arethusa, claim this isle my home,</l>
<l>and do implore thee keep my throne secure,</l>
<l>O greatest of the Gods! A better hour,</l>
<l>when thou art lightened of thy cares, will come,</l>
<l>and when thy countenance again is kind;</l>
<l>and then may I declare what cause removed</l>
<l>me from my native place—and through the waves</l>
<l>of such a mighty ocean guided me</l>
<l>to find Ortygia.</l>

    
<l>‘Through the porous earth</l>
<l>by deepest caverns, I uplift my head</l>
<l>and see unwonted stars. Now it befell,</l>
<l>as I was gliding far beneath the world,</l>
<l>where flow dark Stygian streams, I saw</l>
<l>thy Proserpine. Although her countenance</l>
<l>betrayed anxiety and grief, a queen She reigned</l>
<l>supremely great in that opacous world</l>
<l>queen consort mighty to the King of Hell.’</l>

<l>“Astonished and amazed, as thunderstruck,</l>
<l>when Proserpina's mother heard these words,</l>
<l>long while she stood till great bewilderment</l>
<l>gave way to heavy grief. Then to the skies,</l>
<l>ethereal, she mounted in her car</l>
<l>and with beclouded face and streaming hair</l>
<l>stood fronting Jove, opprobrious. ‘I have come</l>
<l>O Jupiter, a suppliant to thee,</l>
<l>both for my own offspring as well as thine.</l>
<l>If thy hard heart deny a mother grace,</l>
<l>yet haply as a father thou canst feel</l>
<l>some pity for thy daughter; and I pray</l>
<l>thy care for her may not be valued less</l>
<l>because my groaning travail brought her forth.—</l>
<l>My long-sought daughter has at last been found,</l>
<l>if one can call it, found, when certain loss</l>
<l>more certain has been proved; or so may deem</l>
<l>the knowledge of her state.—But I may bear</l>
<l>his rude ways, if again he bring her back.</l>

    
<l>‘Thy worthy child should not be forced to wed</l>
<l>a bandit-chief, nor should my daughter's charms</l>
<l>reward his crime.’ She spoke;—and Jupiter</l>
<l>took up the word; ‘This daughter is a care,</l>
<l>a sacred pledge to me as well as thee;</l>
<l>but if it please us to acknowledge truth,</l>
<l>this is a deed of love and injures not.</l>
<l>And if, O goddess, thou wilt not oppose,</l>
<l>such law-son cannot compass our disgrace:</l>
<l>for though all else were wanting, naught can need</l>
<l>Jove's brother, who in fortune yields to none</l>
<l>save me. But if thy fixed desire compel</l>
<l>dissent, let Proserpine return to Heaven;</l>
<l>however, subject to the binding law,</l>
<l>if there her tongue have never tasted food—</l>
<l>a sure condition, by the Fates decreed.’</l>
<l>he spoke; but Ceres was no less resolved</l>
<l>to lead her daughter thence.</l>

    
<l>“Not so the Fates</l>
<l>permit.—The virgin, thoughtless while she strayed</l>
<l>among the cultivated Stygian fields,</l>
<l>had broken fast. While there she plucked the fruit</l>
<l>by bending a pomegranate tree, and plucked,</l>
<l>and chewed seven grains, picked from the pallid rind;</l>
<l>and none had seen except Ascalaphus—</l>
<l>him Orphne, famed of all Avernian Nymphs,</l>
<l>had brought to birth in some infernal cave,</l>
<l>days long ago, from Acheron's embrace—</l>
<l>he saw it, and with cruel lips debarred</l>
<l>young Proserpine's return. Heaving a sigh,</l>
<l>the Queen of Erebus, indignant changed</l>
<l>that witness to an evil bird: she turned</l>
<l>his head, with sprinkled Phlegethonian lymph,</l>
<l>into a beak, and feathers, and great eyes;</l>
<l>his head grew larger and his shape, deformed,</l>
<l>was cased in tawny wings; his lengthened nails</l>
<l>bent inward;—and his sluggish arms</l>
<l>as wings can hardly move. So he became</l>
<l>the vilest bird; a messenger of grief;</l>
<l>the lazy owl; sad omen to mankind.</l>

    
<l>“The telltale's punishment was only just;</l>
<l>O Siren Maids, but wherefore thus have ye</l>
<l>the feet and plumes of birds, although remain</l>
<l>your virgin features? Is it from the day</l>
<l>when Proserpina gathered vernal flowers;</l>
<l>because ye mingled with her chosen friends?</l>
<l>And after she was lost, in vain ye sought</l>
<l>through all the world; and wished for wings to waft</l>
<l>you over the great deep, that soon the sea</l>
<l>might feel your great concern.—The Gods were kind:</l>
<l>ye saw your limbs grow yellow, with a growth</l>
<l>of sudden-sprouting feathers; but because</l>
<l>your melodies that gently charm the ear,</l>
<l>besides the glory of your speech, might lose</l>
<l>the blessing, of a tongue, your virgin face</l>
<l>and human voice remained.</l>

    
<l>“But Jupiter,</l>
<l>the mediator of these rival claims,</l>
<l>urged by his brother and his grieving sister,</l>
<l>divided the long year in equal parts.</l>
<l>Now Proserpina, as a Deity,</l>
<l>of equal merit, in two kingdoms reigns:—</l>
<l>for six months with her mother she abides,</l>
<l>and six months with her husband.—Both her mind</l>
<l>and her appearance quickly were transformed;</l>
<l>for she who seemed so sad in Pluto's eyes,</l>
<l>now as a goddess beams in joyful smiles;</l>
<l>so, when the sun obscured by watery mist</l>
<l>conquers the clouds, it shines in splendour forth.</l>


Arethusa.
CALLIOPE SINGS OF ARETHUSA AND ALPHEUS

<l>“And genial Ceres, full of joy, that now</l>
<l>her daughter was regained, began to speak;</l>
<l>‘Declare the reason of thy wanderings,</l>
<l>O Arethusa! tell me wherefore thou</l>
<l>wert made a sacred stream.’ The waters gave</l>
<l>no sound; but soon that goddess raised her head</l>
<l>from the deep springs; and after sue had dried</l>
<l>her green hair with her hand, with fair address</l>
<l>she told the ancient amours of that stream</l>
<l>which flows through Elis.—‘I was one among</l>
<l>the Nymphs of old Achaia,’—so she said—</l>
<l>‘And none of them more eager sped than I,</l>
<l>along the tangled pathways; and I fixed</l>
<l>the hunting-nets with zealous care.—Although</l>
<l>I strove not for the praise that beauty gives,</l>
<l>and though my form was something stout for grace,</l>
<l>it had the name of being beautiful.</l>

    
<l>‘So worthless seemed the praise, I took no joy</l>
<l>in my appearance—as a country lass</l>
<l>I blushed at those endowments which would give</l>
<l>delight to others—even the power to please</l>
<l>seemed criminal.—And I remember when</l>
<l>returning weary from Stymphal fan woods,</l>
<l>and hot with toil, that made the glowing sun</l>
<l>seem twice as hot, I chanced upon a stream,</l>
<l>that flowed without a ripple or a sound</l>
<l>so smoothly on, I hardly thought it moved.</l>

    
<l>‘The water was so clear that one could see</l>
<l>and count the pebbles in the deepest parts,</l>
<l>and silver willows and tall poplar trees,</l>
<l>nourished by flowing waters, spread their shade</l>
<l>over the shelving banks. So I approached,</l>
<l>and shrinkingly touched the cool stream with my feet;</l>
<l>and then I ventured deeper to my knees;</l>
<l>and not contented doffed my fleecy robes,</l>
<l>and laid them on a bending willow tree.</l>
<l>Then, naked, I plunged deeply in the stream,</l>
<l>and while I smote the water with my hands,</l>
<l>and drew it towards me, striking boldly forth,</l>
<l>moving my body in a thousand ways,</l>
<l>I thought I heard a most unusual sound,</l>
<l>a murmuring noise beneath the middle stream.</l>

    
<l>‘Alarmed, I hastened to the nearest bank,</l>
<l>and as I stood upon its edge, these words</l>
<l>hoarsely Alpheus uttered from his waves;</l>
<l>‘Oh, whither dost thou hasten?’ and again,</l>
<l>‘Oh, whither dost thou hasten?’ said the voice.</l>

    
<l>‘Just as I was, I fled without my clothes,</l>
<l>for I had left them on the other bank;</l>
<l>which, when he saw, so much the more inflamed,</l>
<l>more swiftly he pursued: my nakedness</l>
<l>was tempting to his gaze. And thus I ran;</l>
<l>and thus relentlessly he pressed my steps:</l>
<l>so from the hawk the dove with trembling wings;</l>
<l>and so, the hawk pursues the frightened dove.</l>

    
<l>‘Swiftly and long I fled, with winding course,</l>
<l>to Orchamenus, Psophis and Cyllene,</l>
<l>and Maenalus and Erymanthus cold,</l>
<l>and Elis. Neither could he gain by speed,</l>
<l>although his greater strength must soon prevail,</l>
<l>for I not longer could endure the strain.</l>

    
<l>‘Still I sped onward through the fields and woods,</l>
<l>by tangled wilds and over rocks and crags;</l>
<l>and as I hastened from the setting sun,</l>
<l>I thought I saw a growing shadow move</l>
<l>beyond my feet; it may have been my fear</l>
<l>imagined it, but surely now I heard</l>
<l>the sound of footsteps: I could even feel</l>
<l>his breathing on the loose ends of my hair;</l>
<l>and I was terrified. At last, worn out</l>
<l>by all my efforts to escape, I cried;</l>
<l>‘Oh, help me—thou whose bow and quivered darts</l>
<l>I oft have borne—thy armour-bearer calls—</l>
<l>O chaste Diana help,—or I am lost.’</l>

<l>‘It moved the goddess, and she gathered up</l>
<l>a dense cloud, and encompassed me about.—</l>
<l>The baffled River circled round and round,</l>
<l>seeking to find me, hidden in that cloud—</l>
<l>twice went the River round, and twice cried out,</l>
<l>‘Ho, Arethusa! Arethusa, Ho!’</l>

<l>‘What were my wretched feelings then? Could I</l>
<l>be braver than the Iamb that hears the wolves,</l>
<l>howling around the high-protecting fold?</l>
<l>Or than the hare, which lurking in the bush</l>
<l>knows of the snarling hounds and dares not move?</l>
<l>And yet, Alpheus thence would not depart,</l>
<l>for he could find no footprints of my flight.</l>

    
<l>‘He watched the cloud and spot, and thus besieged,</l>
<l>a cold sweat gathered on my trembling limbs.</l>
<l>The clear-blue drops, distilled from every pore,</l>
<l>made pools of water where I moved my feet,</l>
<l>and dripping moisture trickled from my hair.—</l>
<l>Much quicker than my story could be told,</l>
<l>my body was dissolved to flowing streams.—</l>
<l>But still the River recognized the waves,</l>
<l>and for the love of me transformed his shape</l>
<l>from human features to his proper streams,</l>
<l>that so his waters might encompass mine.</l>

    
<l>‘Diana, therefore, opened up the ground,</l>
<l>in which I plunged, and thence through gloomy caves</l>
<l>was carried to Ortygia—blessed isle!</l>
<l>To which my chosen goddess gave her name!</l>
<l>Where first I rose amid the upper air!’</l>

CALLIOPE SINGS OF TRIPTOLEMUS AND LYNCUS

<l>“Thus Arethusa made an end of speech:</l>
<l>and presently the fertile goddess yoked</l>
<l>two dragons to her chariot: she curbed</l>
<l>their mouths with bits: they bore her through the air,</l>
<l>in her light car betwixt the earth and skies,</l>
<l>to the Tritonian citadel, and to</l>
<l>Triptolemus, to whom she furnished seed,</l>
<l>that he might scatter it in wasted lands,</l>
<l>and in the fallow fields; which, after long</l>
<l>neglect, again were given to the plow.</l>

    
<l>“After he had traveled through uncharted skies,</l>
<l>over wide Europe and vast Asian lands,</l>
<l>he lit upon the coast of Scythia, where</l>
<l>a king called Lyncus reigned. And there, at once</l>
<l>he sought the palace of that king, who said;</l>
<l>‘Whence come you, stranger, wherefore in this land?</l>
<l>Come, tell to me your nation and your name.’</l>

<l>“And after he was questioned thus, he said,</l>
<l>‘I came from far-famed Athens and they call</l>
<l>my name Triptolemus. I neither came</l>
<l>by ship through waves, nor over the dry land;</l>
<l>for me the yielding atmosphere makes way.—</l>
<l>I bear the gifts of Ceres to your land,</l>
<l>which scattered over your wide realm may yield</l>
<l>an ample harvest of nutritious food.’</l>

<l>“The envious Lyncus, wishing to appear</l>
<l>the gracious author of all benefits,</l>
<l>received the unsuspecting youth with smiles;</l>
<l>but when he fell into a heavy sleep</l>
<l>that savage king attacked him with a sword—</l>
<l>but while attempting to transfix his guest,</l>
<l>the goddess Ceres changed him to a lynx:—</l>
<l>and once again she sent her favoured youth</l>
<l>to drive her sacred dragons through the clouds.</l>

THE NINE OPPONENTS OF THE NINE MUSES CHANGED TO MAGPIES

<l>“The greatest of our number ended thus</l>
<l>her learned songs; and with concordant voice</l>
<l>the chosen Nymphs adjudged the Deities,</l>
<l>on Helicon who dwell, should be proclaimed</l>
<l>the victors.</l>

    
<l>“But the vanquished nine began</l>
<l>to scatter their abuse; to whom rejoined</l>
<l>the goddess; ‘Since it seems a trifling thing</l>
<l>that you should suffer a deserved defeat,</l>
<l>and you must add unmerited abuse</l>
<l>to heighten your offence, and since by this</l>
<l>appears the end of our endurance, we</l>
<l>shall certainly proceed to punish you</l>
<l>according to the limit of our wrath.’</l>

    
<l>“But these Emathian sisters laughed to scorn</l>
<l>our threatening words; and as they tried to speak,</l>
<l>and made great clamour, and with shameless hands</l>
<l>made threatening gestures, suddenly stiff quills</l>
<l>sprouted from out their finger-nails, and plumes</l>
<l>spread over their stretched arms; and they could see</l>
<l>the mouth of each companion growing out</l>
<l>into a rigid beak.—And thus new birds</l>
<l>were added to the forest.—While they made</l>
<l>complaint, these Magpies that defile our groves,</l>
<l>moving their stretched-out arms, began to float,</l>
<l>suspended in the air. And since that time</l>
<l>their ancient eloquence, their screaming notes,</l>
<l>their tiresome zeal of speech have all remained.”</l>
