<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 2

PHAETHON AND PHOEBUS

<l>Glowing with gold, flaming with carbuncles</l>
<l>on stately columns raised, refulgent shone</l>
<l>the palace of the Sun, with polished dome</l>
<l>of ivory gleaming, and with portals twain</l>
<l>of burnished silver. And the workmanship</l>
<l>exceeded all the wealth of gems and gold;</l>
<l>for there had Mulciber engraved the seas</l>
<l>encircling middle earth; the round of earth,</l>
<l>and heaven impending over the land.</l>

    
<l>And there</l>
<l>amid the waves were azure deities:</l>
<l>melodious Triton and elusive Proteus; there</l>
<l>Aegeaan pressing with his arms the backs.</l>
<l>Of monstrous whales; and Doris in the sea</l>
<l>and all her daughters; some amid the waves</l>
<l>and others sitting on the bank to dry</l>
<l>their sea-green hair, and others borne about</l>
<l>by fishes. Each was made to show a fair</l>
<l>resemblance to her sisters—yet not one</l>
<l>appearance was assigned to all—they seemed</l>
<l>as near alike as sisters should in truth.</l>
<l>And men and cities, woods and savage beasts,</l>
<l>and streams and nymphs, and sylvan deities</l>
<l>were carved upon the land; and over these</l>
<l>an image of the glittering sky was fixed;—</l>
<l>six signs were on the right, six on the left.</l>

    
<l>Here when audacious Phaethon arrived</l>
<l>by steep ascending paths, without delay</l>
<l>he entered in the shining palace-gates</l>
<l>of his reputed parent, making haste</l>
<l>to stand in his paternal presence. There,</l>
<l>unable to endure the dazzling light,</l>
<l>he waited at a distance.</l>

    
<l>Phoebus sat,</l>
<l>arrayed in royal purple, on a throne</l>
<l>that glittered with the purest emeralds.—  </l>
<l>there to the left and right, Day, Month and Year,</l>
<l>time and the Hours, at equal distance stood;</l>
<l>and vernal Spring stood crowned with wreathed flowers;</l>
<l>and naked Summer stood with sheaves of wheat;</l>
<l>and Autumn stood besmeared with trodden grapes;</l>
<l>and icy Winter rough with hoary hair.</l>

    
<l>And from the midst, with orbs that view the world,</l>
<l>Phoebus beheld the trembling youth, fear-struck,</l>
<l>in mute amazement, and he said; “Declare</l>
<l>the reason of thy journey. What wilt thou</l>
<l>in this my palace, Phaethon my child</l>
<l>beloved?”</l>

    
<l>And to him replied the youth;</l>
<l>“O universal light of all the world,</l>
<l>my father Phoebus, if thy name be mine,</l>
<l>if Clymene has not concealed her sin</l>
<l>beneath some pretext, give to me, my sire,</l>
<l>a token to declare thy fatherhood</l>
<l>which may establish my assured descent,</l>
<l>and leave no dark suspicions in our minds.”—</l>

    
<l>then Phoebus from his shining brows cast down</l>
<l>his circling rays; called Phaethon to him,</l>
<l>and as he held him to his breast replied;</l>

<l>“O child most worthy of thy sire, the truth</l>
<l>was told thee by thy mother; wherefore doubts</l>
<l>to dissipate, consider thy desire,</l>
<l>and ask of me that I may freely give:</l>
<l>yea, let the Nether Lake, beyond our view,</l>
<l>(which is the oath of Gods inviolate)</l>
<l>be witness to my word.”</l>

    
<l>When this was said</l>
<l>the happy youth at once began to plead</l>
<l>command and guidance of his father's steeds,</l>
<l>wing-footed, and his chariot for a day.</l>

    
<l>But Phoebus much repented that he sware,</l>
<l>and thrice and four times shook his radiant head;</l>
<l>“Ah, would I might refuse my plighted word;</l>
<l>and oh, that it were lawful to deny</l>
<l>the promised boon.—For I confess, O son,</l>
<l>this only I should keep from thee—and yet</l>
<l>'Tis lawful to dissuade. It is unsafe</l>
<l>to satisfy thy will. It is a great</l>
<l>request, O Phaethon, which neither suits</l>
<l>thy utmost strength nor tender years; for thou</l>
<l>art mortal, and thou hast aspired to things</l>
<l>immortal. Ignorance has made thy thought</l>
<l>transcend the province of the Gods. I vaunt</l>
<l>no vain exploits; but only I can stand</l>
<l>securely on the flame-fraught axle-tree:</l>
<l>even the Ruler of Olympian Gods,</l>
<l>who hurls fierce lightnings with his great right hand,</l>
<l>may never dare to drive this chariot,</l>
<l>and what art thou to equal mighty Jove?</l>

<l>“The opening path is steep and difficult,</l>
<l>for scarcely can the steeds, refreshed at dawn,</l>
<l>climb up the steeps: and when is reached the height,</l>
<l>extreme of midmost Heaven, and sea and earth</l>
<l>are viewed below, my trembling breast is filled</l>
<l>with fearful apprehensions: and requires</l>
<l>the last precipitous descent a sure</l>
<l>command. Then, also, Tethys, who receives</l>
<l>me in her subject waves, is wont to fear</l>
<l>lest I should fall disastrous. And around</l>
<l>the hastening sky revolves in constant whirl,</l>
<l>drawing the lofty stars with rapid twist.</l>

<l>“I struggle on. The force that overcomes</l>
<l>the heavenly bodies overwhelms me not,</l>
<l>and I am borne against that rapid globe.</l>
<l>Suppose the chariot thine: what canst thou do?</l>
<l>Canst thou drive straight against the twisted pole</l>
<l>and not be carried from the lofty path</l>
<l>by the swift car? Art thou deceived to think</l>
<l>there may be groves and cities of the Gods,</l>
<l>and costly temples wondrously endowed?</l>

<l>“The journey is beset with dreadful snares</l>
<l>and shapes of savage animals. If thou</l>
<l>shouldst hold upon thy way without mistake</l>
<l>yet must thy journey be through Taurus' horns,</l>
<l>and through the Bow Haemonian, and the jaws</l>
<l>of the fierce Lion, and the cruel arms</l>
<l>of Scorpion, bent throughout a vast expanse,—</l>
<l>and Cancer's curving arms reversely bent.</l>

<l>“It is no easy task for thee to rule</l>
<l>the mettled four-foot steeds, enflamed in fires</l>
<l>that kindle in their breasts, forth issuing</l>
<l>in breathings from their mouths and nostrils hot;—</l>
<l>I scarce restrain them, as their struggling necks</l>
<l>pull on the harness, when their heated fires</l>
<l>are thus aroused.</l>

<l>“And, O my son, lest I</l>
<l>may be the author of a baneful gift,</l>
<l>beware, and as the time permits recall</l>
<l>thy rash request. Forsooth thou hast besought</l>
<l>undoubted signs of thy descent from me?</l>
<l>My fears for thee are certain signs that thou</l>
<l>art of my race—by my paternal fears</l>
<l>'Tis manifest I am thy father. Lo!</l>
<l>Behold my countenance! and oh, that thou</l>
<l>couldst even pierce my bosom with thine eyes,</l>
<l>and so discover my paternal cares!</l>

<l>“Look round thee on the treasured world's delights</l>
<l>and ask the greatest blessing of the sky,</l>
<l>or sea or land, and thou shalt suffer no</l>
<l>repulse: but only this I must deplore,</l>
<l>which rightly named would be a penalty</l>
<l>and not an honour.—Thou hast made request</l>
<l>of punishment and not a gift indeed.</l>
<l>O witless boy! why dost thou hold my neck</l>
<l>with thy caressing arms? For, doubt it not,</l>
<l>as I have sworn it by the Stygian Waves,</l>
<l>whatever thou shalt wish, it shall be given—</l>
<l>but thou shouldst wish more wisely.”</l>


    
<l>So were all</l>
<l>his admonitions said, availing naught;</l>
<l>for Phaethon resisted his advice,</l>
<l>and urged again his claim, and eagerly burned</l>
<l>to use the chariot. Wherefore, Phoebus long</l>
<l>delaying and reluctant, took the youth</l>
<l>to view the spacious chariot, gift of Vulcan.—</l>
<l>gold was the axle and the beam was gold,</l>
<l>the great Wheel had a golden tire and spokes</l>
<l>of silver; chrysolites and diamonds</l>
<l>reflected from the spangled yoke the light</l>
<l>of Phoebus.</l>

    
<l>While aspiring Phaethon admired</l>
<l>the glittering chariot and its workmanship,</l>
<l>the vigilant Aurora opened forth</l>
<l>her purple portals from the ruddy east,</l>
<l>disclosing halls replete with roses. All</l>
<l>the stars took flight, while Lucifer, the last</l>
<l>to quit his vigil, gathered that great host</l>
<l>and disappeared from his celestial watch.</l>

    
<l>And when his father, Phoebus, saw the earth</l>
<l>and the wide universe in glowing tints</l>
<l>arrayed, as waned the Moon's diminished horns,</l>
<l>far-distant, then he bade the nimble Hours</l>
<l>to yoke the steeds.—At once the Deities</l>
<l>accomplished his commands, and led the steeds,</l>
<l>ambrosia-fed and snorting flames, from out</l>
<l>their spacious stalls; and fixed their sounding bits.</l>

    
<l>Then with a hallowed drug the father touched</l>
<l>the stripling's face, to make him proof against</l>
<l>the rapid flame, and wrought around his hair</l>
<l>the sun-rays. But, foreboding grief, he said,</l>
<l>while many a sigh heaved from his anxious breast;</l>
<l>“If thou canst only heed thy father's voice—</l>
<l>be sparing of the whip and use with nerve</l>
<l>the reins; for of their own accord the steeds</l>
<l>will hasten. Difficult are they to check</l>
<l>in full career. Thou must not drive the car</l>
<l>directly through five circles, for the track</l>
<l>takes a wide curve, obliquely, and is bound</l>
<l>by the extreme edge of three zones.—It avoids</l>
<l>the Southern Pole, and it avoids the Bear</l>
<l>that roams around the north. The way is plain;</l>
<l>the traces of the Wheel are manifest.</l>

<l>“Observe with care that both the earth and sky</l>
<l>have their appropriate heat—Drive not too low,</l>
<l>nor urge the chariot through the highest plane;</l>
<l>for if thy course attain too great a height</l>
<l>thou wilt consume the mansions of the sky,</l>
<l>and if too low the land will scorch with heat.</l>

<l>“Take thou the middle plane, where all is safe;</l>
<l>nor let the Wheel turn over to the right</l>
<l>and bear thee to the twisted Snake! nor let</l>
<l>it take thee to the Altar on the left—</l>
<l>so close to earth—but steer the middle course.—</l>
<l>to Fortune I commit thy fate, whose care</l>
<l>for thee so reckless of thyself I pray.</l>

<l>“While I am speaking humid night has touched</l>
<l>the margin of Hesperian shores. 'Tis not</l>
<l>for us to idle; we are called away;—</l>
<l>when bright Aurora shines the darkness flies.</l>
<l>Take up the reins! But if thy stubborn breast</l>
<l>be capable of change use not our car,</l>
<l>but heed my counsel while the time permits,</l>
<l>and while thy feet are on a solid base,</l>
<l>but not, according to thy foolish wish,</l>
<l>pressing the axle. Rather let me light</l>
<l>the world beneath thy safe and wondering gaze.”</l>

    
<l>But Phaethon with youthful vigor leaped,</l>
<l>and in the light-made chariot lightly stood:</l>
<l>and he rejoiced, and with the reins in hand</l>
<l>thanked his reluctant parent.</l>

    
<l>Instantly</l>
<l>Eous, Aethon, Pyrois and Phlegon,</l>
<l>the winged horses of the Sun, gave vent</l>
<l>to flame-like neighs that filled the shaking air;</l>
<l>they pawed the barriers with their shining hoofs.</l>
<l>Then Tethys, witless of her grandson's fate</l>
<l>let back the barriers,—and the universe</l>
<l>was theirs to traverse. Taking the well-known road,</l>
<l>and moving through the air with winged feet,</l>
<l>they pierced resisting clouds, and spreading wide</l>
<l>their pinions soared upon the eastern wind,</l>
<l>far-wafted from that realm. But Phaethon,</l>
<l>so easy of their yoke, lost all control,</l>
<l>and the great car was tossed,—as tapered ships</l>
<l>when lightened of their ballast toss and heave</l>
<l>unsteady in the surging seas: the car</l>
<l>leaped lightly in the air, and in the heights</l>
<l>was tossed unsteady as an empty shell.</l>

    
<l>Soon as the steeds perceived it, with a rush</l>
<l>impetuous, they left the beaten track;</l>
<l>regardless of all order and control;</l>
<l>and Phaethon filled with fear, knew not to guide</l>
<l>with trusted reins, nor where the way might be—</l>
<l>nor, if he knew, could he control their flight.</l>

    
<l>Warmed in the sunshine, never felt before,</l>
<l>the gelid Triones attempted vain</l>
<l>to bathe in seas forbid: the Serpent cold</l>
<l>and torpid by the frozen Pole, too cold</l>
<l>for contest, warmed, and rage assumed from heat</l>
<l>bootes, troubled by the heat, took flight,</l>
<l>impeded by his wain.</l>

    
<l>And as from skies</l>
<l>of utmost height unhappy Phaethon</l>
<l>beheld the earth receding from his view,</l>
<l>a pallor spread his cheeks with sudden fear;</l>
<l>his knees began to quake; and through the flare</l>
<l>of vast effulgence darkness closed his eyes.</l>
<l>Now vainy he regrets he ever touched</l>
<l>his father's steeds, and he is stunned with grief</l>
<l>that so entreating he prevailed to know</l>
<l>his true descent. He rather would be called</l>
<l>the son of Merops. As a ship is tossed</l>
<l>by raging Boreas, when the conquered helm</l>
<l>has been abandoned, and the pilot leaves</l>
<l>the vessel to his vows and to the Gods;</l>
<l>so, helpless, he is borne along the sky.</l>

    
<l>What can he? Much of heaven remains behind;</l>
<l>a longer distance is in front of him—</l>
<l>each way is measured in his anxious mind.—</l>
<l>at first his gaze is fixed upon the west,</l>
<l>which fate has destined he shall never reach,</l>
<l>and then his eyes turn backward to the east.—</l>
<l>so, stupefied and dazed he neither dares</l>
<l>to loose the bits, nor tighten on the reins,</l>
<l>and he is ignorant of the horses' names.</l>


    
<l>He sees horrific wonders scattered round,</l>
<l>and images of hideous animals.—</l>
<l>and there's a spot where Scorpion bends his claws</l>
<l>in double circles, and with tail and arms</l>
<l>on either side, stretches his limbs throughout</l>
<l>the space of two Celestial Signs; and when</l>
<l>the lad beheld him, steeped in oozing slime</l>
<l>of venom, swart, and threatening to strike</l>
<l>grim wounds with jagged spear-points, he was lost;</l>
<l>and, fixed in chills of horror, dropped the reins.</l>

    
<l>When these they felt upon their rising backs,</l>
<l>the startled steeds sprang forthwith; and, unchecked,</l>
<l>through atmospheres of regions unexplored,</l>
<l>thence goaded by their unchecked violence,</l>
<l>broke through the lawful bounds, and rushed upon</l>
<l>the high fixed stars. They dragged the chariot</l>
<l>through devious ways, and soared amid the heights;</l>
<l>dashed down deep pathways, far, precipitous,</l>
<l>and gained a level near the scorching earth.</l>

    
<l>Phoebe is wondering that her brother's steeds</l>
<l>run lower than her own, and sees the smoke</l>
<l>of scorching clouds. The highest altitudes</l>
<l>are caught in flames, and as their moistures dry</l>
<l>they crack in chasms. The grass is blighted; trees</l>
<l>are burnt up with their leaves; the ripe brown crops</l>
<l>give fuel for self destruction—Oh what small</l>
<l>complaints! Great cities perish with their walls,</l>
<l>and peopled nations are consumed to dust—</l>
<l>the forests and the mountains are destroyed.</l>

    
<l>Cilician Taurus, Athos and Tmolus,</l>
<l>and Oeta are burning; and the far-famed Ida</l>
<l>and all her cooling rills are dry and burning,</l>
<l>and virgin Helicon, and Hoemos—later</l>
<l>Oeagrius called—and Aetna with tremendous,</l>
<l>redoubled flames, and double-peaked Parnassus,</l>
<l>Sicilian Eryx, Cynthus—Othrys, pine-clad,</l>
<l>and Rhodope, deprived his snowy mantle,</l>
<l>and Dindyma and Mycale and Mimas,</l>
<l>and Mount Cithaeron, famed for sacred rites:</l>
<l>and Scythia, though a land of frost, is burning,</l>
<l>and Caucasus,—and Ossa burns with Pindus,—</l>
<l>and greater than those two Olympus burns—</l>
<l>the lofty Alps, the cloud-topped Apennines.</l>

    
<l>And Phaethon, as he inhaled the air,</l>
<l>burning and scorching as a furnace blast,</l>
<l>and saw destruction on the flaming world,</l>
<l>and his great chariot wreathed in quenchless fires,</l>
<l>was suddenly unable to endure the heat,</l>
<l>the smoke and cinders, and he swooned away.—</l>
<l>if he had known the way, those winged steeds</l>
<l>would rush as wild unguided.—</l>

    
<l>then the skin</l>
<l>of Ethiopians took a swarthy hue,</l>
<l>the hot blood tingling to the surface: then</l>
<l>the heat dried up the land of Libya;</l>
<l>dishevelled, the lorn Nymphs, lamenting, sought</l>
<l>for all their emptied springs and lakes in vain;</l>
<l>Boeotia wailed for Dirce's cooling wave,</l>
<l>and Argos wailed for Amymone's stream—</l>
<l>and even Corinth for the clear Pyrene.</l>

    
<l>Not safer from the flames were distant streams;—</l>
<l>the Tanais in middle stream was steaming</l>
<l>and old Peneus and Teuthrantian Caicus,</l>
<l>Ismenus, rapid and Arcadian Erymanthus;</l>
<l>and even Xanthus destined for a second burning,</l>
<l>and tawny-waved Lycormas, and Meander,</l>
<l>turning and twisting, and Thracian Melas burns,</l>
<l>and the Laconian Eurotas burns,</l>
<l>the mighty Babylonian Euphrates,</l>
<l>Orontes and the Ganges, swift Thermodon,</l>
<l>Ister and Phasis and Alpheus boil.</l>
<l>The banks of Spercheus burn, the gold of Tagus</l>
<l>is melting in the flames. The swans whose songs</l>

    
<l>enhanced the beauties of Maeonian banks</l>
<l>are scalded in the Cayster's middle wave.</l>
<l>The Nile affrighted fled to parts remote,</l>
<l>and hid his head forever from the world:</l>
<l>now empty are his seven mouths, and dry</l>
<l>without or wave or stream; and also dry</l>
<l>Ismenian Hebrus, Strymon and the streams</l>
<l>of Hesper-Land, the rivers Rhine and Rhone,</l>
<l>and Po, and Tiber, ruler of the world.</l>

    
<l>And even as the ground asunder burst,</l>
<l>the light amazed in gloomy Tartarus</l>
<l>the King Infernal and his Spouse. The sea</l>
<l>contracted and his level waste became</l>
<l>a sandy desert. The huge mountain tops,</l>
<l>once covered by the ocean's waves, reared up,</l>
<l>by which the scattered Cyclades increased.</l>
<l>Even the fishes sought for deeper pools;—</l>
<l>the crooked dolphins dared not skip the waves;</l>
<l>the lifeless sea-calves floated on the top;</l>
<l>and it is even famed that Nereus hid</l>
<l>with Doris and her daughters, deep below</l>
<l>in seething caverns. With a dauntless mien</l>
<l>thrice Neptune tried to thrust his arms above</l>
<l>the waters;—thrice the heated air overcame</l>
<l>his courage.</l>

    
<l>Then the genial Earth, although</l>
<l>surrounded by the waters of the sea,</l>
<l>was parched and dry; for all her streams had hid</l>
<l>deep in the darkness of her winding caves.—</l>
<l>she lifted her productive countenance,</l>
<l>up to her rounded neck, and held her palms</l>
<l>on her sad brows; and as the mountains huge</l>
<l>trembled and tottered, beneath her wonted plane</l>
<l>declined she for a space—and thus began,</l>
<l>with parched voice;</l>

<l>“If this is thy decree,</l>
<l>O, Highest of the Gods,—if I have sinned</l>
<l>why do thy lightnings linger? For if doomed</l>
<l>by fires consuming I to perish must,</l>
<l>let me now die in thy celestial flames—</l>
<l>hurled by thine arm—and thus alleviate,</l>
<l>by thine omnipotence, this agony.</l>

<l>“How difficult to open my parched mouth,</l>
<l>and speak these words! (the vapours choking her),</l>
<l>behold my scorching hair, and see the clouds</l>
<l>of ashes falling on my blinded eyes,</l>
<l>and on my features! What a recompense</l>
<l>for my fertility! How often I</l>
<l>have suffered from the wounds of crooked plows</l>
<l>and rending harrows—tortured year by year!</l>
<l>For this I give to cattle juicy leaves</l>
<l>and fruits to man and frankincense to thee!</l>

<l>“Suppose destruction is my just award</l>
<l>what have the waters and thy brother done?</l>
<l>Why should thy brother's cooling waves decrease</l>
<l>and thus recede so distant from the skies?</l>
<l>If not thy brother's good nor mine may touch</l>
<l>thy mercy, let the pity of thy Heaven,</l>
<l>for lo, the smoking poles on either side</l>
<l>attest, if flames consume them or destroy, </l>
<l>the ruin of thy palace. Atlas, huge, </l>
<l>with restive shoulders hardly can support</l>
<l>the burning heavens. If the seas and lands</l>
<l>together perish and thy palace fall, </l>
<l>the universe confused will plunge once more</l>
<l>to ancient Chaos. Save it from this wreck—</l>
<l>if anything survive the fury of the flames.”</l>


    
<l>So made the tortured Earth an end of speech;</l>
<l>and she was fain to hide her countenance</l>
<l>in caves that border on the nether night.</l>

    
<l>But now the Almighty Father, having called</l>
<l>to witness all the Gods of Heaven, and him</l>
<l>who gave the car, that, else his power be shown,</l>
<l>must perish all in dire confusion, high</l>
<l>he mounted to the altitude from which</l>
<l>he spreads the mantling clouds, and fulminates</l>
<l>his dreadful thunders and swift lightning-bolts</l>
<l>terrific.—Clouds were none to find on the earth, </l>
<l>and the surrounding skies were void of rain.—</l>

    
<l>Jove, having reached that summit, stood and poised</l>
<l>in his almighty hand a flashing dart, </l>
<l>and, hurling it, deprived of life and seat</l>
<l>the youthful charioteer, and struck with fire</l>
<l>the raging flames— and by the same great force</l>
<l>those flames enveloping the earth were quenched,</l>
<l>and he who caused their fury lost his life.</l>

    
<l>Frantic in their affright the horses sprang</l>
<l>across the bounded way and cast their yokes,</l>
<l>and through the tangled harness lightly leaped.</l>
<l>And here the scattered harness lay, and there</l>
<l>the shattered axle, wrenched from off the pole,</l>
<l>and various portions of the broken car;</l>
<l>spokes of the broken Wheel were scattered round.</l>

    
<l>And far fell Phaethon with flaming hair;</l>
<l>as haply from the summer sky appears</l>
<l>a falling star, although it never drops</l>
<l>to startled earth.—Far distant from his home</l>
<l>the deep Eridanus received the lad</l>
<l>and bathed his foaming face. His body charred</l>
<l>by triple flames Hesperian Naiads bore,</l>
<l>still smoking, to a tomb, and this engraved</l>
<l>upon the stone; “Here Phaethon's remains</l>
<l>lie buried. He who drove his father's car</l>
<l>and fell, although he made a great attempt.”</l>

    
<l>Filled with consuming woe, his father hid</l>
<l>his countenance which grief had overcast.</l>
<l>And now, surpassing our belief, they say</l>
<l>a day passed over with no glowing sun;—</l>
<l>but light-affording flames appeared to change</l>
<l>disaster to the cause of good.</l>

    
<l>Amazed,</l>
<l>the woeful Clymene, when she had moaned</l>
<l>in grief, amid her lamentations tore</l>
<l>her bosom, as across the world she roamed,</l>
<l>at first to seek his lifeless corpse, and then</l>
<l>his bones. She wandered to that distant land</l>
<l>and found at last his bones ensepulchred.</l>
<l>There, clinging to the grave she fell and bathed</l>
<l>with many tears his name on marble carved,</l>
<l>and with her bosom warmed the freezing </l>
<l>stone.</l>

    
<l>And all the daughters of the Sun went there</l>
<l>giving their tears, alas a useless gift;—</l>
<l>they wept and beat their breasts, and day and night</l>
<l>called, “Phaethon,” who heard not any sound</l>
<l>of their complaint:—and there they lay foredone,</l>
<l>all scattered round the tomb.</l>

    
<l>The silent moon</l>
<l>had four times joined her horns and filled her disk,</l>
<l>while they, according to an ancient rite,</l>
<l>made lamentation. Prone upon the ground,</l>
<l>the eldest, Phaethusa, would arise</l>
<l>from there, but found her feet were growing stiff;</l>
<l>and uttered moan. Lampetia wished to aid</l>
<l>her sister but was hindered by new roots;</l>
<l>a third when she would tear her hair, plucked forth</l>
<l>but leaves: another wailed to find her legs</l>
<l>were fastened in a tree; another moaned</l>
<l>to find her arms to branches had been changed.</l>
<l>And while they wondered, bark enclosed their thighs,</l>
<l>and covered their smooth bellies, and their breasts,</l>
<l>and shoulders and their hands, but left untouched</l>
<l>their lips that called upon their mother's name.</l>
<l>What can she do for them? Hither she runs</l>
<l>and thither runs, wherever frenzy leads.</l>
<l>She kisses them, alas, while yet she may!</l>

    
<l>But not content with this, she tried to hale</l>
<l>their bodies from the trees; and she would tear</l>
<l>the tender branches with her hands, but lo!</l>
<l>The blood oozed out as from a bleeding wound;</l>
<l>and as she wounded them they shrieked aloud,</l>
<l>“Spare me! O mother spare me; in the tree</l>
<l>my flesh is torn! farewell! farewell! farewell!”</l>
<l>And as they spoke the bark enclosed their lips.</l>

    
<l>Their tears flow forth, and from the new-formed</l>
<l>boughs</l>
<l>amber distils and slowly hardens in the sun;</l>
<l>and far from there upon the waves is borne</l>
<l>to deck the Latin women.</l>

    
<l>Cycnus, son</l>
<l>of Sthenelus, by his maternal house</l>
<l>akin to Phaethon, and thrice by love</l>
<l>allied, beheld this wonderful event.—</l>
<l>he left his kingdom of Liguria,</l>
<l>and all its peopled cities, to lament</l>
<l>where the sad sisters had increased the woods,</l>
<l>beside the green banks of Eridanus.</l>

    
<l>There, as he made complaint, his manly voice</l>
<l>began to pipe a treble, shrill; and long</l>
<l>gray plumes concealed his hair. A slender neck</l>
<l>extended from his breast, and reddening toes</l>
<l>were joined together by a membrane. Wings</l>
<l>grew from his sides, and from his mouth was made</l>
<l>a blunted beak. Now Cycnus is a swan,</l>
<l>and yet he fears to trust the skies and Jove,</l>
<l>for he remembers fires, unjustly sent,</l>
<l>and therefore shuns the heat that he abhors,</l>
<l>and haunts the spacious lakes and pools and streams</l>
<l>that quench the fires.</l>

    
<l>In squalid garb, meanwhile,</l>
<l>and destitute of all his rays, the sire</l>
<l>of Phaethon, as dark as when eclipse bedims</l>
<l>his Wheel, abhors himself and hates the light,</l>
<l>shuns the bright day, gives up his mind to grief,</l>
<l>adds passion to his woe, denies the earth</l>
<l>his countenance, and thus laments; “My lot</l>
<l>was ever restless from the dawn of time,</l>
<l>and I am weary of this labour, void</l>
<l>and endless. Therefore, let who will urge forth</l>
<l>my car, light-bearing, and if none may dare,</l>
<l>when all the Gods of Heaven acknowledge it,</l>
<l>let Jove himself essay the task. Perchance,</l>
<l>when he takes up the reins, he may forget</l>
<l>his dreadful lightning that bereaves of child</l>
<l>a father's love; and as he tries the strength</l>
<l>of those flame-footed steeds will know, in truth,</l>
<l>the lad who failed to guide my chariot</l>
<l>deserved not death.”</l>

    
<l>But all the Deities</l>
<l>encircle Phoebus as he makes complaint,</l>
<l>and with their supplications they entreat</l>
<l>him not to plunge the world in darkness. Jove</l>
<l>would find excuses for the lightning-bolt,</l>
<l>hurled from his hand, and adds imperious threats</l>
<l>to his entreaties. Phoebus calls his steeds,</l>
<l>frenzied with their maddening fires, and </l>
<l>breaks</l>
<l>their fury, as he vents with stinging lash</l>
<l>his rage upon them, and in passion lays</l>
<l>on them the death of Phaethon his son.</l>


Callisto.
CALISTO AND JUPITER

<l>Now after Phaethon had suffered death</l>
<l>for the vast ruin wrought by scorching flames,</l>
<l>all the great walls of Heaven's circumference,</l>
<l>unmeasured, views the Father of the Gods,</l>
<l>with searching care, that none impaired by heat</l>
<l>may fall in ruins. Well assured they stand</l>
<l>in self-sustaining strength, his view, at last,</l>
<l>on all the mundane works of man is turned;—</l>
<l>his loving gaze long resting on his own</l>
<l>Arcadia. And he starts the streams and springs</l>
<l>that long have feared to flow; paints the wide earth</l>
<l>with verdant fields; covers the trees with leaves,</l>
<l>and clothes the injured forests in their green.</l>

    
<l>While wandering in the world, he stopped amazed,</l>
<l>when he beheld the lovely Nymph, Calisto,</l>
<l>and fires of love were kindled in his breast.</l>

    
<l>Calisto was not clothed in sumptuous robes,</l>
<l>nor did she deck her hair in artful coils;</l>
<l>but with a buckle she would gird her robe,</l>
<l>and bind her long hair with a fillet white.</l>
<l>She bore a slender javelin in her hand,</l>
<l>or held the curving bow; and thus in arms</l>
<l>as chaste Diana, none of Maenalus</l>
<l>was loved by that fair goddess more than she.</l>

    
<l>But everything must change. When bright the sun</l>
<l>rolled down the sky, beyond his middle course,</l>
<l>she pierced a secret thicket, known to her,</l>
<l>and having slipped the quiver from her arm,</l>
<l>she loosed the bended bow, and softly down</l>
<l>upon the velvet turf reclining, pressed</l>
<l>her white neck on the quiver while she slept.</l>

    
<l>When Jupiter beheld her, negligent</l>
<l>and beautiful, he argued thus, “How can</l>
<l>my consort, Juno, learn of this? And yet,</l>
<l>if chance should give her knowledge, what care I?</l>
<l>Let gain offset the scolding of her tongue!”</l>

    
<l>This said, the god transformed himself and took</l>
<l>Diana's form—assumed Diana's dress  </l>
<l>and imitating her awoke the maid,</l>
<l>and spoke in gentle tones, “What mountain slope,</l>
<l>O virgin of my train, hath been thy chase?”</l>
<l>Which, having heard, Calisto, rose and said,</l>
<l>“Hail, goddess! greater than celestial Jove!</l>
<l>I would declare it though he heard the words.”</l>

    
<l>Jove heard and smiled, well pleased to be preferred</l>
<l>above himself, and kissed her many times,</l>
<l>and strained her in his arms, while she began</l>
<l>to tell the varied fortunes of her hunt.—</l>
<l>but when his ardent love was known to her,</l>
<l>she struggled to escape from his embrace:</l>
<l>ah, how could she, a tender maid, resist</l>
<l>almighty Jove?—Be sure, Saturnia</l>
<l>if thou hadst only witnessed her thy heart</l>
<l>had shown more pity!—</l>

    
<l>Jupiter on wings,</l>
<l>transcendent, sought his glorious heights;</l>
<l>but she, in haste departing from that grove,</l>
<l>almost forgot her quiver and her bow.</l>

    
<l>Behold, Diana, with her virgin train,</l>
<l>when hunting on the slopes of Maenalus,</l>
<l>amidst the pleasures of exciting sport,</l>
<l>espied the Nymph and called her, who, afraid</l>
<l>that Jove apparelled in disguise deceived,</l>
<l>drew backward for a moment, till appeared</l>
<l>to her the lovely Nymphs that followed: thus,</l>
<l>assured deceit was none, she ventured near.</l>

    
<l>Alas, how difficult to hide disgrace!</l>
<l>She could not raise her vision from the ground,</l>
<l>nor as the leader of the hunting Nymphs,</l>
<l>as was her wont, walk by the goddess' side.</l>
<l>Her silence and her blushes were the signs</l>
<l>of injured honour. Ah Diana, thou,</l>
<l>if thou wert not a virgin, wouldst perceive</l>
<l>and pity her unfortunate distress.</l>

    
<l>The Moon's bent horns were rising from their ninth</l>
<l>sojourn, when, fainting from Apollo's flames,</l>
<l>the goddess of the Chase observed a cool</l>
<l>umbrageous grove, from which a murmuring stream</l>
<l>ran babbling gently over golden sands.</l>
<l>When she approved the spot, lightly she struck</l>
<l>her foot against the ripples of the stream,</l>
<l>and praising it began; “Far from the gaze</l>
<l>of all the curious we may bathe our limbs,</l>
<l>and sport in this clear water.” Quickly they</l>
<l>undid their garments,—but Calisto hid</l>
<l>behind the others, till they knew her state.—</l>
<l>Diana in a rage exclaimed, “Away!</l>
<l>Thou must not desecrate our sacred springs!”</l>
<l>And she was driven thence.</l>


    
<l>Ere this transpired,</l>
<l>observed the consort of the Thunder-God</l>
<l>her altered mien; but she for ripening time</l>
<l>withheld severe resentment. Now delay</l>
<l>was needless for distracted Juno heard</l>
<l>Calisto of the god of Heaven had borne</l>
<l>a boy called Arcas. Full of jealous rage,</l>
<l>her eyes and thoughts enkindled as she cried;</l>

<l>“And only this was wanting to complete</l>
<l>your wickedness, that you should bear a son</l>
<l>and flaunt abroad the infamy of Jove!</l>
<l>Unpunished you shall not escape, for I</l>
<l>will spoil the beauty that has made you proud</l>
<l>and dazzled Jupiter with wanton art.”</l>

    
<l>So saying, by her forehead's tresses seized</l>
<l>the goddess on her rival; and she dragged</l>
<l>her roughly to the ground. Pleading she raised</l>
<l>her suppliant arms and begged for mercy.—While</l>
<l>she pled, black hair spread over her white limbs;</l>
<l>her hands were lengthened into feet, and claws</l>
<l>long-curving tipped them; snarling jaws deformed</l>
<l>the mouth that Jove had kissed. And lest her prayers</l>
<l>and piteous words might move some listening God,</l>
<l>and give remembrance, speech was so denied,</l>
<l>that only from her throat came angry growls,</l>
<l>now uttered hoarse and threatening.</l>

    
<l>Still remains</l>
<l>her understanding, though her body, thus</l>
<l>transformed, makes her appear a savage bear.—</l>
<l>her sorrows are expressed in many a groan,</l>
<l>repeated as she lifts her hands—if we</l>
<l>may call them so—repeated as she lifts</l>
<l>them towards the stars and skies, ungrateful Jove</l>
<l>regarding; but her voice accuses not.</l>

    
<l>Afraid to rest in unfrequented woods,</l>
<l>she wandered in the fields that once were hers,</l>
<l>around her well-known dwelling. Over crags,</l>
<l>in terror, she was driven by the cries</l>
<l>of hounds; and many a time she fled in fear,</l>
<l>a huntress from the hunters, or she hid</l>
<l>from savage animals; forgetting her</l>
<l>transformed condition. Changed into a bear,</l>
<l>she fled affrighted from the bears that haunt</l>
<l>the rugged mountains; and she feared and fled</l>
<l>the wolves,—although her father was a wolf.</l>

    
<l>When thrice five birthdays rounded out the youth</l>
<l>of Arcas, offspring of Lycaon's child,</l>
<l>he hunted in the forest of his choice;</l>
<l>where, hanging with his platted nets the trees</l>
<l>of Erymanthian forest, he espied</l>
<l>his transformed mother,—but he knew her not;</l>
<l>no one had told him of his parentage.</l>

    
<l>Knowing her child, she stood with levelled gaze,</l>
<l>amazed and mute as he began approach;</l>
<l>but Arcas, frightened at the sight drew back</l>
<l>to pierce his mother's breast with wounding spear.—</l>
<l>but not permitting it the god of Heaven</l>
<l>averted, and removed them from that crime.</l>
<l>He, in a mighty wind—through vacant space,</l>
<l>upbore them to the dome of starry heaven,</l>
<l>and fixed them, Constellations, bright amid</l>
<l>the starry host.</l>

    
<l>Juno on high beheld</l>
<l>Calisto crowned with glory—great with rage</l>
<l>her bosom heaved. She flew across the sea,</l>
<l>to hoary Tethys and to old Oceanus,</l>
<l>whom all the Gods revere, and thus to them</l>
<l>in answer to their words she made address;</l>

<l>“And is it wondered that the Queen of Gods</l>
<l>comes hither from ethereal abodes?</l>
<l>My rival sits upon the Throne of Heaven:</l>
<l>yea, when the wing of Night has darkened</l>
<l>let my fair word be deemed of no repute,</l>
<l>if you behold not in the height of Heaven</l>
<l>those new made stars, now honoured to my shame,</l>
<l>conspicuous; fixed in the highest dome of space</l>
<l>that circles the utmost axis of the world.</l>

<l>“Who, then, should hesitate to put affront</l>
<l>on Juno? matchless goddess! each offense</l>
<l>redounds in benefit! Who dreads her rage?</l>
<l>Oh boundless powers! Oh unimagined deeds!</l>
<l>My enemy assumes a goddess' form</l>
<l>when my decree deprives her human shape;—</l>
<l>and thus the guilty rue their chastisement!</l>

<l>“Now let high Jove to human shape transform</l>
<l>this hideous beast, as once before he changed</l>
<l>his Io from a heifer.—Let him now</l>
<l>divorce his Juno and consort with her,</l>
<l>and lead Calisto to his couch, and take</l>
<l>that wolf, Lycaon, for a father-in-law!</l>

<l>“Oh, if an injury to me, your child,</l>
<l>may move your pity! drive the Seven Stars</l>
<l>from waters crystalline and azure-tint,</l>
<l>and your domain debar from those that shine</l>
<l>in Heaven, rewarded for Jove's wickedness.—</l>
<l>bathe not a concubine in waters pure.”—</l>


Corvus. Coronis. Cornix. Ocyroe.

<l>the Gods of Ocean granted her request.</l>

CORONIS AND PHOEBUS

<l>High in her graceful chariot through the air,</l>
<l>translucent, wends the goddess, glorious child</l>
<l>of Saturn, with her peacocks many-hued:</l>
<l>her peacocks, by the death of Argus limped,</l>
<l>so gay were made when black as midnight turned</l>
<l>thy wings, O chattering raven! white of yore.</l>
<l>For, long ago the ravens were not black—</l>
<l>their plumage then was white as any dove—</l>
<l>white-feathered, snow-white as the geese that guard</l>
<l>with watchful cries the Capitol: as white</l>
<l>as swans that haunt the streams. Disgrace reversed</l>
<l>the raven's hue from white to black, because</l>
<l>offense was given by his chattering tongue.</l>

    
<l>O glorious Phoebus! dutiful to thee,</l>
<l>Coronis of Larissa, fairest maid</l>
<l>of all Aemonia, was a grateful charm,</l>
<l>a joy to thee whilst faithful to thy love,—</l>
<l>while none defamed her chastity. But when</l>
<l>the Raven, bird of Phoebus, learned the Nymph</l>
<l>had been unfaithful, mischief-bent that bird,</l>
<l>spreading his white wings, hastened to impart</l>
<l>the sad news to his master. After him</l>
<l>the prattling Crow followed with flapping wings,</l>
<l>eager to learn what caused the Raven's haste.</l>

    
<l>Concealing nothing, with his busy tongue</l>
<l>the Raven gave the scandal to that bird:</l>
<l>and unto him the prattling Crow replied;</l>

<l>“A fruitless errand has befooled thy wits!</l>
<l>Take timely warning of my fateful cries:</l>
<l>consider what I was and what I am:</l>
<l>was justice done? 'Twas my fidelity</l>
<l>that caused my downfall. For, it came to pass,</l>
<l>within a basket, fashioned of small twigs,</l>
<l>Minerva had enclosed that spawn; begot</l>
<l>without a mother, Ericthonius;</l>
<l>which to the wardship of three virgins, born</l>
<l>of double-natured Cecrops, she consigned</l>
<l>with this injunction, ‘Look ye not therein,</l>
<l>nor learn the secret.’—</l>
<l>“But I saw their deeds</l>
<l>while hidden in the leaves of a great tree</l>
<l>two of the sisters, Herse and Pandrosos,</l>
<l>observed the charge, but scoffing at their fears,</l>
<l>the third, Aglauros, with her nimble hands</l>
<l>untied the knotted cords, and there disclosed</l>
<l>a serpent and an infant. This I told</l>
<l>Minerva; but in turn, she took away</l>
<l>her long protection, and degraded me</l>
<l>beneath the boding Owl.—My punishment</l>
<l>should warn the birds how many dangers they</l>
<l>incur from chattering tongues.</l>

<l>“Not my desire</l>
<l>impelled me to report to her, nor did</l>
<l>I crave protection; which, if thou wilt ask</l>
<l>Minerva, though enraged she must confirm.</l>
<l>And when is told to thee what lately fame</l>
<l>established, thou wilt not despise the Crow. </l>

<l>“Begot by Coronaeus, who was lord</l>
<l>of all the land of Phocis, I was once</l>
<l>a royal virgin, sought by suitors rich</l>
<l>and powerful. But beauty proved the cause</l>
<l>of my misfortune; for it came to pass,</l>
<l>as I was slowly walking on the sands</l>
<l>that skirt the merge of ocean, where was oft</l>
<l>my wont to roam, the god of Ocean gazed</l>
<l>impassioned, and with honied words implored</l>
<l>my love—but finding that I paid no heed,</l>
<l>and all his words despised, he fumed with rage</l>
<l>and followed me.</l>

<l>“I fled from that sea-shore,</l>
<l>to fields of shifting sands that all my steps</l>
<l>delayed: and in despair upon the Gods</l>
<l>and all mankind I called for aid, but I</l>
<l>was quite alone and helpless. Presently</l>
<l>the chaste Minerva, me, a virgin, heard</l>
<l>and me assistance gave: for as my arms</l>
<l>implored the Heavens, downy feathers grew</l>
<l>from out the flesh; and as I tried to cast</l>
<l>my mantle from my shoulders, wings appeared</l>
<l>upon my tender sides; and as I strove</l>
<l>to beat my naked bosom with my hands,</l>
<l>nor hands remained nor naked breast to beat.</l>

<l>“I ran, and as I sped the sands no more</l>
<l>delayed me; I was soaring from the ground;</l>
<l>and as I winged the air, Minerva chose</l>
<l>me for a life-companion; but alas,</l>
<l>although my life was blameless, fate or chance</l>
<l>deprived me of Minerva's loving aid;</l>
<l>for soon Nictimene succeeded me</l>
<l>to her protection and deserved esteem.—</l>
<l>it happened in this way,—Nictimene</l>
<l>committed the most wicked crimes, for which</l>
<l>Minerva changed her to the bird of night—</l>
<l>and ever since has claimed her as her own</l>
<l>instead of me; and this despite the deed</l>
<l>for which she shuns the glorious light of day,</l>
<l>and conscious of her crime conceals her shame</l>
<l>in the dark night—Minerva's Owl now called.</l>
<l>All the glad birds of day, indignant shun,</l>
<l>and chase her from the skies.”</l>

    
<l>But now replied</l>
<l>the Raven to the Crow, that talked so much,</l>
<l>“A mischief fall upon your prating head</l>
<l>for this detention of my flight. Your words</l>
<l>and warnings I despise.” With which retort</l>
<l>he winged upon his journey, swiftly thence</l>
<l>in haste, despite the warning to inform</l>
<l>his patron, Phoebus, how he saw the fair</l>
<l>Coronis with a lad of Thessaly.</l>

    
<l>And when Apollo, Phoebus, heard the tale</l>
<l>the busy Raven made such haste to tell,</l>
<l>he dropped his plectrum and his laurel wreath,</l>
<l>and his bright countenance went white with rage.</l>
<l>He seized his trusted arms, and having bent</l>
<l>his certain bow, pierced with a deadly shaft</l>
<l>that bosom which so often he had pressed</l>
<l>against his own.</l>

    
<l>Coronis moaned in pain,—</l>
<l>and as she drew the keen shaft from the wound,</l>
<l>her snow-white limbs were bathed in purple blood:</l>
<l>and thus she wailed, “Ah, Phoebus! punishment</l>
<l>is justly mine! but wherefore didst thou not</l>
<l>await the hour of birth? for by my death</l>
<l>an innocent is slain.” This said, her soul</l>
<l>expired with her life-blood, and death congealed</l>
<l>her drooping form.</l>

    
<l>Sadly the love-lore God</l>
<l>repents his jealous deed; regrets too late</l>
<l>his ready credence to the Raven's tale.</l>
<l>Mourning his thoughtless deed, blaming himself,</l>
<l>he vents his rage upon the talking bird;</l>
<l>he hates his bow, the string, his own right hand,</l>
<l>the fateful arrow. As a last resource,</l>
<l>and thus to overcome her destiny,</l>
<l>he strove to cherish her beloved form;</l>
<l>for vain were all his medicinal arts.</l>

    
<l>But when he saw upraised the funeral pyre,</l>
<l>where wreathed in flames her body should be burnt,</l>
<l>the sorrow of his heart welled forth in sighs;</l>
<l>but tearless orbed, for no celestial face</l>
<l>may tide of woe bedew. So grieves the poor dam,</l>
<l>when, swinging from his right the flashing ax,</l>
<l>the butcher with a sounding blow divides</l>
<l>the hollow temples of her sucking calf.</l>

    
<l>Yet, after Phoebus poured the fragrant myrrh,</l>
<l>sweet perfumes on her breast, that now once more</l>
<l>against his own he pressed, and after all</l>
<l>the prematurely hastened rites were done,</l>
<l>he would not suffer the offspring of his loins</l>
<l>to mingle with her ashes, but he plucked</l>
<l>from out the flames, forth from the mother's thighs</l>
<l>his child, unborn, and carried to the cave</l>
<l>of double-natured Chiron.</l>

    
<l>Then to him</l>
<l>he called the silly raven, high in hopes</l>
<l>of large requital due for all his words;</l>
<l>but, angry with his meddling ways, the God</l>
<l>turned the white feathers of that bird to black</l>
<l>and then forbade forever more to perch</l>
<l>among the favoured birds whose plumes are white.</l>


OCYROE AND AESCULAPIUS

<l>Chiron, the Centaur, taught his pupil; proud</l>
<l>that he was honoured by that God-like charge.</l>
<l>Behold, his lovely daughter, who was born</l>
<l>beside the margin of a rapid stream,</l>
<l>came forward, with her yellow hair as gold</l>
<l>adown her shoulders.—She was known by name</l>
<l>Ocyroe. The hidden things that Fate</l>
<l>conceals, she had the power to tell; for not</l>
<l>content was she to learn her father's arts,</l>
<l>but rather pondered on mysterious things.</l>

    
<l>So, when the god of Frenzy warmed her breast,</l>
<l>gazing on Aesculapius,—the child</l>
<l>of Phoebus and Coronis, while her soul</l>
<l>was gifted, with prophetic voice she said;</l>

<l>“O thou who wilt bestow on all the world</l>
<l>the blessed boon of health, increase in strength!</l>
<l>To thee shall mortals often owe their lives:</l>
<l>to thee is given the power to raise the dead.</l>
<l>But when against the power of Deities</l>
<l>thou shalt presume to dare thy mortal skill,</l>
<l>the bolts of Jove will shatter thy great might,</l>
<l>and health no more be thine from thence to grant.</l>
<l>And from a god thou shalt return to dust,</l>
<l>and once again from dust become a God;</l>
<l>and thou shalt thus renew thy destiny.—</l>

<l>“And thou, dear father Chiron, brought to birth</l>
<l>with pledge of an immortal life, informed</l>
<l>with ever-during strength, when biting flames</l>
<l>of torment from the baneful serpent's blood</l>
<l>are coursing in thy veins, thou shalt implore</l>
<l>a welcome death; and thy immortal life</l>
<l>the Gods shall suffer to the power of death.—</l>
<l>and the three Destinies shall cut thy thread.”</l>

    
<l>She would continue these prophetic words</l>
<l>but tears unbidden trickled down her face;</l>
<l>and, as it seemed her sighs would break her heart,</l>
<l>she thus bewailed; “The Fates constrain my speech</l>
<l>and I can say no more; my power has gone.</l>
<l>Alas, my art, although of little force</l>
<l>and doubtful worth, has brought upon my head</l>
<l>the wrath of Heaven.</l>

<l>“Oh wherefore did I know</l>
<l>to cast the future? Now my human form</l>
<l>puts on another shape, and the long grass</l>
<l>affords me needed nourishment. I want</l>
<l>to range the boundless plains and have become,</l>
<l>in image of my father's kind, a mare:</l>
<l>but gaining this, why lose my human shape?</l>
<l>My father's form is one of twain combined.”</l>

    
<l>And as she wailed the words became confused</l>
<l>and scarcely understood; and soon her speech</l>
<l>was only as the whinny of a mare.</l>
<l>Down to the meadow's green her arms were stretched;</l>
<l>her fingers joined together, and smooth hoofs</l>

    
<l>made of five nails a single piece of horn.</l>
<l>Her face and neck were lengthened, and her hair</l>
<l>swept downward as a tail; the scattered locks</l>
<l>that clung around her neck were made a mane,</l>
<l>tossed over to the right. Her voice and shape</l>
<l>were altogether changed, and since that day</l>
<l>the change has given her a different name.</l>


Battus.

<l>In vain her hero father, Chiron, prayed</l>
<l>the glorious God, Apollo, her to aid.</l>
<l>He could not thwart the will of mighty Jove;</l>
<l>and if the power were his, far from the spot,</l>
<l>from thence afar his footsteps trod the fields</l>
<l>of Elis and Messenia, far from thence.</l>

BATTUS AND MERCURY

<l>Now while Apollo wandered on those plains,—</l>
<l>his shoulders covered with a shepherd's skin,</l>
<l>his left hand holding his long shepherd's staff,</l>
<l>his right hand busied with the seven reeds</l>
<l>of seven sizes, brooding over the death</l>
<l>of Hymenaeus, lost from his delight;</l>
<l>while mournful ditties on the reeds were tuned,—</l>
<l>his kine, forgotten, strayed away to graze</l>
<l>over the plains of Pylos. Mercury</l>
<l>observed them, unattended, and from thence</l>
<l>drove them away and hid them in the forest.</l>

    
<l>So deftly did he steal them, no one knew</l>
<l>or noticed save an ancient forester,</l>
<l>well known to all the neighbor-folk, by them</l>
<l>called Battus. He was keeper of that wood,</l>
<l>and that green pasture where the blooded mares</l>
<l>of rich Neleus grazed.</l>

    
<l>As Mercury</l>
<l>distrusted him, he led him to one side</l>
<l>and said; “Good stranger, whosoever thou art,</l>
<l>if any one should haply question thee,</l>
<l>if thou hast seen these kine, deny it all;</l>
<l>and for thy good will, ere the deed is done,</l>
<l>I give as thy reward this handsome cow.”</l>

    
<l>Now when the gift was his, old Battus said,</l>
<l>“Go hence in safety, if it be thy will;</l>
<l>and should my tongue betray thee, let that stone</l>
<l>make mention of the theft.” And as he spoke,</l>
<l>he pointed to a stone.</l>

    
<l>The son of Jove</l>
<l>pretended to depart, but quickly changed</l>
<l>his voice and features, and retraced his steps,</l>
<l>and thus again addressed that ancient man;</l>
<l>“Kind sir, if thou wouldst earn a fair reward,</l>
<l>a heifer and a bull, if thou hast seen</l>
<l>some cattle pass, I pray thee give thy help,</l>
<l>and tell me of the theft.” So the reward</l>
<l>was doubled; and the old man answered him,</l>
<l>“Beyond those hills they be,” and so they were</l>
<l>‘Beyond those hills.’</l>

    
<l>And, laughing, Mercury said,</l>
<l>“Thou treacherous man to me dost thou betray</l>
<l>myself? Dost thou bewray me to myself?”</l>
<l>The god indignant turned his perjured breast</l>
<l>into a stone which even now is called</l>
<l>“The Spy of Pylos,” a disgraceful name,</l>
<l>derived from days of old, but undeserved.</l>


Aglauros. Invidia.
AGLAUROS AND MERCURY

<l>High in the dome of Heaven, behold the bright</l>
<l>Caduceus-Bearer soared on balanced wings;</l>
<l>and far below him through a fruitful grove,</l>
<l>devoted to Minerva's hallowed reign,</l>
<l>some virgins bearing on their lovely heads,</l>
<l>in wicker baskets wreathed and decked with flowers,</l>
<l>their sacred offerings to the citadel</l>
<l>of that chaste goddess. And the winged God,</l>
<l>while circling in the clear unbounded skies,</l>
<l>beheld that train of virgins, beautiful,</l>
<l>as they were thence returning on their way.</l>

    
<l>Not forward on a level line he flew,</l>
<l>but wheeled in circles round. Lo, the swift kite</l>
<l>swoops round the smoking entrails, while the priests</l>
<l>enclose in guarded ranks their sacrifice:</l>
<l>wary with fear, that swiftest of all birds,</l>
<l>dares not to venture from his vantage height,</l>
<l>but greedily hovers on his waving wings</l>
<l>around his keen desire. So, the bright God</l>
<l>circled those towers, Actaean, round and round,</l>
<l>in mazey circles, greedy as the bird.</l>

    
<l>As much as Lucifer outshines the stars</l>
<l>that emulate the glory of his rays,</l>
<l>as greatly as bright Phoebe pales thy light,</l>
<l>O lustrous Lucifer! so far surpassed</l>
<l>in beauty the fair maiden Herse, all</l>
<l>those lovely virgins of that sacred train,</l>
<l>departing joyous from Minerva's grove.</l>

    
<l>The Son of Jove, astonished, while he wheeled</l>
<l>on balanced pinions through the yielding air,</l>
<l>burned hot; as oft from Balearic sling</l>
<l>the leaden missile, hurled with sudden force,</l>
<l>burns in a glowing heat beneath the clouds.</l>

    
<l>Then sloped the god his course from airy height,</l>
<l>and turned a different way; another way</l>
<l>he went without disguise, in confidence</l>
<l>of his celestial grace. But though he knew</l>
<l>his face was beautiful, he combed his hair,</l>
<l>and fixed his flowing raiment, that the fringe</l>
<l>of radiant gold appeared. And in his hand</l>
<l>he waved his long smooth wand, with which he gives</l>
<l>the wakeful sleep or waketh ridded eyes.</l>
<l>He proudly glanced upon his twinkling feet</l>
<l>that sparkled with their scintillating wings.</l>

    
<l>In a secluded part of that great fane,</l>
<l>devoted to Minerva's hallowed rites,</l>
<l>three chambers were adorned with tortoise shell</l>
<l>and ivory and precious woods inlaid;</l>
<l>and there, devoted to Minerva's praise,</l>
<l>three well known sisters dwelt. Upon the right</l>
<l>dwelt Pandrosos and over on the left</l>
<l>Aglauros dwelt, and Herse occupied</l>
<l>the room between those two.</l>

    
<l>When Mercury</l>
<l>drew near to them, Aglauros first espied</l>
<l>the God, and ventured to enquire his name,</l>
<l>and wherefore he was come. Then gracious spoke</l>
<l>to her in answer the bright son of Jove;</l>

<l>“Behold the god who carries through the air</l>
<l>the mandates of almighty Jupiter!</l>
<l>But I come hither not to waste my time</l>
<l>in idle words, but rather to beseech</l>
<l>thy kindness and good aid, that I may win</l>
<l>the love of thy devoted sister Herse.”</l>

    
<l>Aglauros, on the son of Jupiter,</l>
<l>gazed with those eyes that only lately viewed</l>
<l>the guarded secret of the yellow-haired</l>
<l>Minerva, and demanded as her price</l>
<l>gold of great weight; before he paid denied</l>
<l>admittance of the house.</l>

    
<l>Minerva turned,</l>
<l>with orbs of stern displeasure, towards the maid</l>
<l>Aglauros; and her bosom heaved with sighs</l>
<l>so deeply laboured that her Aegis-shield</l>
<l>was shaken on her valiant breast. For she</l>
<l>remembered when Aglauros gave to view</l>
<l>her charge, with impious hand, that monster form</l>
<l>without a mother, maugre Nature's law,</l>
<l>what time the god who dwells on Lemnos loved.—</l>

    
<l>now to requite the god and sister; her</l>
<l>to punish whose demand of gold was great;</l>
<l>Minerva to the Cave of Envy sped.</l>
<l>Dark, hideous with black gore, her dread abode</l>
<l>is hidden in the deepest hollowed cave,</l>
<l>in utmost limits where the genial sun</l>
<l>may never shine, and where the breathing winds</l>
<l>may never venture; dismal, bitter cold,</l>
<l>untempered by the warmth of welcome fires,</l>
<l>involved forever in abounding gloom.</l>

    
<l>When the fair champion came to this abode</l>
<l>she stood before its entrance, for she deemed</l>
<l>it not a lawful thing to enter there:</l>
<l>and she whose arm is mortal to her foes,</l>
<l>struck the black door-posts with her pointed spear,</l>
<l>and shook them to the center. Straight the doors</l>
<l>flew open, and, behold, within was Envy</l>
<l>ravening the flesh of vipers, self-begot,</l>
<l>the nutriment of her depraved desires.—</l>

    
<l>when the great goddess met her evil gaze</l>
<l>she turned her eyes away. But Envy slow,</l>
<l>in sluggish languor from the ground uprose,</l>
<l>and left the scattered serpents half-devoured;</l>
<l>then moving with a sullen pace approached.—</l>
<l>and when she saw the gracious goddess, girt</l>
<l>with beauty and resplendent in her arms,</l>
<l>she groaned aloud and fetched up heavy sighs.</l>

    
<l>Her face is pale, her body long and lean,</l>
<l>her shifting eyes glance to the left and right,</l>
<l>her snaggle teeth are covered with black rust,</l>
<l>her hanging paps overflow with bitter gall,</l>
<l>her slavered tongue drips venom to the ground;</l>
<l>busy in schemes and watchful in dark snares</l>
<l>sweet sleep is banished from her blood-shot eyes;</l>
<l>her smiles are only seen when others weep;</l>
<l>with sorrow she observes the fortunate,</l>
<l>and pines away as she beholds their joy;</l>
<l>her own existence is her punishment,</l>
<l>and while tormenting she torments herself.</l>

    
<l>Although Minerva held her in deep scorn</l>
<l>she thus commanded her with winged words;</l>
<l>“Instil thy poison in Aglauros, child</l>
<l>of Cecrops; I command thee; do my will.”</l>

    
<l>She spake; and spurning with her spear the ground</l>
<l>departed; and the sad and furtive-eyed</l>
<l>envy observed her in her glorious flight:</l>
<l>she murmured at the goddess, great in arms:</l>
<l>but waiting not she took in hand her staff,</l>
<l>which bands of thorns encircled as a wreath,</l>
<l>and veiled in midnight clouds departed thence.</l>
<l>She blasted on her way the ripening fields;</l>
<l>scorched the green meadows, starred with flowers,</l>
<l>and breathed a pestilence throughout the land</l>
<l>and the great cities. When her eyes beheld</l>
<l>the glorious citadel of Athens, great</l>
<l>in art and wealth, abode of joyful peace,</l>
<l>she hardly could refrain from shedding tears,</l>
<l>that nothing might be witnessed worthy tears.</l>

    
<l>She sought the chamber where Aglauros slept,</l>
<l>and hastened to obey the God's behest.</l>
<l>She touched the maiden's bosom with her hands,</l>
<l>foul with corrupting stains, and pierced her heart</l>
<l>with jagged thorns, and breathed upon her face</l>
<l>a noxious venom; and distilled through all</l>
<l>the marrow of her bones, and in her lungs,</l>
<l>a poison blacker than the ooze of pitch.</l>

    
<l>And lest the canker of her poisoned soul</l>
<l>might spread unchecked throughout increasing space,</l>
<l>she caused a vision of her sister's form</l>
<l>to rise before her, happy with the God</l>
<l>who shone in his celestial beauty. All</l>
<l>appeared more beautiful than real life.—</l>

    
<l>when the most wretched daughter of Cecrops</l>
<l>had seen the vision secret torment seized</l>
<l>on all her vitals; and she groaned aloud,</l>
<l>tormented by her frenzy day and night.</l>

    
<l>A slow consumption wasted her away,</l>
<l>as ice is melted by the slant sunbeam,</l>
<l>when the cool clouds are flitting in the sky.</l>
<l>If she but thought of Herse's happiness</l>
<l>she burned, as thorny bushes are consumed</l>
<l>with smoldering embers under steaming stems.</l>
<l>She could not bear to see her sister's joy,</l>
<l>and longed for death, an end of misery;</l>
<l>or schemed to end the torture of her mind</l>
<l>by telling all she knew in shameful words,</l>
<l>whispered to her austere and upright sire.</l>

    
<l>But after many agonizing hours,</l>
<l>she sat before the threshold of their home</l>
<l>to intercept the God, who as he neared</l>
<l>spoke softly in smooth blandishment.</l>
<l>“Enough,” she said, “I will not move from here</l>
<l>until thou hast departed from my sight.”</l>
<l>“Let us adhere to that which was agreed.”</l>
<l>Rejoined the graceful-formed Cyllenian God,</l>
<l>who as he spoke thrust open with a touch</l>
<l>of his compelling wand the carved door.</l>

    
<l>But when she made an effort to arise,</l>
<l>her thighs felt heavy, rigid and benumbed;</l>
<l>and as she struggled to arise her knees</l>
<l>were stiffened? and her nails turned pale and cold;</l>
<l>her veins grew pallid as the blood congealed.</l>
<l>And even as the dreaded cancer spreads</l>
<l>through all the body, adding to its taint</l>
<l>the flesh uninjured; so, a deadly chill</l>
<l>entered by slow degrees her breast, and stopped</l>
<l>her breathing, and the passages of life.</l>
<l>She did not try to speak, but had she made</l>
<l>an effort to complain there was not left</l>
<l>a passage for her voice. Her neck was changed</l>
<l>to rigid stone, her countenance felt hard;</l>
<l>she sat a bloodless statue, but of stone</l>
<l>not marble-white—her mind had stained it black.</l>


Europa.

<l>So from the land of Pallas went the God,</l>
<l>his great revenge accomplished on the head</l>
<l>of impious Aglauros; and he soared</l>
<l>on waving wings into the opened skies:</l>
<l>and there his father called him to his side,</l>
<l>and said,—with words to hide his passion;—Son,—</l>
<l>thou faithful minister of my commands.—</l>
<l>let naught delay thee—swiftly take the way,</l>
<l>accustomed, to the land of Sidon (which</l>
<l>adores thy mother's star upon the left)</l>
<l>when there, drive over to the sounding shore</l>
<l>that royal herd, which far away is fed</l>
<l>on mountain grass.—</l>

    
<l>he spoke, and instantly</l>
<l>the herd was driven from the mountain side;</l>
<l>then headed for the shore, as Jove desired,—</l>
<l>to where the great king's daughter often went</l>
<l>in play, attended by the maids of Tyre.—</l>
<l>can love abide the majesty of kings?</l>
<l>Love cannot always dwell upon a throne.—</l>

EUROPA AND JUPITERTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS

<l>Jove laid aside his glorious dignity,</l>
<l>for he assumed the semblance of a bull</l>
<l>and mingled with the bullocks in the groves,</l>
<l>his colour white as virgin snow, untrod,</l>
<l>unmelted by the watery Southern Wind.</l>

    
<l>His neck was thick with muscles, dewlaps hung</l>
<l>between his shoulders; and his polished horns,</l>
<l>so small and beautifully set, appeared</l>
<l>the artifice of man; fashioned as fair</l>
<l>and more transparent than a lucent gem.</l>
<l>His forehead was not lowered for attack,</l>
<l>nor was there fury in his open eyes;</l>
<l>the love of peace was in his countenance.</l>

    
<l>When she beheld his beauty and mild eyes,</l>
<l>the daughter of Agenor was amazed;</l>
<l>but, daring not to touch him, stood apart</l>
<l>until her virgin fears were quieted;</l>
<l>then, near him, fragrant flowers in her hand</l>
<l>she offered,—tempting, to his gentle mouth:</l>
<l>and then the loving god in his great joy</l>
<l>kissed her sweet hands, and could not wait her will.</l>

    
<l>Jove then began to frisk upon the grass,</l>
<l>or laid his snow-white side on the smooth sand,</l>
<l>yellow and golden. As her courage grew</l>
<l>he gave his breast one moment for caress,</l>
<l>or bent his head for garlands newly made,</l>
<l>wreathed for his polished horns.</l>

    
<l>The royal maid,</l>
<l>unwitting what she did, at length sat down</l>
<l>upon the bull's broad back. Then by degrees</l>
<l>the god moved from the land and from the shore,</l>
<l>and placed his feet, that seemed but shining hoofs,</l>
<l>in shallow water by the sandy merge;</l>
<l>and not a moment resting bore her thence,</l>
<l>across the surface of the Middle Sea,</l>
<l>while she affrighted gazed upon the shore—</l>
<l>so fast receding. And she held his horn</l>
<l>with her right hand, and, steadied by the left,</l>
<l>held on his ample back—and in the breeze</l>
<l>her waving garments fluttered as they went.</l>
