<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 7


Iason et Medea.
JASON AND MEDEA

<l>Over the storm-tossed waves, the Argonauts</l>
<l>had sailed in Argo, their long ship to where</l>
<l>King Phineus, needy in his old age, reigned—</l>
<l>deprived of sight and feeble. When the sons</l>
<l>of Boreas had landed on the shore,</l>
<l>and seen the Harpies snatching from the king</l>
<l>his nourishment, befouling it with beaks</l>
<l>obscene, they drove those human-vultures thence.</l>

    
<l>And having suffered hardships and great toils,</l>
<l>after the day they rescued the sad king</l>
<l>from the vile Harpies, those twin valiant youths,</l>
<l>Zetes and Calais came with their chief,</l>
<l>the mighty Jason, where the Phasis flows.</l>

    
<l>From the green margin of that river, all</l>
<l>the crew of Argonauts, by Jason led,</l>
<l>went to the king Aeetes and required</l>
<l>the Golden Fleece, that he received from Phryxus.</l>
<l>When they had bargained with him, full of wiles</l>
<l>he offered to restore the Golden Fleece</l>
<l>only to those who might to him return,</l>
<l>victorious from hard labors of great risk.</l>

    
<l>Medea, the king's daughter, near his throne,</l>
<l>saw Jason, leader of the Argonauts,</l>
<l>as he was pressing to secure a prize—</l>
<l>and loved at sight with a consuming flame.</l>

    
<l>Although she struggled to suppress her love,</l>
<l>unable to restrain herself, she said,</l>
<l>“In vain I've striven to subdue my heart:</l>
<l>some god it must be, which I cannot tell,</l>
<l>is working to destroy my hapless life;</l>
<l>or else it is the burning flame of love</l>
<l>that in me rages. If it is not love,</l>
<l>why do the mandates of my father seem</l>
<l>too harsh? They surely are too harsh. Why do</l>
<l>I fear that he may perish whom I have</l>
<l>seen only once? What is the secret cause</l>
<l>that I am agitated by such fears?—</l>
<l>It is no other than the god of Love.</l>

    
<l>“Thrust from your virgin breast such burning flames</l>
<l>and overcome their hot unhappiness—</l>
<l>if I could do so, I should be myself:</l>
<l>but some deluding power is holding me</l>
<l>helpless against my will. Desire persuades</l>
<l>me one way, but my reason still persuades</l>
<l>another way. I see a better course</l>
<l>and I approve, but follow its defeat. —</l>

    
<l>“O royal maiden, why are you consumed</l>
<l>with love for this strange man, and why are you</l>
<l>so willing to be carried by the nuptial ties</l>
<l>so far from your own country, where, indeed,</l>
<l>are many brave men worthy of your love?</l>

    
<l>“Whether for life or death his numbered hours</l>
<l>are in the mercy of the living Gods,</l>
<l>and that he may not suffer risk of death,</l>
<l>too well foreseen, now let my prayers prevail—</l>
<l>righteously uttered of a generous heart</l>
<l>without the stress of love. What wicked thing</l>
<l>has Jason done? His handsome person, youth,</l>
<l>and noble ways, would move a heart of stone.</l>

    
<l>“Have I a heart of flint, or was I born</l>
<l>a tigress to deny him timely aid?—</l>
<l>Unless I interpose, he will be slain</l>
<l>by the hot breath of brazen-footed bulls,</l>
<l>or will be slaughtered by the warriors, sprung</l>
<l>miraculous from earth, or will be given</l>
<l>to satisfy the ravenous appetite</l>
<l>of a huge dragon.</l>

    
<l>“Let my gloating eyes</l>
<l>be satiate with his dying agonies!</l>
<l>Let me incite the fury of these bulls!</l>
<l>Stir to their blood-lust mad-born sons of Earth!</l>
<l>Rouse up the never-sleeping dragon's rage!—</l>
<l>“Avert it Gods!—</l>

    
<l>“But why should I cry out</l>
<l>upon the Gods to save him from such wrong,</l>
<l>when, by my actions and my power, myself</l>
<l>may shield him from all evils?</l>

    
<l>“Such a course</l>
<l>would wreck the kingdom of my father—and by me</l>
<l>the wily stranger would escape from him;</l>
<l>and spreading to the wind his ready sails</l>
<l>he would forget and leave me to my fate.—</l>
<l>Oh, if he should forget my sacrifice,</l>
<l>and so prefer those who neglected him,</l>
<l>let him then perish in his treachery.—</l>

    
<l>“But these are idle thoughts: his countenance,</l>
<l>reveals innate nobility and grace,</l>
<l>that should dispel all fear of treachery,</l>
<l>and guarantee his ever-faithful heart.</l>
<l>The Gods will witness our united souls,</l>
<l>and he shall pledge his faith. Secure of it</l>
<l>my fear will be removed. Be ready, then—</l>
<l>and make a virtue of necessity:</l>
<l>your Jason owes himself to you; and he</l>
<l>must join you in true wedlock. Then you shall</l>
<l>be celebrated through the land of Greece,</l>
<l>by throngs of women, for the man you saved.</l>

    
<l>“Shall I then sail away, and so forsake</l>
<l>my sister, brother, father, Gods, and land</l>
<l>that gave me birth? My father is indeed</l>
<l>a stern man, and my native land is all</l>
<l>too barbarous; my brother is a child,—</l>
<l>my sister's goodwill is good help for me;</l>
<l>and heaven's supreme god is within my breast.</l>

    
<l>“I shall not so be leaving valued hopes,</l>
<l>but will be going surely to great things.</l>
<l>And I should gain applause from all the world,</l>
<l>as having saved the threatened Argonauts,</l>
<l>most noble of the Greeks; and in their land,</l>
<l>which certainly is better than my own,</l>
<l>become the bride of Jason, for whose love</l>
<l>I should not hesitate to give the world—</l>
<l>and in whose love the living Gods rejoice</l>
<l>so greatly; for his sake they would bestow</l>
<l>their favors on my head, and make the stars</l>
<l>my habitation.</l>

    
<l>“Should I hesitate</l>
<l>because the wreck-strewn mountains bar the way,</l>
<l>and clash together in the Euxine waves;</l>
<l>or fear Charybdis, fatal to large ships,</l>
<l>that sucks the deep sea in its whirling gulf</l>
<l>and spouts far upward, with alternate force,</l>
<l>or Scylla, circled with infuriate hounds</l>
<l>howling in rage from deep Sicilian waves?</l>

    
<l>“Safe in the shielding arms of him I love,</l>
<l>on Jason's bosom leaning, I shall be</l>
<l>borne safely over wide and hostile seas;</l>
<l>and in his dear embrace forget my fears—</l>
<l>or if for anything I suffer dread,</l>
<l>it will be only for the one I love.—</l>

    
<l>“Alas, Medea, this vain argument</l>
<l>has only furnished plausible excuse</l>
<l>for criminal desires, and desecrates</l>
<l>the marriage rite. It is a wicked thing</l>
<l>to think upon. Before it is too late</l>
<l>forget your passion and deny this guilt.”</l>

    
<l>And after she had said these words, her eyes</l>
<l>were opened to the prize of modesty,</l>
<l>chaste virtue, and a pure affection:</l>
<l>and Cupid, vanquished, turned away and fled.</l>

    
<l>Then, to an ancient altar of the goddess named</l>
<l>Hecate, Perse's daughter took her way</l>
<l>in the deep shadows of a forest. She</l>
<l>was strong of purpose now, and all the flames</l>
<l>of vanquished passion had died down; but when</l>
<l>she saw the son of Aeson, dying flames</l>
<l>leaped up again. Her cheeks grew red, then all</l>
<l>her face went pale again; as a small spark</l>
<l>when hid beneath the ashes, if fed by</l>
<l>a breath of wind grows and regains its strength,</l>
<l>as it is fanned to life; so now her love</l>
<l>that had been smoldering, and which you would</l>
<l>have thought was almost dead, when she had see</l>
<l>again his manly youth, blazed up once more.</l>

    
<l>For on that day his graceful person seemed</l>
<l>as glorious as a God;—and as she gazed,</l>
<l>and fixed her eyes upon his countenance,</l>
<l>her frenzy so prevailed, she was convinced</l>
<l>that he was not a mortal. And her eyes</l>
<l>were fascinated; and she could not turn</l>
<l>away from him. But when he spoke to her,</l>
<l>and promised marriage, grasping her right hand:</l>
<l>she answered, as her eyes suffused with tears;</l>
<l>“I see what I will do, and ignorance</l>
<l>of truth will not be my undoing now,</l>
<l>but love itself. By my assistance you</l>
<l>shall be preserved; but when preserved fulfill</l>
<l>your promise.”</l>

    
<l>He swore that she could trust in him.</l>
<l>Then by the goddess of the triple form,</l>
<l>Diana, Trivia, or Luna called,</l>
<l>and by her sacred groves and fanes, he vowed,</l>
<l>and by the hallowed Sun that sees all things,</l>
<l>and by his own adventures, and his life,—</l>
<l>on these the youthful Jason took his oath.—</l>
<l>With this she was assured and quickly gave</l>
<l>to him the magic herbs: he learnt their use</l>
<l>and full of joy withdrew into his house.</l>

    
<l>Now when the dawn had dimmed the glittering stars,</l>
<l>the people hastened to the sacred field</l>
<l>of Mars, and on the hills expectant stood.—</l>
<l>Arrayed in purple, and in majesty</l>
<l>distinguished by his ivory sceptre, sat</l>
<l>the king, surrounded by a multitude.</l>
<l>Below them on the visioned Field of Mars,</l>
<l>huge brazen-footed bulls were breathing forth</l>
<l>from adamantine nostrils living flames,</l>
<l>blasting the verdant herbage in their path!</l>

    
<l>As forges glowing with hot flames resound,</l>
<l>or as much quick-lime, burnt in earthen kilns,</l>
<l>crackles and hisses as if mad with rage,</l>
<l>sprinkled with water, liberating heat;</l>
<l>so their hot throats and triple-heated sides,</l>
<l>resounding told of pent-up fires within.</l>

    
<l>The son of Aeson went to meet them. As</l>
<l>he came to meet them the fierce animals</l>
<l>turned on him faces terrible, and sharp</l>
<l>horns tipped with iron, and they pawed</l>
<l>the dusty earth with cloven feet, and filled</l>
<l>the place with fiery bellowings. The Minyans</l>
<l>were stark with fear; he went up to the bulls</l>
<l>not feeling their hot breath at all, so great</l>
<l>the power of his charmed drugs; and while he</l>
<l>was stroking their down-hanging dewlaps with</l>
<l>a fearless hand, he placed the yoke down on</l>
<l>their necks and made them draw the heavy plow,</l>
<l>and cut through fields that never felt the steel</l>
<l>before. The Colchians were amazed and silent;</l>
<l>but the loud shouting of the Minyans</l>
<l>increased their hero's courage. Taking then</l>
<l>the serpent's teeth out of a brazen helmet</l>
<l>he sowed them broadcast in the new-plowed field.</l>

    
<l>The moist earth softened these seeds that were steeped</l>
<l>in virulent poison and the teeth swelled up</l>
<l>and took new forms. And just as in its mother</l>
<l>an infant gradually assumes the form</l>
<l>of man, and is perfected through all parts</l>
<l>within, and does not come forth to the light</l>
<l>till fully formed; so, when the forms of men</l>
<l>had been completed in the womb of earth</l>
<l>made pregnant, they rose up from it,</l>
<l>and what is yet more wonderful, each one</l>
<l>clashed weapons that had been brought forth with him.</l>

    
<l>When his companions saw the warriors turn</l>
<l>as if with one accord, to hurl their spears,</l>
<l>sharp-pointed, at the head of Jason, fear</l>
<l>unnerved the boldest and their courage failed.</l>
<l>So, too, the maid whose sorcery had saved</l>
<l>him from much danger, when she saw the youth</l>
<l>encompassed by those raging enemies,</l>
<l>and he alone against so many—struck</l>
<l>with sudden panic, she turned ashen white,</l>
<l>her bloodless cheeks were blanched; and chilled with fear</l>
<l>she wilted to the ground; and lest the herbs,</l>
<l>so lately given him, might fail his need</l>
<l>she added incantations and invoked</l>
<l>mysterious arts. While she protected him</l>

    
<l>He seized upon a heavy stone, and hurled</l>
<l>it in the midst of his new enemies—</l>
<l>distracted by this cast, and murderous,</l>
<l>they turned from him, and clashing their new arms,</l>
<l>those earth-born brothers fought among themselves</l>
<l>till all were slaughtered in blood-thirsty strife.</l>

    
<l>Gladly the Greeks acclaimed him conqueror,</l>
<l>and pressed around him for the first embrace.</l>
<l>Then, too, Medea, barbarous Colchian maid,</l>
<l>although her modesty restrained her heart,</l>
<l>eagerly longed to fold him in her arms,</l>
<l>but careful of her good name, held aloof,—</l>
<l>rejoicing in deep, silent love; and she</l>
<l>acknowledged to the Gods her mighty gift</l>
<l>of incantations.</l>

    
<l>But the dragon, still</l>
<l>alert,—magnificent and terrible</l>
<l>with gorgeous crest and triple tongue, and fangs</l>
<l>barbed as a javelin, guards the Golden Fleece:</l>
<l>and Jason can obtain that quest only</l>
<l>if slumber may seal up the monster's eyes.—</l>

    
<l>Jason, successful, sprinkled on his crest</l>
<l>Lethean juices of a magic herb,</l>
<l>and then recited thrice the words which bring</l>
<l>deep slumber, potent words which would becalm</l>
<l>the storm-tossed ocean, and would stop the flow</l>
<l>of the most rapid rivers of our earth:</l>
<l>and slowly slumber sealed the dragon's eyes.</l>

    
<l>While that great monster slept, the hero took</l>
<l>the Golden Fleece; and proudly sailed away</l>
<l>bearing his treasure and the willing maid,</l>
<l>(whose aid had saved him) to his native port</l>
<l>Iolcus—victorious with the Argonauts.</l>


Aeson.
REJUVENATION OF AESON

<l>Now when the valiant Argonauts returned</l>
<l>to Thessaly, their happy relatives,</l>
<l>fathers and mothers, praised the living Gods;</l>
<l>and with their hallowed gifts enhanced the flames</l>
<l>with precious incense; and they offered Jove</l>
<l>a sacred bullock, rich with gilded horns.</l>

    
<l>But Jason's father, Aeson, came not down</l>
<l>rejoicing to behold his son, for now</l>
<l>worn out with many years, he waited death.</l>
<l>And Jason to Medea grieving said:</l>

    
<l>“Dearest, to whom my life and love are due,</l>
<l>although your kindness has been great to me,</l>
<l>and you have granted more than I should ask,</l>
<l>yet one thing more I beg of you; if your</l>
<l>enchantments can accomplish my desire,</l>
<l>take from my life some years that I should live</l>
<l>and add them to my father's ending days.”—</l>
<l>And as he spoke he could not check his tears.</l>

    
<l>Medea, moved by his affection, thought</l>
<l>how much less she had grieved for her loved sire:</l>
<l>and she replied:—“A wicked thing you ask!</l>
<l>Can I be capable of using you</l>
<l>in such a manner as to take your life</l>
<l>and give it to another? Ask not me</l>
<l>a thing so dreadful! May the Gods forbid!—</l>
<l>I will endeavor to perform for you</l>
<l>a task much greater. By the powers of Night</l>
<l>I will most certainly return to him</l>
<l>the lost years of your father, but must not</l>
<l>deprive you of your own. — Oh grant the power,</l>
<l>great goddess of the triple form, that I</l>
<l>may fail not to accomplish this great deed!”</l>

    
<l>Three nights were wanting for the moon to join</l>
<l>her circling horns and form a perfect orb.</l>
<l>When these were passed, the rounded light shone full</l>
<l>and bright upon the earth.—Through the still night</l>
<l>alone, Medea stole forth from the house</l>
<l>with feet bare, and in flowing garment clothed—</l>
<l>her long hair unadorned and not confined.</l>
<l>Deep slumber has relaxed the world, and all</l>
<l>that's living, animals and birds and men,</l>
<l>and even the hedges and the breathing leaves</l>
<l>are still—and motionless the laden air.</l>

    
<l>Only the stars are twinkling, and to them</l>
<l>she looks and beckons with imploring hands.</l>
<l>Now thrice around she paces, and three times</l>
<l>besprinkles her long hair with water dipt</l>
<l>from crystal streams, which having done</l>
<l>she kneels a moment on the cold, bare ground,</l>
<l>and screaming three times calls upon the Night,—</l>

    
<l>“O faithful Night, regard my mysteries!</l>
<l>O golden-lighted Stars! O softly-moving Moon—</l>
<l>genial, your fire succeeds the heated day!</l>
<l>O Hecate! grave three-faced queen of these</l>
<l>charms of enchanters and enchanters, arts!</l>
<l>O fruitful Earth, giver of potent herbs!</l>
<l>O gentle Breezes and destructive Winds!</l>
<l>You Mountains, Rivers, Lakes and sacred Groves,</l>
<l>and every dreaded god of silent Night!</l>
<l>Attend upon me!—</l>

    
<l>“When my power commands,</l>
<l>the rivers turn from their accustomed ways</l>
<l>and roll far backward to their secret springs!</l>
<l>I speak—and the wild, troubled sea is calm,</l>
<l>and I command the waters to arise!</l>
<l>The clouds I scatter—and I bring the clouds;</l>
<l>I smooth the winds and ruffle up their rage;</l>
<l>I weave my spells and I recite my charms;</l>
<l>I pluck the fangs of serpents, and I move</l>
<l>the living rocks and twist the rooted oaks;</l>
<l>I blast the forests. Mountains at my word</l>
<l>tremble and quake; and from her granite tombs</l>
<l>the liberated ghosts arise as Earth</l>
<l>astonished groans! From your appointed ways,</l>
<l>O wonder-working Moon, I draw you down</l>
<l>against the magic-making sound of gongs</l>
<l>and brazen vessels of Temesa's ore;</l>
<l>I cast my spells and veil the jeweled rays</l>
<l>of Phoebus' wain, and quench Aurora's fires.</l>

    
<l>“At my command you tamed the flaming bulls</l>
<l>which long disdained to bend beneath the yoke,</l>
<l>until they pressed their necks against the plows;</l>
<l>and, subject to my will, you raised up war</l>
<l>till the strong company of dragon-birth</l>
<l>were slaughtered as they fought amongst themselves;</l>
<l>and, last, you lulled asleep the warden's eyes—</l>
<l>guards of the Golden Fleece—till then awake</l>
<l>and sleeping never—so, deceiving him,</l>
<l>you sent the treasure to the Grecian cities!</l>

    
<l>“Witness my need of super-natured herbs,</l>
<l>elixirs potent to renew the years of age,</l>
<l>giving the bloom of youth.—You shall not fail</l>
<l>to grant me this; for not in vain the stars</l>
<l>are flashing confirmation; not in vain</l>
<l>the flying dragons, harnessed by their necks,</l>
<l>from skies descending bring my chariot down.”</l>

    
<l>A chariot, sent from heaven, came to her—</l>
<l>and soon as she had stroked the dragons' necks,</l>
<l>and shaken in her hands the guiding reins—</l>
<l>as soon as she had mounted, she was borne</l>
<l>quickly above, through unresisting air.</l>
<l>And, sailing over Thessaly, she saw</l>
<l>the vale of Tempe, where the level soil</l>
<l>is widely covered with a crumbling chalk—</l>
<l>she turned her dragons towards new regions there:</l>
<l>and she observed the herbs by Ossa born,</l>
<l>the weeds on lofty Pelion, Othrys, Pindus</l>
<l>and vast Olympus—and from here she plucked</l>
<l>the needed roots, or there, the blossoms clipped</l>
<l>all with a moon-curved sickle made of brass—</l>
<l>many the wild weeds by Apidanus,</l>
<l>as well as blue Amphrysus' banks, she chose,</l>
<l>and not escaped Enipeus from her search;</l>
<l>Peneian stretches and Spercheian banks</l>
<l>all yielded what she chose:—and Boebe's shore</l>
<l>where sway the rushes; and she plucked up grass,</l>
<l>a secret grass, from fair Euboean fields</l>

    
<l>life-giving virtues in their waving blades,</l>
<l>as yet unknown for transformation wrought</l>
<l>on Glaucus.</l>

    
<l>All those fields she visited,</l>
<l>with ceaseless diligence in quest of charms,</l>
<l>nine days and nine nights sought strong herbs,</l>
<l>and the swift dragons with their active wings,</l>
<l>failed not to guide the chariot where she willed—</l>
<l>until they reached her home. The dragons then</l>
<l>had not been even touched by anything,</l>
<l>except the odor of surrounding herbs,</l>
<l>and yet they sloughed their skins, the growth of years.</l>


    
<l>She would not cross the threshold of her home</l>
<l>nor pass its gates; but, standing in the field,</l>
<l>alone beneath the canopy of Heaven,</l>
<l>she shunned all contact with her husband, while</l>
<l>she built up from the ever-living turf</l>
<l>two altars, one of which upon the right</l>
<l>to Hecate was given, but the one</l>
<l>upon the left was sacred then to you,</l>
<l>O Hebe, goddess of eternal youth!</l>

    
<l>Festooning woodland boughs and sweet vervain</l>
<l>adorned these altars, near by which she dug</l>
<l>as many trenches. Then, when all was done,</l>
<l>she slaughtered a black ram, and sprinkled with blood</l>
<l>the thirsty trenches; after which she poured</l>
<l>from rich carchesian goblets generous wine</l>
<l>and warm milk, grateful to propitious Gods—</l>
<l>the Deities of earth on whom she called—</l>
<l>entreating, as she did so, Pluto, lord</l>
<l>of ghostly shades, and ravished Proserpine,</l>
<l>that they should not, in undue haste,</l>
<l>deprive her patient's aged limbs of life.</l>

    
<l>When certain she compelled the God's regard,</l>
<l>assured her incantations and long prayers</l>
<l>were both approved and heard, she bade her people</l>
<l>bring out the body of her father-in-law—</l>
<l>old Aeson's worn out body—and when she</l>
<l>had buried him in a deep slumber by</l>
<l>her spells, as if he were a dead man, she</l>
<l>then stretched him out upon a bed of herbs.</l>

    
<l>She ordered Jason and his servants thence,</l>
<l>and warned them not to spy upon her rites,</l>
<l>with eyes profane. As soon as they retired,</l>
<l>Medea, with disheveled hair and wild</l>
<l>abandon, as a Bacchanalian, paced</l>
<l>times three around the blazing altars, while</l>
<l>she dipped her torches, splintered at the top,</l>
<l>into the trenches, dark: with blood, and lit</l>
<l>the dipt ends in the sacred altar flames.</l>
<l>Times three she purified the ancient man</l>
<l>with flames, and thrice with water, and three times</l>
<l>with sulphur,—as the boiling mixture seethed</l>
<l>and bubbled in the brazen cauldron near.</l>

    
<l>And into this, acerbic juices, roots,</l>
<l>and flowers and seeds—from vales Hemonian—</l>
<l>and mixed elixirs, into which she cast</l>
<l>stones of strange virtue from the Orient,</l>
<l>and sifted sands of ebbing ocean's tide;</l>
<l>white hoar-frost, gathered when the moon was full,</l>
<l>the nauseating flesh and luckless wings</l>
<l>of the uncanny screech-owl, and the entrails</l>
<l>from a mysterious animal that changed</l>
<l>from wolf to man, from man to wolf again;</l>
<l>the scaly sloughing of a water-snake,</l>
<l>the medic liver of a long-lived stag,</l>
<l>and the hard beak and head of an old crow</l>
<l>which was alive nine centuries before;</l>
<l>these, and a thousand nameless things</l>
<l>the foreign sorceress prepared and mixed,</l>
<l>and blended all together with a branch</l>
<l>of peaceful olive, old and dry with years. —</l>
<l>And while she stirred the withered olive branch</l>
<l>in the hot mixture, it began to change</l>
<l>from brown to green; and presently put forth</l>
<l>new leaves, and soon was heavy with a wealth</l>
<l>of luscious olives.—As the ever-rising fire</l>
<l>threw bubbling froth beyond the cauldron's rim,</l>
<l>the ground was covered with fresh verdure — flowers</l>
<l>and all luxuriant grasses, and green plants.</l>

    
<l>Medea, when she saw this wonder took</l>
<l>her unsheathed knife and cut the old man's throat;</l>
<l>then, letting all his old blood out of him</l>
<l>she filled his ancient veins with rich elixir.</l>
<l>As he received it through his lips or wound,</l>
<l>his beard and hair no longer white with age,</l>
<l>turned quickly to their natural vigor, dark</l>
<l>and lustrous; and his wasted form renewed,</l>
<l>appeared in all the vigor of bright youth,</l>
<l>no longer lean and sallow, for new blood</l>
<l>coursed in his well-filled veins.—Astonished, when</l>
<l>released from his deep sleep, and strong in youth,</l>
<l>his memory assured him, such he was</l>
<l>years four times ten before that day!—</l>

    
<l>Bacchus, from his celestial vantage saw</l>
<l>this marvel, and convinced his nurses might</l>
<l>then all regain their former vigor, he</l>
<l>pled with Medea to restore their youth.</l>
<l>The Colchian woman granted his request.</l>


Pelias.
MEDEA AND PELIAS

<l>but so her malice might be satisfied</l>
<l>Medea feigned she had a quarrel with</l>
<l>her husband, and for safety she had fled</l>
<l>to Pelias. There, since the king himself</l>
<l>was heavy with old age, his daughters gave</l>
<l>her generous reception. And these girls</l>
<l>the shrewd Medea in a short time won,</l>
<l>by her false show of friendliness; and while</l>
<l>among the most remarkable of her</l>
<l>achievements she was telling how she had</l>
<l>rejuvenated Aeson, and she dwelt</l>
<l>particularly, on that strange event,</l>
<l>these daughters were induced to hope that by</l>
<l>some skill like this their father might regain</l>
<l>his lost youth also. And they begged of her</l>
<l>this boon, persuading her to name the price;</l>
<l>no matter if it was large. She did not</l>
<l>reply at once and seemed to hesitate,</l>
<l>and so she held their fond minds in a deep</l>
<l>suspense by her feigned meditation. When</l>
<l>she had at length declared she would restore</l>
<l>his youth, she said to them: “That you may have</l>
<l>strong confidence in this my promised boon,</l>
<l>the oldest leader of your flock of sheep shall be</l>
<l>changed to a lamb again by my prized drugs.”</l>

    
<l>Straightway a wooly ram, worn out with length</l>
<l>of untold years was brought, his great horns curved</l>
<l>around his hollow temples. After she</l>
<l>had cut his scrawny throat with her sharp knife</l>
<l>Thessalian, barely staining it with his</l>
<l>thin blood, Medea plunged his carcass in</l>
<l>a bronze-made kettle, throwing in it at</l>
<l>the same time juices of great potency.</l>
<l>These made his body shrink and burnt away</l>
<l>his two horns, and with horns his years. And now</l>
<l>thin bleating was heard from within the pot;</l>
<l>and even while they wondered at the sound,</l>
<l>a lamb jumped out and frisking, ran away</l>
<l>to find some udder with its needed milk.</l>

    
<l>Amazed the daughters looked on and, now that</l>
<l>these promises had been performed, they urged</l>
<l>more eagerly their first request. Three times</l>
<l>Phoebus unyoked his steeds after their plunge</l>
<l>in Ebro's stream, and on the fourth night stars</l>
<l>shown brilliant on the dark foil of the sky,</l>
<l>and then the treacherous daughter of Aeetes</l>
<l>set some clear water over a hot fire</l>
<l>and put in it herbs of no potency.</l>
<l>And now a death-like sleep held the king down,</l>
<l>his body all relaxed, and with the king</l>
<l>his guards, a sleep which incantations with</l>
<l>the potency of magic words had given.</l>

    
<l>The sad king's daughters, as they had been bid,</l>
<l>were in his room, and with Medea stood</l>
<l>around his bed. “Why do you hesitate,”</l>
<l>Medea said. “You laggards, come and draw</l>
<l>your swords; let out his old blood that</l>
<l>I may refill his empty veins again</l>
<l>with young blood. In your hands your father's life</l>
<l>and youth are resting. You, his daughters, must</l>
<l>have love for him, and if the hopes you have</l>
<l>are not all vain, come, do your duty by</l>
<l>your father; drive out old age at the point</l>
<l>of your good weapons; and let out his blood</l>
<l>enfeebled—cure him with the stroke of iron.”</l>

    
<l>Spurred on by these words, as each one of them</l>
<l>was filial she became the leader in</l>
<l>the most unfilial act, and that she might</l>
<l>not be most wicked did the wicked deed.</l>
<l>Not one could bear to see her own blows, so</l>
<l>they turned their eyes away; and every face</l>
<l>averted so, they blindly struck him with</l>
<l>their cruel hands. The old man streaming with</l>
<l>his blood, still raised himself on elbow, and</l>
<l>half mangled tried to get up from his bed;</l>
<l>with all those swords around him, he stretched out</l>
<l>his pale arms and he cried: “What will you do,</l>
<l>my daughters? What has armed you to the death</l>
<l>of your loved father?” Their wrong courage left</l>
<l>them, and their hands fell. When he would have said</l>
<l>still more, Medea cut his throat and plunged</l>
<l>his mangled body into boiling water.</l>


Medeae fuga.

<l>Only because her winged dragons sailed</l>
<l>swiftly with her up to the lofty sky,</l>
<l>escaped Medea punishment for this</l>
<l>unheard of crime.</l>

    
<l>Her chariot sailed above</l>
<l>embowered Pelion — long the lofty home</l>
<l>of Chiron—over Othrys, and the vale</l>
<l>made famous where Cerambus met his fate.</l>
<l>Cerambus, by the aid of nymphs, from there</l>
<l>was wafted through the air on wings, when earth</l>
<l>was covered by the overwhelming sea—</l>
<l>and so escaped Deucalion's flood, uncrowned.</l>

    
<l>She passed by Pittane upon the left,</l>
<l>with its huge serpent-image of hard stone,</l>
<l>and also passed the grove called Ida's, where</l>
<l>the stolen bull was changed by Bacchus' power</l>
<l>into a hunted stag—in that same vale</l>
<l>Paris lies buried in the sand; and over fields</l>
<l>where Mera warning harked, Medea flew;</l>
<l>over the city of Eurypylus</l>
<l>upon the Isle of Cos, whose women wore</l>
<l>the horns of cattle when from there had gone</l>
<l>the herd of Hercules; and over Rhodes</l>
<l>beloved of Phoebus, where Telchinian tribes</l>
<l>dwelt, whose bad eyes corrupting power shot forth;—</l>
<l>Jove, utterly despising, thrust them deep</l>
<l>beneath his brother's waves; over the walls</l>
<l>of old Carthaea, where Alcidamas</l>
<l>had seen with wonder a tame dove arise</l>
<l>from his own daughter's body.</l>

    
<l>And she saw</l>
<l>the lakes of Hyrie in Teumesia's Vale,</l>
<l>by swans frequented—There to satisfy</l>
<l>his love for Cycnus, Phyllius gave</l>
<l>two living vultures: shell for him subdued</l>
<l>a lion, and delivered it to him;</l>
<l>and mastered a great bull, at his command;</l>
<l>but when the wearied Phyllius refused</l>
<l>to render to his friend the valued bull.</l>
<l>Indignant, the youth said, “You shall regret</l>
<l>your hasty words;” which having said, he leaped</l>
<l>from a high precipice, as if to death;</l>
<l>but gliding through the air, on snow-white wings,</l>
<l>was changed into a swan—Dissolved in tears,</l>
<l>his mother Hyrie knew not he was saved;</l>
<l>and weeping, formed the lake that bears her name.</l>

    
<l>And over Pleuron, where on trembling wings</l>
<l>escaped the mother Combe from her sons,</l>
<l>Medea flew; and over the far isle</l>
<l>Calauria, sacred to Latona.—She</l>
<l>beheld the conscious fields whose lawful king,</l>
<l>together with his queen were changed to birds.</l>

    
<l>Upon her right Cyllene could be seen;</l>
<l>there Menephon, degraded as a beast,</l>
<l>outraged his mother. In the distance, she</l>
<l>beheld Cephisius, who lamented long</l>
<l>his hapless grandson, by Apollo changed</l>
<l>into a bloated sea-calf. And she saw</l>
<l>the house where king Eumelus mourned the death</l>
<l>of his aspiring son.—Borne on the wings</l>
<l>of her enchanted dragons, she arrived</l>
<l>at Corinth, whose inhabitants, 'tis said,</l>
<l>from many mushrooms, watered by the rain</l>
<l>sprang into being.</l>

    
<l>There she spent some years.</l>
<l>But after the new wife had been burnt by</l>
<l>the Colchian witchcraft and two seas</l>
<l>had seen the king's own palace all aflame,</l>
<l>then, savagely she drew her sword, and bathed</l>
<l>it in the blood of her own infant sons;</l>
<l>by which atrocious act she was revenged;</l>
<l>and she, a wife and mother, fled the sword</l>
<l>of her own husband, Jason.</l>

MEDEA AND AEGEUS

<l>On the wings</l>
<l>of her enchanted Titan Dragons borne,</l>
<l>she made escape, securely, nor delayed</l>
<l>until she entered the defended walls</l>
<l>of great Minerva's city, at the hour</l>
<l>when aged Periphas — transformed by Jove,</l>
<l>together with his queen, on eagle wings</l>
<l>flew over its encircling walls: with whom</l>
<l>the guilty Halcyone, skimming seas</l>
<l>safely escaped, upon her balanced wings.</l>

    
<l>And after these events, Medea went</l>
<l>to Aegeus, king of Athens, where she found</l>
<l>protection from her enemies for all</l>
<l>this evil done. With added wickedness</l>
<l>Aegeus, after that, united her</l>
<l>to him in marriage.—</l>


Theseus.

<l>All unknown to him</l>
<l>came Theseus to his kingly court.—Before</l>
<l>the time his valor had established peace</l>
<l>on all the isthmus, raved by dual seas.</l>

    
<l>Medea, seeking his destruction, brewed</l>
<l>the juice of aconite, infesting shores</l>
<l>of Scythia, where, 'tis fabled, the plant grew</l>
<l>on soil infected by Cerberian teeth.</l>

    
<l>There is a gloomy entrance to a cave,</l>
<l>that follows a declivitous descent:</l>
<l>there Hercules with chains of adamant</l>
<l>dragged from the dreary edge of Tartarus</l>
<l>that monster-watch-dog, Cerberus, which, vain</l>
<l>opposing, turned his eyes aslant from light—</l>
<l>from dazzling day. Delirious, enraged,</l>
<l>that monster shook the air with triple howls;</l>
<l>and, frothing, sprinkled as it raved, the fields,</l>
<l>once green—with spewing of white poison-foam.</l>
<l>And this, converted into plants, sucked up</l>
<l>a deadly venom with the nourishment</l>
<l>of former soils,—from which productive grew</l>
<l>upon the rock, thus formed, the noxious plant;</l>
<l>by rustics, from that cause, named aconite.</l>

    
<l>Medea worked on Aegeus to present</l>
<l>his own son, Theseus, with a deadly cup</l>
<l>of aconite; prevailing by her art</l>
<l>so that he deemed his son an enemy.</l>

    
<l>Theseus unwittingly received the cup,</l>
<l>but just before he touched it to his lips,</l>
<l>his father recognized the sword he wore,</l>
<l>for, graven on its ivory hilt was wrought</l>
<l>a known device—the token of his race.</l>
<l>Astonished, Aegeus struck the poison-cup</l>
<l>from his devoted son's confiding lips.</l>
<l>Medea suddenly escaped from death,</l>
<l>in a dark whirlwind her witch-singing raised.</l>

THE MYRMIDONS

<l>Recoiling from such utter wickedness,</l>
<l>rejoicing that his son escaped from death,</l>
<l>the grateful father kindled altar-fires,</l>
<l>and gave rich treasure to the living Gods. —</l>
<l>He slaughtered scores of oxen, decked with flowers</l>
<l>and gilded horns. The sun has never shone</l>
<l>upon a day more famous in that land,</l>
<l>for all the elders and the common folk</l>
<l>united in festivities,—with wine</l>
<l>inspiring wit and song;—“O you,” they sang,</l>

    
<l>“Immortal Theseus, victory was yours!</l>
<l>Did you not slaughter the huge bull of Crete?</l>

    
<l>“Yes, you did slay the boar of Cromyon —</l>
<l>where now the peasant unmolested plows;</l>

    
<l>“And Periphetes, wielder of the club,</l>
<l>was worsted when he struggled with your strength;</l>

    
<l>“And fierce Procrustes, matched with you</l>
<l>beside the rapid river, met his death;</l>

    
<l>“And even Cercyon, in Eleusis lost</l>
<l>his wicked life—inferior to your might;</l>

    
<l>“And Sinis, a monstrosity of strength,</l>
<l>who bent the trunks of trees, and used his might</l>

    
<l>“Against the world for everything that's wrong.</l>
<l>For evil, he would force down to the earth,</l>

    
<l>“Pine tops to shoot men's bodies through the air.</l>
<l>Even the road to Megara is safe,</l>

    
<l>“For you did hurl the robber Scyron,—sheer—</l>
<l>over the cliff. Both land and sea denied</l>

    
<l>“His bones a resting place—as tossed about</l>
<l>they changed into the cliffs that bear his name.</l>

    
<l>“How can we tell the number of your deeds,—</l>
<l>deeds glorious, that now exceed your years!</l>

    
<l>“For you, brave hero, we give public thanks</l>
<l>and prayers; to you we drain our cups of wine!”</l>

    
<l>And all the palace rings with happy songs,</l>
<l>and with the grateful prayers of all the people.</l>
<l>And sorrow in that city is not known.—</l>


Aeacus. Pestilentia. Myrmidones.

<l>But pleasure always is alloyed with grief,</l>
<l>and sorrow mingles in the joyous hour.</l>

    
<l>While the king Aegeus and his son rejoiced,</l>
<l>Minos prepared for war. He was invincible</l>
<l>in men and ships—and stronger in his rage</l>
<l>to wreak due vengeance on the king who slew</l>
<l>his son Androgeus. But first he sought</l>
<l>some friends to aid his warfare; and he scoured</l>
<l>the sea with a swift fleet—which was his strength.</l>
<l>Anaphe and Astypalaea, both</l>
<l>agreed to join his cause—the first one moved</l>
<l>by promises, the second by his threats.</l>
<l>Level Myconus and the chalky fields</l>
<l>of Cimolus agreed to aid, and Syros</l>
<l>covered with wild thyme, level Seriphos,</l>
<l>Paros of marble cliffs, and that place which</l>
<l>Arne the impious Siphnian had betrayed,</l>
<l>who having got the gold which in her greed</l>
<l>she had demanded, was changed to a bird</l>
<l>which ever since that day imagines gold</l>
<l>its chief delight—a black-foot black-winged daw.</l>

    
<l>But Oliarus, Didymae, and Tenos,</l>
<l>Gyaros, Andros, and Peparethos</l>
<l>rich in its glossy olives, gave no aid</l>
<l>to the strong Cretan fleet. Sailing from them</l>
<l>Minos went to Oenopia, known realm</l>
<l>of the Aeacidae.—Men of old time</l>
<l>had called the place Oenopia; but Aeacus</l>
<l>styled it Aegina from his mother's name.</l>
<l>At his approach an eager rabble rushed</l>
<l>resolved to see and know so great a man.</l>
<l>Telamon met him, and his brother,</l>
<l>younger than Telamon, and Phocus who</l>
<l>was third in age. Even Aeacus appeared,</l>
<l>slow with the weight of years, and asked him what</l>
<l>could be a reason for his coming there.</l>
<l>The ruler of a hundred cities, sighed,</l>
<l>as he beheld the sons of Aeacus,</l>
<l>for they reminded him of his lost son;—</l>
<l>and heavy with his sorrow, he replied:</l>
<l>“I come imploring you to take up arms,</l>
<l>and aid me in the war against my foes;</l>
<l>for I must give that comfort to the shade</l>
<l>of my misfortuned son—whose blood they shed.”</l>

    
<l>But Aeacus replied to Minos, “Nay,</l>
<l>it is a vain request you make, for we</l>
<l>are bound in strict alliance to the land</l>
<l>and people of Cecropia.”</l>

    
<l>Full of rage,</l>
<l>because he was denied, the king of Crete,</l>
<l>Minos, as he departed from their shores</l>
<l>replied, “Let such a treaty be your bane.”</l>
<l>And he departed with his crafty threat,</l>
<l>believing it expedient not to waste</l>
<l>his power in wars until the proper time.</l>

    
<l>Before the ships of Crete had disappeared,</l>
<l>before the mist and blue of waves concealed</l>
<l>their fading outlines from the anxious throng</l>
<l>which gathered on Oenopian shores, a ship</l>
<l>of Athens covered with wide sails appeared,</l>
<l>and anchored safely by their friendly shore;</l>
<l>and, presently, the mighty Cephalus,</l>
<l>well known through all that nation for his deeds,</l>
<l>addressed them as he landed, and declared</l>
<l>the good will of his people. Him the sons</l>
<l>of Aeacus remembered well, although</l>
<l>they had not seen him for some untold years.</l>
<l>They led him to their father's welcome home;</l>
<l>and with him, also, his two comrades went,</l>
<l>Clytus and Butes.</l>

    
<l>Center of all eyes,</l>
<l>the hero still retained his charm,</l>
<l>the customary greetings were exchanged,</l>
<l>the graceful hero, bearing in his hands</l>
<l>a branch of olive from his native soil,</l>
<l>delivered the Athenian message, which</l>
<l>requested aid and offered for their thought</l>
<l>the treaty and the ancestral league between</l>
<l>their nations. And he added, Minos sought</l>
<l>not only conquest of the Athenian state</l>
<l>but sovereignty of all the states of Greece.</l>
<l>And when this eloquence had shown his cause;</l>
<l>with left hand on his gleaming sceptre's hilt,</l>
<l>King Aeacus exclaimed: “Ask not our aid,</l>
<l>but take it, Athens; and count boldly yours</l>
<l>all of the force this island holds, and all</l>
<l>things which the state of my affairs supplies.</l>
<l>My strength for this war is not light, and I</l>
<l>have many soldiers for myself and for</l>
<l>my enemy. Thanks to the Gods! the times</l>
<l>are happy, giving no excuse for my</l>
<l>refusal.” “May it prove so,” Cephalus</l>
<l>replied, “and may your city multiply</l>
<l>in men: just now as I was landing, I</l>
<l>rejoiced to meet youths, fair and matched in age.</l>
<l>And yet I miss among them many whom</l>
<l>I saw before when last I visited</l>
<l>your city.” Aeacus then groaned and with</l>
<l>sad voice replied: “With weeping we began,</l>
<l>but better fortune followed. Would that I</l>
<l>could tell the last of it, and not the first!</l>
<l>Giving my heart command that simple words</l>
<l>and briefly spoken may not long detain.</l>
<l>Those happy youths who waited at your need,</l>
<l>who smiled upon you and for whom you ask,</l>
<l>because their absence grieves your noble mind,</l>
<l>they've perished! and their bleaching bones</l>
<l>or scattered ashes, only may remain,</l>
<l>sad remnants, impotent, of vanished power,</l>
<l>so recently my hope and my resource.</l>

    
<l>“Because this island bears a rival's name,</l>
<l>a deadly pestilence was visited</l>
<l>on my confiding people, through the rage</l>
<l>of jealous Juno flaming for revenge.</l>
<l>This great calamity at first appeared</l>
<l>a natural disease—but soon its power</l>
<l>baffled our utmost efforts. Medicines</l>
<l>availing not, a reign of terror swept</l>
<l>from shore to shore and fearful havoc raged.</l>

    
<l>“Thick darkness, gathered from descending skies,</l>
<l>enveloped our devoted land with heat</l>
<l>and languid sickness, for the space of full</l>
<l>four moons.—Four times the Moon increased her size.</l>
<l>Hot south winds blew with pestilential breath</l>
<l>upon us. At the same time the diseased</l>
<l>infection reached our needed springs and pools,</l>
<l>thousands of serpents crawling over our</l>
<l>deserted fields, defiled our rivers with</l>
<l>their poison. The swift power of the disease</l>
<l>at first was limited to death of dogs</l>
<l>and birds and cattle, or among wild beasts.</l>
<l>The luckless plowman marvels when he sees</l>
<l>his strong bulls fall while at their task</l>
<l>and sink down in the furrow. Woolly flocks</l>
<l>bleat feebly while their wool falls off without</l>
<l>a cause, and while their bodies pine away.</l>
<l>The prized horse of high courage, and of great</l>
<l>renown when on the race-course, has now lost</l>
<l>victorious spirit, and forgetting his</l>
<l>remembered glory groans in his shut stall,</l>
<l>doomed for inglorious death. The boar forgets</l>
<l>to rage, the stag to trust his speed; and even</l>
<l>the famished bear to fight the stronger herd.</l>

    
<l>“Death seizes on the vitals of all life;</l>
<l>and in the woods, and in the fields and roads</l>
<l>the loathsome bodies of the dead corrupt</l>
<l>the heavy-hanging air. Even the dogs,</l>
<l>the vultures and the wolves refuse to touch</l>
<l>the putrid flesh, there in the sultry sun</l>
<l>rotting upon the earth; emitting steams,</l>
<l>and exhalations, with a baneful sweep</l>
<l>increasing the dread contagion's wide extent.</l>


    
<l>So spreading, with renewed destruction gained</l>
<l>from its own poison, the fierce pestilence</l>
<l>appeared to leap from moulding carcases</l>
<l>of all the brute creation, till it struck</l>
<l>the wretched tillers of the soil, and then</l>
<l>extended its dominion over all</l>
<l>this mighty city.</l>

    
<l>“Always it began</l>
<l>as if the patient's bowels were scorched with flames;</l>
<l>red blotches on the body next appeared,</l>
<l>and sharp pains in the lungs prevented breath.</l>
<l>The swollen tongue would presently loll out,</l>
<l>rough and discolored from the gaping mouth,</l>
<l>wide-gasping to inhale the noxious air—</l>
<l>and show red throbbing veins. The softest bed.</l>
<l>And richest covering gave to none relief;</l>
<l>but rather, the diseased would bare himself</l>
<l>to cool his burning breast upon the ground,</l>
<l>only to heat the earth—and no relief</l>
<l>returned. And no physician could be found;</l>
<l>for those who ministered among the sick</l>
<l>were first to suffer from the dread disease—</l>
<l>the cruel malady broke out upon</l>
<l>the very ones who offered remedies.</l>
<l>The hallowed art of medicine became</l>
<l>a deadly snare to those who knew it best.</l>

    
<l>“The only safety was in flight; and those</l>
<l>who were the nearest to the stricken ones,</l>
<l>and who most faithfully observed their wants,</l>
<l>were always first to suffer as their wards.</l>

    
<l>“And many, certain of approaching death,</l>
<l>indulged their wicked passions—recklessly</l>
<l>abandoned and without the sense of shame,</l>
<l>promiscuously huddled by the wells,</l>
<l>and rivers and cool fountains; but their thirst</l>
<l>no water could assuage, and death alone</l>
<l>was able to extinguish their desire.</l>
<l>Too weak to rise, they die in water they</l>
<l>pollute, while others drink its death.</l>

    
<l>“A madness seizing on them made their beds</l>
<l>become most irksome to their tortured nerves.</l>
<l>Demented they could not endure the pain,</l>
<l>and leaped insanely forth. Or if too weak,</l>
<l>the wretches rolled their bodies on the ground,</l>
<l>insistent to escape from hated homes—</l>
<l>imagined sources of calamity;</l>
<l>for, since the cause was hidden and unknown,</l>
<l>the horrible locality was blamed.</l>
<l>Suspicion seizes on each frail presence</l>
<l>as proof of what can never be resolved.</l>

    
<l>“And many half-dead wretches staggered out</l>
<l>on sultry roads as long as they could stand;</l>
<l>and others weeping, stretched out on the ground,</l>
<l>died in convulsions, as their rolling eyes</l>
<l>gazed upwards at the overhanging clouds;</l>
<l>under the sad stars they breathed out their souls.</l>

    
<l>“And oh, the deep despair that seized on me,</l>
<l>the sovereign of that wretched people! I</l>
<l>was tortured with a passionate desire</l>
<l>to die the same death—And I hated life.</l>

    
<l>“No matter where my shrinking eyes were turned,</l>
<l>I saw a multitude of gruesome forms</l>
<l>in ghastly attitudes bestrew the ground,</l>
<l>scattered as rotten apples that have dropped</l>
<l>from moving branches, or as acorns thick</l>
<l>around a gnarled oak.</l>

    
<l>“Lift up your eyes!</l>
<l>Behold that holy temple! unto Jove</l>
<l>long dedicated!—What availed the prayers</l>
<l>of frightened multitudes, or incense burned</l>
<l>on those devoted altars?—In the midst</l>
<l>of his most fervent supplications,</l>
<l>the husband as he pled for his dear wife,</l>
<l>or the fond father for his stricken son,</l>
<l>would suddenly, before a word prevailed,</l>
<l>die clutching at the altars of his Gods,</l>
<l>while holding in his stiffened hand, a spray</l>
<l>of frankincense still waiting for the fire.</l>
<l>How often sacrificial bulls have been</l>
<l>brought to those temples, and while white-robed priest</l>
<l>was pouring offered wine between their horns,</l>
<l>have fallen without waiting for the stroke.</l>

    
<l>“While I prepared a sacrifice to Jove,</l>
<l>for my behalf, my country and three sons,</l>
<l>the victim, ever moaning dismal sounds,</l>
<l>before a blow was struck, fell suddenly</l>
<l>beside the altar; and his scanty blood</l>
<l>ran thinly from the knives that slaughtered him.</l>
<l>His entrails, wanting all the marks of truth</l>
<l>were so diseased, the warnings of the Gods</l>
<l>could not be read—the baneful malady</l>
<l>had penetrated to the heart of life.</l>

    
<l>“And I have seen the carcases of men</l>
<l>lie rotting at the sacred temple gates,</l>
<l>or by the very altars, where they fell,</l>
<l>making death odious to the living Gods.</l>
<l>And often I have seen some desperate man</l>
<l>end life by his own halter, and so cheat</l>
<l>by voluntary death his fear of death,</l>
<l>in mad haste to outrun approaching fate.</l>

    
<l>“The bodies of the dead, indecently</l>
<l>were cast forth, lacking sacred funeral rites</l>
<l>as hitherto the custom. All the gates</l>
<l>were crowded with processions of the dead.</l>
<l>Unburied, they might lie upon the ground,</l>
<l>or else, deserted, on their lofty pyres</l>
<l>with no one to lament their dismal end,</l>
<l>dissolve in their dishonored ashes. All</l>
<l>restraint forgotten, a mad rabble fought</l>
<l>and took possession of the burning pyres,</l>
<l>and even the dead were ravished of their rest.—</l>
<l>And who should mourn them wanting, all the souls</l>
<l>of sons and husbands, and of old and young,</l>
<l>must wander unlamented: and the land</l>
<l>sufficed not for the crowded sepulchers:</l>
<l>and the dense forest was denuded of all trees.</l>

    
<l>“Heart-broken at the sight of this great woe,</l>
<l>I wailed, ‘O Jupiter! if truth were told</l>
<l>of your sweet comfort in Aegina's arms,</l>
<l>if you were not ashamed of me, your son,</l>
<l>restore my people, or entomb my corpse,</l>
<l>that I may suffer as the ones I love.’—</l>
<l>Great lightning flashed around me, and the sound</l>
<l>of thunder proved that my complaint was heard.</l>
<l>Accepting it, I cried, ‘Let these, Great Jove,</l>
<l>the happy signs of your assent, be shown</l>
<l>good omens given as a sacred pledge.’</l>

    
<l>“Near by, a sacred oak tree grown from seed</l>
<l>brought thither from Dodona, spread abroad</l>
<l>its branches thinly covered with green leaves;</l>
<l>and creeping as an army, on the tree</l>
<l>we saw a train of ants that carried grain,</l>
<l>half-hidden in the deep and wrinkled bark.</l>
<l>And while I wondered at the endless line</l>
<l>I said, ‘Good father, give me citizens</l>
<l>of equal number for my empty walls.’</l>
<l>Soon as I said those words, though not a wind</l>
<l>was moving nor a breeze,—the lofty tree</l>
<l>began to tremble, and I heard a sound</l>
<l>of motion in its branches. Wonder not</l>
<l>that sudden fear possessed me; and my hair</l>
<l>began to rise; and I could hardly stand</l>
<l>for so my weak knees tottered!—As I made</l>
<l>obeisance to the soil and sacred tree,</l>
<l>perhaps I cherished in my heart a thought,</l>
<l>that, not acknowledged, cheered me with some hope.</l>


    
<l>“At night I lay exhausted by such thoughts,</l>
<l>a deep sleep seized my body, but the tree</l>
<l>seemed always present—to my gaze distinct</l>
<l>with all its branches—I could even see</l>
<l>the birds among its leaves; and from its boughs,</l>
<l>that trembled in the still air, moving ants</l>
<l>were scattered to the ground in troops below;</l>
<l>and ever, as they touched the soil, they grew</l>
<l>larger and larger.—As they raised themselves,</l>
<l>they stood with upright bodies, and put off</l>
<l>their lean shapes; and absorbed their many feet:</l>
<l>and even as their dark brown color changed,</l>
<l>their rounded forms took on a human shape.</l>

    
<l>“When my strange dream departed, I awoke,</l>
<l>the vision vanished, I complained to Heaven</l>
<l>against the idle comfort of such dreams;</l>
<l>but as I voiced my own lament, I heard</l>
<l>a mighty murmur echoing through the halls</l>
<l>of my deserted palace, and a multitude</l>
<l>of voices in confusion; where the sound</l>
<l>of scarce an echo had disturbed the still</l>
<l>deserted chambers for so many days.</l>

    
<l>“All this I thought the fancy of my dream,</l>
<l>until my brave son Telamon, in haste</l>
<l>threw open the closed doorway, as he called,</l>
<l>‘Come quickly father, and behold a sight</l>
<l>beyond the utmost of your fondest dreams!’</l>
<l>I did go out, and there I saw such men</l>
<l>each in his turn, as I had seen transformed</l>
<l>in that weird vision of the moving ants.</l>

    
<l>“They all advanced, and hailed me as their king.</l>
<l>So soon as I had offered vows to Jove,</l>
<l>I subdivided the deserted farms,</l>
<l>and dwellings in the cities to these men</l>
<l>miraculously raised —which now are called</l>
<l>my Myrmidons, —the living evidence</l>
<l>of my strange vision. You have seen these men;</l>
<l>and since that day, their name has been declared,</l>
<l>‘Decisive evidence.’ They have retained</l>
<l>the well-known customs of the days before</l>
<l>their transformation. Patiently they toil;</l>
<l>they store the profits of their labor; which</l>
<l>they guard with valiant skill. They'll follow you</l>
<l>to any war, well matched in years and courage,</l>
<l>and I do promise, when this east wind turns,</l>
<l>this wind that favored you and brought you here,</l>
<l>and when a south wind favors our design,</l>
<l>then my brave Myrmidons will go with you.”</l>


Cephalus et Procris.
CEPHALUS AND PROCRIS

<l>This narrative and many other tales</l>
<l>had occupied the day. As twilight fell,</l>
<l>festivities were blended in the night—</l>
<l>the night, in turn, afforded sweet repose.</l>
<l>Soon as the golden Sun had shown his light,</l>
<l>the east wind blowing still, the ships were stayed</l>
<l>from sailing home. The sons of Pallas came</l>
<l>to Cephalus, who was the elder called;</l>
<l>and Cephalus together with the sons</l>
<l>of Pallas, went to see the king. Deep sleep</l>
<l>still held the king; and Phocus who was son</l>
<l>of Aeacus, received them at the gate,</l>
<l>instead of Telamon and Peleus who</l>
<l>were marshalling the men for war. Into</l>
<l>the inner court and beautiful apartments</l>
<l>Phocus conducted the Athenians,</l>
<l>and they sat down together. Phocus then</l>
<l>observed that Cephalus held in his hand</l>
<l>a curious javelin with golden head,</l>
<l>and shaft of some rare wood. And as they talked,</l>
<l>he said; “It is my pleasure to explore</l>
<l>the forest in the chase of startled game,</l>
<l>and so I've learned the nature of rare woods,</l>
<l>but never have I seen the match of this</l>
<l>from which was fashioned this good javelin;</l>
<l>it lacks the yellow tint of forest ash,</l>
<l>it is not knotted like all corner-wood;</l>
<l>although I cannot name the kind of wood,</l>
<l>my eyes have never seen a javelin-shaft</l>
<l>so beautiful as this.”</l>

    
<l>To him replied</l>
<l>a friend of Cephalus; “But you will find</l>
<l>its beauty is not equal to its worth,</l>
<l>for whatsoever it is aimed against,</l>
<l>its flight is always certain to the mark,</l>
<l>nor is it subject to the shift of chance;</l>
<l>and after it has struck, although no hand</l>
<l>may cast it back, it certainly returns,</l>
<l>bloodstained with every victim.”</l>

    
<l>Then indeed,</l>
<l>was Phocus anxious to be told, whence came</l>
<l>and who had given such a precious gift.</l>
<l>And Cephalus appeared to tell him all;</l>
<l>but craftily was silent on one strange</l>
<l>condition of the fatal gift. As he</l>
<l>recalled the mournful fate of his dear wife,</l>
<l>his eyes filled up with tears. “Ah, pity me,”</l>
<l>he said, “If Fate should grant me many years,</l>
<l>I must weep every time that I regard</l>
<l>this weapon which has been my cause of tears;</l>
<l>the unforgiven death of my dear wife—</l>
<l>ah, would that I had never handled it!</l>

    
<l>“My sweet wife, Procris!—if you could compare</l>
<l>her beauty with her sister's—Orithyia's,</l>
<l>(ravished by the blustering Boreas)</l>
<l>you would declare my wife more beautiful.</l>

    
<l>“'Tis she her sire Erectheus joined to me,</l>
<l>'Tis she the god Love also joined to me.</l>
<l>They called me happy, and in truth I was,</l>
<l>and all pronounced us so until the Gods</l>
<l>decreed it otherwise. Two joyful months</l>
<l>of our united love were almost passed,</l>
<l>when, as the grey light of the dawn dispelled,</l>
<l>upon the summit of Hymettus green,</l>
<l>Aurora, glorious in her golden robes,</l>
<l>observed me busy with encircling nets,</l>
<l>trapping the antlered deer.</l>

    
<l>“Against my will</l>
<l>incited by desire, she carried me</l>
<l>away with her. Oh, let me not increase</l>
<l>her anger, for I tell you what is true,</l>
<l>I found no comfort in her lovely face!</l>
<l>And, though she is the very queen of light,</l>
<l>and reigns upon the edge of shadowy space</l>
<l>where she is nourished on rich nectar-wine,</l>
<l>adding delight to beauty, I could give</l>
<l>no heed to her entreaties, for the thought</l>
<l>of my beloved Procris intervened;</l>
<l>and only her sweet name was on my lips.</l>

    
<l>“I told Aurora of our wedding joys</l>
<l>and all refreshing joys of love — and my</l>
<l>first union of my couch deserted now:</l>

    
<l>“Enraged against me, then the goddess said:</l>
<l>‘Keep to your Procris, I but trouble you,</l>
<l>ungrateful clown! but, if you can be warned,</l>
<l>you will no longer wish for her!’ And so,</l>
<l>in anger, she returned me to my wife.</l>

    
<l>“Alas, as I retraced the weary way,</l>
<l>long-brooding over all Aurora said,</l>
<l>suspicion made me doubtful of my wife,</l>
<l>so faithful and so fair.—But many things</l>
<l>reminding me of steadfast virtue, I</l>
<l>suppressed all doubts; until the dreadful thought</l>
<l>of my long absence filled my jealous mind:</l>
<l>from which I argued to the criminal</l>
<l>advances of Aurora; for if she,</l>
<l>so lovely in appearance, did conceal</l>
<l>such passion in the garb of innocence</l>
<l>until the moment of temptation, how</l>
<l>could I be certain of the purity</l>
<l>of even the strongest when the best are frail?</l>

    
<l>“So brooding—every effort I devised</l>
<l>to cause my own undoing. By the means</l>
<l>of bribing presents, favored by disguise,</l>
<l>I sought to win her guarded chastity.</l>
<l>Aurora had disguised me, and her guile</l>
<l>determined me to work in subtle snares.</l>

    
<l>“Unknown to all my friends, I paced the streets</l>
<l>of sacred Athens till I reached my home.</l>
<l>I hoped to search out evidence of guilt:</l>
<l>but everything seemed waiting my return;</l>
<l>and all the household breathed an air of grief.</l>

    
<l>“With difficulty I, disguised, obtained</l>
<l>an entrance to her presence by the use</l>
<l>of artifices many: and when I</l>
<l>there saw her, silent in her grief,—amazed,</l>
<l>my heart no longer prompted me to test</l>
<l>such constant love. An infinite desire</l>
<l>took hold upon me. I could scarce restrain</l>
<l>an impulse to caress and kiss her. Pale</l>
<l>with grief that I was gone, her lovely face</l>
<l>in sorrow was more beautiful—the world</l>
<l>has not another so divinely fair.</l>

    
<l>“Ah, Phocus, it is wonderful to think</l>
<l>of beauty so surpassing fair it seems</l>
<l>more lovable in sorrow! Why relate</l>
<l>to you how often she repulsed my feigned</l>
<l>attempts upon her virtue? To each plea</l>
<l>she said: ‘I serve one man: no matter where</l>
<l>he may be I will keep my love for one.’</l>

    
<l>“Who but a man insane with jealousy,</l>
<l>would doubt the virtue of a loving wife,</l>
<l>when tempted by the most insidious wiles,</l>
<l>whose hallowed honor was her husband's love?</l>
<l>But I, not satisfied with proof complete,</l>
<l>would not abandon my depraved desire</l>
<l>to poison the pure fountain I should guard;—</l>
<l>increasing my temptations, I caused her</l>
<l>to hesitate, and covet a rich gift.</l>

    
<l>“Then, angered at my own success I said,</l>
<l>discarding all disguise, ‘Behold the man</l>
<l>whose lavish promise has established proof,</l>
<l>the witness of your shameful treachery;</l>
<l>your absent husband has returned to this!’</l>

    
<l>“Unable to endure a ruined home,</l>
<l>where desecration held her sin to view,</l>
<l>despairing and in silent shame she fled;</l>
<l>and I, the author of that wickedness</l>
<l>ran after: but enraged at my deceit</l>
<l>and hating all mankind, she wandered far</l>
<l>in wildest mountains; hunting the wild game.</l>

    
<l>“I grieved at her desertion; and the fires</l>
<l>of my neglected love consumed my health;</l>
<l>with greater violence my love increased,</l>
<l>until unable to endure such pain,</l>
<l>I begged forgiveness and acknowledged fault:</l>
<l>nor hesitated to declare that I</l>
<l>might yield, the same way tempted, if such great</l>
<l>gifts had been offered to me. When I had made</l>
<l>abject confession and she had avenged</l>
<l>her outraged feelings, she came back to me</l>
<l>and we spent golden years in harmony.</l>

    
<l>“She gave to me the hound she fondly loved,</l>
<l>the very one Diana gave to her</l>
<l>when lovingly the goddess had declared,</l>
<l>‘This hound all others shall excel in speed.’</l>
<l>Nor was that gift the only one was given</l>
<l>by kind Diana when my wife was hers,</l>
<l>as you may guess—this javelin I hold forth,</l>
<l>no other but a goddess could bestow.</l>

    
<l>“Would you be told the story of both gifts</l>
<l>attend my words and you shall be amazed,</l>
<l>for never such another sad event</l>
<l>has added sorrow to the grieving world.</l>


    
<l>“After the son of Laius,—Oedipus,—</l>
<l>had solved the riddle of the monster-sphinx,</l>
<l>so often baffling to the wits of men,</l>
<l>and after she had fallen from her hill,</l>
<l>mangled, forgetful of her riddling craft;</l>
<l>not unrevenged the mighty Themis brooked</l>
<l>her loss. Without delay that goddess raised</l>
<l>another savage beast to ravage Thebes,</l>
<l>by which the farmer's cattle were devoured,</l>
<l>the land was ruined and its people slain.</l>

    
<l>“Then all the valiant young men of the realm,</l>
<l>with whom I also went, enclosed the field</l>
<l>(where lurked the monster) in a mesh</l>
<l>of many tangled nets: but not a strand</l>
<l>could stay its onrush, and it leaped the crest</l>
<l>of every barrier where the toils were set.</l>

    
<l>“Already they had urged their eager dogs,</l>
<l>which swiftly as a bird it left behind,</l>
<l>eluding all the hunters as it fled.</l>

    
<l>“At last all begged me to let slip the leash</l>
<l>of straining Tempest; such I called the hound,</l>
<l>my dear wife's present. As he tugged and pulled</l>
<l>upon the tightened cords, I let them slip:</l>
<l>no sooner done, then he was lost to sight;</l>
<l>although, wherever struck his rapid feet</l>
<l>the hot dust whirled. Not swifter flies the spear,</l>
<l>nor whizzing bullet from the twisted sling,</l>
<l>nor feathered arrow from the twanging bow!</l>

    
<l>“A high hill jutted from a rolling plain,</l>
<l>on which I mounted to enjoy the sight</l>
<l>of that unequalled chase. One moment caught,</l>
<l>the next as surely free, the wild beast seemed</l>
<l>now here now there, elusive in its flight;</l>
<l>swiftly sped onward, or with sudden turn</l>
<l>doubled in circles to deceive or gain.</l>
<l>With equal speed pursuing at each turn,</l>
<l>the rapid hound could neither gain nor lose.</l>
<l>Now springing forward and now doubling back,</l>
<l>his great speed foiled, he snapped at empty air.</l>

    
<l>“I then turned to my javelin's aid; and while</l>
<l>I poised it in my right hand, turned away</l>
<l>my gaze a moment as I sought to twine</l>
<l>my practiced fingers in the guiding thongs;</l>
<l>but when again I lifted up my eyes,</l>
<l>to cast the javelin where the monster sped,</l>
<l>I saw two marble statues standing there,</l>
<l>transformed upon the plain. One statue seemed</l>
<l>to strain in attitude of rapid flight,</l>
<l>the other with wide-open jaws was changed,</l>
<l>just in the act of barking and pursuit.</l>
<l>Surely some God—if any god controls—</l>
<l>decreed both equal, neither could succeed.”</l>

    
<l>Now after these miraculous events,</l>
<l>it seemed he wished to stop, but Phocus said.</l>
<l>“What charge have you against the javelin?”</l>

    
<l>And Cephalus rejoined; “I must relate</l>
<l>my sorrows last; for I would tell you first</l>
<l>the story of my joys—'Tis sweet to think,</l>
<l>upon the gliding tide of those few years</l>
<l>of married life, when my dear wife and I</l>
<l>were happy in our love and confidence.</l>
<l>No woman could allure me then from her;</l>
<l>and even Venus could not tempt my love;</l>
<l>all my great passion for my dearest wife</l>
<l>was equalled by the passion she returned.</l>

    
<l>“As early as the sun, when golden rays</l>
<l>first glittered on the mountains, I would rise</l>
<l>in youthful ardor, to explore the fields</l>
<l>in search of game. With no companions, hounds,</l>
<l>nor steeds nor nets, this javelin was alone</l>
<l>my safety and companion in my sport.</l>

    
<l>“And often when my right hand felt its weight,</l>
<l>a-wearied of the slaughter it had caused,</l>
<l>I would come back to rest in the cool shade,</l>
<l>and breezes from cool vales—the breeze I wooed,</l>
<l>blowing so gently on me in the heat;</l>
<l>the breeze I waited for; she was my rest</l>
<l>from labor. I remember, ‘Aura come,’</l>
<l>I used to say, ‘Come soothe me, come into</l>
<l>my breast most welcome one, and yes indeed,</l>
<l>you do relieve the heat with which I burn.’</l>

    
<l>“And as I felt the sweet breeze of the morn,</l>
<l>as if in answer to my song, my fate impelled</l>
<l>me further to declare my joy in song;</l>

    
<l>“ ‘You are my comfort, you are my delight!</l>
<l>Refresh me, cherish me, breathe on my face!</l>
<l>I love you child of lonely haunts and trees!’</l>

    
<l>“Such words I once was singing, not aware</l>
<l>of some one spying on me from the trees,</l>
<l>who thought I sang to some beloved Nymph,</l>
<l>or goddess by the name of Aura—so</l>
<l>I always called the breeze.—Unhappy man!</l>
<l>The meddling tell-tale went to Procris with</l>
<l>a story of supposed unfaithfulness,</l>
<l>and slyly told in whispers all he heard.</l>
<l>True love is credulous; (and as I heard</l>
<l>the story) Procris in a swoon fell down.</l>
<l>When she awakened from her bitter swoon,</l>
<l>she ceased not wailing her unhappy fate,</l>
<l>and, wretched, moaned for an imagined woe.</l>

    
<l>“So she lamented what was never done!</l>
<l>Her woe incited by a whispered tale,</l>
<l>she feared the fiction of a harmless name!</l>
<l>But hope returning soothed her wretched state;</l>
<l>and now, no longer willing to believe</l>
<l>such wrong, unless her own eyes saw it, she</l>
<l>refused to think her husband sinned.</l>

    
<l>“When dawn</l>
<l>had banished night, and I, rejoicing, ranged</l>
<l>the breathing woods, victorious in the hunt</l>
<l>paused and said, ‘Come Aura—lovely breeze—</l>
<l>relieve my panting breast!’ It seemed I heard</l>
<l>the smothered moans of sorrow as I spoke:</l>
<l>but not conceiving harm, I said again;</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Come here, oh my delight!’ And as those words</l>
<l>fell from my lips, I thought I heard a soft</l>
<l>sound in the thicket, as of moving leaves;</l>
<l>and thinking surely 'twas a hidden beast,</l>
<l>I threw this winged javelin at the spot.—</l>

    
<l>“It was my own wife, Procris, and the shaft</l>
<l>was buried in her breast—‘Ah, wretched me!’</l>
<l>She cried; and when I heard her well-known voice,</l>
<l>distracted I ran towards her,—only to find</l>
<l>her bathed in blood, and dying from the wound</l>
<l>of that same javelin she had given to me:</l>
<l>and in her agony she drew it forth,—</l>
<l>ah me! alas! from her dear tender side.</l>

    
<l>“I lifted her limp body to my own,</l>
<l>in these blood-guilty arms, and wrapped the wound</l>
<l>with fragments of my tunic, that I tore</l>
<l>in haste to staunch her blood; and all the while</l>
<l>I moaned, ‘Oh, do not now forsake me—slain</l>
<l>by these accursed hands!’</l>

    
<l>“Weak with the loss</l>
<l>of blood, and dying, she compelled herself</l>
<l>to utter these few words, ‘It is my death;</l>
<l>but let my eyes not close upon this life</l>
<l>before I plead with you! — By the dear ties</l>
<l>of sacred marriage; by your god and mine;</l>
<l>and if my love for you can move your heart;</l>
<l>and even by the cause of my sad death,—</l>
<l>my love for you increasing as I die,—</l>
<l>ah, put away that Aura you have called,</l>
<l>that she may never separate your soul,—</l>
<l>your love from me.’</l>

    
<l>“So, by those dying words</l>
<l>I knew that she had heard me call the name</l>
<l>of Aura, when I wished the cooling breeze,</l>
<l>and thought I called a goddess,—cause of all</l>
<l>her jealous sorrow and my bitter woe</l>

    
<l>“Alas, too late, I told her the sad truth;</l>
<l>but she was sinking, and her little strength</l>
<l>swiftly was ebbing with her flowing blood.</l>
<l>As long as life remained her loving gaze</l>
<l>was fixed on mine; and her unhappy life</l>
<l>at last was breathed out on my grieving face.</l>
<l>It seemed to me a look of sweet content</l>
<l>was in her face, as if she feared not death.”</l>

    
<l>In tears he folds these things; and, as they wept</l>
<l>in came the aged monarch, Aeacus,</l>
<l>and with the monarch his two valiant sons,</l>
<l>and troops, new-levied, trained to glorious arms.</l>
