<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 13


Armorum iudicium. Aiax.
AJAX AND ULYSSES

The chiefs were seated, and the soldiers form<lb/>
a circle round them. Then Ajax, the approved<lb/>
lord of the seven-fold shield, arose and spoke.<lb/>
Impatient in his wrath, he looked with stern,<lb/>
set features, out over Sigaean shores,<lb/>
and over the fleet of ships upon the beach,<lb/>
and, stretching out his hands, he said,<lb/>

    
“We plead,<lb/>
O Jupiter, our cause before the ships,—<lb/>
Ulysses vies with me! He did not shrink<lb/>
from giving way before the flames of Hector,<lb/>
when I withstood them and I saved the fleet.<lb/>
'Tis safer then to fight with lying words<lb/>
than with his hands. I am not prompt to speak,<lb/>
nor he to act. I am as good in war<lb/>
and deadly battle as he is in talk.<lb/>
Pelasgians, I do not suppose my deeds<lb/>
must here be mentioned: you have witnessed them<lb/>
but let Ulysses tell of deeds which he<lb/>
performed without a witness and which Night<lb/>
alone is conscious of. I own the prize<lb/>
we seek is great, but such a rival makes<lb/>
it small. To Ajax there s no cause for pride<lb/>
in having any prize, however great,<lb/>
for which Ulysses hoped. But he has won<lb/>
reward enough already. He can boast,<lb/>
when vanquished, that he strove with me.<lb/>

    
“I, even if my merit were in doubt<lb/>
should still excell in birth. I am the son<lb/>
of Telamon, who with great Hercules<lb/>
brought low the power of Troy and in the ship<lb/>
of Jason voyaged even to the Colchian shores.<lb/>
His father, Aeacus, now is a judge<lb/>
among the silent shades—where Sisyphus<lb/>
toils and is mocked forever with the stone.<lb/>
Great Jove himself calls Aeacus his son.<lb/>
Thus, Ajax is the third from Jupiter.<lb/>
But, Greeks, let not this line of my descent<lb/>
avail me, if I do not share it with<lb/>
my cousin, great Achilles. I demand<lb/>
these arms now due me as a cousin. Why<lb/>
should this one, from the blood of Sisyphus,<lb/>
and like him for his thefts and frauds, intrude<lb/>
the names of that loathed family upon<lb/>
honored descendants of brave Aeacus?<lb/>

    
“Will you deny me arms because I took<lb/>
arms earlier, no man prompting me,<lb/>
and call this man the better, who last of all<lb/>
took up arms, and, pretending he was mad,<lb/>
declined war, till the son of Naplius<lb/>
more shrewd than he (but to his future cost)<lb/>
discovered the contrivance of the fraud<lb/>
and had the coward dragged forth to the arms<lb/>
he had avoided. And shall this man have<lb/>
the world's best arms, who wanted none?<lb/>
Shall I lack honor and my cousin's gift<lb/>
because I faced the danger with the first?<lb/>

    
“Would that his madness had been real, or<lb/>
had been accepted as reality<lb/>
and that he never had attended us,<lb/>
as our companion to the Phrygian towers,<lb/>
this counsellor of evil! Then, good son<lb/>
of Poeas, Lemnos would not hold you now,<lb/>
exposed through guilt of ours! You, as men say,<lb/>
hidden in forest lairs, are moving with your groans<lb/>
the very rocks and asking for Ulysses<lb/>
what he so well deserves—what, if indeed<lb/>
there still are gods, you shall not ask in vain.<lb/>
And now, one of our leaders, he that was<lb/>
sworn to the same arms with ourselves! by whom<lb/>
the arrows of great Hercules are used,<lb/>
as his successor; broken by disease<lb/>
and famine, clothed with feathers, now must feed<lb/>
on birds and squander for his wretched fare<lb/>
the arrows destined for the wreck of Troy.<lb/>

    
“At least he lives, because he has not stayed<lb/>
too near Ulysses. Hapless Palamedes<lb/>
might wish that he too had been left behind,<lb/>
then he would live or would have met a death<lb/>
without dishonor. For this man, who well<lb/>
remembered the unfortunate discovery<lb/>
of his feigned madness, made a fraudulent<lb/>
attack on Palamedes, who he said<lb/>
betrayed the Grecian interest. He proved<lb/>
his false charge to the Greeks by showing them<lb/>
the gold which he himself hid in the ground.<lb/>
By exile or by death he has decreased<lb/>
the true strength of the Greeks. And so he fights,<lb/>
for such things men have cause to fear Ulysses!<lb/>

    
“Should he excel the faithful Nestor by<lb/>
his eloquence, I'd yet be well convinced<lb/>
the way he forsook Nestor was a crime,<lb/>
old Nestor, who implored in vain his aid,<lb/>
when he was hindered by his wounded steed<lb/>
and wearied with the years of his old age,<lb/>
was then deserted by that scheming man.<lb/>
The charge that I have made is strictly true,<lb/>
and the son of Tydeus knows it all too well;<lb/>
for he at that time called him by his name,<lb/>
rebuked him and upbraided his weak friend<lb/>
for coward flight.<lb/>

    
“The gods above behold<lb/>
the affairs of men with justice. That same man<lb/>
who would not help a friend now calls for help;<lb/>
he who forsook a friend, should be forsaken,<lb/>
the law he made returns upon himself.<lb/>
He called aloud on his companions;<lb/>
I came and saw him trembling, pale with fear,<lb/>
and shuddering, at the thought of coming death.<lb/>
I held my shield above him where he lay,<lb/>
and that way saved the villain's dastard life,<lb/>
and little praise I have deserved for that.<lb/>
If you still wish to claim this armor, let<lb/>
us both return to that place and restore<lb/>
the enemy, your wound, and usual fear—<lb/>
there hide behind my shield, and under that<lb/>
contend with me! Yet, when I faced the foe,<lb/>
he, whom his wound had left no power to stand,<lb/>
forgot the wound and took to headlong flight.<lb/>

    
“Hector approached, and brought the gods with him<lb/>
to battle; and, wherever he rushed on,<lb/>
not only this Ulysses was alarmed,<lb/>
but even the valiant, for so great the fear<lb/>
he caused them. Hector, proud in his success<lb/>
in blood and slaughter, I then dared to meet<lb/>
and with a huge: stone from a distance hurled<lb/>
I laid him flat. When he demanded one<lb/>
to fight with, I engaged him quite alone,<lb/>
for you my Greek friends, prayed the lot<lb/>
might fall upon me, and your prayers prevailed.<lb/>
If you should ask me of this fight, I will<lb/>
declare I was not vanquished there by him.<lb/>

    
“Behold, the Trojans brought forth fire and sword<lb/>
and Jove, as well, against the Grecian fleet,<lb/>
where now has eloquent Ulysses gone?<lb/>
Truly, I did protect a thousand ships<lb/>
with my breast, saving the hopes of your return.—<lb/>
for all these many ships, award me arms!<lb/>
But, let me speak the truth, the arms will gain<lb/>
more fame than I, for they will share my glory.<lb/>
And they need Ajax, Ajax needs not them.<lb/>

Let the Ithacan compare with deeds like mine<lb/>
his sleeping Rhesus, his unwarlike Dolon,<lb/>
Helenus taken, and Pallas gained by theft—<lb/>
all done by night and all with Diomed.<lb/>
If you must give these arms for deeds so mean,<lb/>
then give the greater share to Diomed.<lb/>

    
“Why give arms to Ulysses, who by stealth<lb/>
and quite unarmed, has always done his work,<lb/>
deceiving his unwary enemy<lb/>
by stratagems? This brilliant helmet, rich<lb/>
with sparkling gold, will certainly betray<lb/>
his plans, and will discover him when hid.<lb/>
His soft Dulichian head beneath the helm<lb/>
of great Achilles will not bear the weight;<lb/>
Achilles' heavy spear from Pelion must<lb/>
be burdensome for his unwarlike hands:<lb/>
nor will the shield, graven with the vasty world<lb/>
beseem a dastard left hand, smooth for theft.<lb/>

    
“Why caitiff, will you beg them for a gift,<lb/>
which will but weaken you? If by mistake,<lb/>
the Grecian people should award you this,<lb/>
it would not fright the foe but offer spoils<lb/>
and that swift flight (in which alone you have<lb/>
excelled all others, dastard wretch!) would soon<lb/>
grow laggard, dragging such a weight. And that<lb/>
good shield of yours, which has but rarely felt<lb/>
a conflict, is unhurt; for mine, agape<lb/>
with wounds a thousand from swift-striking darts,<lb/>
a new one must be found.<lb/>

    
“In short, what need<lb/>
is there for words? Let us be tried in war.<lb/>
Let all the arms of brave Achilles now<lb/>
be thrown among the foe; order them all<lb/>
to be retrieved; and decorate for war<lb/>
whoever brings them back, a worthy prize.”<lb/>

    
Ajax, the son of Telamon, stopped speech,<lb/>
and murmuring among the multitude<lb/>
followed his closing words, until Ulysses,<lb/>
Laertian hero, stood up there and fixed<lb/>
his eyes a short time on the ground; then raised<lb/>
them towards the chiefs; and with his opening words,<lb/>
which they awaited, the grace of his art<lb/>
was not found wanting to his eloquence.<lb/>

    
“If my desire and yours could have prevailed,<lb/>
O noble Greeks, the man who should receive<lb/>
a prize so valued, would not be in doubt,<lb/>
and you would now enjoy your arms, and we<lb/>
enjoy you, great Achilles. Since unjust<lb/>
fate has denied him both to me and you,<lb/>
(and here he wiped his eyes dry with his hands,<lb/>
as though then shedding tears,) who could succeed<lb/>
the great Achilles better than the one<lb/>
through whom the great Achilles joined the Greeks?<lb/>
Let Ajax win no votes because he seems<lb/>
to be as stupid as the truth declares.<lb/>
Let not my talents, which were always used<lb/>
for service of the Greeks, increase my harm:<lb/>
and let this eloquence of mine (if such<lb/>
we call it) which is pleading now for me,<lb/>
as it has pleaded many times for you,<lb/>
awake no envy. Let each man show his best.<lb/>

    
“Now as for ancestors and noble birth<lb/>
and deeds we have not done ourselves, all these<lb/>
I hardly call them ours. But, if he boasts<lb/>
because he is the great grandson of Jove,<lb/>
the founder of my family, you know,<lb/>
is Jupiter; by birth I am just the same<lb/>
degree removed from Jupiter as he.<lb/>
Laertes is my father, my grandsire is<lb/>
Arcesius; and my great grandsire is Jove,<lb/>
and my line: has no banished criminal.<lb/>
My mother's grandsire, Mercury, would give<lb/>
me further claims of birth—on either side a god.<lb/>

    
“But not because my mother's line is better<lb/>
and not because my father certainly,<lb/>
is innocent of his own brother's blood,<lb/>
have I advanced my claim to own those arms.<lb/>
Let personal merit weigh the cause alone.<lb/>
Let Ajax win no credit from the fact<lb/>
that Telamon, was brother unto Peleus.<lb/>
Let not his merit be that he is near by blood,<lb/>
may honor of manhood weigh in your award!<lb/>

    
“But, if you seek the heir and next of kin,<lb/>
Peleus is father, and Pyrrhus is the son<lb/>
of great Achilles. Where is Ajax then?<lb/>
These arms might go to Phthia or to Scyros!<lb/>
Teucer might claim the prize because he is<lb/>
Achilles' cousin. Does he seek these arms?<lb/>
And, if he did, would you allow his claim?<lb/>

    
“Since then the contest lies in deeds alone,<lb/>
though I have done more than may be well told,<lb/>
I will recall them as they have occurred.<lb/>

    
“Achilles' Nereid mother, who foresaw<lb/>
his death, concealed her son by change of dress.<lb/>
By that disguise Ajax, among the rest,<lb/>
was well deceived. I showed with women's wares<lb/>
arms that might win the spirit of a man.<lb/>
The hero still wore clothing of a girl,<lb/>
when, as he held a shield and spear, I said<lb/>
‘Son of a goddess! Pergama but waits<lb/>
to fall by you, why do you hesitate<lb/>
to assure the overthrow of mighty Troy?’<lb/>
With these bold words, I laid my hand on him—<lb/>
and to: brave actions I sent forth the brave:<lb/>
his deeds of Bravery are therefore mine<lb/>
it was my power that conquered Telephus,<lb/>
as he fought with his lance; it was through me<lb/>
that, vanquished and suppliant? he at last was healed.<lb/>
I caused the fall of Thebes; believe me, I<lb/>
took Lesbos, Tenedos, Chryse and Cilla—<lb/>
the cities of Apollo; and I took<lb/>
Scyros; think too, of the Lyrnesian wall<lb/>
as shaken by my hand, destroyed, and thrown <lb/>
down level with the ground. Let this suffice:<lb/>
I found the man who caused fierce Hector's death,<lb/>
through me the famous Hector now, lies low!<lb/>
And for those arms which made Achilles known<lb/>
I now demand these arms. To him alive<lb/>
I gave them—at his death they should be mine.<lb/>

    
“After the grief of one had reached all Greece,<lb/>
and ships a thousand, filled Euboean Aulis;<lb/>
the breezes long expected would not blow<lb/>
or adverse held the helpless fleet ashore.<lb/>
Then ruthless oracles gave their command,<lb/>
that Agamemnon should make sacrifice<lb/>
of his loved daughter and so satisfy<lb/>
Diana's cruel heart. The father stood<lb/>
up resolute, enraged against the gods,<lb/>
a parent even though a king. I turned,<lb/>
by tactful! words, a father's tender heart<lb/>
to the great issue of the public weal.<lb/>
I will confess it, and when I have confessed,<lb/>
may the son of Atreus pardon: I had to plead<lb/>
a difficult case before a partial judge.<lb/>
The people's good, his brother's, and stern duty,<lb/>
that followed his great office, won his ear,<lb/>
till royal honor outweighed claims of blood.<lb/>
I sought the mother, who could not be won<lb/>
by pleading but must be deceived by craft.<lb/>
Had Ajax gone to her, our thousand sails<lb/>
would still droop, waiting for the favoring breeze.<lb/>

    
“As a bold envoy I was even sent<lb/>
off to the towers of Ilium, and there<lb/>
I saw the senate-house of lofty Troy,<lb/>
and, fearless, entered it, while it was full<lb/>
of heroes. There, undaunted, I spoke for<lb/>
the cause which all the Greeks had given me.<lb/>
Accusing Paris, I demanded back<lb/>
the gold and stolen Helen, and I moved<lb/>
both Priam and Antenor. All the while<lb/>
Paris, his brothers, and their robber crew<lb/>
could scarce withhold their wicked hands from me.<lb/>
And all this, Menelaus, is well known to you:<lb/>
that was the first danger I shared with you.<lb/>


    
“I need not linger over the many things<lb/>
which by my counsel and my bravery<lb/>
I have accomplished through this long-drawn war.<lb/>

    
“A long time, after the first battle clash,<lb/>
the foe lay quiet within city walls,<lb/>
giving no challenge for an open fight—<lb/>
he stood nine years of siege before we fought<lb/>
what were you doing all that tedious time,<lb/>
what use were you, good only in a fight?<lb/>
If you will make inquiry of my deeds:<lb/>
I fashioned ambuscades for enemies;<lb/>
and circled our defenses with a trench;<lb/>
I cheered allies so they might all endure<lb/>
with patient minds a long, protracted war;<lb/>
I showed how our own army might subsist<lb/>
and how it could be armed; and I was sent<lb/>
wherever the necessity required.<lb/>

    
“Then, at the wish of Jove, our king, deceive<lb/>
by A false dream, bids us give up the war—<lb/>
he could excuse his order by the cause.<lb/>
Let Ajax tell him Troy must be laid low<lb/>
or let him fight—at least he can do that!<lb/>
Why does he fail to stop the fugitives?<lb/>
Why not take arms and tell the wavering crowd<lb/>
to rally round him? Would that be too much<lb/>
for one who never speaks except to boast?<lb/>
But now words fail me: Ajax turns and flees!<lb/>
I witnessed it and was ashamed to see<lb/>
you turn disgraced, preparing sails for flight.<lb/>
With exclamations and without delay,<lb/>
I said, ‘What are you doing? O my friends,<lb/>
has madness seized you that you will quit Troy,<lb/>
which is as good as taken? What can you<lb/>
bear home, after ten years, but your disgrace?’<lb/>

    
“With these commanding words, which grief itself<lb/>
gave eloquence, I brought resisting Greeks<lb/>
back from their purposed flight. Atrides called<lb/>
together his allies, all terror struck.<lb/>
Even then, Ajax the son of Telamon<lb/>
dared not vouchsafe one word. But impudent<lb/>
Thersites hurled vile words against the kings,<lb/>
and, thanks to me, he did not miss reproof.<lb/>
I rose and spoke to my disheartened friends,<lb/>
reviving their lost courage with my words<lb/>
from that time forth, whatever deeds this man,<lb/>
my rival, may have done, belong to me.<lb/>
'Twas I who stayed his flight and brought him back.<lb/>

    
“Which of the noble Greeks has given you praise<lb/>
or sought your company? Yet Diomed<lb/>
has shared his deeds with me and praises me,<lb/>
and, while Ulysses is with him, is brave<lb/>
and confident. 'Tis worthy of regard,<lb/>
when out of many thousands of the Greeks,<lb/>
a man becomes the choice of Diomed!<lb/>

    
“It was not lot that ordered me to go;<lb/>
and yet, despising dangers of the night,<lb/>
despising dangers of the enemy,<lb/>
I slew one, Dolon, of the Phrygian race,<lb/>
who dared to do the very things we dared,<lb/>
but not before I had prevailed on him<lb/>
to tell me everything, by which I learned<lb/>
perfidious actions which Troy had designed.<lb/>

    
“Of such things now, I had discovered all<lb/>
that should be found out, and I might have then<lb/>
returned to enjoy the praise I had deserved.<lb/>
But not content with that, I sought the tent<lb/>
of Rhesus, and within his camp I slew<lb/>
him and his proved attendants. Having thus<lb/>
gained as a conqueror my own desires,<lb/>
I drove back in a captured chariot,—<lb/>
a joyous triumph. Well, deny me, then.<lb/>
The arms of him whose steeds the enemy<lb/>
demanded as the price of one night's aid.<lb/>
Ajax himself has been more generous.<lb/>

    
“Why should I name Sarpedon's Lycian troops<lb/>
among whom I made havoc with my sword?<lb/>
I left Coeranos dead and streaming blood,<lb/>
with the sword I killed Alastor, Chromius,<lb/>
Alcander, Prytanis, Halius, and Noemon,<lb/>
Thoon and Charops with Chersidamas,<lb/>
and Ennomus—all driven by cruel fate,<lb/>
not reckoning humbler men whom I laid low,<lb/>
battling beneath the shadow of the city walls.<lb/>
And fellow citizens, I have my wounds<lb/>
honorable in the front. Do not believe<lb/>
my word alone. Look for yourselves and see!”<lb/>
Then with one hand, he drew his robe aside.<lb/>
“Here is a breast,” he cried, “that bled for you!<lb/>
But Ajax never shed a drop of blood<lb/>
to aid his friends, in all these many years,<lb/>
and has a body free of any wound.<lb/>

    
“What does it prove, if he declares that he<lb/>
fought for our ships against both Troy and Jove?<lb/>
I grant he did, for it is not my wont<lb/>
with malice to belittle other's deeds.<lb/>
But let him not claim for himself alone<lb/>
an honor in which all may have a share,<lb/>
let him concede some credit due to you.<lb/>
Disguised within the fear inspiring arms<lb/>
of great Achilles, Actor's son drove back<lb/>
the host of Trojans from our threatened fleet<lb/>
or ships and Ajax would have burned together.<lb/>

    
“Unmindful of the king, the chiefs, and me,<lb/>
he dreams that he alone dared to engage<lb/>
in single fight with Hector—he the ninth<lb/>
to volunteer and chosen just by lot.<lb/>
But yet, O brave chief! What availed the fight?<lb/>
Hector returned, not injured by a wound.<lb/>

    
“Ah, bitter fate, with how much grief I am<lb/>
compelled to recollect the time, when brave<lb/>
Achilles, bulwark of the Greeks, was slain.<lb/>
Nor tears, nor grief, nor fear, could hinder me:<lb/>
I carried his dead body from the ground,<lb/>
uplifted on these shoulders, I repeat,<lb/>
upon these shoulders from that ground<lb/>
I bore off dead Achilles, and those arms<lb/>
which now I want to bear away again.<lb/>
I have the strength to walk beneath their weight,<lb/>
I have a mind to understand their worth.<lb/>
Did the hero's mother, goddess of the sea,<lb/>
win for her son these arms, made by a god,<lb/>
a work of wondrous art, to have them clothe<lb/>
a rude soldier, who has no mind at all?<lb/>
He never could be made to understand<lb/>
the rich engravings, pictured on the shield—<lb/>
the ocean, earth, and stars in lofty skies;<lb/>
the Pleiades, and Hyades, the Bear,<lb/>
which touches not the ocean, far beyond<lb/>
the varied planets, and the fire-bright sword<lb/>
of high Orion. He demands a prize,<lb/>
which, if he had it, would be lost on him.<lb/>

    
“What of his taunting me, because I shrank<lb/>
from hardships of this war and I was slow<lb/>
to join the expedition? Does he not see,<lb/>
that he reviles the great Achilles too?<lb/>
Was my pretense a crime? then so was his.<lb/>
Was our delay a fault? mine was the less,<lb/>
for I came sooner; me a loving wife<lb/>
detained from war, a loving mother him.<lb/>
Some hours we gave to them, the rest to you.<lb/>
Why should I be alarmed, if now I am<lb/>
unable to defend myself against<lb/>
this accusation, which is just the same<lb/>
as you have brought against so great a man?<lb/>
Yet he was found by the dexterity<lb/>
of me, Ulysses, and Ulysses was<lb/>
not found by the dexterity of Ajax.<lb/>

    
“It is no wonder that he pours on me<lb/>
reproaches of his silly tongue, because<lb/>
he charges you with what is worthy shame.<lb/>
Am I depraved because this Palamedes has<lb/>
improperly been charged with crime by me?<lb/>
Then was it honorable for all of you,<lb/>
if you condemned him? Only think, that he,<lb/>
the son of Naplius, made no defence<lb/>
against the crime, so great, so manifest:<lb/>
nor did you only hear the charges brought<lb/>
against him, but you saw the proof yourselves,<lb/>
and in the gold his villainy was shown.<lb/>


    
“Nor am I to be blamed, if Vulcan's isle<lb/>
of Lemnos has become the residence<lb/>
of Philoctetes. Greeks, defend yourselves,<lb/>
for you agreed to it! Yes, I admit<lb/>
I urged him to withdraw from toils of war<lb/>
and those of travel and attempt by rest<lb/>
to ease his cruel pain. He took my advice<lb/>
and lives! The advice was not alone well meant<lb/>
(that would have been enough) but it was wise.<lb/>
Because our prophets have declared, he must<lb/>
lead us, if we may still maintain our hope<lb/>
for Troy's destruction—therefore, you must not<lb/>
intrust that work to me. Much better, send<lb/>
the son of Telamon. His eloquence<lb/>
will overcome the hero's rage, most fierce<lb/>
from his disease and anger: or else his<lb/>
invention of some wile will skilfully<lb/>
deliver him to us.—The Simois<lb/>
will first flow backward, Ida stand without<lb/>
its foliage, and Achaia promise aid<lb/>
to Troy itself; ere, lacking aid from me,<lb/>
the craft of stupid Ajax will avail.<lb/>

    
“Though, Philoctetes, you should be enraged<lb/>
against your friends, against the king and me;<lb/>
although you curse and everlastingly<lb/>
devote my head to harm; although you wish,<lb/>
to ease your anguish, that I may be given<lb/>
into your power, that you may shed my blood;<lb/>
and though you wait your turn and chance at me;<lb/>
still I will undertake the quest and will<lb/>
try all my skill to bring you back with me.<lb/>
If my good fortune then will favor me,<lb/>
I shall obtain your arrows; as I made<lb/>
the Trojan seer my captive, as I learned<lb/>
the heavenly oracles and fate of Troy,<lb/>
and as I brought back through a host of foes<lb/>
Minerva's image from the citadel.<lb/>

    
“And is it possible, Ajax may now<lb/>
compare himself with me? Truly the Fates<lb/>
will hold Troy from our capture, if we leave<lb/>
the statue. Where is valiant Ajax now,<lb/>
where are the boasts of that tremendous man?<lb/>
Why are you trembling, while Ulysses dares<lb/>
to go beyond our guards and brave the night?<lb/>
In spite of hostile swords, he goes within<lb/>
not only the strong walls of Troy but even<lb/>
the citadel, lifts up the goddess from<lb/>
her shrine, and takes her through the enemy!<lb/>
If I had not done this, Telamon's son<lb/>
would bear his shield of seven bull hides in vain.<lb/>
That night I gained the victory over Troy—<lb/>
'Twas then I won our war with Pergama,<lb/>
because I made it possible to win.<lb/>

    
“Stop hinting by your look and muttered words<lb/>
that Diomed was my partner in the deed.<lb/>
The praise he won is his. You, certainly<lb/>
fought not alone, when you held up your shield<lb/>
to save the allied fleet: a multitude<lb/>
was with you, but a single man gave me<lb/>
his valued help.<lb/>

    
“And if he did not know<lb/>
a fighting man can not gain victory<lb/>
so surely as the wise man, that the prize<lb/>
is given to something rarer than a brave right hand,<lb/>
he would himself be a contender now<lb/>
for these illustrious arms. Ajax the less<lb/>
would have come forward too, so would the fierce<lb/>
Eurypylus, so would Andraemon's son.<lb/>
Nor would Idomeneus withhold his claim,<lb/>
nor would his countryman Meriones.<lb/>
Yes, Menelaus too would seek the prize.<lb/>
All these brave men, my equals in the field,<lb/>
have yielded to my wisdom.<lb/>

    
“Your right hand<lb/>
is valuable in war, your temper stands<lb/>
in need of my direction. You have strength<lb/>
without intelligence; I look out for<lb/>
the future. You are able in the fight;<lb/>
I help our king to find the proper time.<lb/>
Your body may give service, and my mind<lb/>
must point the way: and just as much as he<lb/>
who guides the ship must be superior<lb/>
to him who rows it; and we all agree<lb/>
the general is greater than the soldier; so,<lb/>
do I excel you. In the body lives<lb/>
an intellect much rarer than a hand,<lb/>
by that we measure human excellence.<lb/>

    
“O chieftains, recompense my vigilance!<lb/>
For all these years of anxious care, award<lb/>
this honor to my many services.<lb/>
Our victory is in sight; I have removed<lb/>
the opposing fates and, opening wide the way<lb/>
to capture Pergama, have captured it.<lb/>
Now by our common hopes, by Troy's high walls<lb/>
already tottering and about to fall,<lb/>
and by the gods that I won from the foe,<lb/>
by what remains for wisdom to devise<lb/>
or what may call for bold and fearless deeds—<lb/>
if you think any hope is left for Troy,<lb/>
remember me! Or, if you do not give<lb/>
these arms to me, then give them all to her!”<lb/>
And he pointed to Minerva's fateful head.<lb/>

    
The assembled body of the chiefs was moved;<lb/>
and then, appeared the power of eloquence:<lb/>
the fluent man received, amid applause,<lb/>
the arms of the brave man. His rival, who<lb/>
so often when alone, stood firm against<lb/>
great Hector and the sword, and flames and Jove,<lb/>
stood not against a single passion, wrath.<lb/>
The unconquerable was conquered by his grief.<lb/>

    
He drew his sword, and said:—“This is at least<lb/>
my own; or will Ulysses also claim<lb/>
this, for himself. I must use this against<lb/>
myself—the blade which often has been wet,<lb/>
dripping with blood of Phrygians I have slain,.<lb/>
Will drip with his own master's:blood,<lb/>
lest any man but Ajax vanquish Ajax.”<lb/>
Saying this, he turned toward the vital spot<lb/>
in his own breast, which never had felt a wound,<lb/>
the fated sword and plunged it deeply in. <lb/>
though many sought to aid, no hand had strength<lb/>
to draw that steel—deep driven. The blood itself<lb/>
unaided drove it out. The ensanguined earth<lb/>
sprouted from her green turf that purple flower<lb/>
which grew of old from Hyacinthine blood.<lb/>
Its petals now are charged with double freight—<lb/>
the warrior's name, Apollo's cry of woe.<lb/>


Hecuba.
HECUBA TRANSFORMED

The conqueror, Ulysses, now set sail,<lb/>
for Lemnos, country of Hypsipyle,<lb/>
and for the land of Thoas, famed afar,<lb/>
those regions infamous in olden days,<lb/>
where women slew their husbands. So he went<lb/>
that he might capture and bring back with him<lb/>
the arrows of brave Hercules. When these<lb/>
were given back to the Greeks, their lord with them,<lb/>
a final hand at last prevailed to end<lb/>
that long fought war. Both Troy and Priam fell,<lb/>
and Priam's wretched wife lost all she had,<lb/>
until at last she lost her human form.<lb/>
Her savage barkings frightened foreign lands,<lb/>
where the long Hellespont is narrowed down.<lb/>

    
Great Troy was burning: while the fire still raged,<lb/>
Jove's altar drank old Priam's scanty blood.<lb/>
The priestess of Apollo then, alas!<lb/>
Was dragged by her long hair, while up towards heaven<lb/>
she lifted supplicating hands in vain.<lb/>
The Trojan matrons, clinging while they could<lb/>
to burning temples and ancestral gods,<lb/>
victorious Greeks drag off as welcome spoil.<lb/>
Astyanax was hurled down from the very tower<lb/>
from which he often had looked forth and seen<lb/>
his father, by his mother pointed out,<lb/>
when Hector fought for honor and his country's weal.<lb/>

    
Now Boreas counsels to depart. The sails,<lb/>
moved by a prosperous breeze, resound and wave—<lb/>
the Trojan women cry,—“Farewell to Troy!<lb/>
Ah, we are hurried off! ” and, falling down,<lb/>
they kiss the soil, and leave the smoking roofs<lb/>
of their loved native land. The last to go<lb/>
on board the fleet was Hecuba, a sight<lb/>
most pitiful. She was found among the tombs<lb/>
of her lost sons. While she embraced each urn<lb/>
and fondly kissed their bones, Ulysses came<lb/>
with ruthless hands and bore her off, his prize<lb/>
she in her bosom took away the urn<lb/>
of Hector only, and upon his grave<lb/>
she left some white hair taken from her head,<lb/>
a meager gift, her white hair and her tears.<lb/>

    
Across the strait from Troy, there is a land<lb/>
claimed by Bistonian men, and in that land<lb/>
was a rich palace, built there by a king<lb/>
named Polymnestor. To him the Phrygian king<lb/>
in secret gave his youngest son to rear,<lb/>
his Polydorus, safe from Troy and war,<lb/>
a prudent course, if he had not sent gold<lb/>
arousing greed, incitement to a crime.<lb/>
Soon, when the fortunes of the Trojans fell,<lb/>
that wicked king of Thrace took his own sword,<lb/>
and pierced the throat of his poor foster son<lb/>
and then, as if the deed could be concealed,<lb/>
if he removed the body, hurled the boy<lb/>
from a wild cliff into the waves below.<lb/>

    
Until the sea might be more calm, and gales<lb/>
of wind might be subdued, Atrides moored<lb/>
his fleet of ships upon the Thracian shore;<lb/>
there, from wide gaping earth, Achilles rose,<lb/>
as large as when he lived, with look as fierce,<lb/>
as when his sword once threatened Agamemnon.<lb/>
“Forgetting me do you depart, O Greeks?”<lb/>
He said, “And is your grateful! memory<lb/>
of all my worth interred with my bones?<lb/>
Do not do so. And that my sepulchre<lb/>
may have due worship, let Polyxena<lb/>
be immolated to appease the ghost:<lb/>
of dead Achilles.” Fiercely so he spoke.<lb/>

    
The old friends of Achilles all obeyed<lb/>
his unforgiving shade; and instantly<lb/>
the noble and unhappy virgin—brave,<lb/>
more like a man than woman—was torn from<lb/>
her mother's bosom, cherished more by her,<lb/>
since widowed and alone. And then they led<lb/>
the virgin as a sacrifice from there<lb/>
up to the cruel altar. When the maid<lb/>
observed the savage rites prepared for her,<lb/>
and when she noticed Neoptolemus<lb/>
stand by her with his cruel sword in hand,<lb/>
his fixed eyes on her countenance; she said:—<lb/>

    
“Do not delay my generous gift of blood,<lb/>
with no resistance thrust the ready steel<lb/>
into my throat or breast!” And then she laid<lb/>
both throat and bosom bare. “Polyxena<lb/>
would never wish to live in slavery.<lb/>
And such rites win no favor from a god.<lb/>
Only I fondly wish my mother might<lb/>
not know that I have died. My love of her<lb/>
takes from my joy in death and gives me fear.<lb/>
Not my death truly, but her own sad life<lb/>
should be the most lamented in her tears.<lb/>
Now let your men stand back, that I may go<lb/>
with dignity down to the Stygian shades,<lb/>
and, if my plea is just, let no man's hand<lb/>
touch my pure virgin body. A nobler gift<lb/>
to him, whoever he may be, whom you<lb/>
desire to placate with my death today,<lb/>
shall be a free maid's blood. But, if my words—<lb/>
my parting wish, has power to touch your hearts,<lb/>
(King Priam's daughter, not a captive, pleads)<lb/>
freely return my body to my mother,<lb/>
let her not pay with gold for the sad right<lb/>
to bury me—but only with her tears!<lb/>
Yes, when she could, she also paid with gold.”<lb/>

    
After she said these words, the people could<lb/>
no more restrain their tears; but no one saw<lb/>
her shed one tear. Even the priest himself,<lb/>
reluctantly and weeping, drove the steel<lb/>
into her proffered breast. On failing knees<lb/>
she sank down to the earth; but still maintained<lb/>
a countenance undaunted to the last:<lb/>
and, even unto death, it was her care<lb/>
to cover all that ought to be concealed,<lb/>
and save the value of chaste modesty.<lb/>

    
The Trojan matrons took her and recalled,<lb/>
lamenting, all the sons of Priam dead,<lb/>
the wealth of blood one house had shed for all.<lb/>
And they bewailed the chaste Polyxena<lb/>
and you, her mother, only lately called<lb/>
a royal mother and a royal wife,—<lb/>
the soul of Asia's fair prosperity,;<lb/>
now lowest fallen in all the wreck of Troy.<lb/>

    
The conquering Ulysses only claimed<lb/>
her his because she had brought Hector forth:<lb/>
and Hector hardly found a master for<lb/>
his mother. She continued to embrace<lb/>
the body of a soul so brave, and shed<lb/>
her tears, as she had shed them often before<lb/>
for country lost, for sons, for royal mate.<lb/>
She bathed her daughter's wounds with tears and kissed<lb/>
them with her lips and once more beat her breast.<lb/>
Her white hair streamed down in the clotting blood,<lb/>
she tore her breast, and this and more she said:<lb/>


    
“My daughter, what further sorrow can be mine?<lb/>
My daughter you lie dead, I see your wounds—<lb/>
they are indeed my own. Lest I should lose<lb/>
one child of mine without a cruel sword,<lb/>
you have your wound. I thought, because<lb/>
you were a woman, you were safe from swords.<lb/>
But you, a woman, felt the deadly steel.<lb/>
That same Achilles, who has given to death<lb/>
so many of your brothers, caused your death,<lb/>
the bane of Troy and the serpent by my nest!<lb/>
When Paris and when Phoebus with their shafts<lb/>
had laid him low, ‘Ah, now at least,’ I said,<lb/>
‘Achilles will no longer cause me dread.’<lb/>
Yet even then he still was to be feared.<lb/>
For him I have been fertile! Mighty Troy<lb/>
now lies in ruin, and the public woe<lb/>
is ended in one vast calamity.<lb/>
For me alone the woe of Troy still lives.<lb/>

    
“But lately on the pinnacle of fame,<lb/>
surrounded by my powerful sons-in-law,<lb/>
daughters, and daughters-in-law, and strong<lb/>
in my great husband, I am exiled now,<lb/>
and destitute, and forced from the sad tombs<lb/>
of those I love, to wretched slavery,<lb/>
serving Penelope: who showing me<lb/>
to curious dames of Ithaca, will point<lb/>
and say, while I am bending to my task,<lb/>
‘Look at that woman who was widely known,<lb/>
the mother of great Hector, once the wife<lb/>
of Priam!’ After so many have been lost,<lb/>
now you, last comfort of a mother's grief,<lb/>
must make atonement on the foeman's tomb.<lb/>
I bore a victim for my enemy.<lb/>

    
“Why do I live—an iron witted wretch?<lb/>
Why do I linger? Why does cruel age<lb/>
detain me? Why, pernicious deities,<lb/>
thus hold me to this earth, unless you will<lb/>
that I may weep at future funerals?<lb/>
After the fall of Troy, who would suppose<lb/>
King Priam could be happy? Blest in death,<lb/>
he has not seen my daughter's dreadful fate.<lb/>
He lost at once his kingdom and his life.<lb/>

    
“Can I imagine you, a royal maid,<lb/>
will soon be honored with due funeral rites,<lb/>
and will be buried in our family tomb?<lb/>
Such fortune comes no more to your sad house.<lb/>
A drift of foreign sand will be your grave,<lb/>
the parting gift will be your mother's tears.<lb/>
We have lost everything! But no, there is<lb/>
one reason why I should endure a while.<lb/>
His mother's dearest, now her only child,<lb/>
once youngest of that company of sons,<lb/>
my Polydorus lives here on these shores<lb/>
protected by the friendly Thracian king.<lb/>
Then why delay to bathe these cruel wounds,<lb/>
her dear face spattered with the dreadful blood?”<lb/>

    
So Hecuba went wailing towards the shore<lb/>
with aged step and tearing her gray hair.<lb/>
At last the unhappy mother said, “Give me<lb/>
an urn; O, Trojan women!” for, she wished<lb/>
to dip up salt sea water. But just then,<lb/>
she saw the corpse of her last son, thrown out<lb/>
upon the shore; her Polydorus, killed,<lb/>
disfigured with deep wounds of Thracian swords.<lb/>

    
The Trojan women cried aloud, and she<lb/>
was struck dumb with her agony, which quite<lb/>
consumed both voice and tears within her heart—<lb/>
rigid and still she seemed as a hard rock.<lb/>
And now she gazes at the earth in front<lb/>
now lifts her haggard face up toward the skies,<lb/>
now scans that body lying stark and dead,<lb/>
now scans his wounds and most of all the wounds.<lb/>
She arms herself and draws up all her wrath.<lb/>
It burned as if she still held regal power<lb/>
she gave up all life to the single thought<lb/>
of quick revenge. Just as a lioness<lb/>
rages when plundered of her suckling cub<lb/>
and follows on his trail the unseen foe,<lb/>
so, Hecuba with rage mixed in her grief<lb/>
forgetful of her years, not her intent,<lb/>
went hastily to Polymnestor, who<lb/>
contrived this dreadful murder, and desired<lb/>
an interview, pretending it was her wish<lb/>
to show him hidden gold, for her lost son.<lb/>

    
The Odrysian king believed it all:<lb/>
accustomed to the love of gain, he went<lb/>
with her, in secret, to the spot she chose.<lb/>
Then craftily he said in his bland way:<lb/>
“Oh, Hecuba, you need not wait, give now,<lb/>
munificently to your son—and all<lb/>
you give, and all that you have given,<lb/>
by the good gods, I swear, shall be his own.”<lb/>

    
She eyed him sternly as he spoke<lb/>
and swore so falsely.—Then her rage boiled over,<lb/>
and, seconded by all her captive train,<lb/>
she flew at him and drove her fingers deep<lb/>
in his perfidious eyes; and tore them from<lb/>
his face—and plunged her hands into the raw<lb/>
and bleeding sockets (passion made her strong),<lb/>
defiled with his bad blood. How could she tear<lb/>
his eyes, gone from their seats? She wildly gouged<lb/>
the sightless sockets of his bleeding face!<lb/>

    
The Thracians, angered by such violence done<lb/>
upon their king, immediately attacked<lb/>
the Trojan matron with their stones and darts<lb/>
but she with hoarse growling and snapping jaws<lb/>
sprang at the stones, and, when she tried to speak,<lb/>
she barked like a fierce dog. The place still bears<lb/>
a name suggested by her hideous change.<lb/>
And she, long mindful! of her old time woe,<lb/>
ran howling dismally in Thracian fields.<lb/>

    
Her sad fate moved the Trojans and the Greeks,<lb/>
her friends and foes, and all the heavenly gods.<lb/>
Yes all, for even the sister-wife of Jove<lb/>
denied that Hecuba deserved such fate.<lb/>


Memnon.
THE BIRDS OF MEMNON

Although Aurora had given aid to Troy,<lb/>
she had no heart nor leisure to be moved<lb/>
by fall of Troy or fate of Hecuba.<lb/>
At home she bore a greater grief and care;<lb/>
her loss of Memnon is afflicting her.<lb/>
Aurora, his rose-tinted mother, saw<lb/>
him perish by Achilles' deadly spear,<lb/>
upon the Phrygian plain. She saw his death,<lb/>
and the loved rose that lights the dawning hour<lb/>
turned death-pale, and the sky was veiled in clouds.<lb/>

    
The parent could not bear to see his limbs<lb/>
laid on the final flames. Just as she was,<lb/>
with loose hair streaming round her, she did not<lb/>
disdain to crouch down at the knees of Jove,<lb/>
and said these sad words added to her tears:<lb/>

    
“Beneath all those whom golden heaven sustains;<lb/>
(inferior, for see, through all the world<lb/>
my temples are so few) I have come now<lb/>
a goddess, to you; not with any hope<lb/>
that you may grant me temples, festivals,<lb/>
and altars, heated with devoted fires:<lb/>
but if you will consider the good deeds,<lb/>
which I, a woman, may yet do for you,<lb/>
when at the dawn I mark the edge of night;<lb/>
then you may think of some reward for me.<lb/>
But that is not my care; nor is it now<lb/>
Aurora's purpose here, that she should plead<lb/>
for honors, though deserved. I come bereaved,<lb/>
of my son Memnon, who in vain bore arms<lb/>
to aid his uncle and in prime of life<lb/>
(0, thus you willed it!) fell stricken by the sword<lb/>
of great Achilles. Give my son, I pray,<lb/>
O highest ruler of the gods, some honor,<lb/>
some comfort for his death, a little ease<lb/>
his mother's grief.” Jove nodded his assent.<lb/>

    
Immediately the high-wrought funeral-pile<lb/>
of Memnon fell down with its lofty fire,<lb/>
and volumes of black smoke obscured the day,<lb/>
as streams exhaling their dense rising fogs,<lb/>
exclude the bright sun from the land below.<lb/>
Black ashes fly and, rolling up a shape,<lb/>
retain a form and gather heat and life<lb/>
out of the fire. Their lightness gave them wings,<lb/>
first like a bird and then in fact a bird.<lb/>

    
The wings move whirring. In the neighboring air<lb/>
uncounted sisters, of one birth and growth<lb/>
together make one noise. Three times they flew<lb/>
around the funeral pile; and thrice the sound<lb/>
accordant of their fluttering wings went swift<lb/>
upon the soft breeze. When they turned about,<lb/>
their fourth flight in the skies divided them.<lb/>
As two fierce races from two hostile camps,<lb/>
clash in their warfare, these bird-sisters with<lb/>
their beaks and crooked claws clashed, passionate,<lb/>
until their tired wings and opposing breasts<lb/>
could not sustain them. And those kindred-foes<lb/>
fell down a sacrifice, memorial,<lb/>
to Memnon's ashes buried in that place.<lb/>

    
Brave Memnon, author of their birth, has given<lb/>
his name to those birds, marvellously formed,—<lb/>
and from him they are called Memnonides.—<lb/>
now, always when the Sun has passed the twelve<lb/>
signs of the Zodiac, they war again,<lb/>
to perish as a sacrifice for him.<lb/>

    
So others grieved, while Dymas' royal daughter<lb/>
was barking: but Aurora overcome<lb/>
with lasting sorrows, could not think of her:<lb/>
and even now, she sheds affectionate tears:<lb/>
and sprinkles them as dew on all the world.<lb/>


Aeneas apud Anium. Scylla.
DAUGHTERS OF ANIUS TRANSFORMED

The Fates did not allow the hope of Troy<lb/>
to be destroyed entirely with her walls.<lb/>
Aeneas, the heroic son of Venus,<lb/>
bore on his shoulders holy images<lb/>
and still another holy weight, his sire,<lb/>
a venerable burden. From all his wealth<lb/>
the pious hero chose this for his care<lb/>
together with his child, Ascanius.<lb/>
Then with a fleet of exiles he sails forth,<lb/>
he leaves Antandrus, leaves the wicked realm<lb/>
and shore of Thrace now dripping with the blood<lb/>
of Polydorus. With fair winds and tide<lb/>
he and his comrades reach Apollo's isle.<lb/>

    
Good Anius, king of Delos, vigilant<lb/>
for all his subjects' welfare, and as priest<lb/>
devoted to Apollo, took him there<lb/>
into his temple and his home, and showed<lb/>
the city, the famed shrines, and the two trees<lb/>
which once Latona, while in labor, held.<lb/>
They burned sweet incense, adding to it wine,<lb/>
and laid the flesh of cattle in the flames,<lb/>
an offering marked by custom for the god.<lb/>
Then in the palace and its kingly hall,<lb/>
reclining on luxurious couches, they<lb/>
drank flowing wine with Ceres' gifts of food.<lb/>

    
But old Anchises asked: “O chosen priest<lb/>
of Phoebus, can I be deceived? When first<lb/>
I saw these walls, did you not have a son,<lb/>
and twice two daughters? Is it possible<lb/>
I am mistaken?” Anius replied,—<lb/>
shaking his temples wreathed with fillets white,—<lb/>
“It can be no mistake, great hero, you<lb/>
did see the father of five children then,<lb/>
(so much the risk of fortune may affect<lb/>
the best of men). You see me now, almost<lb/>
bereft of all. For what assistance can<lb/>
my absent son afford, while he is king,<lb/>
the ruler over Andros—that land named<lb/>
for his name—over which he rules for me?<lb/>

    
“The Delian god gave to my son the art<lb/>
of augury; and likewise, Liber gave<lb/>
my daughters precious gifts exceeding all<lb/>
my wishes and belief: since, every thing<lb/>
my daughters touched assumed the forms of corn,<lb/>
of sparkling wine, or gray-green olive oil.<lb/>
Most surely, wonderful advantages.<lb/>

    
“Soon as Atrides, he who conquered Troy<lb/>
had heard of this (for you should not suppose<lb/>
that we, too, did not suffer from your storms)<lb/>
he dragged my daughters there with savage force,<lb/>
from my loved bosom to his hostile camp,<lb/>
and ordered them to feed the Argive fleet,<lb/>
by their divinely given power of touch.<lb/>

    
“Whichever way they could, they made escape<lb/>
two hastened to Euboea, and two sought<lb/>
their brother's island, Andros. Quickly then<lb/>
an Argive squadron, following, threatened war,<lb/>
unless they were surrendered. The brother's love<lb/>
gave way to fear. And there is reason why<lb/>
you should forgive a timid brother's fear:<lb/>
he had no warrior like Aeneas, none<lb/>
like Hector, by whose prowess you held Troy<lb/>
from its destruction through ten years of war.<lb/>

    
“Strong chains were brought to hold my daughters' arms.<lb/>
Both lifted suppliant hands, which still were free,<lb/>
to heaven and cried, ‘0, Father Bacchus! give<lb/>
us needed aid!’ And he who had before<lb/>
given them the power of touch, did give them aid—<lb/>
if giving freedom without human shape<lb/>
can be called giving aid.—I never knew<lb/>
by what means they lost shape, and cannot tell;<lb/>
but their calamity is surely known:<lb/>
my daughters were transformed to snow-white doves,<lb/>
white birds of Venus, guardian of your days.”<lb/>

    
With this and other talk they shared the feast,<lb/>
then left the table and retired to sleep.<lb/>
They rose up with the day, and went at once<lb/>
to hear the oracle of Phoebus speak.<lb/>
He counselled them to leave that land and find<lb/>
their ancient mother and their kindred shores.<lb/>

    
The king attended them, and gave them gifts<lb/>
when ready to depart; a sceptre to<lb/>
Anchises, and a robe and quiver to<lb/>
his grandson, and he gave a goblet to<lb/>
Aeneas, that which formerly was sent<lb/>
to him by Therses, once his Theban guest.<lb/>
Therses had sent it from Aonian shores;<lb/>
but Alcon the Hylean should be named,<lb/>
for he had made the goblet and inscribed<lb/>
a pictured story on the polished side.<lb/>

    
There was a city shown with seven gates,<lb/>
from which the name could be derived by all.<lb/>
Outside the walls was a sad funeral, <lb/>
and tombs and fires and funeral pyres were shown,<lb/>
and many matrons with dishevelled hair<lb/>
and naked breasts, expressive of their grief,<lb/>
and many nymphs too, weeping mournfully<lb/>
because their streams were dry. Without a leaf<lb/>
the bare trees stood straight up and the she goats<lb/>
were nibbling in dry, stony fields. And there he carved<lb/>
Orion's daughters in the Theban square,<lb/>
one giving her bare throat a cruel cut,<lb/>
one with her shuttle making clumsy wounds;<lb/>
both dying for their people. Next they were borne<lb/>
out through the city with doe funeral pomp,<lb/>
and mourning crowds were gathered round their pyre.<lb/>
Then from the virgin ashes, lest the race<lb/>
should die. twin youths arose, whom fame<lb/>
has named Coroni and they shared<lb/>
in all the rites becoming for their mothers' dust.<lb/>
Even so in shining figures all was shown<lb/>
inscribed on ancient bronze. The top rim, made<lb/>
quite rough, was gilded with acanthus leaves.<lb/>

    
Presents of equal worth the Trojans gave:<lb/>
a maple incense casket for the priest,<lb/>
a bowl, a crown adorned with gold and gems.<lb/>


GALATEA AND POLYPHEMUS

Then, recollecting how the Trojans had<lb/>
derived their origin from Teucer's race,<lb/>
they sailed to Crete but there could not endure<lb/>
ills sent by Jove, and, having left behind<lb/>
the hundred cities, they desired to reach<lb/>
the western harbors of the Ausonian land.<lb/>
Wintry seas then tossed the heroic band,<lb/>
and in a treacherous harbor of those isles,<lb/>
called Strophades, Aello frightened them.<lb/>
They passed Dulichium's port, and Ithaca,<lb/>
Samos, and all the homes of Neritos,—<lb/>
the kingdom of the shrewd deceitful man,<lb/>
Ulysses; and they reached Ambracia,<lb/>
contended for by those disputing gods;<lb/>
which is today renowned abroad, because<lb/>
of Actian Apollo, and the stone<lb/>
seen there conspicuous as a transformed judge;<lb/>
they saw Dodona, vocal with its oaks;<lb/>
and also, the well known Chaonian bays,<lb/>
where sons of the Molossian king escaped<lb/>
with wings attached, from unavailing flames.<lb/>

    
They set their sails then for the neighboring land<lb/>
of the Phaeacians, rich with luscious fruit:<lb/>
then for Epirus and to Buthrotos,<lb/>
and came then to a mimic town of Troy,<lb/>
ruled by the Phrygian seer. With prophecies<lb/>
which Helenus, the son of Priam, gave,<lb/>
they came to Sicily, whose three high capes<lb/>
jut outward in the sea. Of these three points<lb/>
Pachynos faces towards the showery south;<lb/>
and Lilybaeum is exposed to soft<lb/>
delicious zephyrs; but Peloros looks<lb/>
out towards the Bears which never touch the sea.<lb/>
The Trojans came there. Favored by the tide,<lb/>
and active oars, by nightfall all the fleet<lb/>
arrived together on Zanclaean sands.<lb/>
Scylla upon the right infests the shore,<lb/>
Charybdis, restless on the left, destroys.<lb/>

    
Charybdis swallows and then vomits forth<lb/>
misfortuned ships that she has taken down;<lb/>
Scylla's dark waist is girt with savage dogs.<lb/>
She has a maiden's face, and, if we may believe<lb/>
what poets tell, she was in olden time<lb/>
a maiden. Many suitors courted her,<lb/>
but she repulsed them; and, because she was<lb/>
so much beloved by all the Nereids,<lb/>
she sought these nymphs and used to tell<lb/>
how she escaped from the love-stricken youths.<lb/>

    
But Galatea, while her loosened locks<lb/>
were being combed, said to her visitor,—<lb/>
“Truly, O maiden, a gentle race of men<lb/>
courts you, and so you can, and do, refuse<lb/>
all with impunity. But I, whose sire<lb/>
is Nereus, whom the azure Doris bore,<lb/>
though guarded by so many sister nymphs,<lb/>
escaped the Cyclops' love with tragic loss.”<lb/>
And, sobbing, she was choked with tears.<lb/>

    
When with her fingers, marble white and smooth,<lb/>
Scylla had wiped away the rising tears<lb/>
of sorrow and had comforted the nymph,<lb/>
she said, “Tell me, dear goddess, and do not<lb/>
conceal from me (for I am true to you)<lb/>
the cause of your great sorrows.” And the nymph,<lb/>
daughter of Nereus, thus replied to her:—<lb/>


Acis et Galatea. Polyphemus.

“Acis, the son of Faunus and the nymph<lb/>
Symaethis, was a great delight to his<lb/>
dear father and his mother, but even more<lb/>
to me, for he alone had won my love.<lb/>
Eight birthdays having passed a second time,<lb/>
his tender cheeks were marked with softest down.<lb/>

    
“While I pursued him with a constant love,<lb/>
the Cyclops followed me as constantly.<lb/>
And, should you ask me, I could not declare<lb/>
whether my hatred of him, or my love<lb/>
of Acis was the stronger.—They were equal.<lb/>

    
“O gentle Venus! what power equals yours!<lb/>
That savage, dreaded by the forest trees,<lb/>
feared by the stranger who beholds his face<lb/>
contemner of Olympus and the gods,<lb/>
now he can feel what love is. He is filled<lb/>
with passion for me. He burns hot for me,<lb/>
forgetful of his cattle and his caves.<lb/>

    
“Now, Polyphemus, wretched Cyclops, you<lb/>
are careful of appearance, and you try<lb/>
the art of pleasing. You have even combed<lb/>
your stiffened hair with rakes: it pleases you<lb/>
to trim your shaggy beard with sickles, while<lb/>
you gaze at your fierce features in a pool<lb/>
so earnest to compose them. Love of flesh,<lb/>
ferocity and your keen thirst for blood<lb/>
have ceased. The ships may safely come and go!<lb/>

    
“While all this happened, Telemus arrived<lb/>
at the Sicilian Aetna—Telemus,<lb/>
the son of Eurymus, who never could<lb/>
mistake an omen, met the dreadful fierce,<lb/>
huge Cyclops, Polyphemus, and he said,<lb/>
‘That single eye now midmost in your brow<lb/>
Ulysses will take from you.’ In reply,<lb/>
the Cyclops only laughed at him and said,<lb/>
‘Most silly of the prophets! you are wrong,<lb/>
a maiden has already taken it!’<lb/>
So he made fun of Telemus, who warned<lb/>
him vainly of the truth—and after that,<lb/>
he either burdened with his bulk the shore,<lb/>
by stalking back and forth with lengthy strides,<lb/>
or came back weary to his shaded cave.<lb/>

    
“A wedge-formed hill projects far in the sea<lb/>
and either side there flow the salty waves.<lb/>
To this the giant savage climbed and sat<lb/>
upon the highest point. The wooly flock,<lb/>
no longer guided by him, followed after.<lb/>
There, after he had laid his pine tree down,<lb/>
which served him for a staff, although so tall<lb/>
it seemed best fitted for a ship's high mast,<lb/>
he played his shepherd pipes—in them I saw<lb/>
a hundred reeds. The very mountains felt<lb/>
the pipings of that shepherd, and the waves<lb/>
beneath him shook respondent to each note.<lb/>
All this time I was hidden by a rock,<lb/>
reclining on the bosom of my own<lb/>
dear Acis; and, although afar, I heard<lb/>
such words as these, which I can not forget:—<lb/>

    
‘O Galatea, fairer than the flower<lb/>
of snow-white privet, and more blooming than<lb/>
the meadows, and more slender than the tall<lb/>
delightful alder, brighter than smooth glass,<lb/>
more wanton than the tender skipping kid,<lb/>
smoother than shells worn by continual floods,<lb/>
more pleasing than the winter sun, or than<lb/>
the summer shade, more beautiful than fruit<lb/>
of apple trees, more pleasing to the sight<lb/>
than lofty plane tree, clearer than pure ice,<lb/>
and sweeter than the ripe grape, softer than<lb/>
soft swan-down and the softest curdled milk;<lb/>
alas, and if you did not fly from me,<lb/>
I would declare you are more beautiful<lb/>
than any watered garden of this world.<lb/>

    
‘And yet, O Galatea; I must say,<lb/>
that you are wilder than all untrained bullocks,<lb/>
harder than seasoned oak, more treacherous<lb/>
than tumbled waters, tougher than the twigs<lb/>
of osier and the white vine, harder to move<lb/>
than cliffs which front these waves, more violent<lb/>
than any torrent, you are prouder than<lb/>
the flattered peacock, fiercer than hot fire,<lb/>
rougher than thistles, and more cruel than<lb/>
the pregnant she-bear, deafer than the waves<lb/>
of stormy seas, more deadly savage than<lb/>
the trodden water-snake: and, (what I would<lb/>
endeavor surely to deprive you of)<lb/>
your speed is fleeter than the deer<lb/>
pursued by frightful barkings, and more swift<lb/>
than rapid storm-winds and the flitting air.<lb/>

    
‘But Galatea, if you knew me well<lb/>
you would regret your hasty flight from me,<lb/>
and you would even blame your own delay,<lb/>
and strive for my affection. I now hold<lb/>
the choice part of this mountain for my cave,<lb/>
roofed over with the native rock. The sun<lb/>
is not felt in the heat of middle day,<lb/>
nor is the winter felt there: apples load<lb/>
the bending boughs and luscious grapes<lb/>
hang on the lengthened vines, resembling gold,<lb/>
and purple grapes as rich—I keep for you<lb/>
those two delicious fruits. With your own hands,<lb/>
you shall yourself uncover strawberries,<lb/>
growing so soft beneath the woodland shade;<lb/>
you shall pluck corners in the autumn ripe,<lb/>
and plums, not only darkened with black juice<lb/>
but larger kinds as yellow as new wax.<lb/>
If I may be your mate, you shall have chestnuts,<lb/>
fruits of the arbute shall be always near,<lb/>
and every tree shall yield at your desire.<lb/>

    
‘The ewes here all are mine, and many more<lb/>
are wandering in the valleys; and the woods<lb/>
conceal a multitude—and many more<lb/>
are penned within my caves. If you perchance<lb/>
should ask me, I could never even guess<lb/>
or count the number; it is for the poor<lb/>
to count their cattle. Do not trust my word,<lb/>
but go yourself and see with your own eyes,<lb/>
how they can hardly stand up on their legs<lb/>
because of their distended udders' weight.<lb/>

    
‘I have lambs also, as a future flock,<lb/>
kept in warm folds, and kids of their same age<lb/>
in other folds. I always have supplies<lb/>
of snow-white milk for drinking, and much more<lb/>
is hardened with good rennet liquefied.<lb/>

    
‘The common joys of ordinary things<lb/>
will not be all you should expect of me—<lb/>
tame does and hares and she-goats or a pair<lb/>
of doves, or even a nest from a tall tree—<lb/>
for I have found upon a mountain top,<lb/>
the twin cubs of a shaggy wild she-bear,<lb/>
of such appearance you can hardly know<lb/>
the one from other. They will play with you.<lb/>
The very day I found them I declared,<lb/>
these I will keep for my dear loved one's joy.<lb/>

    
‘Do now but raise your shining head above<lb/>
the azure sea: come Galatea come,<lb/>
and do not scorn my presents. Certainly,<lb/>
I know myself, for only recently<lb/>
I saw my own reflection pictured clear<lb/>
in limpid water, and my features pleased<lb/>
and charmed me when I saw it. See how huge<lb/>
I am. Not even Jove in his high heaven<lb/>
is larger than my body: this I say<lb/>
because you tell me how imperial Jove<lb/>
surpasses.—Who is he? I never knew.<lb/>

    
‘My long hair plentifully hangs to hide<lb/>
unpleasant features; as a grove of trees<lb/>
overshadowing my shoulders. Never think<lb/>
my body is uncomely, although rough,<lb/>
thick set with wiry bristles. Every tree<lb/>
without leaves is unseemly; every horse,<lb/>
unless a mane hangs on his tawny neck;<lb/>
feathers must cover birds; and their soft wool<lb/>
is ornamental on the best formed sheep:<lb/>
therefore a beard, and rough hair spread upon<lb/>
the body is becoming to all men.<lb/>
I have but one eye centered perfectly<lb/>
within my forehead, so it seems most like<lb/>
a mighty buckler. Ha! does not the Sun<lb/>
see everything from heaven? Yet it has<lb/>
but one eye.—<lb/>

    
‘Galatea, you must know,<lb/>
my father is chief ruler in your sea,<lb/>
and therefor I now offer him to you<lb/>
as your own father-in-law—But oh, do take<lb/>
some pity on a suppliant,— and hear his prayer,<lb/>
for only unto you my heart is given.<lb/>

    
‘I, who despise the power of Jove, his heavens<lb/>
and piercing lightnings, am afraid of you—<lb/>
your wrath more fearful than the lightning's flash—<lb/>
but I should be more patient under slights,<lb/>
if you avoided all men: why reject<lb/>
the Cyclops for the love that Acis gives?<lb/>
And why prefer his smiles to my embraces,<lb/>
but let him please himself, and let him please<lb/>
you, Galatea, though against my will.<lb/>

    
‘If I am given an opportunity<lb/>
he will be shown that I have every strength<lb/>
proportioned to a body vast as mine:<lb/>
I will pull out his palpitating entrails,<lb/>
and scatter his torn limbs about the fields<lb/>
and over and throughout your salty waves;<lb/>
and then let him unite himself to you.—<lb/>
I burn so, and my slighted passion raves<lb/>
with greater fury and I seem to hold<lb/>
and carry Aetna in my breast—transferred<lb/>
there with its flames—Oh Galatea! can<lb/>
you listen to my passion thus unmoved!’<lb/>

    
“I saw all this; and, after he in vain<lb/>
had uttered such complaints, he stood up like<lb/>
a raging bull whose heifer has been lost,<lb/>
that cannot stand still, but must wander on<lb/>
through brush and forests, that he knows so well:<lb/>
when that fierce monster saw me and my Acis—<lb/>
we neither knew nor guessed our fate—he roared:<lb/>
‘I see you and you never will again<lb/>
parade your love before me!’ In such a voice<lb/>
as matched his giant size. All Aetna shook<lb/>
and trembled at the noise; and I amazed<lb/>
with horror, plunged into the adjoining sea.<lb/>

    
“My loved one, Acis turned his back and fled<lb/>
and cried out, ‘Help me Galatea, help!<lb/>
0, let your parents help me, and admit<lb/>
me safe within their realm; for I am now<lb/>
near my destruction!’ But the Cyclops rushed<lb/>
at him and hurled a fragment, he had torn<lb/>
out from the mountain, and although the extreme<lb/>
edge only of the rock could reach him there.<lb/>
It buried him entirely.<lb/>

    
“Then I did<lb/>
the only thing the Fates permitted me:<lb/>
I let my Acis take ancestral power<lb/>
of river deities. The purple blood<lb/>
flowed from beneath the rock, but soon<lb/>
the sanguine richness faded and became<lb/>
at first the color of a stream, disturbed<lb/>
and muddied by a shower. And presently<lb/>
it clarified.— The rock that had been thrown<lb/>
then split in two, and through the cleft a reed,<lb/>
stately and vigorous, arose to life.<lb/>
And soon the hollow mouth in the great rock,<lb/>
resounded with the waters gushing forth.<lb/>
And wonderful to tell, a youth emerged,<lb/>
the water flowing clear about his waist,<lb/>
his new horns circled with entwining reeds,<lb/>
and the youth certainly was Acis, though<lb/>
he was of larger stature and his face<lb/>
and features all were azure. Acis changed<lb/>
into a stream which ever since that time<lb/>
has flowed there and retained its former name.<lb/>


Glaucus.
GLAUCUS TRANSFORMED TO A SEA GOD

So Galatea, after she had told<lb/>
her sorrow, ceased; and, when the company<lb/>
had gone from there, the Nereids swam again<lb/>
in the calm and quiet waves. But Scylla soon<lb/>
returned (because she did not trust herself<lb/>
in deep salt waters) and she wandered there<lb/>
naked of garments on the thirsty sand;<lb/>
but, tired, by chance she found a lonely bay,<lb/>
and cooled her limbs with its enclosing waves.<lb/>

    
Then suddenly appeared a newly made<lb/>
inhabitant of that deep sea, whose name<lb/>
was Glaucus. Cleaving through the blue sea waves,<lb/>
he swam towards her. His shape had been transformed<lb/>
but lately for this watery life, while he<lb/>
was living at Anthedon in Euboea.—<lb/>
now he is lingering from desire for her<lb/>
he saw there and speaks whatever words<lb/>
he thought might stop her as she fled from him.<lb/>
Yet still she fled from him, and swift through fear,<lb/>
climbed to a mountain top above the sea.<lb/>
Facing the waves, it rose in one huge peak,<lb/>
parting the waters with a forest crown.<lb/>
She stood on that high summit quite secure:<lb/>
and, doubtful whether he might be a god<lb/>
or monster, wondered at his flowing hair<lb/>
which covered his broad shoulders and his back,—<lb/>
and marvelled at the color of his skin<lb/>
and at his waist merged into a twisted fish.<lb/>

    
All this he noticed, and while leaning there<lb/>
against a rock that stood near by, he said: —<lb/>

    
“I am no monster, maiden, I am not<lb/>
a savage beast; I am in truth a god<lb/>
of waters, with such power upon the seas<lb/>
as that of Proteus, Triton, or Palaemon—<lb/>
reared on land the son of Athamas.<lb/>

    
“Not long ago I was a mortal man,<lb/>
yet even then my thought turned to the sea<lb/>
and all my living came from waters deep,<lb/>
for I would drag the nets that swept up fish,<lb/>
or, seated on a rock, I flung the line<lb/>
forth from the rod. The shore I loved was near<lb/>
a verdant meadow. One side were the waves,<lb/>
the other grass, which never had been touched<lb/>
by horned, grazing cattle. Harmless sheep<lb/>
and shaggy goats had never cropped it—no<lb/>
industrious bee came there to harvest flowers;<lb/>
no festive garlands had been gathered there,<lb/>
adornments of the head; no mower's hands<lb/>
had ever cut it. I was certainly<lb/>
the first who ever sat upon that turf,—<lb/>
while I was drying there the dripping nets.<lb/>
And so that I might in due order count<lb/>
the fish that I had caught, I laid out those<lb/>
which by good chance were driven into my nets,<lb/>
or credulous, were caught on my barbed hooks.<lb/>

    
“It all seems like a fiction (but what good<lb/>
can I derive from fictions?) just as soon<lb/>
as any of my fish-prey touched the grass,<lb/>
they instantly began to move and skip<lb/>
as usual in sea water. While I paused<lb/>
and wondered, all of them slid to the waves,<lb/>
and left me, their late captor, and the shore.<lb/>

    
“I was amazed and doubtful, a long time;<lb/>
while I considered what could be the cause.<lb/>
What god had done this? Or perhaps the juice<lb/>
of some herb caused it? ‘But,’ I said, ‘what herb<lb/>
can have such properties?’ and with my hand<lb/>
I plucked the grass and chewed it with my teeth.<lb/>
My throat had hardly time to swallow those<lb/>
unheard of juices, when I suddenly<lb/>
felt all my entrails throbbing inwardly,<lb/>
and my entire mind also, felt possessed<lb/>
by passions foreign to my life before.<lb/>

    
“I could not stay in that place, and I said<lb/>
with shouting, ‘Farewell! dry land! never more<lb/>
shall I revisit you;’ and with those words<lb/>
upon my lips, I plunged beneath the waves.<lb/>
The gods of that deep water gave to me,<lb/>
when they received me, kindred honors, while<lb/>
they prayed Oceanus and Tethys both<lb/>
to take from me such mortal essence as<lb/>
might yet remain. So I was purified<lb/>
by them and after a good charm had been<lb/>
nine times repeated over me, which washed<lb/>
away all guilt, I was commanded then<lb/>
to put my breast beneath a hundred streams.<lb/>

    
“So far I can relate to you all things<lb/>
most worthy to be told; for all so far<lb/>
I can remember; but from that time on<lb/>
I was unconscious of the many things<lb/>
that followed. When my mind returned to me,<lb/>
I found myself entirely different<lb/>
from what I was before; and my changed mind<lb/>
was not the same as it had always been.<lb/>
Then, for the first time I beheld this beard<lb/>
so green in its deep color, and I saw<lb/>
my flowing hair which now I sweep along<lb/>
the spacious seas, and my huge shoulders with<lb/>
their azure colored arms, and I observed<lb/>
my leg extremities hung tapering<lb/>
exactly perfect as a finny fish.<lb/>

    
“But what avail is this new form to me.<lb/>
Although it pleased the Ocean deities?<lb/>
What benefit, although I am a god,<lb/>
if you are not persuaded by these things?”<lb/>

    
While he was telling wonders such as these—<lb/>
quite ready to say more—Scylla arose<lb/>
and left the god. Provoked at his repulse—<lb/>
enraged, he hastened to the marvellous court<lb/>
of Circe, well known daughter of the Sun.<lb/>
