<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 14

Scylla et Circe.
SCYLLA TRANSFORMED TO A ROCK

<l>Now the Euboean dweller in great waves,</l>
<l>Glaucus, had left behind the crest of Aetna,</l>
<l>raised upward from a giant's head; and left</l>
<l>the Cyclops' fields, that never had been torn</l>
<l>by harrow or by plough and never were</l>
<l>indebted to the toil of oxen yoked;</l>
<l>left Zancle, also, and the opposite walls</l>
<l>of Rhegium, and the sea, abundant cause</l>
<l>of shipwreck, which confined with double shores</l>
<l>bounds the Ausonian and Sicilian lands.</l>

    
<l>All these behind him, Glaucus, swimming on</l>
<l>with his huge hands through those Tyrrhenian seas,</l>
<l>drew near the hills so rich in magic herbs</l>
<l>and halls of Circe, daughter of the Sun,—</l>
<l>halls filled with men in guise of animals.</l>
<l>After due salutations had been given—</l>
<l>received by her as kindly—Glaucus said,</l>

    
<l>“You as a goddess, certainly should have</l>
<l>compassion upon me, a god; for you</l>
<l>alone (if I am worthy of it) can</l>
<l>relieve my passion. What the power of herbs</l>
<l>can be, Titania, none knows more than I,</l>
<l>for by their power I was myself transformed.</l>
<l>To make the cause of my strange madness known,</l>
<l>I have found Scylla on Italian shores,</l>
<l>directly opposite Messenian walls.</l>

    
<l>“It shames me to recount my promises,</l>
<l>entreaties, and caresses, and at last</l>
<l>rejection of my suit. If you have known</l>
<l>a power of incantation, I implore</l>
<l>you now repeat that incantation here,</l>
<l>with sacred lips—If herbs have greater power,</l>
<l>use the tried power of herbs. But I would not</l>
<l>request a cure—the healing of this wound.</l>
<l>Much better than an end of pain, let her</l>
<l>share, and feel with me my impassioned flame.”</l>

    
<l>But Circe was more quick than any other</l>
<l>to burn with passion's flame. It may have been</l>
<l>her nature or it may have been the work</l>
<l>of Venus, angry at her tattling sire.</l>

    
<l>“You might do better,” she replied, “to court</l>
<l>one who is willing, one who wants your love,</l>
<l>and feels a like desire. You did deserve</l>
<l>to win her love, yes, to be wooed yourself.</l>
<l>In fact you might be. If you give some hope,</l>
<l>you have my word, you shall indeed be wooed.</l>
<l>That you may have no doubt, and so retain</l>
<l>all confidence in your attraction's power—</l>
<l>behold! I am a goddess, and I am</l>
<l>the daughter also, of the radiant Sun!</l>
<l>And I who am so potent with my charms,</l>
<l>and I who am so potent with my herbs,</l>
<l>wish only to be yours. Despise her who</l>
<l>despises you, and her who is attached</l>
<l>to you repay with like attachment—so</l>
<l>by one act offer each her just reward.”</l>

    
<l>But Glaucus answered her attempt of love,</l>
<l>“The trees will sooner grow in ocean waves,</l>
<l>the sea-weed sooner grow on mountain tops,</l>
<l>than I shall change my love for graceful! Scylla.”</l>

    
<l>The goddess in her jealous rage could not</l>
<l>and would not injure him, whom she still loved,</l>
<l>but turned her wrath upon the one preferred.</l>
<l>She bruised immediately the many herbs</l>
<l>most infamous for horrid juices, which,</l>
<l>when bruised, she mingled with most artful care</l>
<l>and incantations given by Hecate.</l>
<l>Then, clothed in azure vestments, she passed through</l>
<l>her troop of fawning savage animals,</l>
<l>and issued from the center of her hall.</l>
<l>Pacing from there to Rhegium, opposite</l>
<l>the dangerous rocks of Zancle, she at once</l>
<l>entered the tossed waves boiling up with tides:</l>
<l>on these as if she walked on the firm shore,</l>
<l>she set her feet and, hastening on dry shod,</l>
<l>she skimmed along the surface of the deep.</l>

    
<l>Not far away there was an inlet curved,</l>
<l>round as a bent bow, which was often used</l>
<l>by Scylla as a favorite retreat.</l>
<l>There, she withdrew from heat of sea and sky</l>
<l>when in the zenith blazed the unclouded sun</l>
<l>and cast the shortest shadows on the ground.</l>
<l>Circe infected it before that hour,</l>

    
<l>polluting it with monster-breeding drugs.</l>
<l>She sprinkled juices over it, distilled</l>
<l>from an obnoxious root, and thrice times nine</l>
<l>she muttered over it with magic lips,</l>
<l>her most mysterious charm involved in words</l>
<l>of strangest import and of dubious thought.</l>

    
<l>Scylla came there and waded in waist deep,</l>
<l>then saw her loins defiled with barking shapes.</l>
<l>Believing they could be no part of her,</l>
<l>she ran and tried to drive them back and feared</l>
<l>the boisterous canine jaws. But what she fled</l>
<l>she carried with her. And, feeling for her thighs,</l>
<l>her legs, and feet, she found Cerberian jaws</l>
<l>instead. She rises from a rage of dogs,</l>
<l>and shaggy backs encircle her shortened loins.</l>

    
<l>The lover Glaucus wept. He fled the embrace</l>
<l>of Circe and her hostile power of herbs</l>
<l>and magic spells. But Scylla did not leave</l>
<l>the place of her disaster; and, as soon</l>
<l>as she had opportunity, for hate</l>
<l>of Circe, she robbed Ulysses of his men.</l>
<l>She would have wrecked the Trojan ships, if she</l>
<l>had not been changed beforehand to a rock</l>
<l>which to this day reveals a craggy rim.</l>
<l>And even the rock awakes the sailors' dread.</l>


Cercopes.
THE CERCOPES TRANSFORMED TO APES

<l>After the Trojan ships, pushed by their oars,</l>
<l>had safely passed by Scylla and the fierce</l>
<l>Charybdis, and with care had then approached</l>
<l>near the Ausonian shore, a roaring gale</l>
<l>bore them far southward to the Libyan coast.</l>

    
<l>And then Sidonian Dido, who was doomed</l>
<l>not calmly to endure the loss of her</l>
<l>loved Phrygian husband, graciously received</l>
<l>Aeneas to her home and her regard:</l>
<l>and on a pyre, erected with pretense</l>
<l>of holy rites, she fell upon the sword.</l>
<l>Deceived herself, she there deceived them all.</l>

    
<l>Aeneas, fleeing the new walls built on</l>
<l>that sandy shore, revisited the land</l>
<l>of Eryx and Acestes, his true friend.</l>
<l>There he performed a hallowed sacrifice</l>
<l>and paid due honor to his father's tomb.</l>
<l>And presently he loosened from that shore</l>
<l>the ships which Iris, Juno's minister,</l>
<l>had almost burned; and sailing, passed far off</l>
<l>the kingdom of the son of Hippotas,</l>
<l>in those hot regions smoking with the fumes</l>
<l>of burning sulphur, and he left behind</l>
<l>the rocky haunt of Achelous' daughters,</l>
<l>the Sirens. Then, when his good ship had lost</l>
<l>the pilot, he coasted near Inarime,</l>
<l>near Prochyta, and near the barren hill</l>
<l>which marks another island, Pithecusae,</l>
<l>an island named from strange inhabitants.</l>

    
<l>The father of the gods abhorred the frauds</l>
<l>and perjuries of the Cercopians</l>
<l>and for the crimes of that bad treacherous race,</l>
<l>transformed its men to ugly animals,</l>
<l>appearing unlike men, although like men.</l>
<l>He had contracted and had bent their limbs,</l>
<l>and flattened out their noses, bent back towards</l>
<l>their foreheads; he had furrowed every face</l>
<l>with wrinkles of old age, and made them live</l>
<l>in that spot, after he had covered all</l>
<l>their bodies with long yellow ugly hair.</l>
<l>Besides all that, he took away from them</l>
<l>the use of language and control of tongues,</l>
<l>so long inclined to dreadful perjury;</l>
<l>and left them always to complain of life</l>
<l>and their ill conduct in harsh jabbering.</l>


Sibylla.
THE SIBYL BECOMES GRAY AND DECREPIT

<l>After Aeneas had passed by all those</l>
<l>and seen to his right hand the distant walls</l>
<l>guarding the city of Parthenope,</l>
<l>he passed on his left hand a mound,</l>
<l>grave of the tuneful son of Aeolus.</l>
<l>Landing on Cumae's marshy shore, he reached</l>
<l>a cavern, home of the long lived Sibylla,</l>
<l>and prayed that she would give him at the lake,</l>
<l>Avernus, access to his father's shade.</l>

    
<l>She raised her countenance, from gazing on</l>
<l>the ground, and with an inspiration given</l>
<l>to her by influence of the god, she said,</l>
<l>“Much you would have, O man of famous deeds,</l>
<l>whose courage is attested by the sword,</l>
<l>whose filial piety is proved by flame.</l>
<l>But, Trojan, have no fear. I grant your wish,</l>
<l>and with my guidance you shall look upon</l>
<l>the latest kingdom of the world, shall see</l>
<l>Elysian homes and your dear father's shade,</l>
<l>for virtue there is everywhere a way.”</l>

    
<l>She spoke, and pointed out to him a branch</l>
<l>refulgent with bright gold, found in the woods</l>
<l>of Juno of Avernus, and commanded him</l>
<l>to pluck it from the stem. Aeneas did</l>
<l>what she advised him. Then he saw the wealth</l>
<l>of the dread Orcus, and he saw his own</l>
<l>ancestors, and beheld the aged ghost</l>
<l>of great Anchises. There he learned the laws</l>
<l>of that deep region, and what dangers must</l>
<l>be undergone by him in future wars.</l>

    
<l>Retracing with his weary steps the path</l>
<l>up to the light, he found relief from toil</l>
<l>in converse with the sage Cumaean guide.</l>
<l>While in thick dusk he trod the frightful way,</l>
<l>“Whether you are a deity,” he said,</l>
<l>“Or human and most favored by the gods,</l>
<l>to me you always will appear divine.</l>
<l>I will confess, too, my existence here</l>
<l>is due to your kind aid, for by your will</l>
<l>I visited the dark abodes of death,</l>
<l>and I escaped the death which I beheld.</l>
<l>For this great service, when I shall emerge</l>
<l>into the sunlit air, I will erect</l>
<l>for you a temple and will burn for you</l>
<l>sweet incense kindled at the altar flame.”</l>

    
<l>The prophetess looked on him and with sighs,</l>
<l>“I am no goddess,” she replied, “nor is</l>
<l>it well to honor any mortal head</l>
<l>with tribute of the holy frankincense.</l>
<l>And, that you may not err through ignorance,</l>
<l>I tell you life eternal without end</l>
<l>was;offered to me, if I would but yield</l>
<l>virginity to Phoebus for his love.</l>
<l>And, while he hoped for this and in desire</l>
<l>offered to bribe me for my virtue, first</l>
<l>with gifts, he said, ‘Maiden of Cumae choose</l>
<l>whatever you may wish, and you shall gain</l>
<l>all that you wish.’ I pointed to a heap</l>
<l>of dust collected there, and foolishly</l>
<l>replied, ‘As many birthdays must be given</l>
<l>to me as there are particles of sand.’</l>

    
<l>“For I forgot to wish them days of changeless youth.</l>
<l>He gave long life and offered youth besides,</l>
<l>if I would grant his wish. This I refused,</l>
<l>I live unwedded still. My happier time</l>
<l>has fled away, now comes with tottering step</l>
<l>infirm old age, which I shall long endure.</l>
<l>You find me ending seven long centuries,</l>
<l>and there remain for me, before my years</l>
<l>equal the number of those grains of sand,</l>
<l>three hundred harvests, three hundred vintages!</l>
<l>The time will come, when long increase of days</l>
<l>will so contract me from my present size</l>
<l>and so far waste away my limbs with age</l>
<l>that I shall dwindle to a trifling weight,</l>
<l>so trifling, it will never be believed </l>
<l>I once was loved and even pleased a god.</l>
<l>Perhaps, even Phoebus will not recognize me,</l>
<l>or will deny he ever bore me love.</l>
<l>But, though I change till eye would never know me,</l>
<l>my voice shall live, the fates will leave my voice.”</l>


Achaemenides apud Polyphemum.
ULYSSES WITH POLYPHEMUS AND CIRCE

<l>Sibylla with such words beguild their way</l>
<l>from Stygian realms up to the Euboean town.</l>
<l>Trojan Aeneas, after he had made</l>
<l>due sacrifice in Cumae, touched the shore</l>
<l>that had not yet been given his nurse's name.</l>
<l>There Macareus of Neritus had come,</l>
<l>companion of long tried Ulysses, there</l>
<l>he rested, weary of his lengthened toils.</l>

    
<l>He recognized one left in Aetna's cave,</l>
<l>greek Achaemenides, and, all amazed</l>
<l>to find him yet alive, he said to him,</l>
<l>“What chance, or what god, Achaemenides,</l>
<l>preserves you? Why is this barbarian ship</l>
<l>conveying you a Greek? What land is sought?”</l>

    
<l>No longer ragged in the clothes he wore</l>
<l>and his own master, wearing clothes not tacked</l>
<l>with sharp thorns, Achaemenides replied,</l>
<l>“Again may I see Polyphemus' jaws</l>
<l>out-streaming with their slaughtered human blood;</l>
<l>if my own home and Ithaca give more</l>
<l>delight to me than this barbarian bark,</l>
<l>or if I venerate Aeneas less</l>
<l>than my own father. If I should give my all,</l>
<l>it never could express my gratitude,</l>
<l>that I can speak and breath, and see the heavens</l>
<l>illuminated by the gleaming sun—</l>
<l>how can I be ungrateful and forget all this?</l>
<l>Because of him these limbs of mine were spared</l>
<l>the Cyclops' jaws; and, though I were even now</l>
<l>to leave the light of life, I should at worst</l>
<l>be buried in a tomb—not in his maw.</l>

    
<l>“What were my feelings when (unless indeed</l>
<l>my terror had deprived me of all sense) left there,</l>
<l>I saw you making for the open sea?</l>
<l>I wished to shout aloud, but was afraid</l>
<l>it would betray me to the enemy.</l>
<l>The shoutings of Ulysses nearly caused</l>
<l>destruction of your ship and there I saw</l>
<l>the Cyclops, when he tore a crag away</l>
<l>and hurled the huge rock in the whirling waves;</l>
<l>I saw him also throw tremendous stones</l>
<l>with his gigantic arms. They flew afar,</l>
<l>as if impelled by catapults of war,</l>
<l>I was struck dumb with terror lest</l>
<l>the waves or stones might overwhelm the ship,</l>
<l>forgetting that I still was on the shore!</l>

    
<l>“But when your flight had saved you from that death</l>
<l>of cruelty, the Cyclops, roaring rage,</l>
<l>paced all about Mount Aetna, groping through</l>
<l>its forests with his outstretched arms. Deprived</l>
<l>of sight, he stumbled there against the rocks,</l>
<l>until he reached the sea; and stretching out</l>
<l>his gore stained arms into its waters there,</l>
<l>he cursed all of the Grecian race, and said,</l>
<l>‘Oh! that some accident would carry back</l>
<l>Ulysses to me, or but one of his</l>
<l>companions; against whom my rage</l>
<l>might vent itself, whose joints my hand might tear</l>
<l>whose blood might drench my throat, whose living limbs</l>
<l>might quiver in my teeth. How trifling then,</l>
<l>how insignificant would be the loss,</l>
<l>of my sight which he took from me!’</l>

    
<l>“All this</l>
<l>and more he said. A ghastly horror took</l>
<l>possession of me when I saw his face</l>
<l>and every feature streaming yet with blood,</l>
<l>his ruthless hands, and the vile open space</l>
<l>where his one eye had been, and his coarse limbs,</l>
<l>and his beard matted through with human blood.</l>

    
<l>“It seemed as if Death were before my eyes,</l>
<l>yet that was but the least part of my woe.</l>
<l>I seemed upon the point of being caught,</l>
<l>my flesh about to be the food of his.</l>
<l>Before my mind was fixed the time I saw</l>
<l>two bodies of my loved companions</l>
<l>dashed three or four times hard against the ground,</l>
<l>when he above them, like a lion, crouched,</l>
<l>devouring quickly in his hideous jaws,</l>
<l>their entrails and their flesh and their crushed bones,</l>
<l>white marrowed, and their mangled quivering limbs.</l>
<l>A trembling fear seized on me as I stood</l>
<l>pallid and without power to move from there,</l>
<l>while I recalled him chewing greedily,</l>
<l>and belching out his bloody banquet from</l>
<l>his huge mouth—vomiting crushed pieces mixed</l>
<l>with phlegmy wine—and I feared such a doom</l>
<l>in readiness, awaited wretched me.</l>

    
<l>“Most carefully concealed for many days,</l>
<l>trembling at every sound and fearing death,</l>
<l>although desiring death; I fed myself</l>
<l>on grass and acorns, mixed with leaves; alone</l>
<l>and destitute, despondent unto death,</l>
<l>awaiting my destruction I lost hope.</l>
<l>In that condition a long while, at last</l>
<l>I saw a ship not far off, and by signs</l>
<l>prayed for deliverance, as I ran in haste,</l>
<l>down to the shore. My prayers prevailed on them.</l>
<l>A Trojan ship took in and saved a Greek!</l>

    
<l>“And now, O dearest to me of all men,</l>
<l>tell me of your adventures, of your chief</l>
<l>and comrades, when you sailed out on the sea.”</l>


Macareus. Ulixes et Circe.

<l>Then Macareus told him of Aeolus,</l>
<l>the son of Hippotas, whose kingdom is</l>
<l>the Tuscan sea, whose prison holds the winds,</l>
<l>and how Ulysses had received the winds</l>
<l>tied in a bull's hide bag, an awesome gift,</l>
<l>how nine days with a favoring breeze they sailed</l>
<l>and saw afar their longed for native land.</l>
<l>How, as the tenth day dawned, the crew was moved</l>
<l>by envy and a lust for gold, which they</l>
<l>imagined hidden in that leathern bag</l>
<l>and so untied the thong which held the winds.</l>
<l>These, rushing out, had driven the vessel back</l>
<l>over the waves which they had safely passed,</l>
<l>back to the harbor of King Aeolus.</l>

    
<l>“From there,” he said, “we sailed until we reached</l>
<l>the ancient city of Lamus, Laestrygon.—</l>
<l>Antiphates was reigning in that land,</l>
<l>and I was sent with two men of our troop,</l>
<l>ambassadors to see him. Two of us</l>
<l>escaped with difficulty, but the third</l>
<l>stained the accursed Lestrygonian's jaws</l>
<l>with his devoted blood. Antiphates</l>
<l>pursued us, calling out his murderous horde.</l>
<l>They came and, hurling stones and heavy beams,</l>
<l>they overwhelmed and sank both ships and men.</l>
<l>One ship escaped, on which Ulysses sailed.</l>

    
<l>“Grieving, lamenting for companions lost,</l>
<l>we finally arrived at that land which</l>
<l>you may discern far off, and, trust my word,</l>
<l>far off it should be seen—I saw it near!</l>
<l>And oh most righteous Trojan, Venus' son,</l>
<l>Aeneas, whom I call no more a foe,</l>
<l>I warn you now: avoid the shores of Circe.</l>

    
<l>“We moored our ship beside that country too;</l>
<l>but, mindful of the dangers we had run</l>
<l>with Laestrygons and cruel Polyphemus,</l>
<l>refused to go ashore. Ulysses chose</l>
<l>some men by lot and told them to seek out</l>
<l>a roof which he had seen among the trees.</l>
<l>The lot took me, then staunch Polytes next,</l>
<l>Eurylochus, Elpenor fond of wine,</l>
<l>and eighteen more and brought us to the walls</l>
<l>of Circe's dwelling.</l>

    
<l>“As we drew near and stood</l>
<l>before the door, a thousand wolves rushed out</l>
<l>from woods near by, and with the wolves there ran</l>
<l>she bears and lionesses, dread to see.</l>
<l>And yet we had no cause to fear, for none</l>
<l>would harm us with the smallest scratch.</l>
<l>Why, they in friendship even wagged their tails</l>
<l>and fawned upon us, while we stood in doubt.</l>

    
<l>“Then handmaids took us in and led us on</l>
<l>through marble halls to the presence of their queen.</l>
<l>She, in a beautiful recess, sat on her throne,</l>
<l>clad richly in a shining purple robe,</l>
<l>and over it she wore a golden veil.</l>
<l>Nereids and nymphs, who never carded fleece</l>
<l>with motion of their fingers, nor drew out</l>
<l>a ductile thread, were setting potent herbs</l>
<l>in proper order and arranging them</l>
<l>in baskets—a confusing wealth of flowers</l>
<l>were scattered among leaves of every hue:</l>
<l>and she prescribed the tasks they all performed.</l>

    
<l>“She knew the natural use of every leaf</l>
<l>and combinations of their virtues, when</l>
<l>mixed properly; and, giving them her close</l>
<l>attention, she examined every herb</l>
<l>as it was weighed. When she observed us there,</l>
<l>and had received our greetings and returned them,</l>
<l>she smiled, as if we should be well received.</l>
<l>At once she had her maidens bring a drink</l>
<l>of parched barley, of honey and strong wine,</l>
<l>and curds of milk. And in the nectarous draught</l>
<l>she added secretly her baleful drugs.</l>

    
<l>“We took the cups presented to us by</l>
<l>her sacred right hand; and, as soon as we,</l>
<l>so thirsty, quaffed them with our parching mouths,</l>
<l>that ruthless goddess with her outstretched wand</l>
<l>touched lightly the topmost hair upon our heads.</l>
<l>(Although I am ashamed, I tell you this)</l>
<l>stiff bristles quickly grew out over me,</l>
<l>and I could speak no more. Instead of words</l>
<l>I uttered hoarse murmurs and towards the ground</l>
<l>began to bend and gaze with all my face.</l>
<l>I felt my mouth take on a hardened skin</l>
<l>with a long crooked snout, and my neck swell</l>
<l>with muscles. With the very member which</l>
<l>a moment earlier had received the cup</l>
<l>I now made tracks in sand of the palace court.</l>
<l>Then with my friends, who suffered a like change</l>
<l>(charms have such power!) I was prisoned in a stye.</l>

    
<l>“We saw Eurylochus alone avoid</l>
<l>our swinish form, for he refused the cup.</l>
<l>If he had drained it, I should still remain</l>
<l>one of a bristly herd. Nor would his news</l>
<l>have made Ulysses sure of our disaster</l>
<l>and brought a swift avenger of our fate.</l>

    
<l>“Peace bearing Hermes gave him a white flower</l>
<l>from a black root, called Moly by the gods.</l>
<l>With this protection and the god's advice</l>
<l>he entered Circe's hall and, as she gave</l>
<l>the treacherous cup and with her magic wand</l>
<l>essayed to touch his hair, he drove her back</l>
<l>and terrified her with his quick drawn sword.</l>
<l>She gave her promise, and, right hands exchanged,</l>
<l>he was received unharmed into her couch,</l>
<l>where he required the bodies of his friends</l>
<l>awarded him, as his prized marriage gift.</l>

    
<l>“We then were sprinkled with more favored juice</l>
<l>of harmless plants, and smitten on the head</l>
<l>with the magic wand reversed. And new charms were</l>
<l>repeated, all conversely to the charms</l>
<l>which had degraded us. Then, as she sings,</l>
<l>more and yet more we raise ourselves erect,</l>
<l>the bristles fall off and the fissures leave</l>
<l>our cloven feet, our shoulders overcome</l>
<l>their lost shape and our arms become attached,</l>
<l>as they had been before. With tears of joy</l>
<l>we all embrace him, also weeping tears;</l>
<l>and we cling fondly to our chieftain's neck;—</l>
<l>not one of us could say a single word</l>
<l>till thus we had attested gratitude.”</l>

PICUS AND CANENS

<l>“The full space of a year detained us there,</l>
<l>and I, remaining that long stretch of time,</l>
<l>saw many things and heard as much besides:</l>
<l>and this among the many other things,</l>
<l>was told me secretly by one of the four</l>
<l>handmaidens of those rites. While Circe passed</l>
<l>her time from all apart except my chief,</l>
<l>she brought me to a white marble shape, a youth</l>
<l>who bore a woodpecker upon his head.</l>
<l>It stood erected in a hallowed place,</l>
<l>adorned with many wreaths. When I had asked</l>
<l>the statue's name and why he stood revered</l>
<l>in that most sacred temple, and what caused</l>
<l>that bird he carried on his head; she said:—</l>
<l>‘Listen, Macareus, and learn from this tale too</l>
<l>the power of Circe, and weigh the knowledge well!’</l>


Picus et Canens.

<l>“Picus, offspring of Saturn, was the king</l>
<l>of the Ausonian land, one very fond</l>
<l>of horses raised for war. The young man's form</l>
<l>was just what you now see, and had you known</l>
<l>him as he lived, you would not change a line.</l>
<l>His nature was as noble as his shape.</l>
<l>He could not yet have seen the steeds contend</l>
<l>four times in races held with each fifth year</l>
<l>at Grecian Elis. But his good looks had charmed</l>
<l>the dryads born on Latin hills, Naiads</l>
<l>would pine for him—both goddesses of spring</l>
<l>and goddesses of fountains, pined for him,</l>
<l>and nymphs that live in streaming Albula,</l>
<l>Numicus, Anio's course, brief flowing Almo,</l>
<l>and rapid Nar and Farfarus, so cool</l>
<l>in its delightful shades; all these and those</l>
<l>which haunt the forest lake of Scythian</l>
<l>Diana and the other nearby lakes.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘But, heedless of all these, he loved a nymph</l>
<l>whom on the hill, called Palatine, 'tis said,</l>
<l>Venilia bore to Janus double faced.</l>
<l>When she had reached the age of marriage, she</l>
<l>was given to Picus Laurentine, preferred</l>
<l>by her above all others—wonderful</l>
<l>indeed her beauty, but more wonderful</l>
<l>her skill in singing, from which art they called</l>
<l>her Canens. The fascination of her voice</l>
<l>would move the woods and rocks and tame wild beasts,</l>
<l>and stay long rivers, and it even detained</l>
<l>the wandering bird. Once, while she sang a lay</l>
<l>with high, clear voice, Picus on his keen horse</l>
<l>rode in Laurentian fields to hunt the boar,</l>
<l>two spears in his left hand, his purple cloak</l>
<l>fastened with gold. The daughter of the Sun</l>
<l>wandered in woods near by to find new herbs</l>
<l>growing on fertile hills, for she had left</l>
<l>Circaean fields called so from her own name.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘From a concealing thicket she observed</l>
<l>the youth with wonder. All the gathered herbs</l>
<l>dropped from her hands, forgotten, to the ground</l>
<l>and a hot fever-flame seemed to pervade</l>
<l>her marrow. When she could collect her thought</l>
<l>she wanted to confess her great desire,</l>
<l>but the swift horse and his surrounding guards</l>
<l>prevented her approach. “Still you shall not</l>
<l>escape me,” she declared, “although you may</l>
<l>be borne on winds, if I but know myself,</l>
<l>and if some potency in herbs remains,</l>
<l>and if my art of charms does not deceive.”</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Such were her;thoughts, and then she formed</l>
<l>an image of a bodiless wild swine</l>
<l>and let it cross the trail before the king</l>
<l>and rush into a woodland dense with trees,</l>
<l>which fallen trunks made pathless for his horse.</l>
<l>Picus at once, unconscious of all harm,</l>
<l>followed the phantom-prey and, hastily</l>
<l>quitting the reeking back of his good steed,</l>
<l>he wandered in pursuit of a vain hope,</l>
<l>on foot through that deep wood. She seized the chance</l>
<l>and by her incantation called strange gods</l>
<l>with a strange charm, which had the power to hide</l>
<l>the white moon's features and draw thirsty clouds</l>
<l>about her father's head. The changing sky</l>
<l>then lowered more black at each repeated tone</l>
<l>of incantation, and the ground exhaled</l>
<l>its vapours, while his people wandered there</l>
<l>along the darkened paths until no guard</l>
<l>was near to aid the imperiled king.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Having now gained an opportunity</l>
<l>and place, she said, “ O, youth most beautiful!</l>
<l>By those fine eyes, which captivated mine,</l>
<l>and by that graceful person, which brings me,</l>
<l>even me, a goddess, suppliant to you,</l>
<l>have pity on my passion; let the Sun,</l>
<l>who looks on all things, be your father-in-law;</l>
<l>do not despise Circe, the Titaness.”</l>

    
<l>“But fiercely he repelled her and her prayer,</l>
<l>“Whoever you may be, you are not mine,”</l>
<l>he said. “Another lady has my heart.</l>
<l>I pray that for a lengthening space of time</l>
<l>she may so hold me. I will not pollute</l>
<l>conjugal ties with the unhallowed loves</l>
<l>of any stranger, while the Fates preserve</l>
<l>to me the child of Janus, my dear Canens.”</l>

    
<l>“‘Titan's daughter, when many pleas had failed,</l>
<l>said angrily, “You shall not leave me with</l>
<l>impunity, and you shall not return</l>
<l>to Canens; and by your experience</l>
<l>you shall now learn what can be done by her</l>
<l>so slighted—what a woman deep in love</l>
<l>can do— and Circe is that slighted love.”</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Then twice she turned herself to face the west</l>
<l>and twice to face the East; and three times then</l>
<l>she touched the young man with her wand,</l>
<l>and sang three incantations. Picus fled,</l>
<l>but, marvelling at his unaccustomed speed,</l>
<l>he saw new wings, that spread on either side</l>
<l>and bore him onward. Angry at the thought</l>
<l>of transformation—all so suddenly</l>
<l>added a strange bird to the Latian woods,</l>
<l>he struck the wild oaks with his hard new beak,</l>
<l>and in his rage inflicted many wounds</l>
<l>on the long waving branches his wings took</l>
<l>the purple of his robe. The piece of gold</l>
<l>which he had used so nicely in his robe</l>
<l>was changed to golden feathers, and his neck</l>
<l>was rich as yellow gold. Nothing remained</l>
<l>of Picus as he was except the name.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘While all this happened his attendants called</l>
<l>on Picus often but in vain throughout</l>
<l>surrounding fields, and finding not a trace</l>
<l>of their young king, at length by chance they met</l>
<l>with Circe, who had cleared the darkened air</l>
<l>and let the clouds disperse before the wind</l>
<l>and clear rays of the sun. Then with good cause</l>
<l>they blamed her, they demanded the return</l>
<l>of their lost king, and with their hunting spears</l>
<l>they threatened her. She, sprinkling baleful drugs</l>
<l>and poison juices over them, invoked</l>
<l>the aid of Night and all the gods of Night</l>
<l>from Erebus and Chaos, and desired</l>
<l>the aid of Hecat with long, wailing cries.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Most wonderful to tell, the forests leaped</l>
<l>from fixed localities and the torn soil</l>
<l>uttered deep groans, the trees surrounding changed</l>
<l>from life-green to sick pallor, and the grass</l>
<l>was moistened with besprinkling drops of blood;</l>
<l>the stones sent forth harsh longings, unknown dogs</l>
<l>barked loudly, and the ground became a mass</l>
<l>of filthy snakes, and unsubstantial hosts</l>
<l>of the departed flitted without sound.</l>
<l>The men all quaked appalled. With magic rod</l>
<l>she touched their faces, pale and all amazed,</l>
<l>and at her touch the youths took on strange forms</l>
<l>of wild animals. None kept his proper shape.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘The setting sun is resting low upon</l>
<l>the far Tartessian shores, and now in vain</l>
<l>her husband is expected by the eyes</l>
<l>of longing Canens. Her slaves and people run</l>
<l>about through all the forest, holding lights</l>
<l>to meet him. Nor is it enough for that</l>
<l>dear nymph to weep and frenzied tear her hair</l>
<l>and beat her breast—she did all that and more.</l>
<l>Distracted she rushed forth and wandered through</l>
<l>the Latin fields. Six nights, six brightening dawns</l>
<l>found her quite unrefreshed with food or sleep</l>
<l>wandering at random over hill and dale.</l>
<l>The Tiber saw her last, with grief and toil</l>
<l>wearied and lying on his widespread bank.</l>
<l>In tears she poured out words with a faint voice,</l>
<l>lamenting her sad woe, as when the swan</l>
<l>about to die sings a funereal dirge.</l>
<l>Melting with grief at last she pined away;</l>
<l>her flesh, her bones, her marrow liquified</l>
<l>and vanished by degrees as formless air</l>
<l>and yet the story lingers near that place,</l>
<l>fitly named Canens by old-time Camenae!.’</l>

    
<l>“Such things I heard and saw through a long year.</l>
<l>Sluggish, inactive through our idleness,</l>
<l>we were all ordered to embark again</l>
<l>out on the deep, again to set our sails.</l>
<l>The Titaness explained the doubtful paths,</l>
<l>the great extent and peril, of wild seas.</l>
<l>I was alarmed, I will confess to you;</l>
<l>so, having reached these shores, I have remained.”</l>


Diomedis socii. Oleaster.
DIOMED'S FOLLOWERS TRANSFORMED

<l>Macareus finished. And Aeneas' nurse,</l>
<l>now buried in a marble urn, had this</l>
<l>brief, strange inscription on her tomb:—</l>
<l>“My foster-child of proven piety,</l>
<l>burned me Caieta here: although</l>
<l>I was at first preserved from Argive fire,</l>
<l>I later burned with fire which was my due.”</l>

    
<l>The cable loosened from the grassy bank,</l>
<l>they steered a course which kept them well away</l>
<l>from ill famed Circe's wiles and from her home</l>
<l>and sought the groves where Tiber dark with shade,</l>
<l>breaks with his yellow sands into the sea.</l>

    
<l>Aeneas then fell heir to the home and won</l>
<l>the daughter of Latinus, Faunus' son,</l>
<l>not without war. A people very fierce</l>
<l>made war, and Turnus, their young chief,</l>
<l>indignant fought to hold a promised bride.</l>
<l>With Latium all Etruria was embroiled,</l>
<l>a victory hard to win was sought through war.</l>
<l>By foreign aid each side got further strength:</l>
<l>the camp of Rutuli abounds in men,</l>
<l>and many throng the opposing camp of Troy.</l>
<l>Aeneas did not find Evander's home</l>
<l>in vain. But Venulus with no success</l>
<l>came to the realm of exiled Diomed.</l>
<l>That hero had marked out his mighty walls</l>
<l>with favor of Iapygian Daunus and</l>
<l>held fields that came to him as marriage dower.</l>

    
<l>When Venulus, by Turnus' orders, made</l>
<l>request for aid, the Aetolian hero said</l>
<l>that he was poor in men: he did not wish</l>
<l>to risk in battle himself nor any troops</l>
<l>belonging to his father-in-law and had</l>
<l>no troops of his that he could arm for battle.</l>
<l>“Lest you should think I feign,” he then went on</l>
<l>“Although my grief must be renewed because</l>
<l>of bitter recollections of the past,</l>
<l>I will endure recital now to you:—</l>

    
<l>“After the lofty Ilion was burnt</l>
<l>and Pergama had fed the Grecian flames,</l>
<l>and Ajax, the Narycian hero, had</l>
<l>brought from a virgin, for a virgin wronged,</l>
<l>the punishment which he alone deserved</l>
<l>on our whole expedition, we were then</l>
<l>dispersed and driven by violent winds</l>
<l>over the hostile seas; and we, the Greeks,</l>
<l>had to endure in darkness, lightning, rain,</l>
<l>the wrath both of the heavens and of the sea,</l>
<l>and Caphareus, the climax of our woe.</l>
<l>Not to detain you by relating such</l>
<l>unhappy things in order, Greece might then</l>
<l>have seemed to merit even Priam's tears.</l>

    
<l>“Although well armed Minerva's care preserved</l>
<l>me then and brought me safe through rocks and waves,</l>
<l>from my native Argos I was driven again,</l>
<l>for outraged Venus took her full revenge</l>
<l>remembering still that wound of long ago;</l>
<l>and I endured such hardships on the deep,</l>
<l>and hazards amid armies on the shore,</l>
<l>that often I called those happy whom the storm—</l>
<l>an ill that came on all, or Cephareus had drowned.</l>
<l>I even wished I had been one of them.</l>

    
<l>“My best companions having now endured</l>
<l>utmost extremities in wars and seas,</l>
<l>lost courage and demanded a swift end</l>
<l>of our long wandering. Acmon, by nature hot,</l>
<l>and much embittered by misfortune, said,</l>
<l>‘What now remains for you, my friends,</l>
<l>that patience can endure? What can be done</l>
<l>by Venus (if she wants to) more than she</l>
<l>already has done? While we have a dread</l>
<l>of greater evils, reason will be found</l>
<l>for patience; but, when fortune brings her worst,</l>
<l>we scorn and trample fear beneath our feet.</l>
<l>Upon the height of woe, why should we care?</l>
<l>Let Venus listen, let her hate Diomed</l>
<l>more than all others—as indeed she does,</l>
<l>we all despise her hate. At a great price</l>
<l>we have bought and won the right to such contempt!’</l>

    
<l>“With language of this kind Pleuronian Acmon.</l>
<l>Provoking Venus further than before,</l>
<l>revived her former anger. His fierce words</l>
<l>were then approved of by a few, while we</l>
<l>the greater number of his real friends,</l>
<l>rebuked the words of Acmon: and while he</l>
<l>prepared to answer us, his voice, and even</l>
<l>the passage of his voice, were both at once</l>
<l>diminished, his hair changed to feathers, while</l>
<l>his neck took a new form. His breast and back</l>
<l>covered themselves with down, and both his arms</l>
<l>grew longer feathers, and his elbows curved</l>
<l>into light wings, much of each foot was changed</l>
<l>to long toes, and his mouth grew still and hard</l>
<l>with pointed horn.</l>

    
<l>“Amazed at his swift change</l>
<l>were Lycus, Abas, Nycteus and Rhexenor.</l>
<l>And, while they stared, they took his feathered shape.</l>
<l>The larger portion of my company</l>
<l>flew from their boat, resounding all around</l>
<l>our oars with flapping of new-fashioned wings.</l>
<l>If you should ask the form of these strange birds</l>
<l>they were like snowy swans, though not the same.</l>

    
<l>“Now as Iapygian Daunus' son-in-law</l>
<l>I scarcely hold this town and arid fields</l>
<l>with my small remnant of trustworthy men.”</l>

METAMORPHOSES RELATED TO AENEAS

<l>So Diomed made answer. Venulus</l>
<l>soon after left the Calydonian realms,</l>
<l>Peucetian bays, and the Messapian fields.</l>
<l>Among those fields he saw a darkened cave</l>
<l>in woods and waving reeds. The halfgoat Pan</l>
<l>now lives there, but in older time the nymphs</l>
<l>possessed it. An Apulian shepherd scared</l>
<l>them from that spot. At first he terrified</l>
<l>them with a sudden fear, but soon in scorn,</l>
<l>as they considered what the intruder was,	</l>
<l>they danced before him, moving feet to time.</l>
<l>The shepherd clown abused them, capering,</l>
<l>grotesquely imitating graceful steps,</l>
<l>and railed at them with coarse and foolish words.</l>
<l>He was not silent till a tree's new bark</l>
<l>had closed his mouth for now he is a tree.</l>
<l>And the wild olive's fruit took bitterness</l>
<l>from him. It has the tartness of his tongue.</l>


Aeneae naves. Ardea.

<l>When the ambassadors returned and told</l>
<l>their tale about Aetolian arms refused,</l>
<l>the bold Rutulians carried on the war</l>
<l>without those forces, and much blood was shed.</l>
<l>Then Turnus with a greedy torch drew near</l>
<l>the Trojan fleet, well built of close-knit pine.</l>
<l>What had escaped the waves, now feared the flame.</l>
<l>Soon Mulciber was burning pitch and wax</l>
<l>and other food of fire, up the high masts</l>
<l>he ran and fed upon the tight furled sails,</l>
<l>and even the benches in the curved hull smoked.</l>
<l>When the holy mother of the gods, recalling</l>
<l>how those same pines were felled on Ida's crest,</l>
<l>filled the wind with a sound of cymbals clashed</l>
<l>and trill of boxwood flutes. Borne through light air</l>
<l>by her famed lion yoke, she came and said,</l>
<l>“In vain you cast the fire with impious hand,</l>
<l>Turnus, for I will save this burning fleet.</l>
<l>I will not let the greedy flame consume</l>
<l>trees that were part and members of my grove.”</l>

    
<l>It thundered while she spoke, and heavy clouds,</l>
<l>following the thunder, brought a storm</l>
<l>of bounding hail. The Astraean brothers filled</l>
<l>both air and swollen waters with their rage</l>
<l>and rushed to battle. With the aid of one</l>
<l>of them the kindly mother broke the ropes</l>
<l>which held the Phrygian ships, and, drawing all</l>
<l>prow foremost, plunged them underneath the wave.</l>
<l>Softening quickly in the waters quiet depth,</l>
<l>their wood was changed to flesh, the curving prows</l>
<l>were metamorphosed into human heads,</l>
<l>blades of the oars made feet, the looms were changed</l>
<l>to swimming legs, the sides turned human flanks,</l>
<l>each keel below the middle of a ship</l>
<l>transformed became a spine, the cordage changed</l>
<l>to soft hair, and the sail yards changed to arms.</l>
<l>The azure color of the ships remained.</l>

    
<l>As sea-nymphs in the water they began</l>
<l>to agitate with virgin sports the waves,</l>
<l>which they had always dreaded. Natives of</l>
<l>the rugged mountains they are now so changed,</l>
<l>they swim and dwell in the soft flowing sea,</l>
<l>with every influence of birth forgot.</l>
<l>Never forgetful of the myriad risks</l>
<l>they have endured among the boisterous waves,</l>
<l>they often give a helping hand to ships</l>
<l>tossed in the power of storms—unless, of course,</l>
<l>the ship might carry men of Grecian race.</l>

    
<l>Never forgetful of the Phrygians and</l>
<l>catastrophe, their hatred was so great</l>
<l>of all Pelasgians, that they looked with joy</l>
<l>upon the fragments of Ulysses' ship;</l>
<l>and were delighted when they saw the ship</l>
<l>of King Alcinous growing hard upon</l>
<l>the breakers, as its wood was turned to stone.</l>

    
<l>Many were hopeful that a fleet which had</l>
<l>received life strangely in the forms of nymphs</l>
<l>would cause the chieftain of the Rutuli</l>
<l>to feel such awe that he would end their strife.</l>
<l>But he continued fighting, and each side</l>
<l>had its own gods, and each had courage too,</l>
<l>which often can be as potent as the gods.</l>

    
<l>Now they forgot the kingdom as a dower,</l>
<l>forgot the scepter of a father-in-law,</l>
<l>and even forgot the pure Lavinia:</l>
<l>their one thought was to conquer, and they waged</l>
<l>war to prevent the shame of a defeat.</l>

    
<l>But Venus finally beheld the arms</l>
<l>of her victorious son; for Turnus fell,</l>
<l>and Ardea fell, a town which, while he lived,</l>
<l>was counted strong. The Trojan swords</l>
<l>destroyed it.—All its houses burned and sank</l>
<l>down in the heated embers: and a bird</l>
<l>not known before that time, flew upward from</l>
<l>a wrecked heap, beating the dead ashes with</l>
<l>its flapping wings. The voice, the lean pale look,</l>
<l>the sorrows of a captured city, even</l>
<l>the name of the ruined city, all these things</l>
<l>remain in that bird—Ardea's fallen walls</l>
<l>are beaten in lamentation by his wings.</l>


Aeneas Indiges.

<l>The merit of Aeneas now had moved</l>
<l>the gods. Even Juno stayed her lasting hate,</l>
<l>when, with the state of young Iulus safe,</l>
<l>the hero son of Cytherea was</l>
<l>prepared for heaven. In a council of the gods</l>
<l>Venus arose, embraced her father's neck,</l>
<l>and said: “ My father, ever kind to me,</l>
<l>I do beseech your kind indulgence now;</l>
<l>grant, dearest, to Aeneas, my own son</l>
<l>and also your own grandson, grant to him</l>
<l>a godhead power, although of lowest class,</l>
<l>sufficient if but granted. It is enough</l>
<l>to have looked once upon the unlovely realm.</l>
<l>And once to have gone across the Stygian streams.”</l>

    
<l>The gods assented, and the queen of Jove</l>
<l>nodded consent with calm, approving face.</l>
<l>The father said, “You well deserve the gift,</l>
<l>both you who ask it, and the one for whom</l>
<l>you ask it: what you most desire is yours,</l>
<l>my daughter.” He decreed, and she rejoiced</l>
<l>and thanked her parent. Borne by harnessed doves</l>
<l>over and through the light air, she arrived</l>
<l>safe on Laurentine shores: Numicius there</l>
<l>winds through his tall reeds to the neighboring sea</l>
<l>the waters of his stream: and there she willed</l>
<l>Numicius should wash perfectly away</l>
<l>from her Aeneas every part that might</l>
<l>be subject unto death; and bear it far</l>
<l>with quiet current into Neptune's realm.</l>

    
<l>The horned Numicius satisfied the will</l>
<l>of Venus; and with flowing waters washed</l>
<l>from her Aeneas every mortal part,</l>
<l>and sprinkled him, so that the essential part</l>
<l>of immortality remained alone,</l>
<l>and she anointed him, thus purified,</l>
<l>with heavenly essence, and she touched his face</l>
<l>with sweetest nectar and ambrosia mixt,</l>
<l>thereby transforming him into a god.</l>
<l>The throng of the Quirini later named</l>
<l>the new god Indiges, and honored him.</l>


Pomona et Vertumnus. Anaxarete.
VERTUMNUS AND POMONA

<l>Under the scepter of Ascanius</l>
<l>the Latin state, transferred, was Alban too.</l>
<l>Silvius ruled after him. Latinus then,</l>
<l>wearing the crown, brought back an older name.</l>
<l>Illustrious Alba followed after him,</l>
<l>Epytus next in time, and Capys next,</l>
<l>then Capetus. And reigning after them</l>
<l>King Tiberinus followed. He was drowned</l>
<l>in waves of that Etrurian stream, to which</l>
<l>he gave his name. His sons were Remulus</l>
<l>and fierce Acrota—each in turn was king.</l>
<l>The elder, Remulus, would imitate</l>
<l>the lightning, and he perished by a flash</l>
<l>of lightning. Then Acrota, not so rash,</l>
<l>succeeded to his brother, and he left</l>
<l>his scepter to the valiant Aventinus,</l>
<l>hill-buried on the very mountain which</l>
<l>he ruled upon and which received his name.</l>
<l>And Proca ruled then—on the Palatine.</l>

    
<l>Under this king, Pomona lived, and none</l>
<l>of all the Latin hamadryads could</l>
<l>attend her garden with more skill, and none</l>
<l>was more attentive to the fruitful trees,</l>
<l>because of them her name was given to her.</l>

    
<l>She cared not for the forests or the streams,</l>
<l>but loved the country and the boughs that bear</l>
<l>delicious fruit. Her right hand never felt</l>
<l>a javelin's weight, always she loved to hold</l>
<l>a sharp curved pruning-knife with which she would</l>
<l>at one time crop too largely growing shoots,</l>
<l>or at another time reduce the branch</l>
<l>that straggled; at another time she would</l>
<l>engraft a sucker in divided bark,</l>
<l>and so find nourishment for some young, strange</l>
<l>nursling. She never suffered them to thirst,</l>
<l>for she would water every winding thread</l>
<l>of twisting roots with freshly flowing streams.</l>

    
<l>All this was her delight, her chief pursuit;</l>
<l>she never felt the least desire of love;</l>
<l>but fearful of some rustic's violence,</l>
<l>she had her orchard closed within a wall;</l>
<l>and both forbade and fled the approach of males.</l>

    
<l>What did not satyrs do to gain her love,</l>
<l>a youthful crew expert at every dance?</l>
<l>And also Pans their brows wreathed with the pine,</l>
<l>Silenus too, more youthful than his years,</l>
<l>and that god who is ever scaring thieves</l>
<l>with pruning-hook or limb—what did they not</l>
<l>to gain her love? And though Vertumnus did</l>
<l>exceed them in his love, yet he was not</l>
<l>more fortunate than they.</l>

    
<l>How often disguised</l>
<l>as a rough reaper he brought her barley ears—</l>
<l>truly he seemed a reaper to the life!</l>
<l>Often he came, his temples wreathed with hay,</l>
<l>as if he had been tossing new mown grass.</l>
<l>He often held a whip in his tough hand,</l>
<l>you could have sworn he had a moment before</l>
<l>unyoked his wearied oxen. When he had</l>
<l>a pruning-knife, he seemed to rear fine fruit</l>
<l>in orchard trees or in the well kept vines.</l>
<l>When he came with a ladder, you would think</l>
<l>he must be gathering fruit. Sometimes he was</l>
<l>a soldier with a sword—a fisherman,</l>
<l>the rod held in his hand.—In fact by means</l>
<l>of many shapes he often had obtained</l>
<l>access to her and joyed in seeing her beauty.</l>

    
<l>At length he had his brows bound with a cap</l>
<l>of color, and then leaning on a stick,</l>
<l>with white hair round his temples, he assumed</l>
<l>the shape of an old woman. Entering so</l>
<l>the cultivated garden, he admired</l>
<l>the fruit and said, “But you are so much lovelier!”</l>
<l>And, while he praised her, gave some kisses too,</l>
<l>such as no real beldame ever gave.</l>
<l>The bent old creature then sat on the grass.</l>
<l>Gazing at branches weighed down with their fruit</l>
<l>of autumn. Opposite to them there was</l>
<l>an elm-tree beautiful with shining grapes;</l>
<l>and, after he had praised it with the vine</l>
<l>embracing it, he said,</l>

    
<l>“But only think,</l>
<l>if this trunk stood unwedded to this vine,</l>
<l>it would have nothing to attract our hearts</l>
<l>beyond its leaves, and this delightful vine,</l>
<l>united to the elm tree finds its rest;</l>
<l>but, if not so joined to it, would fall down,</l>
<l>prostrate upon the ground. And yet you find</l>
<l>no warning in the example of this tree.</l>
<l>You have avoided marriage, with no wish</l>
<l>to be united—I must wish that you</l>
<l>would change and soon desire it. Helen would</l>
<l>not have so many suitors for her hand, nor she</l>
<l>who caused the battles of the Lapithae,</l>
<l>nor would the wife of timid, and not bold,</l>
<l>Ulysses. Even now, while you avoid</l>
<l>those who are courting you, and while you turn</l>
<l>in your disgust, a thousand suitors want</l>
<l>to marry you—the demigods and gods,</l>
<l>and deities of Alba's mountain-tops.</l>

    
<l>“But you, if you are wise, and wish to make</l>
<l>a good match, listen patiently to me, </l>
<l>an old, old woman (I love you much more</l>
<l>than all of them, more than you dream or think).</l>
<l>Despise all common persons, and choose now</l>
<l>Vertumnus as the partner of your couch,</l>
<l>and you may take me as a surety for him.</l>
<l>He is not better known even to himself,</l>
<l>than he is known to me. And he is not</l>
<l>now wandering everywhere, from here to there</l>
<l>throughout the world. He always will frequent</l>
<l>the places near here; and he does not, like</l>
<l>so many of your wooers, fall in love</l>
<l>with her he happens to have seen the last.</l>
<l>You are his first and last love, and to you</l>
<l>alone will he devote his life. Besides</l>
<l>all—he is young and has a natural gift</l>
<l>of grace, so that he can most readily</l>
<l>transform himself to any wanted shape,</l>
<l>and will become whatever you may wish—</l>
<l>even though you ask him things unseen before.</l>

    
<l>“And only think, have you not the same tastes?</l>
<l>Will he not be the first to welcome fruits</l>
<l>which are your great delight? And does he not</l>
<l>hold your gifts safely in his glad right hand?</l>
<l>But now he does not long for any fruit</l>
<l>plucked from the tree, and has no thought of herbs</l>
<l>with pleasant juices that the garden gives;</l>
<l>he cannot think of anything but you.</l>
<l>Have pity on his passion, and believe</l>
<l>that he who woos you is here and he pleads</l>
<l>with my lips.</l>

    
<l>“You should not forget to fear</l>
<l>avenging deities, and the Idalian,</l>
<l>who hate all cruel hearts, and also dread</l>
<l>the fierce revenge of her of Rhamnus-Land.</l>
<l>And that you may stand more in awe of them,</l>
<l>(old age has given me opportunities</l>
<l>of knowing many things) I will relate</l>
<l>some happenings known in Cyprus, by which you</l>
<l>may be persuaded and relent with ease.</l>


ANAXARETE TRANSFORMED

<l>“Iphis, born of a humble family,</l>
<l>had seen the famed Anaxarete, who</l>
<l>was of the race of ancient Teucer.—He</l>
<l>had seen her and felt fire inflame his bones.</l>
<l>Struggling a long time, he could not subdue</l>
<l>his passion by his reason, so he came</l>
<l>a suppliant to her doors. And having now</l>
<l>confessed his ardent passion to her nurse,</l>
<l>besought her by the hopes reposed in her</l>
<l>by the loved girl, not to give him a cold heart</l>
<l>and at another time, with fair words given</l>
<l>to each of many servants he besought</l>
<l>their kindest interest with an anxious voice.</l>
<l>He often gave them coaxing words engraved</l>
<l>on tablets of soft wax; and sometimes he</l>
<l>would fasten garlands, wet with dew of tears,</l>
<l>upon the door-posts; and he often laid</l>
<l>his tender side nightlong on the hard threshold,</l>
<l>sadly reproaching the obdurate bolt.</l>

    
<l>“Deafer than the deep sea that rises high</l>
<l>when the rainy Constellation of the Kids</l>
<l>is setting; harder than the iron which</l>
<l>the fire of Noricum refines; more hard</l>
<l>than rock which in its native state is fixed</l>
<l>firm rooted; she despised and laughed at him,</l>
<l>and, adding to her cruel deeds and pride,</l>
<l>she boasted and deprived him of all hope.</l>

    
<l>“Iphis, unable to endure such pain prolonged,</l>
<l>spoke these, his final words, before her door:</l>
<l>‘Anaxarete, you have conquered me,</l>
<l>and you shall have no more annoyances</l>
<l>to bear from me. Be joyful and prepare</l>
<l>your triumph, and invoke god Paean, crown</l>
<l>yourself with shining laurel. You are now</l>
<l>my conqueror, and I resigned will die.</l>
<l>Woman of iron, rejoice in victory!</l>

    
<l>“At least, you will commend me for one thing,</l>
<l>one point in which I must please even you,</l>
<l>and cause you to confess my right of praise.</l>
<l>Remember that my star crossed love for you</l>
<l>died only with the last breath of my life.</l>
<l>And now in one short moment I shall be</l>
<l>deprived a twofold light; and no report</l>
<l>will come to you, no messenger of death.</l>
<l>But doubt not, I will come to you so that</l>
<l>I can be seen in person, and you may</l>
<l>then satiate your cruel eyesight with</l>
<l>my lifeless body. If, you gods above!</l>
<l>You have some knowledge of our mortal ways</l>
<l>remember me, for now my tongue can pray</l>
<l>no longer. Let me be renowned in times</l>
<l>far distant and give all those hours to Fame</l>
<l>which you have taken from my life on earth.’</l>

    
<l>“Then to the doorpost which he often had</l>
<l>adorned with floral wreaths he lifted up</l>
<l>his swimming eyes and both his pallid arms,</l>
<l>and, when he had fastened over the capital</l>
<l>a rope that held a dangling noose, he said,—</l>
<l>“Are these the garlands that delight your heart?</l>
<l>You cruel and unnatural woman?”—Then,</l>
<l>thrust in his head, turning even then towards her,</l>
<l>and hung a hapless weight with broken neck.</l>

    
<l>“The door, struck by the motion of his feet</l>
<l>as they were quivering, seemed to utter sounds</l>
<l>of groaning, and, when it flew open, showed</l>
<l>the sad sight. All the servants cried aloud,</l>
<l>and after they had tried in vain to save him,</l>
<l>carried him from there to his mother's house,</l>
<l>(to her because his father was then dead).</l>

    
<l>“She held him to her bosom and embraced</l>
<l>the cold limbs of her dead child. After she</l>
<l>had uttered words so natural to the grief</l>
<l>of wretched mothers—after she had done</l>
<l>what wretched mothers do at such sad times,</l>
<l>she led a tearful funeral through the streets,</l>
<l>the pale corpse following high upon the bier,</l>
<l>on to a pyre laid in the central square.</l>
<l>By chance, Anaxarete's house was near</l>
<l>the way through which the mournful funeral</l>
<l>was going with the corpse, and the sad sound</l>
<l>of wailing reached the ears of that proud girl—</l>
<l>hardhearted, and already goaded on</l>
<l>by an avenging god. Moved by the sound,</l>
<l>she said; “Let me observe their sniveling rites.”</l>
<l>And she ascended to an upper room,</l>
<l>provided with wide windows. Scarcely had</l>
<l>she looked at Iphis, laid out on the bier,</l>
<l>when her eyes stiffened, and she turned all white,</l>
<l>as warm blood left her body. She tried then</l>
<l>to turn back from the window, but she stood</l>
<l>transfixed there. She then tried to turn her face</l>
<l>away from that sad sight, but could not move;</l>
<l>and by degrees the stone, which always had</l>
<l>existed, petrified in her cold breast,</l>
<l>and took possession of her heart and limbs.</l>

    
<l>“This is not fiction, and that you may know,</l>
<l>Salamis keeps that statue safe today,</l>
<l>formed of the virgin and has also built</l>
<l>a temple called, ‘Venus the watchful Goddess.’</l>
<l>Warned by her fate, O sweet nymph, lay aside</l>
<l>prolonged disdain, and cheerfully unite</l>
<l>yourself to one who loves you. Then may frost</l>
<l>of springtime never nip your fruit in bud,</l>
<l>nor rude winds strike the blossom.”</l>

    
<l>When the god,</l>
<l>fitted for every shape, had said these words in vain,</l>
<l>he laid the old woman's form aside and was</l>
<l>again a youth. On her he seemed to blaze,</l>
<l>as when the full light of the brilliant Sun,</l>
<l>after it has dispelled opposing clouds,</l>
<l>has shone forth with not one to intercept.</l>

    
<l>He purposed violence, but there was then</l>
<l>no need of force. The lovely nymph was charmed,</l>
<l>was captivated by the god's bright form</l>
<l>and felt a passion answering to his love.</l>


Romulus et Hersilia.
TALES ABOUT ROMULUS

<l>At Proca's death unjust Amulius</l>
<l>seized with his troops the whole Ausonian wealth.</l>
<l>And yet old Numitor, obtaining aid</l>
<l>from his two grandsons, won the land again</l>
<l>which he had lost; and on the festival</l>
<l>of Pales were the city walls begun.</l>
<l>King Tatius with his Sabines went to war;</l>
<l>Tarpeia, who betrayed the citadel,</l>
<l>died justly underneath the weight of arms.</l>

    
<l>Then troops from Cures crept, like silent wolves,</l>
<l>without a word toward men subdued by sleep</l>
<l>and tried the gates that Ilia's son had barred.</l>
<l>Then Saturn's daughter opened wide a gate,</l>
<l>turning the silent hinge. Venus alone</l>
<l>perceived the bars of that gate falling down.</l>
<l>She surely would have closed it, were it not</l>
<l>impossible for any deity</l>
<l>to countervail the acts of other gods.</l>

    
<l>The Naiads of Ausonia occupied</l>
<l>a spring that welled up close to Janus' fane.</l>
<l>To them she prayed for aid. The fountain-nymphs</l>
<l>could not resist the prayer of Venus, when</l>
<l>she made her worthy plea and they released</l>
<l>all waters under ground. Till then the path</l>
<l>by Janus' fane was open, never yet had floods</l>
<l>risen to impede the way. But now they laid</l>
<l>hot sulphur of a faint blue light beneath</l>
<l>the streaming fountain and with care applied</l>
<l>fire to the hallowed ways with smoking pitch.</l>

    
<l>By these and many other violent means</l>
<l>hot vapors penetrated to the source</l>
<l>of the good fountain.—Only think of it!</l>
<l>Those waters which had rivalled the cold Alps,</l>
<l>now rivalled with their heat the flames themselves!</l>
<l>And, while each gate post steamed with boiling spray,</l>
<l>the gate, which had been opened (but in vain)</l>
<l>to hardy Sabines just outside, was made</l>
<l>impassable by the heated fountain's flood,</l>
<l>till Roman soldiers had regained their arms.</l>

    
<l>After brave Romulus had led them forth</l>
<l>and covered Roman ground with Sabines dead</l>
<l>and its own people; and the accursed sword</l>
<l>shed blood of father-in-law and son-in-law,</l>
<l>with peace they chose at last to end the war,</l>
<l>rather than fight on to the bitter end:</l>
<l>Tatius and Romulus divide the throne.</l>

    
<l>Tatius had fallen, and you, O Romulus,</l>
<l>were giving laws to peoples now made one,</l>
<l>when Mars put off his helmet and addressed</l>
<l>the father of gods and men in words like these:</l>
<l>“The time has come, for now the Roman state</l>
<l>has been established on a strong foundation</l>
<l>and no more must rely on one man's strength</l>
<l>the time has come for you to give the prize,</l>
<l>promised to me and your deserving grandson,</l>
<l>to raise him from the earth and grant him here</l>
<l>a fitting place in heaven. One day you said</l>
<l>to me before a council of the gods,</l>
<l>(for I recall now with a grateful mind</l>
<l>how I took note of your most gracious speech)</l>
<l>‘Him you shall lift up to the blue of heaven.’</l>
<l>Now let all know the meaning of your words!”</l>

    
<l>The god all-powerful nodded his assent,</l>
<l>and he obscured the air with heavy clouds</l>
<l>and on a trembling world he sent below</l>
<l>harsh thunder and bright lightning. Mars at once</l>
<l>perceived it was a signal plainly given</l>
<l>for promised change—so, leaning on a spear,</l>
<l>he mounted boldly into his chariot,</l>
<l>and over bloodstained yoke and eager steeds</l>
<l>he swung and cracked the loud-resounding lash.</l>

    
<l>Descending through steep air, he halted on</l>
<l>the wooded summit of the Palatine</l>
<l>and there, while Ilia's son was giving laws—</l>
<l>needing no pomp and circumstance of kings,</l>
<l>Mars caught him up. His mortal flesh dissolved</l>
<l>into thin air, as when a ball of lead</l>
<l>shot up from a broad sling melts all away</l>
<l>and soon is lost in heaven. A nobler shape</l>
<l>was given him, one more fitted to adorn</l>
<l>rich couches in high heaven, the shape divine</l>
<l>of Quirinus clad in the trabea.</l>

    
<l>His queen, Hersilia, wept continually,</l>
<l>regarding him as lost, till regal Juno</l>
<l>commanded Iris to glide down along</l>
<l>her curving bow and bring to her these words:</l>

    
<l>“O matron, glory of the Latin race</l>
<l>and of the Sabines, worthy to have been</l>
<l>the consort chosen by so great a man</l>
<l>and now to be his partner as the god</l>
<l>Quirinus, weep no more. If you desire</l>
<l>to see your husband, let me guide you up</l>
<l>to a grove that crowns the hill of Quirinus,</l>
<l>shading a temple of the Roman king.”</l>

    
<l>Iris obeyed her will, and, gliding down</l>
<l>to earth along her tinted bow, conveyed</l>
<l>the message to Hersilia; who replied,</l>
<l>with modest look and hardly lifted eye,</l>
<l>“Goddess (although it is not in my power</l>
<l>to say your name, I am quite certain you</l>
<l>must be a goddess), lead me, O lead me</l>
<l>until you show to me the hallowed form</l>
<l>of my beloved husband. If the Fates</l>
<l>will but permit me once again to see</l>
<l>his features, I will say I have won heaven.”</l>

    
<l>At once Hersilia and the virgin child</l>
<l>of Thaumas, went together up the hill</l>
<l>of Romulus. Descending through thin air</l>
<l>there came a star, and then Hersilia</l>
<l>her tresses glowing fiery in the light,</l>
<l>rose with that star, as it returned through air.</l>
<l>And her the founder of the Roman state</l>
<l>received with dear, familiar hands. He changed</l>
<l>her old time form and with the form her name.</l>
<l>He called her Hora and let her become</l>
<l>a goddess, now the mate of Quirinus.</l>
