<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 15

Myscelus. Croton.
MYSCELUS BUILDS THE CITY OF CROTONA

<l>While this was happening, they began to seek</l>
<l>for one who could endure the weight of such</l>
<l>a task and could succeed a king so great;</l>
<l>and Fame, the harbinger of truth, destined</l>
<l>illustrious Numa for the sovereign power.</l>
<l>It did not satisfy his heart to know</l>
<l>only the Sabine ceremonials,</l>
<l>and he conceived in his expansive mind</l>
<l>much greater views, examining the depth </l>
<l>and cause of things. His country and his cares</l>
<l>forgotten, this desire led him to visit</l>
<l>the city that once welcomed Hercules.</l>
<l>Numa desired to know what founder built</l>
<l>a Grecian city on Italian shores.</l>
<l>One of the old inhabitants, who was well</l>
<l>acquainted with past history, replied:</l>

    
<l>“Rich in Iberian herds, the son of Jove</l>
<l>turned from the ocean and with favoring wind</l>
<l>'Tis said he landed on Lacinian shores.</l>
<l>And, while the herd strayed in the tender grass,</l>
<l>he visited the house, the friendly home,</l>
<l>of far-famed Croton. There he rested from</l>
<l>his arduous labors. At the time of his</l>
<l>departure, he said, ‘Here in future days</l>
<l>shall be a city of your numerous race.’</l>
<l>The passing years have proved the promise true,</l>
<l>for Myscelus, choosing that site, marked out</l>
<l>a city's walls. Argive Alemon's son,</l>
<l>of all men in his generation, he</l>
<l>was most acceptable to the heavenly gods.</l>
<l>Bending over him once at dawn, while he</l>
<l>was overwhelmed with drowsiness of sleep,</l>
<l>the huge club-bearer Hercules addressed</l>
<l>him thus: ‘Come now, desert your native shores.</l>
<l>Go quickly to the pebbly flowing stream</l>
<l>of distant Aesar.’ And he threatened ill</l>
<l>in fearful words, unless he should obey.</l>

    
<l>“Sleep and the god departed instantly.</l>
<l>Alemon's son, arising from his couch,</l>
<l>pondered his recent vision thoughtfully,</l>
<l>with his conclusions at cross purposes.—</l>
<l>the god commanded him to quit that land,</l>
<l>the laws forbade departure, threatening death</l>
<l>to all who sought to leave their native land.</l>

    
<l>“The brilliant Sun had hidden in the sea</l>
<l>his shining head, and darkest Night had then</l>
<l>put forth her starry face; and at that time</l>
<l>it seemed as if the same god Hercules</l>
<l>was present and repeating his commands,</l>
<l>threatening still more and graver penalties,</l>
<l>if he should fail to obey. Now sore afraid</l>
<l>he set about to move his household gods</l>
<l>to a new settlement, but rumors then</l>
<l>followed him through the city, and he was</l>
<l>accused of holding statutes in contempt.</l>

    
<l>“The accusation hardly had been made</l>
<l>when his offense was evidently proved,</l>
<l>even without a witness. Then he raised</l>
<l>his face and hands up to the gods above</l>
<l>and suppliant in neglected garb, exclaimed,</l>
<l>‘Oh mighty Hercules, for whom alone </l>
<l>the twice six labors gave the privilege</l>
<l>of heavenly residence, give me your aid,</l>
<l>for you were the true cause of my offence.’</l>

    
<l>“It was an ancient custom of that land</l>
<l>to vote with chosen pebbles, white and black.</l>
<l>The white absolved, the black condemned the man.</l>
<l>And so that day the fateful votes were given—:</l>
<l>all cast into the cruel urn were black!</l>
<l>Soon as that urn inverted poured forth all</l>
<l>the pebbles to be counted, every one</l>
<l>was changed completely from its black to white,</l>
<l>and so the vote adjudged him innocent.</l>
<l>By that most fortunate aid of Hercules</l>
<l>he was exempted from the country's law.</l>

    
<l>“Myscelus, breathing thanks to Hercules,</l>
<l>with favoring wind sailed on the Ionian sea,</l>
<l>past Sallentine Neretum, Sybaris,</l>
<l>Spartan Tarentum, and the Sirine Bay,</l>
<l>Crimisa, and on beyond the Iapygian fields.</l>
<l>Then, skirting shores which face these lands, he found</l>
<l>the place foretold the river Aesar's mouth,</l>
<l>and found not far away a burial mound</l>
<l>which covered with its soil the hallowed bones</l>
<l>of Croton.—There, upon the appointed land,</l>
<l>he built up walls—and he conferred the name</l>
<l>of Croton, who was there entombed, on his</l>
<l>new city, which has ever since been called</l>
<l>Crotona.” By tradition it is known</l>
<l>such strange deeds caused that city to be built,</l>
<l>by men of Greece upon the Italian coast.</l>


Pythagoras.
PYTHAGORAS TEACHES HIS PHILOSOPHY

<l>Here lived a man, by birth a Samian.</l>
<l>He had fled from Samos and the ruling class,</l>
<l>a voluntary exile, for his hate</l>
<l>against all tyranny. He had the gift</l>
<l>of holding mental converse with the gods,</l>
<l>who live far distant in the highth of heaven;</l>
<l>and all that Nature has denied to man</l>
<l>and human vision, he reviewed with eyes</l>
<l>of his enlightened soul. And, when he had</l>
<l>examined all things in his careful mind</l>
<l>with watchful study, he released his thoughts</l>
<l>to knowledge of the public.</l>

    
<l>He would speak</l>
<l>to crowds of people, silent and amazed,</l>
<l>while he revealed to them the origin</l>
<l>of this vast universe, the cause of things,</l>
<l>what is nature, what a god, whence came the snow,</l>
<l>the cause of lightning—was it Jupiter</l>
<l>or did the winds, that thundered when the cloud</l>
<l>was rent asunder, cause the lightning flash?</l>
<l>What shook the earth, what laws controlled the stars</l>
<l>as they were moved—and every hidden thing</l>
<l>he was the first man to forbid the use</l>
<l>of any animal's flesh as human food,</l>
<l>he was the first to speak with learned lips,</l>
<l>though not believed in this, exhorting them.—</l>

    
<l>“No, mortals,” he would say, “Do not permit</l>
<l>pollution of your bodies with such food,</l>
<l>for there are grain and good fruits which bear down</l>
<l>the branches by their weight, and ripened grapes</l>
<l>upon the vines, and herbs—those sweet by nature</l>
<l>and those which will grow tender and mellow with</l>
<l>a fire, and flowing milk is not denied,</l>
<l>nor honey, redolent of blossoming thyme.</l>

    
<l>“The lavish Earth yields rich and healthful food</l>
<l>affording dainties without slaughter, death,</l>
<l>and bloodshed. Dull beasts delight to satisfy</l>
<l>their hunger with torn flesh; and yet not all:</l>
<l>horses and sheep and cattle live on grass.</l>
<l>But all the savage animals—the fierce</l>
<l>Armenian tigers and ferocious lions,</l>
<l>and bears, together with the roving wolves—</l>
<l>delight in viands reeking with warm blood.</l>

    
<l>“Oh, ponder a moment such a monstrous crime—</l>
<l>vitals in vitals gorged, one greedy body</l>
<l>fattening with plunder of another's flesh,</l>
<l>a living being fed on another's life!</l>
<l>In that abundance, which our Earth, the best</l>
<l>of mothers, will afford have you no joy,</l>
<l>unless your savage teeth can gnaw</l>
<l>the piteous flesh of some flayed animal</l>
<l>to reenact the Cyclopean crime?</l>
<l>And can you not appease the hungry void—</l>
<l>the perverted craving of a stomach's greed,</l>
<l>unless you first destroy another life?</l>

    
<l>“That age of old time which is given the name</l>
<l>of ‘Golden,’ was so blest in fruit of trees,</l>
<l>and in the good herbs which the earth produced </l>
<l>that it never would pollute the mouth with blood.</l>
<l>The birds then safely moved their wings in air,</l>
<l>the timid hares would wander in the fields</l>
<l>with no fear, and their own credulity</l>
<l>had not suspended fishes from the hook.</l>
<l>All life was safe from treacherous wiles,</l>
<l>fearing no injury, a peaceful world.</l>

    
<l>“After that time some one of ill advice</l>
<l>(it does not matter who it might have been)</l>
<l>envied the ways of lions and gulped into</l>
<l>his greedy paunch stuff from a carcass vile.</l>
<l>He opened the foul paths of wickedness.</l>
<l>It may be that in killing beasts of prey</l>
<l>our steel was for the first time warmed with blood.</l>
<l>And that could be defended, for I hold</l>
<l>that predatory creatures which attempt</l>
<l>destruction of mankind, are put to death</l>
<l>without evasion of the sacred laws:</l>
<l>but, though with justice they are put to death,</l>
<l>that cannot be a cause for eating them.</l>

    
<l>“This wickedness went further; and the sow</l>
<l>was thought to have deserved death as the first</l>
<l>of victims, for with her long turned-up snout</l>
<l>she spoiled the good hope of a harvest year.</l>
<l>The ravenous goat, that gnawed a sprouting vine,</l>
<l>was led for slaughter to the altar fires</l>
<l>of angry Bacchus. It was their own fault</l>
<l>that surely caused the ruin of those two.</l>

    
<l>“But why have sheep deserved sad destiny,</l>
<l>harmless and useful for the good of man</l>
<l>with nectar in full udders? Their soft wool</l>
<l>affords the warmest coverings for our use,</l>
<l>their life and not their death would help us more.</l>
<l>Why have the oxen of the field deserved</l>
<l>a sad end—innocent, without deceit,</l>
<l>and harmless, without guile, born to endure</l>
<l>hard labor? Without gratitude is he,</l>
<l>unworthy of the gift of harvest fields,</l>
<l>who, after he relieved his worker from</l>
<l>weight of the curving plow could butcher him,</l>
<l>could sever with an axe that toil worn neck,</l>
<l>by which so often with hard work the ground</l>
<l>had been turned up, so many harvests reared.</l>
<l>For some, even crimes like these are not enough,</l>
<l>they have imputed to the gods themselves</l>
<l>abomination—they believe a god</l>
<l>in heaven above, rejoices at the death</l>
<l>of a laborious ox.</l>

    
<l>“A victim free</l>
<l>of blemish and most beautiful in form</l>
<l>(perfection brings destruction) is adorned</l>
<l>with garlands and with gilded horns before</l>
<l>the altar. In his ignorance he hears</l>
<l>one praying, and he sees the very grain</l>
<l>he labored to produce, fixed on his head</l>
<l>between the horns, and felled, he stains with blood</l>
<l>the knife which just before he may have seen</l>
<l>reflected in clear water. Instantly</l>
<l>they snatch out entrails from his throbbing form,</l>
<l>and seek in them intentions of the gods.</l>
<l>Then, in your lust for a forbidden food</l>
<l>you will presume to batten on his flesh,</l>
<l>O race of mortals! Do not eat such food!</l>
<l>Give your attention to my serious words;</l>
<l>and, when you next present the slaughtered flesh</l>
<l>of oxen to your palates, know and feel</l>
<l>that you gnaw your fellow tillers of the soil.</l>

    
<l>“And, since a god impels me to speak out,</l>
<l>I will obey the god who urges me,</l>
<l>and will disclose to you the heavens above,</l>
<l>and I will even reveal the oracles</l>
<l>of the Divine Will. I will sing to you</l>
<l>of things most wonderful, which never were</l>
<l>investigated by the intellects</l>
<l>of ancient times and things which have been long</l>
<l>concealed from man. In fancy I delight</l>
<l>to float among the stars or take my stand</l>
<l>on mighty Atlas' shoulders, and to look</l>
<l>afar down on men wandering here and there—</l>
<l>afraid in life yet dreading unknown death,</l>
<l>and in these words exhort them and reveal</l>
<l>the sequence of events ordained by fate!</l>


    
<l>“O sad humanity! Why do you fear</l>
<l>alarms of icy death, afraid of Styx,</l>
<l>fearful of moving shadows and empty names—</l>
<l>of subjects harped on by the poets' tales,</l>
<l>the fabled perils of a fancied life?</l>
<l>Whether the funeral pile consumes your flesh</l>
<l>with hot flames, or old age dissolves it with</l>
<l>a gradual wasting power, be well assured</l>
<l>the body cannot meet with further ill.</l>
<l>And souls are all exempt from power of death.</l>
<l>When they have left their first corporeal home,</l>
<l>they always find and live in newer homes.</l>

    
<l>“I can declare, for I remember well,</l>
<l>that in the days of the great Trojan War,</l>
<l>I was Euphorbus, son of Panthous.</l>
<l>In my opposing breast was planted then</l>
<l>the heavy spear-point of the younger son</l>
<l>of Atreus. Not long past I recognised</l>
<l>the shield, once burden of my left arm, where</l>
<l>it hung in Juno's temple at ancient Argos,</l>
<l>the realm of Abas. Everything must change:</l>
<l>but nothing perishes. The moving soul</l>
<l>may wander, coming from that spot to this,</l>
<l>from this to that—in changed possession live</l>
<l>in any limbs whatever. It may pass</l>
<l>from beasts to human bodies, and again</l>
<l>to those of beasts. The soul will never die,</l>
<l>in the long lapse of time. As pliant wax</l>
<l>is moulded to new forms and does not stay</l>
<l>as it has been nor keep the self same form</l>
<l>yet is the selfsame wax, be well assured</l>
<l>the soul is always the same spirit, though</l>
<l>it passes into different forms. Therefore,</l>
<l>that natural love may not be vanquished by</l>
<l>unnatural craving of the appetite,</l>
<l>I warn you, stop expelling kindred souls</l>
<l>by deeds abhorrent as cold murder.—Let</l>
<l>not blood be nourished with its kindred blood!</l>

    
<l>“Since I am launched into the open sea</l>
<l>and I have given my full sails to the wind,</l>
<l>nothing in all the world remains unchanged.</l>
<l>All things are in a state of flux, all shapes</l>
<l>receive a changing nature. Time itself</l>
<l>glides on with constant motion, ever as</l>
<l>a flowing river. Neither river nor</l>
<l>the fleeting hour can stop its constant course.</l>
<l>But, as each wave drives on a wave, as each</l>
<l>is pressed by that which follows, and must press</l>
<l>on that before it, so the moments fly,</l>
<l>and others follow, so they are renewed.</l>
<l>The moment which moved on before is past,</l>
<l>and that which was not, now exists in Time,</l>
<l>and every one comes, goes, and is replaced.</l>

    
<l>“You see how night glides by and then proceeds</l>
<l>on to the dawn, then brilliant light of day</l>
<l>succeeds the dark night. There is not the same</l>
<l>appearance in the heavens,: when all things</l>
<l>for weariness are resting in vast night,</l>
<l>as when bright Lucifer rides his white steed.</l>
<l>And only think of that most glorious change,</l>
<l>when loved Aurora, Pallas' daughter, comes</l>
<l>before the day and tints the world, almost</l>
<l>delivered to bright Phoebus. Even the disk</l>
<l>of that god, rising from beneath the earth,</l>
<l>is of a ruddy color in the dawn</l>
<l>and ruddy when concealed beneath the world.</l>
<l>When highest, it is a most brilliant white,</l>
<l>for there the ether is quite purified,</l>
<l>and far away avoids infection from</l>
<l>impurities of earth. Diana's form</l>
<l>at night remains not equal nor the same!</l>
<l>'Tis less today than it will be tomorrow,</l>
<l>if she is waxing; greater, if she wanes.</l>

    
<l>“Yes, do you not see how the year moves through</l>
<l>four seasons, imitating human life:</l>
<l>in early Spring it has a nursling's ways</l>
<l>resembling infancy, for at that time</l>
<l>the blade is shooting and devoid of strength.</l>
<l>Its flaccid substance swelling gives delight,</l>
<l>to every watching husbandman, alive</l>
<l>in expectation. Then all things are rich</l>
<l>in blossom, and the genial meadow smiles</l>
<l>with tints of blooming flowers; but not as yet</l>
<l>is there a sign of vigor in the leaves.</l>

    
<l>“The year now waxing stronger, after Spring</l>
<l>it passes into Summer, and its youth</l>
<l>becomes robust. Indeed of all the year</l>
<l>the Summer is most vigorous and most</l>
<l>abounds with glowing and life-giving warmth.</l>

    
<l>“Autumn then follows, and, the vim of life</l>
<l>removed, that ripe and mellow time succeeds</l>
<l>between youth and old age, and a few white hairs</l>
<l>are sprinkled here and there upon his brow.</l>

    
<l>“Then aged Winter with his tremulous step</l>
<l>follows, repulsive, strips of graceful locks</l>
<l>or white with those he has retained so long.</l>

    
<l>“Our bodies also, always change unceasingly:</l>
<l>we are not now what we were yesterday</l>
<l>or we shall be tomorrow. And there was</l>
<l>a time when we were only seeds of man,</l>
<l>mere hopes that lived within a mother's womb.</l>
<l>But Nature changed us with her skilfull touch,</l>
<l>determined that our bodies should not be</l>
<l>held in such narrow room, below the entrails</l>
<l>in our distended parent; and in time</l>
<l>she brought us forth into the vacant air.</l>

    
<l>“Brought into light, the helpless infant lies.</l>
<l>Then on all fours he lifts his body up,</l>
<l>feeling his way, like any young wild beast,</l>
<l>and then by slow degrees he stands upright,</l>
<l>weak-kneed and trembling, steadied by support</l>
<l>of some convenient prop. And soon more strong</l>
<l>and swift he passes through the hours of youth,</l>
<l>and, when the years of middle age are past,</l>
<l>slides down the steep path of declining age.</l>

    
<l>“This undermines him and destroys the strength</l>
<l>of former years: and Milon, now grown old,</l>
<l>weeps, when he sees his arms, which once were firm</l>
<l>with muscles big as those of Hercules,</l>
<l>hang flabby at his side: and Helen weeps,</l>
<l>when in the glass she sees her wrinkled face,</l>
<l>and wonders why two heroes fell in love</l>
<l>and carried her away.—O Time,</l>
<l>devourer of all things, and envious Age,</l>
<l>together you destroy all that exists</l>
<l>and, slowly gnawing, bring on lingering death.</l>

    
<l>“Yes, even things which we call elements,</l>
<l>do not endure. Now listen well to me,</l>
<l>and I will show the ways in which they change.</l>

    
<l>“The everlasting universe contains</l>
<l>four elemental parts. And two of these</l>
<l>are heavy—earth and water—and are borne</l>
<l>downwards by weight. The other two devoid</l>
<l>of weight, are air and—even lighter—fire:</l>
<l>and, if these two are not constrained, they seek</l>
<l>the higher regions. These four elements,</l>
<l>though far apart in space, are all derived</l>
<l>from one another. Earth dissolves</l>
<l>as flowing water! Water, thinned still more,</l>
<l>departs as wind and air; and the light air,</l>
<l>still losing weight, sparkles on high as fire.</l>
<l>But they return, along their former way:</l>
<l>the fire, assuming weight, is changed to air;</l>
<l>and then, more dense, that air is changed again</l>
<l>to water; and that water, still more dense,</l>
<l>compacts itself again as primal earth.</l>


    
<l>“Nothing retains the form that seems its own,</l>
<l>and Nature, the renewer of all things,</l>
<l>continually changes every form</l>
<l>into some other shape. Believe my word,</l>
<l>in all this universe of vast extent,</l>
<l>not one thing ever perished. All have changed</l>
<l>appearance. Men say a certain thing is born,</l>
<l>if it takes a different form from what it had;</l>
<l>and yet they say, that certain thing has died,</l>
<l>if it no longer keeps the self same shape.</l>
<l>Though distant things move near, and near things far,</l>
<l>always the sum of all things is unchanged.</l>

    
<l>“For my part, I cannot believe a thing</l>
<l>remains long under the same form unchanged.</l>
<l>Look at the change of times from gold to iron,:</l>
<l>look at the change in places. I have seen</l>
<l>what had been solid earth become salt waves,</l>
<l>and I have seen dry land made from the deep;</l>
<l>and, far away from ocean, sea-shells strewn,</l>
<l>and on the mountain-tops old anchors found.</l>
<l>Water has made that which was once a plain</l>
<l>into a valley, and the mountain has</l>
<l>been levelled by the floods down to a plain.</l>
<l>A former marshland is now parched dry sand,</l>
<l>and places which endured severest drought</l>
<l>are wet with standing pools. Here Nature has</l>
<l>opened fresh springs, but there has shut them up;</l>
<l>rivers aroused by ancient earthquakes have</l>
<l>rushed out or vanished, as they lost their depth.</l>

    
<l>“So, when the Lycus has been swallowed by</l>
<l>a chasm in the earth, it rushes forth</l>
<l>at a distance and is reborn a different stream.</l>
<l>The Erasinus now flows down into a cave,</l>
<l>now runs beneath the ground a darkened course,</l>
<l>then rises lordly in the Argolic fields.</l>
<l>They say the Mysus, wearied of his spring</l>
<l>and of his former banks, appears elsewhere</l>
<l>and takes another name, the Caicus.</l>

    
<l>“The Amenanus in Sicilian sands</l>
<l>now smoothly rolling, at another time</l>
<l>is quenched, because its fountain springs are dry.</l>
<l>The water of the Anigros formerly</l>
<l>was used for drinking, but it pours out now</l>
<l>foul water which you would decline to touch,</l>
<l>because (unless all credit is denied</l>
<l>to poets) long ago the Centaurs, those</l>
<l>strange mortals double-limbed, bathed in the stream</l>
<l>wounds which club-bearing Hercules had made</l>
<l>with his strong bow.—Yes, does not Hypanis</l>
<l>descending fresh from mountains of Sarmatia,</l>
<l>become embittered with the taste of salt?</l>

    
<l>“Antissa, Pharos, and Phoenician Tyre,</l>
<l>were once surrounded by the wavy sea:</l>
<l>they are not islands now. Long years ago</l>
<l>Leucas was mainland, if we can believe</l>
<l>what the old timers there will tell, but now</l>
<l>the waves sweep round it. Zancle was a part</l>
<l>of Italy, until the sea cut off</l>
<l>the neighboring land with strong waves in between.</l>
<l>Should you seek Helice and Buris, those</l>
<l>two cities of Achaea, you will find</l>
<l>them underneath the waves, where sailors point</l>
<l>to sloping roofs and streets in the clear deep.</l>

    
<l>“Near Pittheaan Troezen a steep, high hill,</l>
<l>quite bare of trees, was once a level plain,</l>
<l>but now is a hill, for (dreadful even to tell)</l>
<l>the raging power of winds, long pent in deep,</l>
<l>dark caverns, tried to find a proper vent,</l>
<l>long struggling to attain free sky.</l>
<l>Finding no opening from the prison-caves,</l>
<l>imperious to their force, they raised the earth,</l>
<l>exactly as pent air breathed from the mouth</l>
<l>inflates a bladder, or the bottle-hides</l>
<l>stripped off the two-horned goats. The swollen earth</l>
<l>remained on that spot and has ever since</l>
<l>appearance of a high hill hardened by</l>
<l>the flight of time.</l>

    
<l>“Of many strange events</l>
<l>that I have heard and known, I will add a few.</l>
<l>Why, does not water give and take strange forms?</l>
<l>Your wave, O horned Ammon, will turn cold</l>
<l>at mid-day, but is always mild and warm</l>
<l>at sun-rise and at sun-set. I have heard</l>
<l>that Athamanians kindle wood, if they</l>
<l>pour water on it, when the waning moon</l>
<l>has shrunk away into her smallest orb.</l>
<l>The people of Ciconia have a stream</l>
<l>which turns the drinker's entrails into stone,</l>
<l>which changes into marble all it raves.</l>
<l>The Achaean Crathis and the Sybaris,</l>
<l>which flow not far from here, will turn the hair</l>
<l>to something like clear amber or bright gold.</l>

    
<l>“What is more wonderful, there are some waters</l>
<l>which change not only bodies but the minds:</l>
<l>who has no knowledge of the Salmacis</l>
<l>and of its ill famed waves? Who has not</l>
<l>heard of the lakes of Aethiopia:</l>
<l>how those who drink of them go raving mad</l>
<l>or fall in a deep sleep, most wonderful</l>
<l>in heaviness. Whoever quenches thirst</l>
<l>from the Clitorian spring will hate all wine,</l>
<l>and soberly secure great pleasure from</l>
<l>pure water. Either that spring has a power</l>
<l>the opposite of wine-heat, or perhaps</l>
<l>as natives tell us, after the famed son</l>
<l>of Amythaon by his charms and herbs,</l>
<l>delivered from their base insanity</l>
<l>the stricken Proetides, he threw the rest</l>
<l>of his mind healing herbs into the spring,</l>
<l>where hatred of all wine has since remained.</l>
<l>Unlike in nature flows another stream</l>
<l>of the country, called Lyncestius: everyone</l>
<l>who drinks of it, even with most temperate care,</l>
<l>will reel, as if he had drunk unmixed wine.</l>
<l>In Arcadia is a place, called Pheneos</l>
<l>by men of old, which is mistrusted for</l>
<l>the twofold nature of its waters. Stand</l>
<l>in dread of them at night; if drunk at night,</l>
<l>they harm you, but in daytime they will do</l>
<l>no harm at all.
So lakes and rivers have</l>
<l>now this, now that effect.</l>

    
<l>“Ortygia once</l>
<l>moved like a ship that drifts among the waves.</l>
<l>Now it is fixed. The Argo was in dread</l>
<l>of the Symplegades, which moved apart</l>
<l>with waves in-rushing. Now immovable</l>
<l>they stand, resisting the attack of winds.</l>

    
<l>“Aetna, which burns with sulphur furnaces,</l>
<l>will not be always concentrated fire,</l>
<l>nor was it always fiery. If the earth</l>
<l>is like an animal and is alive</l>
<l>and breathes out flame at many openings,</l>
<l>then it can change these many passages</l>
<l>used for its breathing and, when it is moved,</l>
<l>may close these caverns as it opens up</l>
<l>some others. Or if rushing winds are penned</l>
<l>in deepest caverns, and they drive great stones</l>
<l>against the rock, and substances which have</l>
<l>the properties of flame and fire are made</l>
<l>by those concussions; when the winds are calmed</l>
<l>the caverns will, of course, be cool again.</l>

    
<l>“Or if some black bitumen catches fire</l>
<l>or yellow sulphur burns with little smoke,</l>
<l>then surely, when the ground no longer gives</l>
<l>such food and oily nutriment for flames</l>
<l>and they in time have ravined all their store,</l>
<l>their greedy nature soon will pine with death—</l>
<l>it will not bear such famine but depart</l>
<l>and, when deserted, will desert the place.</l>

    
<l>“'Tis said that Hyperboreans of Pallene</l>
<l>can cover all their bodies with light plumes</l>
<l>by plunging nine times in Minerva's marsh.</l>
<l>But I cannot believe another tale:</l>
<l>that Scythian women get a like result</l>
<l>by having poison sprinkled on their limbs.</l>

    
<l>“If we give any credit to the things</l>
<l>proved by experience, we can surely know</l>
<l>whatever bodies are decayed by time</l>
<l>or by dissolving heat are by such means</l>
<l>changed into tiny animals—Come now,</l>
<l>bury choice bullocks killed for sacrifice,</l>
<l>and it is well known by experience</l>
<l>that the flower-gathering bees are so produced,</l>
<l>miraculous, from entrails putrefied.</l>
<l>These, like the faithful animals from which</l>
<l>they were produced, inhabit the green fields,</l>
<l>delight in toil, and labor for reward.</l>

    
<l>“The warlike steed, when buried in the ground,</l>
<l>is a known source of hornets. If you cut</l>
<l>the bending claws off from the sea-shore crab</l>
<l>and bury the remainder in the earth,</l>
<l>a scorpion will come forth from the dead crab</l>
<l>buried there, threatening with its crooked tail.</l>

    
<l>“The worms which cover leaves with their white threads,</l>
<l>a thing observable by husbandmen,</l>
<l>will change themselves to funeral butterflies.</l>
<l>Mud holds the seeds that generate green frogs,</l>
<l>at first producing tadpoles with no feet,</l>
<l>and soon it gives them legs adapted for</l>
<l>their swimming, and, so they may be as well</l>
<l>adapted to good leaping, their hind legs</l>
<l>are longer than the fore-legs. The mother bear</l>
<l>does not bring forth a cub but a limp mass</l>
<l>of flesh that hardly can be called alive.</l>
<l>By licking it the mother forms the limbs,</l>
<l>and brings it to a shape just like her own.</l>

    
<l>“Do not the offspring of the honey bees,</l>
<l>concealed in cells hexagonal, at first</l>
<l>get life with no limbs, and assume in time</l>
<l>both feet and wings? Unless the fact were known,</l>
<l>could anyone suppose it possible</l>
<l>that Juno's bird, whose tail is bright with stars;</l>
<l>the eagle, armor-bearer of high Jove;</l>
<l>the doves of Cytherea; and all birds</l>
<l>emerge from the middle part of eggs?</l>
<l>And some believe the human marrow turns</l>
<l>into a serpent when the spine at length</l>
<l>has putrefied in the closed sepulchre.</l>

    
<l>“Now these I named derive their origin</l>
<l>from other living forms. There is one bird</l>
<l>which reproduces and renews itself:</l>
<l>the Assyrians gave this bird his name—the Phoenix.</l>
<l>He does not live either on grain or herbs,</l>
<l>but only on small drops of frankincense</l>
<l>and juices of amomum. When this bird</l>
<l>completes a full five centuries of life</l>
<l>straightway with talons and with shining beak</l>
<l>he builds a nest among palm branches, where</l>
<l>they join to form the palm tree's waving top.</l>

    
<l>“As soon as he has strewn in this new nest</l>
<l>the cassia bark and ears of sweet spikenard,</l>
<l>and some bruised cinnamon with yellow myrrh,</l>
<l>he lies down on it and refuses life</l>
<l>among those dreamful odors.—And they say</l>
<l>that from the body of the dying bird</l>
<l>is reproduced a little Phoenix which</l>
<l>is destined to live just as many years.</l>

    
<l>“When time has given to him sufficient strength</l>
<l>and he is able to sustain the weight,</l>
<l>he lifts the nest up from the lofty tree</l>
<l>and dutifully carries from that place</l>
<l>his cradle and the parent's sepulchre.</l>
<l>As soon as he has reached through yielding air</l>
<l>the city of Hyperion, he will lay</l>
<l>the burden just before the sacred doors</l>
<l>within the temple of Hyperion.</l>

    
<l>“But, if we wonder at strange things like these,</l>
<l>we ought to wonder also, when we learn</l>
<l>that a hyena has a change of sex:</l>
<l>the female, quitting her embracing male,</l>
<l>herself becomes a male.—That animal</l>
<l>which feeds upon the winds and air, at once</l>
<l>assumes with contact any color touched.</l>

    
<l>“Conquered India gave to the vine crowned Bacchus</l>
<l>lynxes, whose urine turns, they say to stones,</l>
<l>hardening in air. So coral, too, as soon</l>
<l>as it has risen above the sea, turns hard.</l>
<l>Below the waves it was a tender plant.</l>

    
<l>“The day will fail me; Phoebus will have bathed</l>
<l>his panting horses in the deep sea waves,</l>
<l>before I can include in my discourse</l>
<l>the myriad things transforming to new shapes.</l>
<l>In lapse of time we see the nations change;</l>
<l>some grow in power, some wane. Troy was once great</l>
<l>in riches and in men—so great she could</l>
<l>for ten unequalled years afford much blood;</l>
<l>now she lies low and offers to our gaze</l>
<l>but ancient ruins and, instead of wealth,</l>
<l>ancestral tombs. Sparta was famous once</l>
<l>and great Mycenae was most flourishing.</l>
<l>And Cecrops' citadel and Amphion's shone</l>
<l>in ancient power. Sparta is nothing now</l>
<l>save barren ground, the proud Mycenae fell,</l>
<l>what is the Thebes of storied Oedipus</l>
<l>except a name? And of Pandion's Athens</l>
<l>what now remains beyond the name?</l>

    
<l>“Reports come to me that Dardanian Rome</l>
<l>is rising, and beside the Tiber's waves,</l>
<l>whose springs are high in the Apennines, is laying</l>
<l>her deep foundations. So in her growth</l>
<l>her form is changing, and one day she will</l>
<l>be the sole mistress of the boundless world.</l>

    
<l>“They say that soothsayers and that oracles,</l>
<l>revealers of our destiny, declare</l>
<l>this fate, and, if I recollect it right,</l>
<l>Helenus, son of Priam, prophesied</l>
<l>unto Aeneas, when he was in doubt</l>
<l>of safety and lamenting for the state </l>
<l>of Troy, about to fall, ‘O, son of a goddess,</l>
<l>if you yourself, will fully understand</l>
<l>this prophecy now surging in my mind</l>
<l>Troy shall not, while you are preserved to life</l>
<l>fall utterly. Flames and the sword shall give </l>
<l>you passage. You shall go and bear away</l>
<l>Pergama, ruined; till a foreign soil,</l>
<l>more friendly to you than your native land,</l>
<l>shall be the lot of Troy and of yourself.</l>

    
<l>“Even now I know it is decreed by Fate</l>
<l>that our posterity, born far from Troy,</l>
<l>will build a city greater than exists,</l>
<l>or ever will exist, or ever has</l>
<l>been seen in former times. Through a long lapse</l>
<l>of ages other noted men shall make</l>
<l>it strong, but one of the race of Iulus;</l>
<l>shall make it the great mistress of the world.</l>
<l>After the earth has thoroughly enjoyed </l>
<l>his glorious life, aetherial abodes </l>
<l>shall gain him, and immortal heaven shall be</l>
<l>his destiny.’
Such was the prophesy</l>
<l>of Helenus, when great Aeneas took</l>
<l>away his guardian deities, and I</l>
<l>rejoice to see my kindred walls rise high</l>
<l>and realize how much the Trojans won</l>
<l>by that resounding victory of the Greeks!</l>

    
<l>“But, that we may not range afar with steeds</l>
<l>forgetful of the goal, the heavens and all</l>
<l>beneath them and the earth and everything</l>
<l>upon it change in form. We likewise change,</l>
<l>who are a portion of the universe,</l>
<l>and, since we are not only things of flesh</l>
<l>but winged souls as well, we may be doomed</l>
<l>to enter into beasts as our abode;</l>
<l>and even to be hidden in the breasts</l>
<l>of cattle. Therefore, should we not allow</l>
<l>these bodies to be safe which may contain</l>
<l>the souls of parents, brothers, or of those</l>
<l>allied to us by kinship or of men</l>
<l>at least, who should be saved from every harm?</l>
<l>Let us not gorge down a Thyestean feast!</l>

    
<l>“How greatly does a man disgrace himself,</l>
<l>how impiously does he prepare himself</l>
<l>for shedding human blood, who with u knife</l>
<l>cuts the calf's throat and offers a deaf ear</l>
<l>to its death-longings! who can kill the kid</l>
<l>while it is sending forth heart rending cries</l>
<l>like those of a dear child; or who can feed</l>
<l>upon the bird which he has given food.</l>
<l>How little do such deeds as these fall short</l>
<l>of actual murder? Yes, where will they lead?</l>

    
<l>“Let the ox plough, or let him owe his death</l>
<l>to weight of years; and let the sheep give us</l>
<l>defence against the cold of Boreas;</l>
<l>and let the well-fed she-goats give to man</l>
<l>their udders for the pressure of kind hands.</l>

    
<l>“Away with cruel nets and springs and snares</l>
<l>and fraudulent contrivances: deceive</l>
<l>not birds with bird-limed twigs: do not deceive</l>
<l>the trusting deer with dreaded feather foils:</l>
<l>do not conceal barbed hooks with treacherous bait:</l>
<l>if any beast is harmful, take his life,</l>
<l>but, even so, let killing be enough.</l>
<l>Taste not his flesh, but look for harmless food!”</l>


Egeria. Hippolytus.
EGERIA CHANGED INTO A FOUNTAIN

<l>They say that Numa with a mind well taught</l>
<l>by these and other precepts traveled back</l>
<l>to his own land and, being urged again,</l>
<l>assumed the guidance of the Latin state.</l>
<l>Blest with a nymph as consort, blest also with</l>
<l>the Muses for his guides, he taught the rites</l>
<l>of sacrifice and trained in arts of peace</l>
<l>a race accustomed long to savage war.</l>
<l>When, ripe in years, he ended reign and life,</l>
<l>the Latin matrons, the fathers of the state,</l>
<l>and all the people wept for Numa's death.</l>
<l>For the nymph, his widow, had withdrawn from Rome,</l>
<l>concealed within the thick groves of the vale</l>
<l>Aricia, where with groans and wailing she</l>
<l>disturbed the holy rites of Cynthia,</l>
<l>established by Orestes. Ah! how often</l>
<l>nymphs of the grove and lake entreated her</l>
<l>to cease and offered her consoling words.</l>
<l>How often the son of Theseus said to her</l>
<l>“Control your sorrow; surely your sad lot</l>
<l>is not the only one; consider now</l>
<l>the like calamities by others borne,</l>
<l>and you can bear your sorrow. To my grief</l>
<l>my own disaster was far worse than yours.</l>
<l>At least it can afford you comfort now.</l>


<l>“Is it not true, discourse has reached yours ears</l>
<l>that one Hippolytus met with his death</l>
<l>through the credulity of his loved sire,</l>
<l>deceived by a stepmother's wicked art?</l>
<l>It will amaze you much, and I may fail </l>
<l>to prove what I declare, but I am he!</l>
<l>Long since the daughter of Pasiphae</l>
<l>tempted me to defile my father's bed</l>
<l>and, failing, feigned that I had wished to do</l>
<l>what she herself had wished. Perverting truth—</l>
<l>either through fear of some discovery</l>
<l>or else through spite at her deserved repulse—</l>
<l>she charged me with attempting the foul crime.</l>

    
<l>“Though I was guiltless of all wrong,</l>
<l>my father banished me and, while I was</l>
<l>departing, laid on me a mortal curse.</l>
<l>Towards Pittheus and Troezen I fled aghast,</l>
<l>guiding the swift chariot near the shore</l>
<l>of the Corinthian Gulf, when all at once</l>
<l>the sea rose up and seemed to arch itself</l>
<l>and lift high as a white topped mountain height,</l>
<l>make bellowings, and open at the crest.</l>
<l>Then through the parting waves a horned bull</l>
<l>emerged with head and breast into the wind, </l>
<l>spouting white foam from his nostrils and his mouth.</l>


<l>“The hearts of my attendants quailed with fear,</l>
<l>yet I unfrightened thought but of my exile.</l>
<l>Then my fierce horses turned their necks to face</l>
<l>the waters, and with ears erect they quaked</l>
<l>before the monster shape, they dashed in flight</l>
<l>along the rock strewn ground below the cliff.</l>
<l>I struggled, but with unavailing hand,</l>
<l>to use the reins now covered with white foam;</l>
<l>and throwing myself back, pulled on the thongs</l>
<l>with weight and strength. Such effort might have checked</l>
<l>the madness of my steeds, had not a wheel,</l>
<l>striking the hub on a projecting stump,</l>
<l>been shattered and hurled in fragments from the axle.</l>

    
<l>“I was thrown forward from my chariot</l>
<l>and with the reins entwined about my legs.</l>
<l>My palpitating entrails could be seen</l>
<l>dragged on, my sinews fastened on a stump.</l>
<l>My torn legs followed, but a part</l>
<l>remained behind me, caught by various snags.</l>
<l>The breaking bones gave out a crackling noise,</l>
<l>my tortured spirit soon had fled away,</l>
<l>no part of the torn body could be known—</l>
<l>all that was left was only one crushed wound—</l>
<l>how can, how dare you, nymph, compare your ills</l>
<l>to my disaster?</l>

    
<l>“I saw the Lower World</l>
<l>deprived of light: and I have bathed my flesh,</l>
<l>so tortured, in the waves of Phlegethon.</l>
<l>Life could not have been given again to me,</l>
<l>but through the remedies Apollo's son</l>
<l>applied to me. After my life returned—</l>
<l>by potent herbs and the Paeonian aid,</l>
<l>despite the will of Pluto—Cynthia then</l>
<l>threw heavy clouds around that I might not</l>
<l>be seen and cause men envy by new life:</l>
<l>and that she might be sure my life was safe</l>
<l>she made me seem an old man; and she changed</l>
<l>me so that I could not be recognized.</l>

    
<l>“A long time she debated whether she</l>
<l>would give me Crete or Delos for my home.</l>
<l>Delos and Crete abandoned, she then brought</l>
<l>me here, and at the same time ordered me</l>
<l>to lay aside my former name—one which</l>
<l>when mentioned would remind me of my steeds.</l>
<l>She said to me, ‘You were Hippolytus,</l>
<l>but now instead you shall be Virbius.’</l>
<l>And from that time I have inhabited</l>
<l>this grove; and, as one of the lesser gods,</l>
<l>I live concealed and numbered in her train.”</l>

    
<l>The grief of others could not ease the woe</l>
<l>of sad Egeria, and she laid herself</l>
<l>down at a mountain's foot, dissolved in tears,</l>
<l>till moved by pity for her faithful sorrow,</l>
<l>Diana changed her body to a spring,</l>
<l>her limbs into a clear continual stream.</l>


Tages. Cipus.
CIPPUS WITH HORNS

<l>This wonderful event surprised the nymphs,</l>
<l>and filled Hippolytus with wonder, just</l>
<l>as great as when the Etrurian ploughman saw</l>
<l>a fate-revealing clod move of its own</l>
<l>accord among the fields, while not a hand</l>
<l>was touching it, till finally it took</l>
<l>a human form, without the quality</l>
<l>of clodded earth, and opened its new mouth</l>
<l>and spoke, revealing future destinies.</l>
<l>The natives called him Tages. He was the first</l>
<l>who taught Etrurians to foretell events.</l>

    
<l>They were astonished even as Romulus,</l>
<l>when he observed the spear, which once had grown</l>
<l>high on the Palatine, put out new leaves</l>
<l>and stand with roots—not with the iron point</l>
<l>which he had driven in. Not as a spear</l>
<l>it then stood there, but as a rooted tree</l>
<l>with limber twigs for many to admire</l>
<l>while resting under that surprising shade.</l>

    
<l>Or, as when Cippus first observed his horns</l>
<l>in the clear stream (he truly saw them there).</l>
<l>Believing he had seen a falsity,</l>
<l>he often touched his forehead with his hand</l>
<l>and, so returning, touched the thing he saw.</l>
<l>Assured at last that he could trust his eyes,</l>
<l>he stood entranced, as if he had returned</l>
<l>victorious from the conquest of his foes:</l>
<l>and, raising eyes and hands toward heaven, he cried,</l>
<l>“You gods above! Whatever is foretold</l>
<l>by this great prodigy, if it means good,</l>
<l>then let it be auspicious to my land</l>
<l>and to the inhabitants of Quirinus,—</l>
<l>if ill, let that misfortune fall on me.”</l>

    
<l>He made an offering at new altars, built</l>
<l>of grassy thick green turf, with fragrant fires,</l>
<l>presenting wine in bowls. And he took note</l>
<l>of panting entrails from new-slaughtered sheep,</l>
<l>to learn the meaning of the event for him.</l>

    
<l>When an Etruscan seer examined them,</l>
<l>he found the evidence of great events,</l>
<l>as yet obscure, and, when he raised keen eyes</l>
<l>up from the entrails to the horns of Cippus,</l>
<l>“O king, all hail!” he cried, “For in future time</l>
<l>this country and the Latin towers will live</l>
<l>in homage to you, Cippus, and your horns.</l>
<l>But you must promptly put aside delay;</l>
<l>hasten to enter the wide open gates—</l>
<l>the fates command you. Once received within</l>
<l>the city, you shall be its chosen king</l>
<l>and safely shall enjoy a lasting reign.”</l>

    
<l>Cippus retreated, and he turned his grave</l>
<l>eyes from the city's walls and said, “O far,</l>
<l>O far away, the righteous gods should drive</l>
<l>such omens from me! Better it would be</l>
<l>that I should pass my life in exile than</l>
<l>be seen a king throned in the capitol.”</l>

    
<l>Such words he spoke and forthwith he convoked</l>
<l>the people and the grave and honored Senate.</l>
<l>But first he veiled his horns with laurel, which</l>
<l>betokens peace. Then, standing on a mound</l>
<l>raised by the valiant troops, he made a prayer</l>
<l>after the ancient mode, and then he said,</l>
<l>“There is one here who will be king, if you</l>
<l>do not expel him from your city—I</l>
<l>will show him to you surely by a sign;</l>
<l>although I will not tell his name. He wears</l>
<l>horns on his head. The augur prophecies</l>
<l>that, if he enters this your city, he</l>
<l>will give you laws as if you were his slaves.</l>

    
<l>“He might have forced his way within your gates,</l>
<l>for they stand open, but I have hindered him,</l>
<l>although nobody is to him so close</l>
<l>as I myself. Good Romans, then, forbid</l>
<l>your city to this man; or, if you find</l>
<l>that he deserves still worse, then bind him fast</l>
<l>with heavy fetters; or else end your fears</l>
<l>by knowledge of the destined tyrant's death.”</l>

    
<l>As murmurs which arise among the groves</l>
<l>of pine trees thick above us, when the fierce</l>
<l>east wind is whistling in them, or as sound</l>
<l>produced by breaking waves, when it is heard</l>
<l>afar off, such the noise made by the crowd.</l>
<l>But in that angry stirring of the throng</l>
<l>one cry could be distinguished, “Which is he?”</l>
<l>And they examined foreheads, and they sought</l>
<l>predicted horns. Cippus then spoke again:</l>

    
<l>“The man whom you demand,” he said, “is here!”</l>
<l>And, fearless of the people, he threw back</l>
<l>the chaplet from his forehead, so that all</l>
<l>could see his temples plainly, wonderful</l>
<l>for their two horns. All then turned down their eyes</l>
<l>and uttered groans and (was it possible?)</l>
<l>they looked unwillingly upon that head</l>
<l>famed for its merit. They could not permit</l>
<l>him to remain there long, deprived</l>
<l>of honors, and they placed upon his head</l>
<l>the festive chaplet. And the Senate gave</l>
<l>you, Cippus, since you nevermore must come</l>
<l>within the walls, a proof of their esteem—</l>
<l>so much land as your oxen and their plow</l>
<l>could circle round from dawn to setting sun.</l>
<l>Moreover they engraved the shapely horns</l>
<l>on the bronze pillars of the city gate, </l>
<l>which for long ages kept his name revered.</l>


Aesculapius.
AESCULAPIUS BROUGHT TO ROME

<l>Relate, O Muses, guardian deities</l>
<l>of poets (for you know, and the remote</l>
<l>antiquity conceals it not from you),</l>
<l>the reason why an island, which the deep stream</l>
<l>of Tiber closed about, has introduced</l>
<l>Coronis' child among the deities</l>
<l>guarding the city of famed Romulus.</l>

    
<l>A dire contagion had infested long</l>
<l>the Latin air, and men's pale bodies were</l>
<l>deformed by a consumption that dried up</l>
<l>the blood. When, frightened by so many deaths,</l>
<l>they found all mortal efforts could avail</l>
<l>them nothing, and physicians' skill had no</l>
<l>effect, they sought the aid of heaven. They sent</l>
<l>envoys to Delphi center of the world,</l>
<l>and they entreated Phoebus to give aid</l>
<l>in their distress, and by response renew</l>
<l>their wasting lives and end a city's woe.</l>
<l>While ground, and laurels and the quivers which</l>
<l>the god hung there all shook, the tripod gave</l>
<l>this answer from the deep recesses hid</l>
<l>within the shrine, and stirred with trembling their</l>
<l>astonished hearts—</l>

    
<l>“What you are seeking here,</l>
<l>O Romans, you should seek for nearer you.</l>
<l>Then seek it nearer, for you do not need</l>
<l>Apollo to relieve your wasting plague,</l>
<l>you need Apollo's son. Go then to him</l>
<l>with a good omen and invite his aid.”</l>

    
<l>After the prudent Senate had received</l>
<l>Phoebus Apollo's words, they took much pains</l>
<l>to learn what town the son of Phoebus might</l>
<l>inhabit. They despatched ambassadors</l>
<l>under full sail to the coast of Epidaurus.</l>
<l>When the curved ships had touched the shore, these men</l>
<l>in haste went to the Grecian elders there</l>
<l>and prayed that Rome might have the deity</l>
<l>whose presence would drive out the mortal ill</l>
<l>from their Ausonian nation; for they knew</l>
<l>response unerring had directed them.</l>

    
<l>The councillors dismayed, could not agree</l>
<l>on their reply: some thought that aid ought not</l>
<l>to be refused, but many more held back,</l>
<l>declaring it was wise to keep the god</l>
<l>for their own safety and not give away</l>
<l>a guardian deity. And, while they talked,</l>
<l>discussing it, the twilight had expelled </l>
<l>the waning day, and darkness on the earth</l>
<l>spread a thick mantle over the wide world.</l>

    
<l>Then in your sleep, the healing deity</l>
<l>appeared, O Roman leader, by your couch,</l>
<l>as in his temple he is used to stand, </l>
<l>holding in his left hand a rustic staff.</l>
<l>Stroking his long beard with his right, he seemed</l>
<l>to utter from his kindly breast these words:</l>

    
<l>“Forget your fears; for I will come to you,</l>
<l>and leave my altar. But now look well at </l>
<l>the serpent with its binding folds entwined </l>
<l>around this staff, and accurately mark</l>
<l>it with your eyes that you may recognize it.</l>
<l>I will transform myself into this shape</l>
<l>but of a greater size, I will appear</l>
<l>enlarged and of a magnitude to which</l>
<l>a heavenly being ought to be transformed.”</l>

    
<l>The god departed, when he said those words;</l>
<l>and sleep went, when the god and words were gone;</l>
<l>and genial light came, when the sleep had left.</l>
<l>The morning then dispersed fire-given stars.</l>
<l>The envoys met together in much doubt</l>
<l>within the temple of the long sought god.</l>
<l>They prayed the god to indicate for them,</l>
<l>by clear celestial tokens, in what spot</l>
<l>he wished to dwell.</l>

    
<l>Scarce had they ceased the prayer</l>
<l>for guidance, when the god all glittering</l>
<l>with gold and as a serpent, crest erect,</l>
<l>sent forth a hissing as to notify</l>
<l>a quick approach— and in his coming shook</l>
<l>his statue and the altars and the doors,</l>
<l>the marble pavement and the gilded roof.</l>
<l>Then up to his breast the serpent stood erect</l>
<l>within the temple. He gazed on all with eyes</l>
<l>that sparkled fire. The waiting multitude </l>
<l>was frightened; but the priest, his chaste hair bound</l>
<l>with a white fillet, knew the deity.</l>

    
<l>“Behold the god!” he cried, “It is the god.</l>
<l>Think holy thoughts and walk in reverent silence,</l>
<l>all who are present. Oh, most Beautiful,</l>
<l>let us behold you to our benefit, </l>
<l>and give aid to this people that performs</l>
<l>your sacred rites.”</l>


    
<l>All present then adored</l>
<l>the deity as bidden by the priest.</l>
<l>The multitude repeated his good words,</l>
<l>and the descendants of Aeneas gave</l>
<l>good omen, with their feelings and their speech.</l>
<l>Nodding well pleased and moving his great crest,</l>
<l>the god at once assured them of his favor</l>
<l>and hissed repeatedly with darting tongue.</l>
<l>And then he glided down the polished steps;</l>
<l>turned back his head; and, ready to depart,</l>
<l>gazed on the altars he had known for so long—</l>
<l>a last salute to the temple of his love.</l>

    
<l>While all the people strewed his way with flowers, </l>
<l>the great snake wound in sinuous course along</l>
<l>and, passing through the middle of their town,</l>
<l>came to the harbor and its curving wall.</l>
<l>He stopped there, and it seemed that he dismissed</l>
<l>his train and dutiful attendant crowd,</l>
<l>and with a placid countenance he placed</l>
<l>his mighty body in the Ausonian ship,</l>
<l>which plainly showed the great weight of the god.</l>

    
<l>The glad descendants of Aeneas all</l>
<l>rejoiced, and they sacrificed a bull beside</l>
<l>the harbor, wreathed the ship with flowers, and loosed</l>
<l>the twisted hawsers from the shore. As a soft breeze</l>
<l>impelled the ship, within her curving stern</l>
<l>the god reclined, his coils uprising high,</l>
<l>and gazed down on the blue Ionian waves.</l>
<l>So wafted by the favoring winds, they came</l>
<l>in six days to the shores of Italy.</l>

    
<l>There he was borne past the Lacinian Cape,</l>
<l>ennobled by the goddess Juno's shrine,</l>
<l>and Scylacean coasts. He left behind</l>
<l>Iapygia; then he shunned Amphrysian rocks</l>
<l>upon the left and on the other side</l>
<l>escaped Cocinthian crags. He passed, near by,</l>
<l>Romechium and Caulon and Naricia;</l>
<l>crossed the Sicilian sea; went through the strait;</l>
<l>sailed by Pelorus and the island home </l>
<l>of Aeolus and by the copper mines</l>
<l>of Temesa. He turned then toward Leucosia </l>
<l>and toward mild Paestum, famous for the rose.</l>
<l>He coasted by Capreae and around</l>
<l>Minerva's promontory and the hills</l>
<l>ennobled with Surrentine vines, from there</l>
<l>to Herculaneum and Stabiae</l>
<l>and then Parthenope built for soft ease.</l>
<l>He sailed near the Cumaean Sibyl's temple.</l>
<l>He passed the Warm Springs and Linternum, where</l>
<l>the mastick trees grow, and the river called</l>
<l>Volturnus, where thick sand whirls in the stream,</l>
<l>over to  Sinuessa's snow-white doves;</l>
<l>and then to Antium and its rocky coast.</l>

    
<l>When with all sails full spread the ship came in</l>
<l>the harbor there (for now the seas grew rough),</l>
<l>the god uncoiled his folds, and, gliding out </l>
<l>with sinuous curves and all his mighty length,</l>
<l>entered the temple of his parent, where</l>
<l>it skirts that yellow shore. But, when the sea</l>
<l>was calm again, the Epidaurian god</l>
<l>departing from his father's shrine, where he</l>
<l>a while had shared the sacred residence</l>
<l>reared to a kindred deity, furrowed</l>
<l>the sandy shore with weight of crackling scales,</l>
<l>again he climbed into the lofty stern</l>
<l>and near the rudder laid his head at rest.</l>

    
<l>There he remained until the vessel passed</l>
<l>by Castrum and Lavinium's sacred homes </l>
<l>to where the Tiber flows into the sea</l>
<l>there all the people of Rome came rushing out—</l>
<l>mothers and fathers and even those who tend</l>
<l>your sacred fire, O Trojan goddess Vesta—</l>
<l>and joyous shouted welcome to the god.</l>
<l>Wherever the swift ship steered through the tide,</l>
<l>they built up many altars in a line,</l>
<l>so that perfuming frankincense with smoke</l>
<l>crackled along the banks on either hand,</l>
<l>and victims made the keen knives hot with blood.</l>

    
<l>The serpent-deity has entered Rome,</l>
<l>the world's new capital and, lifting up</l>
<l>his head above the summit of the mast,</l>
<l>looked far and near for a congenial home.</l>
<l>The river there, dividing, flows about</l>
<l>a place known as the Island, on both sides</l>
<l>an equal stream glides past dry middle ground.</l>
<l>And here the serpent child of Phoebus left</l>
<l>the Roman ship, took his own heavenly form,</l>
<l>and brought the mourning city health once more</l>


Divus Iulius.
JULIUS CAESAR, TRANSFORMED TO A STAR

<l>Apollo's son came to us from abroad,</l>
<l>but Caesar is a god in his own land.</l>
<l>The first in war and peace, he rose by wars,</l>
<l>which closed in triumphs, and by civic deeds</l>
<l>to glory quickly won, and even more</l>
<l>his offspring's love exalted him as a new,</l>
<l>a heavenly, sign and brightly flaming star.</l>
<l>Of all the achievements of great Julius Caesar</l>
<l>not one is more ennobling to his fame</l>
<l>than being father of his glorious son.</l>

    
<l>Was it more glorious for him to subdue</l>
<l>the Britons guarded by their sheltering sea</l>
<l>or lead his fleet victorious up the stream</l>
<l>seven mouthed of the papyrus hearing Nile;</l>
<l>to bring beneath the Roman people s rule</l>
<l>rebel Numidia, Libyan Juba, and</l>
<l>strong Pontus, proud of Mithridates' fame;</l>
<l>to have some triumphs and deserve far more;</l>
<l>than to be father of so great a man,</l>
<l>with whom as ruler of the human race,</l>
<l>O gods, you bless us past all reckoning?</l>

    
<l>And, lest that son should come from mortal seed,</l>
<l>Julius Caesar must change and be a god.</l>
<l>When the golden mother of Aeneas was</l>
<l>aware of this and saw a grievous end</l>
<l>plotted against her high priest, saw the armed</l>
<l>conspiracy preparing for his death,</l>
<l>with pallid face she met each god and said:</l>

    
<l>“Look with what might this plot prepares itself</l>
<l>against my cause; with how much guile it dooms</l>
<l>the head which is the last that I have left</l>
<l>from old-time Iulus, prince and heir of Troy.</l>
<l>Shall I alone be harassed through all time</l>
<l>by fear well grounded? First the son of Tydeus</l>
<l>must wound me with his Calydonian spear;</l>
<l>and then I tremble at the tottering walls</l>
<l>of ill defended Troy; I watch my son</l>
<l>driven in long wanderings, tossed upon the sea,</l>
<l>descending to the realm of silent shades, </l>
<l>and waging war with Turnus—or, if I should speak</l>
<l>the truth, with Juno! Why do I recall</l>
<l>disasters of my race from long ago?</l>
<l>The present dread forbids my looking back</l>
<l>at ills now past. See how the wicked swords</l>
<l>are whetted for the crime! Forbid it now,</l>
<l>I pray you, and prevent the deed,</l>
<l>let not the priest's warm blood quench vestal fires!”</l>

    
<l>Such words as these, full of her anxious thoughts,</l>
<l>Venus proclaimed through all the heavens, in vain.</l>
<l>The gods were moved, and, since they could not break</l>
<l>the ancient sisters' iron decree, they gave</l>
<l>instead clear portents of approaching woe.</l>

    
<l>It is declared, resounding arms heard from</l>
<l>the black clouds and unearthly trumpet blasts</l>
<l>and clarions heard through all the highest heavens,</l>
<l>forewarned men of the crime. The sad sun's face</l>
<l>gave to the frightened world a livid light;</l>
<l>and in the night-time torches seemed to burn</l>
<l>amid the stars, and often drops of blood</l>
<l>fell in rain-showers. Then Lucifer shone blue</l>
<l>with all his visage stained by darksome rust.</l>
<l>The chariot of the moon was sprinkled with</l>
<l>red blood. The Stygian owl gave to the world</l>
<l>ill omens. In a thousand places, tears</l>
<l>were shed by the ivory statues. Dirges, too,</l>
<l>are said to have been heard, and threatening words</l>
<l>by unknown speakers in the sacred groves.</l>

    
<l>No victim gave an omen of good life:</l>
<l>the fibers showed great tumults imminent,</l>
<l>the liver's cut-off edge was found among</l>
<l>the entrails. In the Forum, it is said,</l>
<l>and round men's homes and temples of the gods</l>
<l>dogs howled all through the night, and silent shades</l>
<l>wandered abroad, and earthquakes shook the city.</l>

    
<l>But portents of the gods could not avert</l>
<l>the plots of men and stay approaching fate.</l>
<l>Into a temple naked swords were brought—</l>
<l>into the Senate House. No other place</l>
<l>in all our city was considered fit</l>
<l>for perpetrating such a dreadful crime!</l>
<l>With both hands Cytherea beat her breast,</l>
<l>and in a cloud she strove to hide the last</l>
<l>of great Aeneas' line, as in times past</l>
<l>she had hid Paris from fierce Menelaus</l>
<l>Aeneas from the blade of Diomed.</l>

    
<l>But Jove, her father, cautioned her and said,</l>
<l>“Do you my daughter, without aid, alone,</l>
<l>attempt to change the fixed decrees of Fate?</l>
<l>Unaided you may enter the abode</l>
<l>of the three sisters and can witness there</l>
<l>a register of deeds the future brings.</l>
<l>These, wrought of brass and solid iron with</l>
<l>vast labor, are unchangeable through all</l>
<l>eternity; and have no weakening fears</l>
<l>of thunder-shocks from heaven, nor from the rage</l>
<l>of lightnings they are perfectly secure</l>
<l>from all destruction. You will surely find</l>
<l>the destinies of your descendants there,</l>
<l>engraved in everlasting adamant.</l>
<l>'Tis certain. I myself, have read them there:</l>
<l>and I, with care have marked them in my mind.</l>
<l>I will repeat them so that you may have</l>
<l>unerring knowledge of those future days.</l>

    
<l>“Venus, the man on whose behalf you are</l>
<l>so anxious, already has completed his</l>
<l>alloted time. The years are ended which</l>
<l>he owed to life on earth. You with his son,</l>
<l>who now as heir to his estate must bear</l>
<l>the burden of that government, will cause</l>
<l>him, as a deity, to reach the heavens,</l>
<l>and to be worshipped in the temples here.</l>

    
<l>“The valiant son will plan revenge on those</l>
<l>who killed his father and will have our aid</l>
<l>in all his battles. The defeated walls</l>
<l>of scarred Mutina, which he will besiege,</l>
<l>shall sue for peace. Pharsalia's plain will dread</l>
<l>his power and Macedonian Philippi</l>
<l>be drenched with blood a second time, the name</l>
<l>of one acclaimed as ‘Great’ shall be subdued</l>
<l>in the Sicilian waves. Then Egypt's queen,</l>
<l>wife of the Roman general, Antony,</l>
<l>shall fall, while vainly trusting in his word,</l>
<l>while vainly threatening that our Capitol</l>
<l>must be submissive to Canopus' power.</l>
<l>“Why should I mention all the barbarous lands</l>
<l>and nations east and west by ocean's rim?</l>
<l>Whatever habitable earth contains</l>
<l>shall bow to him, the sea shall serve his will!</l>

    
<l>“With peace established over all the lands,</l>
<l>he then will turn his mind to civil rule</l>
<l>and as a prudent legislator will</l>
<l>enact wise laws. And he will regulate</l>
<l>the manners of his people by his own</l>
<l>example. Looking forward to the days</l>
<l>of future time and of posterity,</l>
<l>he will command the offspring born of his</l>
<l>devoted wife, to assume the imperial name</l>
<l>and the burden of his cares. Nor till his age</l>
<l>shall equal Nestor's years will he ascend</l>
<l>to heavenly dwellings and his kindred stars.</l>
<l>Meanwhile transform the soul, which shall be reft</l>
<l>from this doomed body, to a starry light,</l>
<l>that always god-like Julius may look down</l>
<l>in future from his heavenly residence</l>
<l>upon our Forum and our Capitol.”</l>

    
<l>Jupiter hardly had pronounced these words,</l>
<l>when kindly Venus, although seen by none,</l>
<l>stood in the middle of the Senate-house,</l>
<l>and caught from the dying limbs and trunk</l>
<l>of her own Caesar his departing soul.</l>
<l>She did not give it time so that it could</l>
<l>dissolve in air, but bore it quickly up,</l>
<l>toward all the stars of heaven; and on the way,</l>
<l>she saw it gleam and blaze and set it free.</l>
<l>Above the moon it mounted into heaven,</l>
<l>leaving behind a long and fiery trail,</l>
<l>and as a star it glittered in the sky.</l>

    
<l>There, wondering at the younger Caesar's deeds,</l>
<l>Julius confessed they were superior</l>
<l>to all of his, and he rejoiced because</l>
<l>his son was greater even than himself.</l>
<l>Although the son forbade men to regard</l>
<l>his own deeds as the: mightier! Fame, that moves</l>
<l>free and untrammelled by the laws of men,</l>
<l>preferred him even against his own desire</l>
<l>and in that one point disobeyed his will.</l>

    
<l>And so great Atreus yields to greater fame</l>
<l>of Agamemnon, Aegeus yields to Theseus,</l>
<l>and Peleus to Achilles, or, to name</l>
<l>a parallel befitting these two gods,</l>
<l>so Saturn yields to Jove. Now Jupiter</l>
<l>rules in high heavens and is the suzerain</l>
<l>over the waters and the world of shades,</l>
<l>and now Augustus rules in all the lands—</l>
<l>so each is both a father and a god.</l>

    
<l>Gods who once guarded our Aeneas, when</l>
<l>both swords and fire gave way, and native gods</l>
<l>of Italy, and Father Quirinus—</l>
<l>patron of Rome, and you Gradivus too—</l>
<l>the sire of Quirinus the invincible,</l>
<l>and Vesta hallowed among Caesar's gods,</l>
<l>and Phoebus ever worshipped at his hearth,</l>
<l>and Jupiter who rules the citadel</l>
<l>high on Tarpeia's cliff, and other gods—</l>
<l>all gods to whom a poet rightfully</l>
<l>and with all piety may make appeal;</l>
<l>far be that day—postponed beyond our time,</l>
<l>when great Augustus shall foresake the earth</l>
<l>which he now governs, and mount up to heaven,</l>
<l>from that far height to hear his people's prayers!</l>

    
<l>And now, I have completed a great work,</l>
<l>which not Jove's anger, and not fire nor steel,</l>
<l>nor fast-consuming time can sweep away.</l>
<l>Whenever it will, let the day come, which has</l>
<l>dominion only over this mortal frame,</l>
<l>and end for me the uncertain course of life.</l>
<l>Yet in my better part I shall be borne</l>
<l>immortal, far above the stars on high,</l>
<l>and mine shall be a name indelible.</l>
<l>Wherever Roman power extends her sway</l>
<l>over the conquered lands, I shall be read</l>
<l>by lips of men. If Poets' prophecies</l>
<l>have any truth, through all the coming years</l>
<l>of future ages, I shall live in fame.</l>
