<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 8


Nisus et Scylla.
KING MINOS AND SCYLLA

<l>Now Lucifer unveiled the glorious day,</l>
<l>and as the session of the night dissolved,</l>
<l>the cool east wind declined, and vapors wreathed</l>
<l>the moistened valleys. Veering to the south</l>
<l>the welcome wind gave passage to the sons</l>
<l>of Aeacus, and wafted Cephalus</l>
<l>on his returning way, propitious; where</l>
<l>before the wonted hour, they entered port.</l>

    
<l>King Minos, while the fair wind moved their ship,</l>
<l>was laying waste the land of Megara.</l>
<l>He gathered a great army round the walls</l>
<l>built by Alcathous, where reigned in splendor</l>
<l>King Nisus—mighty and renowned in war—</l>
<l>upon the center of whose hoary head</l>
<l>a lock of purple hair was growing.—Its</l>
<l>proved virtue gave protection to his throne.</l>

    
<l>Six times the horns of rising Phoebe grew,</l>
<l>and still the changing fortune of the war</l>
<l>was in suspense; so, Victory day by day</l>
<l>between them hovered on uncertain wings.</l>

    
<l>Within that city was a regal tower</l>
<l>on tuneful walls; where once Apollo laid</l>
<l>his golden harp; and in the throbbing stone</l>
<l>the sounds remained. And there, in times of peace</l>
<l>the daughter of king Nisus loved to mount</l>
<l>the walls and strike the sounding stone with pebbles:</l>
<l>so, when the war began, she often viewed</l>
<l>the dreadful contest from that height;</l>
<l>until, so long the hostile camp remained,</l>
<l>she had become acquainted with the names,</l>
<l>and knew the habits, horses and the arms</l>
<l>of many a chief, and could discern the signs</l>
<l>of their Cydonean quivers.</l>

    
<l>More than all,</l>
<l>the features of King Minos were engraved</l>
<l>upon the tablets of her mind. And when</l>
<l>he wore his helmet, crested with gay plumes,</l>
<l>she deemed it glorious; when he held his shield</l>
<l>shining with gold, no other seemed so grand;</l>
<l>and when he poised to hurl the tough spear home,</l>
<l>she praised his skill and strength; and when he bent</l>
<l>his curving bow with arrow on the cord,</l>
<l>she pictured him as Phoebus taking aim,—</l>
<l>but when, arrayed in purple, and upon</l>
<l>the back of his white war horse, proudly decked</l>
<l>with richly broidered housings, he reined in</l>
<l>the nervous steed, and took his helmet off,</l>
<l>showing his fearless features, then the maid,</l>
<l>daughter of Nisus, could control herself</l>
<l>no longer; and a frenzy seized her mind.</l>

    
<l>She called the javelin happy which he touched,</l>
<l>and blessed were the reins within his hand.</l>

    
<l>She had an impulse to direct her steps,</l>
<l>a tender virgin, through the hostile ranks,</l>
<l>or cast her body from the topmost towers</l>
<l>into the Gnossian camp. She had a wild</l>
<l>desire to open to the enemy</l>
<l>the heavy brass-bound gates, or anything</l>
<l>that Minos could desire.</l>

    
<l>And as she sat</l>
<l>beholding the white tents, she cried, “Alas!</l>
<l>Should I rejoice or grieve to see this war?</l>
<l>I grieve that Minos is the enemy</l>
<l>of her who loves him; but unless the war</l>
<l>had brought him, how could he be known to me?</l>
<l>But should he take me for a hostage? That</l>
<l>might end the war—a pledge of peace, he might</l>
<l>keep me for his companion.</l>

    
<l>“O, supreme</l>
<l>of mankind! she who bore you must have been</l>
<l>as beautiful as you are; ample cause</l>
<l>for Jove to lose his heart.</l>

    
<l>“O, happy hour!</l>
<l>If moving upon wings through yielding air,</l>
<l>I could alight within the hostile camp</l>
<l>in front of Minos, and declare to him</l>
<l>my name and passion!</l>

    
<l>“Then would I implore</l>
<l>what dowry he could wish, and would provide</l>
<l>whatever he might ask, except alone</l>
<l>the city of my father. Perish all</l>
<l>my secret hopes before one act of mine</l>
<l>should offer treason to accomplish it.</l>
<l>And yet, the kindness of a conqueror</l>
<l>has often proved a blessing, manifest</l>
<l>to those who were defeated. Certainly</l>
<l>the war he carries on is justified</l>
<l>by his slain son.</l>

    
<l>“He is a mighty king,</l>
<l>thrice strengthened in his cause. Undoubtedly</l>
<l>we shall be conquered, and, if such a fate</l>
<l>awaits our city, why should he by force</l>
<l>instead of my consuming love, prevail</l>
<l>to open the strong gates? Without delay</l>
<l>and dreadful slaughter, it is best for him</l>
<l>to conquer and decide this savage war.</l>

    
<l>“Ah, Minos, how I fear the bitter fate</l>
<l>should any warrior hurl his cruel spear</l>
<l>and pierce you by mischance, for surely none</l>
<l>can be so hardened to transfix your breast</l>
<l>with purpose known.”</l>

    
<l>Oh, let her love prevail</l>
<l>to open for his army the great gates.</l>
<l>Only the thought of it, has filled her soul;</l>
<l>she is determined to deliver up</l>
<l>her country as a dowry with herself,</l>
<l>and so decide the war! But what avails</l>
<l>this idle talk.</l>

    
<l>“A guard surrounds the gates,</l>
<l>my father keeps the keys, and he alone</l>
<l>is my obstruction, and the innocent</l>
<l>account of my despair. Would to the Gods</l>
<l>I had no father! Is not man the God</l>
<l>of his own fortune, though his idle prayers</l>
<l>avail not to compel his destiny?</l>

    
<l>“Another woman crazed with passionate desires,</l>
<l>which now inflame me, would not hesitate,</l>
<l>but with a fierce abandon would destroy</l>
<l>whatever checked her passion. Who is there</l>
<l>with love to equal mine? I dare to go</l>
<l>through flames and swords; but swords and flames</l>
<l>are not now needed, for I only need</l>
<l>my royal father's lock of purple hair.</l>
<l>More precious than fine gold, it has a power</l>
<l>to give my heart all that it may desire.”</l>


    
<l>While Scylla said this, night that heals our cares</l>
<l>came on, and she grew bolder in the dark.</l>
<l>And now it is the late and silent hour</l>
<l>when slumber takes possession of the breast.</l>
<l>Outwearied with the cares of busy day;</l>
<l>then as her father slept, with stealthy tread</l>
<l>she entered his abode, and there despoiled,</l>
<l>and clipped his fatal lock of purple hair.</l>

    
<l>Concealing in her bosom the sad prize</l>
<l>of crime degenerate, she at once went forth</l>
<l>a gate unguarded, and with shameless haste</l>
<l>sped through the hostile army to the tent</l>
<l>of Minos, whom, astonished, she addressed:</l>

    
<l>“Only my love has led me to this deed.</l>
<l>The daughter of King Nisus, I am called</l>
<l>the maiden Scylla. Unto you I come</l>
<l>and offer up a power that will prevail</l>
<l>against my country, and I stipulate</l>
<l>no recompense except yourself. Take then</l>
<l>this purple hair, a token of my love.—</l>
<l>Deem it not lightly as a lock of hair</l>
<l>held idly forth to you; it is in truth</l>
<l>my father's life.” And as she spoke</l>
<l>she held out in her guilty hand the prize,</l>
<l>and begged him to accept it with her love.</l>

    
<l>Shocked at the thought of such a heinous crime,</l>
<l>Minos refused, and said, “O execrable thing!</l>
<l>Despised abomination of our time!</l>
<l>May all the Gods forever banish you</l>
<l>from their wide universe, and may the earth</l>
<l>and the deep ocean be denied to you!</l>
<l>So great a monster shall not be allowed</l>
<l>to desecrate the sacred Isle of Crete,</l>
<l>where Jupiter was born.” So Minos spoke.</l>

    
<l>Nevertheless he conquered Megara,</l>
<l>(so aided by the damsel's wicked deed)</l>
<l>and as a just and mighty king imposed</l>
<l>his own conditions on the vanquished land.</l>

    
<l>He ordered his great fleet to tarry not;</l>
<l>the hawsers were let loose, and the long oars</l>
<l>quickly propelled his brazen-pointed ships.—</l>

    
<l>When Scylla saw them launching forth,</l>
<l>observed them sailing on the mighty deep,</l>
<l>she called with vain entreaties; but at last,</l>
<l>aware the prince ignored her and refused</l>
<l>to recompense her wickedness, enraged,</l>
<l>and raving, she held up her impious hands,</l>
<l>her long hair streaming on the wind, — and said:</l>

    
<l>“Oh, wherefore have you flown, and left behind</l>
<l>the author of your glory. Oh, wretch! wretch</l>
<l>to whom I offered up my native land,</l>
<l>and sacrificed my father! Where have you</l>
<l>now flown, ungrateful man whose victory</l>
<l>is both my crime and virtue? And the gift</l>
<l>presented to you, and my passion,</l>
<l>have these not moved you? All my love and hope</l>
<l>in you alone!</l>

    
<l>“Forsaken by my prince,</l>
<l>shall I return to my defeated land?</l>
<l>If never ruined it would shut its walls</l>
<l>against me.—Shall I seek my father's face</l>
<l>whom I delivered to all-conquering arms?</l>
<l>My fellow-citizens despise my name;</l>
<l>my friends and neighbors hate me; I have shut</l>
<l>the world against me, only in the hope</l>
<l>that Crete would surely welcome me;—and now,</l>
<l>he has forbidden me.</l>

    
<l>“And is it so</l>
<l>I am requited by this thankless wretch!</l>
<l>Europa could not be your mother! Spawn</l>
<l>of cruel Syrtis! Savage cub of fierce</l>
<l>Armenian tigress;—or Charybdis, tossed</l>
<l>by the wild South-wind begot you! Can you be</l>
<l>the son of Jupiter? Your mother was</l>
<l>not ever tricked by the false semblance</l>
<l>of a bull. All that story of your birth</l>
<l>is false! You are the offspring of a bull</l>
<l>as fierce as you are!</l>

    
<l>“Let your vengeance fall</l>
<l>upon me, O my father Nisus, let</l>
<l>the ruined city I betrayed rejoice</l>
<l>at my misfortunes—richly merited—</l>
<l>destroy me, you whom I have ruined;—I</l>
<l>should perish for my crimes! But why should you,</l>
<l>who conquered by my crime, abandon me?</l>
<l>The treason to my father and my land</l>
<l>becomes an act of kindness in your cause.</l>

    
<l>“That woman is a worthy mate for you</l>
<l>who hid in wood deceived the raging bull,</l>
<l>and bore to him the infamy of Crete.</l>
<l>I do not wonder that Pasiphae</l>
<l>preferred the bull to you, more savage than</l>
<l>the wildest beast. Alas, alas for me!</l>

    
<l>“Do my complaints reach your unwilling ears?</l>
<l>Or do the same winds waft away my words</l>
<l>that blow upon your ships, ungrateful man?—</l>
<l>Ah, wretched that I am, he takes delight</l>
<l>in hastening from me. The deep waves resound</l>
<l>as smitten by the oars, his ship departs;</l>
<l>and I am lost and even my native land</l>
<l>is fading from his sight.</l>

    
<l>“Oh heart of flint!</l>
<l>you shall not prosper in your cruelty,</l>
<l>and you shall not forget my sacrifice;</l>
<l>in spite of everything I follow you!</l>
<l>I'll grasp the curving stern of your swift ship,</l>
<l>and I will follow through unending seas.”</l>

    
<l>And as she spoke, she leaped into the waves,</l>
<l>and followed the receding ships—for strength</l>
<l>from passion came to her. And soon she clung</l>
<l>unwelcome, to the sailing Gnossian ship.</l>

    
<l>Meanwhile, the Gods had changed her father's form</l>
<l>and now he hovered over the salt deep,</l>
<l>a hawk with tawny wings. So when he saw</l>
<l>his daughter clinging to the hostile ship</l>
<l>he would have torn her with his rending beak;—</l>
<l>he darted towards her through the yielding air.</l>
<l>In terror she let go, but as she fell</l>
<l>the light air held her from the ocean spray;</l>
<l>her feather-weight supported by the breeze;</l>
<l>she spread her wings, and changed into a bird.</l>
<l>They called her “Ciris” when she cut the wind,</l>
<l>and “Ciris”—cut-the-lock—remains her name.</l>


Labyrinthus. Ariadnes corona.
MINOS AND THE MINOTAUR

<l>King Minos, when he reached the land of Crete</l>
<l>and left his ships, remembered he had made</l>
<l>a vow to Jupiter, and offered up</l>
<l>a hundred bulls.—The splendid spoils of war</l>
<l>adorned his palace.—</l>

    
<l>Now the infamous</l>
<l>reproach of Crete had grown, till it exposed</l>
<l>the double-natured shame. So, Minos, moved</l>
<l>to cover his disgrace, resolved to hide</l>
<l>the monster in a prison, and he built</l>
<l>with intricate design, by Daedalus</l>
<l>contrived, an architect of wonderful</l>
<l>ability, and famous. This he planned</l>
<l>of mazey wanderings that deceived the eyes,</l>
<l>and labyrinthic passages involved. </l>
<l>so sports the clear Maeander, in the fields</l>
<l>of Phrygia winding doubtful; back and forth</l>
<l>it meets itself, until the wandering stream</l>
<l>fatigued, impedes its wearied waters' flow;</l>
<l>from source to sea, from sea to source involved.</l>
<l>So Daedalus contrived innumerous paths,</l>
<l>and windings vague, so intricate that he,</l>
<l>the architect, hardly could retrace his steps.</l>

    
<l>In this the Minotaur was long concealed,</l>
<l>and there devoured Athenian victims sent</l>
<l>three seasons, nine years each, till Theseus, son</l>
<l>of Aegeus, slew him and retraced his way,</l>
<l>finding the path by Ariadne's thread.</l>

    
<l>Without delay the victor fled from Crete,</l>
<l>together with the loving maid, and sailed</l>
<l>for Dia Isle of Naxos, where he left</l>
<l>the maid forlorn, abandoned. Her, in time,</l>
<l>lamenting and deserted, Bacchus found</l>
<l>and for his love immortalized her name.</l>

    
<l>He set in the dark heavens the bright crown</l>
<l>that rested on her brows. Through the soft air</l>
<l>it whirled, while all the sparkling jewels changed</l>
<l>to flashing fires, assuming in the sky</l>
<l>between the Serpent-holder and the Kneeler</l>
<l>the well-known shape of Ariadne's Crown.</l>


Daedalus et Icarus. Perdix.
DAEDALUS AND ICARUS

<l>But Daedalus abhorred the Isle of Crete—</l>
<l>and his long exile on that sea-girt shore,</l>
<l>increased the love of his own native place.</l>
<l>“Though Minos blocks escape by sea and land.”</l>
<l>He said, “The unconfined skies remain</l>
<l>though Minos may be lord of all the world</l>
<l>his sceptre is not regnant of the air,</l>
<l>and by that untried way is our escape.”</l>

    
<l>This said, he turned his mind to arts unknown</l>
<l>and nature unrevealed. He fashioned quills</l>
<l>and feathers in due order — deftly formed</l>
<l>from small to large, as any rustic pipe</l>
<l>prom straws unequal slants. He bound with thread</l>
<l>the middle feathers, and the lower fixed</l>
<l>with pliant wax; till so, in gentle curves</l>
<l>arranged, he bent them to the shape of birds.</l>

    
<l>While he was working, his son Icarus,</l>
<l>with smiling countenance and unaware</l>
<l>of danger to himself, perchance would chase</l>
<l>the feathers, ruffled by the shifting breeze,</l>
<l>or soften with his thumb the yellow wax,</l>
<l>and by his playfulness retard the work</l>
<l>his anxious father planned.</l>

    
<l>But when at last</l>
<l>the father finished it, he poised himself,</l>
<l>and lightly floating in the winnowed air</l>
<l>waved his great feathered wings with bird-like ease.</l>
<l>And, likewise he had fashioned for his son</l>
<l>such wings; before they ventured in the air</l>
<l>he said, “My son, I caution you to keep</l>
<l>the middle way, for if your pinions dip</l>
<l>too low the waters may impede your flight;</l>
<l>and if they soar too high the sun may scorch them.</l>
<l>Fly midway. Gaze not at the boundless sky,</l>
<l>far Ursa Major and Bootes next.</l>
<l>Nor on Orion with his flashing brand,</l>
<l>but follow my safe guidance.”</l>

    
<l>As he spoke</l>
<l>he fitted on his son the plumed wings</l>
<l>with trembling hands, while down his withered cheeks</l>
<l>the tears were falling. Then he gave his son</l>
<l>a last kiss, and upon his gliding wings</l>
<l>assumed a careful lead solicitous.</l>
<l>As when the bird leads forth her tender young,</l>
<l>from high-swung nest to try the yielding air;</l>
<l>so he prevailed on willing Icarus;</l>
<l>encouraged and instructed him in a]l</l>
<l>the fatal art; and as he waved his wings</l>
<l>looked backward on his son.</l>

    
<l>Beneath their flight,</l>
<l>the fisherman while casting his long rod,</l>
<l>or the tired shepherd leaning on his crook,</l>
<l>or the rough plowman as he raised his eyes,</l>
<l>astonished might observe them on the wing,</l>
<l>and worship them as Gods.</l>

    
<l>Upon the left</l>
<l>they passed by Samos, Juno's sacred isle;</l>
<l>Delos and Paros too, were left behind;</l>
<l>and on the right Lebinthus and Calymne,</l>
<l>fruitful in honey. Proud of his success,</l>
<l>the foolish Icarus forsook his guide,</l>
<l>and, bold in vanity, began to soar,</l>
<l>rising upon his wings to touch the skies;</l>
<l>but as he neared the scorching sun, its heat</l>
<l>softened the fragrant wax that held his plumes;</l>
<l>and heat increasing melted the soft wax—</l>
<l>he waved his naked arms instead of wings,</l>
<l>with no more feathers to sustain his flight.</l>
<l>And as he called upon his father's name</l>
<l>his voice was smothered in the dark blue sea,</l>
<l>now called Icarian from the dead boy's name.</l>

    
<l>The unlucky father, not a father, called,</l>
<l>“Where are you, Icarus?” and “Where are you?</l>
<l>In what place shall I seek you, Icarus?”</l>
<l>He called again; and then he saw the wings</l>
<l>of his dear Icarus, floating on the waves;</l>
<l>and he began to rail and curse his art.</l>

    
<l>He found the body on an island shore,</l>
<l>now called Icaria, and at once prepared</l>
<l>to bury the unfortunate remains;</l>
<l>but while he labored a pert partridge near,</l>
<l>observed him from the covert of an oak,</l>
<l>and whistled his unnatural delight.</l>

    
<l>Know you the cause? 'Twas then a single bird,</l>
<l>the first one of its kind. 'Twas never seen</l>
<l>before the sister of Daedalus had brought</l>
<l>him Perdix, her dear son, to be his pupil.</l>
<l>And as the years went by the gifted youth</l>
<l>began to rival his instructor's art.</l>

    
<l>He took the jagged backbone of a fish,</l>
<l>and with it as a model made a saw,</l>
<l>with sharp teeth fashioned from a strip of iron.</l>
<l>And he was first to make two arms of iron,</l>
<l>smooth hinged upon the center, so that one</l>
<l>would make a pivot while the other, turned,</l>
<l>described a circle. Wherefore Daedalus</l>
<l>enraged and envious, sought to slay the youth</l>
<l>and cast him headlong from Minerva's fane,—</l>
<l>then spread the rumor of an accident.</l>

    
<l>But Pallas, goddess of ingenious men,</l>
<l>saving the pupil changed him to a bird,</l>
<l>and in the middle of the air he flew</l>
<l>on feathered wings; and so his active mind—</l>
<l>and vigor of his genius were absorbed</l>
<l>into his wings and feet; although the name</l>
<l>of Perdix was retained.</l>

    
<l>The Partridge hides</l>
<l>in shaded places by the leafy trees</l>
<l>its nested eggs among the bush's twigs;</l>
<l>nor does it seek to rise in lofty flight,</l>
<l>for it is mindful of its former fall.</l>


Aper Calydonius. Meleager.

<l>Wearied with travel Daedalus arrived</l>
<l>at Sicily,—where Cocalus was king;</l>
<l>and when the wandering Daedalus implored</l>
<l>the monarch's kind protection from his foe,</l>
<l>he gathered a great army for his guest,</l>
<l>and gained renown from an applauding world.</l>


ATALANTA AND MELEAGER

<l>Now after Theseus had destroyed in Crete</l>
<l>the dreadful monster, Athens then had ceased</l>
<l>to pay her mournful tribute; and with wreaths</l>
<l>her people decked the temples of the Gods;</l>
<l>and they invoked Minerva, Jupiter,</l>
<l>and many other Gods whom they adored,</l>
<l>with sacrifice and precious offerings,</l>
<l>and jars of Frankincense.</l>

    
<l>Quick-flying Fame</l>
<l>had spread reports of Theseus through the land;</l>
<l>and all the peoples of Achaia, from that day,</l>
<l>when danger threatened would entreat his aid.</l>
<l>So it befell, the land of Calydon,</l>
<l>through Meleager and her native hero,</l>
<l>implored the valiant Theseus to destroy</l>
<l>a raging boar, the ravage of her realm.</l>

    
<l>Diana in her wrath had sent the boar</l>
<l>to wreak her vengeance; and they say the cause</l>
<l>was this:—The nation had a fruitful year,</l>
<l>for which the good king Oeneus had decreed</l>
<l>that all should offer the first fruits of corn</l>
<l>to Ceres—and to Bacchus wine of grapes—</l>
<l>and oil of olives to the golden haired</l>
<l>Minerva. Thus, the Gods were all adored,</l>
<l>beginning with the lowest to the highest,</l>
<l>except alone Diana, and of all the Gods</l>
<l>her altars only were neglected. No</l>
<l>frankincense unto her was given! Neglect</l>
<l>enrages even Deities.</l>

    
<l>“Am I</l>
<l>to suffer this indignity?” she cried,</l>
<l>“Though I am thus dishonored, I will not</l>
<l>be unrevenged!” And so the boar was sent</l>
<l>to ravage the fair land of Calydon.</l>

    
<l>And this avenging boar was quite as large</l>
<l>as bulls now feeding on the green Epirus,</l>
<l>and larger than the bulls of Sicily.</l>
<l>A dreadful boar.—His burning, bloodshot eyes</l>
<l>seemed coals of living fire, and his rough neck</l>
<l>was knotted with stiff muscles, and thick-set</l>
<l>with bristles like sharp spikes. A seething froth</l>
<l>dripped on his shoulders, and his tusks</l>
<l>were like the spoils of Ind. Discordant roars</l>
<l>reverberated from his hideous jaws;</l>
<l>and lightning—belched forth from his horrid throat—</l>
<l>scorched the green fields. He trampled the green corn</l>
<l>and doomed the farmer to lament his crops,</l>
<l>in vain the threshing-floor has been prepared,</l>
<l>in vain the barns await the promised yield.</l>
<l>Long branches of the vine and heavy grapes</l>
<l>are scattered in confusion, and the fruits</l>
<l>and branches of the olive tree, whose leaves</l>
<l>should never wither, are cast on the ground.</l>

    
<l>His spleen was vented on the simple flocks,</l>
<l>which neither dogs nor shepherd could protect;</l>
<l>and the brave bulls could not defend their herds.</l>
<l>The people fled in all directions from the fields,</l>
<l>for safety to the cities. Terror reigned.</l>
<l>There seemed no remedy to save the land,</l>
<l>till Meleager chose a band of youths,</l>
<l>united for the glory of great deeds.</l>

    
<l>What heroes shall immortal song proclaim?</l>
<l>Castor and Pollux, twins of Tyndarus;</l>
<l>one famous for his skill in horsemanship,</l>
<l>the other for his boxing. Jason, too, was there,</l>
<l>the glorious builder of the world's first ship,</l>
<l>and Theseus with his friend Perithous,</l>
<l>and Toxeus and Plexippus, fated sons</l>
<l>of Thestius, and the son of Aphareus,</l>
<l>Lynkeus with his fleet-foot brother Idas</l>
<l>and Caeneus, first a woman then a man</l>
<l>the brave Leucippus and the argonaut</l>
<l>Acastus, swift of dart; and warlike Dryas,</l>
<l>Hippothous and Phoenix, not then blind,</l>
<l>the son of King Amyntor, and the twain</l>
<l>who sprung from Actor, Phyleus thither brought</l>
<l>from Elis; Telamon was one of them</l>
<l>and even Peleus, father of the great</l>
<l>Achilles; and the son of Pheres joined,</l>
<l>and Iolas, the swift Eurytion,</l>
<l>Echion fleet of foot, Narycian Lelex—</l>
<l>and Panopeus, and Hyleus and Hippasus,</l>
<l>and Nestor (youthful then), and the four sons</l>
<l>Hippocoon from eld Amyclae sent,</l>
<l>the father-in-law of queen Penelope,</l>
<l>Ancaeus of Arcadia, and the wise</l>
<l>soothsayer Mopsus, and the prophet, son</l>
<l>of Oeclus, victim of a traitor-wife.—</l>

    
<l>And Atalanta, virgin of the groves,</l>
<l>of Mount Lycaeus, glory of her sex;</l>
<l>a polished buckle fastened her attire;</l>
<l>her lustrous hair was fashioned in a knot;</l>
<l>her weapons rattled in an ivory case,</l>
<l>swung from her white left shoulder, and she held</l>
<l>a bow in her left hand. Her face appeared</l>
<l>as maidenly for boy, or boyish for girl.</l>

    
<l>When Meleager saw her, he at once</l>
<l>longed for her beauty, though some god forbade.</l>
<l>The fires of love flamed in him; and he said,</l>
<l>“Happy the husband who shall win this girl!”</l>
<l>Neither the time nor his own modesty</l>
<l>permitted him to say another word.</l>
<l>But now the dreadful contest with the boar</l>
<l>engaged this hero's energy and thought.</l>

    
<l>A wood, umbrageous, not impaired with age,</l>
<l>slopes from a plain and shadows the wide fields,</l>
<l>and there this band of valiant heroes went—</l>
<l>eager to slay the dreaded enemy,</l>
<l>some spread the nets and some let loose the dogs,</l>
<l>some traced the wide spoor of the monster's hoofs.</l>

    
<l>There is a deep gorge where the rivulets</l>
<l>that gather from the rain, discharge themselves;</l>
<l>and there the bending willow, the smooth sedge,</l>
<l>the marsh-rush, ozier and tall tangled reed</l>
<l>in wild profusion cover up the marsh.</l>
<l>Aroused from this retreat the startled boar,</l>
<l>as quick as lightning from the clashing clouds</l>
<l>crashed all the trees that cumbered his mad way.—</l>

    
<l>The young men raised a shout, leveled their spears,</l>
<l>and brandished their keen weapons; but the boar</l>
<l>rushed onward through the yelping dogs,</l>
<l>and scattered them with deadly sidelong stroke.</l>

    
<l>Echion was the first to hurl his spear,</l>
<l>but slanting in its course it only glanced</l>
<l>a nearby maple tree, and next the spear</l>
<l>of long-remembered Jason cut the air;</l>
<l>so swiftly hurled it seemed it might transfix</l>
<l>the boar's back, but with over-force it sped</l>
<l>beyond the monster. Poising first his dart,</l>
<l>the son of Ampyx, as he cast it, he</l>
<l>implored Apollo, “Grant my prayer if I</l>
<l>have truly worshiped you, harken to me</l>
<l>as always I adore you! Let my spear</l>
<l>unerring strike its aim.” Apollo heard,</l>
<l>and guided the swift spear, but as it sped</l>
<l>Diana struck the iron head from the shaft,</l>
<l>and the blunt wood fell harmless from his hide.</l>

    
<l>Then was the monster's savage anger roused;</l>
<l>as the bright lightning's flash his red eyes flamed;</l>
<l>his breath was hot as fire. As when a stone</l>
<l>is aimed at walls or strong towers, which protect</l>
<l>encompassed armies,—launched by the taut rope</l>
<l>it strikes with dreaded impact; so the boar</l>
<l>with fatal onset rushed among this band</l>
<l>of noble lads, and stretched upon the ground</l>
<l>Eupalamon and Pelagon whose guard</l>
<l>was on the right; and their companions bore</l>
<l>their bodies from the field.</l>

    
<l>Another youth,</l>
<l>the brave son of Hippocoon received</l>
<l>a deadly wound—while turning to escape,</l>
<l>the sinew of his thigh was cut and failed</l>
<l>to bear his tottering steps.—
And Nestor might</l>
<l>have perished then, so long before he fought</l>
<l>the heroes of old Troy, but ever wise,</l>
<l>he vaulted on his long lance from the ground</l>
<l>into the branches of a sheltering tree;</l>
<l>where in a safe position, he could look</l>
<l>down on his baffled foe. The raging boar</l>
<l>whetted his gleaming tushes on an oak.</l>

    
<l>Then with his sharpened tusks he gored the thigh</l>
<l>of mighty Hippasus. Observed of all,</l>
<l>and mounted on their horses—whiter than</l>
<l>the northern snow—the twins (long afterward</l>
<l>transformed to constellations) sallied forth,</l>
<l>and brandishing their lances, poised in air,</l>
<l>determined to destroy the bristling boar.</l>
<l>It thwarted their design by hiding in</l>
<l>a thicket intricate; where neither steed</l>
<l>nor lance could penetrate. But Telamon</l>
<l>pursued undaunted, and in haste tripped up</l>
<l>by tangled roots, fell headlong.—Peleus stooped</l>
<l>to rescue him.</l>

    
<l>While he regained his feet,</l>
<l>the virgin, Atalanta, took her bow</l>
<l>and fitting a sharp arrow to the notch,</l>
<l>twanged the tight cord. The feathered shaft</l>
<l>quivered beneath the monster's ear, the red blood</l>
<l>stained his hard bristles.</l>

    
<l>Flushed with her success</l>
<l>rejoiced the maid, but not more gladly than</l>
<l>the hero Meleager. He it was</l>
<l>who first observed the blood, and pointed out</l>
<l>the stain to his companions as he cried,</l>
<l>“Give honor to the courage of a maid!”</l>
<l>Unwilling to be worsted by a maid,</l>
<l>the rushing heroes raised a mighty cry</l>
<l>and as they shouted in excitement, hurled</l>
<l>their weapons in confusion; and so great</l>
<l>the multitude their actions interfered.</l>

    
<l>Behold! Ancaeus wielding his war-axe,</l>
<l>and rushing madly to his fate, exclaimed,</l>
<l>“Witness it! See the weapons of a man</l>
<l>excel a woman's! Ho, make way for my</l>
<l>achievement! Let Diana shield the brute!</l>
<l>Despite her utmost effort my right hand</l>
<l>shall slaughter him!” So mighty in his boast</l>
<l>he puffed himself; and, lifting with both hands</l>
<l>his double-edged axe, he stood erect,</l>
<l>on tiptoe fiercely bold. The savage boar</l>
<l>caught him, and ripped his tushes through his groin,</l>
<l>a spot where death is sure.—Ancaeus fell;</l>
<l>and his torn entrails and his crimson blood</l>
<l>stained the fair verdure of the spot with death.</l>

    
<l>Ixion's doughty son was running straight</l>
<l>against the monster, shaking his long lance</l>
<l>with nervous vigor in his strong right hand;</l>
<l>but Theseus, standing at a distance called:</l>
<l>“Beware! beware, O, dearest of my friends;</l>
<l>be valiant at a distance, or the fate</l>
<l>of rashly-bold Ancaeus may be yours!”</l>

    
<l>Even as he spoke he balanced in his hand</l>
<l>his brazen-pointed lance of corner wood;</l>
<l>with aim so true it seemed the great boar's death</l>
<l>was certain, but an evergreen oak branch</l>
<l>shielded the beast.—Then Jason hurled his dart,</l>
<l>which turned by chance, transfixed a luckless dog</l>
<l>and pinned him yelping, to the sanguine earth.—</l>

    
<l>So fared those heroes. Better fortune gave</l>
<l>success to Meleager; first he threw</l>
<l>a spear that missed and quivered in the ground;</l>
<l>but next he hurled a spear with certain aim.</l>
<l>It pierced the middle of the monster's back;</l>
<l>and rushing in upon the dreaded beast,</l>
<l>while raging it was whirling round and round,</l>
<l>the fearless prince provoked to greater rage</l>
<l>the wounded adversary. Bloody froth</l>
<l>dripped down his champing jaws—his purple blood</l>
<l>poured from a rankling wound. Without delay</l>
<l>the mighty Meleager plunged a spear</l>
<l>deep in the monster's shoulder. All his friends</l>
<l>raised a glad shout, and gathering round him, tried</l>
<l>to grasp his hand.—With wonder they beheld</l>
<l>the monster's bulk stretched out upon the plain;</l>
<l>and fearful still to touch him, they began</l>
<l>to stain their weapons in his spouting blood.</l>

    
<l>At length the hero Meleager pressed</l>
<l>his conquering foot upon the monster's head</l>
<l>and said, “O Atalanta, glorious maid,</l>
<l>of Nonacris, to you is yielded spoil,</l>
<l>my lawful right, and I rejoice to share</l>
<l>the merit of this glorious victory.”</l>

    
<l>And while he spoke, he gave to her the pelt,</l>
<l>covered with horrid bristles, and the head</l>
<l>frightful with gory tusks: and she rejoiced</l>
<l>in Meleager and his royal gift.</l>

    
<l>But all the others, envious, began</l>
<l>to murmur; and the sons of Thestius</l>
<l>levelled their pointed spears, and shouted out;</l>
<l>“Give up the prize! Let not the confidence</l>
<l>of your great beauty be a snare to you!</l>
<l>A woman should not interfering filch</l>
<l>the manly honors of a mighty hunt!</l>
<l>Aside! and let your witless lover yield!”</l>
<l>So threatened they and took from her the prize;</l>
<l>and forcibly despoiled him of his rights.</l>

    
<l>The warlike prince, indignant and enraged,—</l>
<l>rowed with resentment, shouted out. “What! Ho!</l>
<l>You spoilers of this honor that is ours,</l>
<l>brave deeds are different far from craven threats!”</l>
<l>And with his cruel sword he pierced the breast</l>
<l>of rash Plexippus, taken unawares,</l>
<l>and while his brother, Toxeus, struck with fear,</l>
<l>stood hesitating whether to avenge</l>
<l>or run to safety, Meleager plunged</l>
<l>the hot sword, smoking with a brother's blood,</l>
<l>in his breast also. And so perished they.</l>

ALTHAEA AND THE DEATH OF MELEAGER

<l>Ere this, Althaea, mother of the prince,</l>
<l>and sister of the slaughtered twain,—because</l>
<l>her son had killed the boar, made haste to bear</l>
<l>rich offerings to the temples of the Gods;</l>
<l>but when she saw her slaughtered brothers borne</l>
<l>in sad procession, she began to shriek,</l>
<l>and filled the city with her wild lament.</l>
<l>Unwilling to abide her festal robes</l>
<l>she dressed in sable.—When she was informed</l>
<l>her own son Meleager was the cause,</l>
<l>she banished grief and lamentations,—</l>
<l>thirsting for vengeance.</l>


    
<l>She remembered well,</l>
<l>how, when she lay in childbirth round her stood</l>
<l>the three attendant sisters of his fate.</l>
<l>There was a billet in the room, and this</l>
<l>they took and cast upon the wasting flames,</l>
<l>and as they spun and drew the fatal threads</l>
<l>they softly chanted, “Unto you we give,</l>
<l>O child new-born! only the life of this;</l>
<l>the period of this billet is your life.”</l>
<l>And having spoken so, they vanished in the smoke.</l>

    
<l>Althaea snatched the billet from the fire,</l>
<l>and having quenched it with drawn water, hid</l>
<l>it long and secretly in her own room,</l>
<l>where, thus preserved, it acted as a charm</l>
<l>to save the life of Meleager. This</l>
<l>the mother now brought forth, and fetched a pile</l>
<l>of seasoned tinder ready for the torch.</l>
<l>She lit the torches and the ready pile,</l>
<l>and as the flames leaped up, four times prepared</l>
<l>to cast the fatal billet in the midst;</l>
<l>and four times hesitated to commit</l>
<l>the dreadful deed,—so long the contest veered</l>
<l>between the feelings of a mother's breast</l>
<l>and the fierce vengeance of a sister's rage.</l>

    
<l>Now is the mother's visage pale with fear,</l>
<l>and now the sister's sanguinary rage</l>
<l>glows in her eyes. Her countenance contorts</l>
<l>with cruel threats and in bewildered ways</l>
<l>dissolves compassionate: And even when</l>
<l>the heat of anger had dried up her eyes</l>
<l>the conflict of her passion brought new tears.</l>

    
<l>As when the wind has seized upon a ship</l>
<l>and blows against a tide of equal force,</l>
<l>the vexed vessel feels repellent powers,</l>
<l>and with unsteady motion sways to both;</l>
<l>so did Althaea hesitate between</l>
<l>the conflict of her passions: when her rage</l>
<l>had cooled, her fury was as fast renewed:</l>
<l>but always the unsatisfied desire</l>
<l>of blood, to ease the disembodied shades</l>
<l>of her slain brothers, seemed to overcome</l>
<l>the mother-instinct; and intensity</l>
<l>of conduct proved the utmost test of love.</l>

    
<l>She took the billet in her arms and stood</l>
<l>before the leaping flames, and said, “Alas,</l>
<l>be this the funeral pyre of my own flesh!”</l>
<l>And as she held in her relentless hand</l>
<l>the destiny of him she loved, and stood</l>
<l>before the flames, in all her wretchedness</l>
<l>she moaned, “You sad Eumenides attend!</l>
<l>Relentless Gods of punishment,—turn, turn</l>
<l>your dreadful vision on these baneful rites!</l>
<l>I am avenging and committing crime!</l>
<l>With death must death be justified and crime</l>
<l>be added unto crime! Let funerals</l>
<l>upon succeeding funerals attend!</l>

    
<l>“Let these accumulating woes destroy</l>
<l>a wicked race. Shall happy Oeneus bask</l>
<l>in the great fame of his victorious son,</l>
<l>and Thestius mourn without slaughtered ones?</l>
<l>'Tis better they should both lament the deed!</l>
<l>Witness the act of my affection, shades</l>
<l>of my departed brothers! and accept</l>
<l>my funeral offering, given at a cost</l>
<l>beyond my strength to bear. Ah wretched me!</l>
<l>Distracted is my reason! Pity me,</l>
<l>the yearnings of a stricken mother's heart</l>
<l>withholding me from duty! Aye, although</l>
<l>his punishment be just, my hands refuse</l>
<l>the office of such vengeance. What, shall he</l>
<l>alive, victorious, flushed with his success,</l>
<l>inherit the broad realms of Calydon,</l>
<l>and you, my slaughtered brothers, unavenged,</l>
<l>dissolved in ashes, float upon the air,</l>
<l>unpalpitating phantoms? How can I</l>
<l>endure the thought of it? Oh let the wretch</l>
<l>forever perish, and with him be lost</l>
<l>the hopes of his sad father, in the wreck</l>
<l>of his distracted kingdom. Where are now</l>
<l>the love and feelings of a mother; how</l>
<l>can I forget the bitter pangs endured</l>
<l>while twice times five the slow moon waxed and waned?</l>

    
<l>“O had you perished in your infancy</l>
<l>by those first fires, and I had suffered it!</l>
<l>Your life was in my power! and now your death</l>
<l>is the result of wrongs which you have done—</l>
<l>take now a just reward for what you did:</l>
<l>return to me the life I gave and saved.</l>
<l>When from the flames I snatched the fatal brand.</l>
<l>Return that gift or take my wretched life,</l>
<l>that I may hasten to my brothers' tomb.</l>

    
<l>“What dreadful deed can satisfy the law,</l>
<l>when I for love against my love am forced?</l>
<l>For even as my brothers' wounds appear</l>
<l>in visions dreadful to denounce my son,</l>
<l>the love so nurtured in a mother's breast</l>
<l>breaks down the resolution! Wretched me!</l>
<l>Such vengeance for my brothers overcomes</l>
<l>first at your birth I gave it, and again</l>
<l>the yearning of a mother for her son!</l>
<l>Let not my love denounce my vengeance!</l>
<l>My soul may follow with its love the shade</l>
<l>of him I sacrifice, and following him</l>
<l>my shade and his and yours unite below.”</l>

    
<l>She spoke and as she turned her face away,</l>
<l>she threw the fatal billet on the fire,</l>
<l>and as the flames devoured it, a strange groan</l>
<l>was heard to issue from the burning wood</l>

    
<l>but Meleager at a distance knows</l>
<l>of naught to wreck his hour of victory,</l>
<l>until he feels the flame of burning wood</l>
<l>scorching with secret fire his forfeit life.</l>
<l>Yet with a mighty will, disdaining pain</l>
<l>he grieves his bloodless and ignoble death.</l>
<l>He calls Ancaeus happy for the wounds</l>
<l>that caused his death. With sighs and groans he called</l>
<l>his aged father's name, and then the names</l>
<l>of brothers, sisters, and his wife—and last,</l>
<l>they say he called upon his mother's name.</l>

    
<l>His torment always with the fire increased,</l>
<l>until, as little of the wood remained,—</l>
<l>his pain diminished with the heat's decrease;</l>
<l>and as the flames extinguished, so his life</l>
<l>slowly ascended in the rising air.</l>

    
<l>And all the mighty realm of Calydon</l>
<l>was filled with lamentations —young and old</l>
<l>the common people and the nobles mourned;</l>
<l>and all the wailing women tore their hair</l>
<l>his father threw his body on the ground,</l>
<l>and as he covered his white hair and face</l>
<l>with ashy dust, bewailed his aged days.</l>

    
<l>Althaea, maddened in her mother's grief,</l>
<l>has punished herself with a ruthless hand;</l>
<l>she pierced her heart with iron. —Oh! if some God</l>
<l>had given a resounding harp, a voice</l>
<l>an hundred-fold more mighty, and a soul</l>
<l>enlarged with genius, I could never tell</l>
<l>the grief of his unhappy sisters.—They,</l>
<l>regardless of all shame, beat on their breasts;</l>
<l>before the body was consumed with fire,</l>
<l>embraced it, and again embracing it,</l>
<l>rained kisses on their loved one and the bier.</l>
<l>And when the flames had burnt his shrinking form</l>
<l>they strained his gathered ashes to their breasts,</l>
<l>and prostrate on the tomb kissed his dear name,</l>
<l>cut only in the stone,—and bathed it with their tears</l>

    
<l>Latona's daughter, glutted with the woes</l>
<l>inflicted on Parthaon's house, now gave</l>
<l>two of the weeping sisters wide-spread wings,</l>
<l>but Gorge and the spouse of Hercules</l>
<l>not so were changed. Latona stretched long wings</l>
<l>upon their arms, transformed their mouths to beaks,</l>
<l>and sent them winging through the lucent air.</l>


Theseus apud Acheloum. Perimele.
PERIMELA AND ACHELOUS

<l>And Theseus, meantime, having done great deeds,</l>
<l>was wending towards Tritonian Athen's towers,</l>
<l>but Achelous, swollen with great rains,</l>
<l>opposed his journey and delayed his steps.</l>

    
<l>“O famous son of Athens, come to me,</l>
<l>beneath my roof, and leave my rapid floods;</l>
<l>for they are wont to bear enormous beams,</l>
<l>and hurl up heavy stones to bar the way,—</l>
<l>mighty with roaring, down the steep ravines.</l>
<l>And I have seen the sheep-folds on my banks</l>
<l>swept down the flood, together with the sheep;</l>
<l>and in the current neither strength availed</l>
<l>the ox for safety, nor swift speed the horse.</l>
<l>When rushed the melting snows from mountain peaks</l>
<l>how many bodies of unwary men</l>
<l>this flood has overwhelmed in whirling waves!</l>
<l>Rest safely then, until my river runs</l>
<l>within its usual bounds—till it contains</l>
<l>its flowing waters in its proper banks.”</l>

    
<l>and gladly answered Theseus, “I will make</l>
<l>good use of both your dwelling and advice.”</l>
<l>And waiting not he entered a rude hut,</l>
<l>of porous pumice and of rough stone built.</l>
<l>The floor was damp and soft with springy moss,</l>
<l>and rows of shells and murex arched the roof.</l>

    
<l>And now Hyperion having measured quite</l>
<l>two thirds of daylight, Theseus and his friends</l>
<l>reclined upon the couches.—On his right</l>
<l>Ixion's son was placed, and on his left</l>
<l>the gray-haired hero Lelex; and others</l>
<l>deemed worthy by the Acarnanian-god</l>
<l>who was so joyful in his noble guests.</l>
<l>Without delay the barefoot nimble Nymphs</l>
<l>attending to the banquet, rich food brought;</l>
<l>and after all were satisfied with meat</l>
<l>and dainties delicate, the careful Nymphs</l>
<l>removed all traces of the feast, and served</l>
<l>delicious wine in bowls embossed with gems.</l>

    
<l>And after they had eaten, Theseus arose,</l>
<l>and as he pointed with his finger, said,</l>
<l>“Declare to me what name that island bears,</l>
<l>or is it one or more than one I see?”</l>
<l>To which the ready River-God replied:</l>

    
<l>“It is not one we see but five are there,</l>
<l>deceptive in the distance. And that you</l>
<l>may wonder less at what Diana did,</l>
<l>those islands were five Naiads.—Long ago,</l>
<l>ten bullocks for a sacrifice they slew;</l>
<l>and when the joyous festival was given,</l>
<l>ignoring me they bade all other Gods.</l>
<l>Indignant at the slight, I swelled with rage</l>
<l>as great as ever when my banks are full,—</l>
<l>and so redoubled both in rage and flood,</l>
<l>I ravished woods from woods, and fields from fields,</l>
<l>and hurled into the sea the very soil,</l>
<l>together with the Nymphs, who then at last</l>
<l>remembered their neglect. And soon my waves,</l>
<l>united with the ocean streams, cut through</l>
<l>the solid soil, and fashioned from the one,</l>
<l>five islands you may see amid the waves,</l>
<l>which men since then, have called Echinades.</l>

    
<l>“But yet beyond you can observe how one</l>
<l>most beautiful of all is far withdrawn;</l>
<l>and this which most delights me, mariners</l>
<l>have Perimela named. She was so fair</l>
<l>that I deprived her of a precious wealth.</l>
<l>And when Hippodamas, her father, knew,</l>
<l>enraged he pushed her, heavy then with child,</l>
<l>forth from a rock into the cruel sea,</l>
<l>where she must perish,—but I rescued her;</l>
<l>and as I bore her on my swimming tide,</l>
<l>I called on Neptune, ruler of the deep,</l>
<l>‘O Trident-wielder, you who are preferred</l>
<l>next to the god most mighty! who by lot</l>
<l>obtained the empire of the flowing deep,</l>
<l>to which all sacred rivers flow and end;</l>
<l>come here, O Neptune, and with gracious will</l>
<l>grant my desire;—I injured her I save;—</l>
<l>but if Hippodamas, her father, when</l>
<l>he knew my love, had been both kind and just,</l>
<l>if he had not been so unnatural,</l>
<l>he would have pitied and forgiven her.</l>
<l>Ah, Neptune, I beseech you, grant your power</l>
<l>may find a place of safety for this Nymph,</l>
<l>abandoned to the deep waves by her sire.</l>
<l>Or if that cannot be, let her whom I</l>
<l>embrace to show my love, let her become</l>
<l>a place of safety.’ Instantly to me</l>
<l>the King of Ocean moved his mighty head,</l>
<l>and all the deep waves quivered in response.</l>

    
<l>“The Nymph, afraid, still struggled in the deep,</l>
<l>and as she swam I touched her throbbing breast;</l>
<l>and as I felt her bosom, trembling still,</l>
<l>I thought her soft flesh was becoming hard;</l>
<l>for even then, new earth enclosed her form;</l>
<l>and as I prayed to Neptune, earth encased</l>
<l>her floating limbs;—and on her changing form</l>
<l>the heavy soil of that fair island grew.”</l>


Philemon et Baucis.
BAUCIS AND PHILEMON

<l>And at this point, the River said no more.</l>
<l>This wonderful event astonished all;</l>
<l>but one was there, Ixion's haughty son—</l>
<l>a known despiser of the living Gods—</l>
<l>who, laughing, scorned it as an idle tale.</l>
<l>He made a jest of those who heard, and said,</l>

    
<l>“A foolish fiction! Achelous, how</l>
<l>can such a tale be true? Do you believe</l>
<l>a god there is, in heaven so powerful,</l>
<l>a god to give and take away a form—</l>
<l>transform created shapes?</l>

    
<l>Such impious words</l>
<l>found no response in those who heard him speak.</l>
<l>Amazed he could so doubt known truth, before</l>
<l>them all, uprose to vindicate the Gods</l>
<l>the hero Lelex, wise in length of days.</l>
<l>“The glory of the living Gods,” he said,</l>
<l>“Is not diminished, nor their power confined,</l>
<l>and whatsoever they decree is done.</l>

    
<l>“And I have this to tell, for all must know</l>
<l>the evil of such words:—Upon the hills</l>
<l>of Phrygia I have seen two sacred trees,</l>
<l>a lime-tree and an oak, so closely grown</l>
<l>their branches interlace. A low stone wall</l>
<l>is built around to guard them from all harm.</l>
<l>And that you may not doubt it, I declare</l>
<l>again, I saw the spot, for Pittheus there</l>
<l>had sent me to attend his father's court.</l>

    
<l>“Near by those trees are stagnant pools and fens,</l>
<l>where coots and cormorants delight to haunt;</l>
<l>but it was not so always. Long ago</l>
<l>'Twas visited by mighty Jupiter,</l>
<l>together with his nimble-witted son,</l>
<l>who first had laid aside his rod and Wings.</l>

    
<l>“As weary travelers over all the land</l>
<l>they wandered, begging for their food and bed;</l>
<l>and of a thousand houses, all the doors</l>
<l>were bolted and no word of kindness given—</l>
<l>so wicked were the people of that land.</l>
<l>At last, by chance, they stopped at a small house,</l>
<l>whose humble roof was thatched with reeds and straw;—</l>
<l>and here a kind old couple greeted them.</l>

    
<l>“The good dame, Baucis, seemed about the age</l>
<l>of old Philemon, her devoted man;</l>
<l>they had been married in their early youth,</l>
<l>in that same cottage and had lived in it,</l>
<l>and grown together to a good old age;</l>
<l>contented with their lot because they knew</l>
<l>their poverty, and felt no shame of it;</l>
<l>they had no need of servants; the good pair</l>
<l>were masters of their home and served themselves;</l>
<l>their own commands they easily obeyed.</l>

    
<l>“Now when the two Gods, Jove and Mercury,</l>
<l>had reached this cottage, and with bending necks</l>
<l>had entered the low door, the old man bade</l>
<l>them rest their wearied limbs, and set a bench,</l>
<l>on which his good wife, Baucis, threw a cloth;</l>
<l>and then with kindly bustle she stirred up</l>
<l>the glowing embers on the hearth, and then</l>
<l>laid tinder, leaves and bark; and bending down</l>
<l>breathed on them with her ancient breath until</l>
<l>they kindled into flame. Then from the house</l>
<l>she brought a store of faggots and small twigs,</l>
<l>and broken branches, and above them swung</l>
<l>a kettle, not too large for simple folk.</l>
<l>And all this done, she stripped some cabbage leaves,</l>
<l>which her good husband gathered for the meal.</l>

    
<l>“Then with a two-pronged fork the man let down</l>
<l>a rusty side of bacon from aloft,</l>
<l>and cut a little portion from the chine;</l>
<l>which had been cherished long. He softened it</l>
<l>in boiling water. All the while they tried</l>
<l>with cheerful conversation to beguile,</l>
<l>so none might notice a brief loss of time.</l>

    
<l>“Swung on a peg they had a beechwood trough,</l>
<l>which quickly with warm water filled, was used</l>
<l>for comfortable washing. And they fixed,</l>
<l>upon a willow couch, a cushion soft</l>
<l>of springy sedge, on which they neatly spread</l>
<l>a well worn cloth preserved so many years;</l>
<l>'Twas only used on rare and festive days;</l>
<l>and even it was coarse and very old,</l>
<l>though not unfit to match a willow couch!</l>

    
<l>“Now as the Gods reclined, the good old dame,</l>
<l>whose skirts were tucked up, moving carefully,</l>
<l>for so she tottered with her many years,</l>
<l>fetched a clean table for the ready meal—</l>
<l>but one leg of the table was too short,</l>
<l>and so she wedged it with a potsherd—so</l>
<l>made firm, she cleanly scoured it with fresh mint.</l>

    
<l>“And here is set the double-tinted fruit</l>
<l>of chaste Minerva, and the tasty dish</l>
<l>of corner, autumn-picked and pickled; these</l>
<l>were served for relish; and the endive-green,</l>
<l>and radishes surrounding a large pot</l>
<l>of curdled milk; and eggs not overdone</l>
<l>but gently turned in glowing embers—all</l>
<l>served up in earthen dishes. Then sweet wine</l>
<l>served up in clay, so costly! all embossed,</l>
<l>and cups of beechwood smoothed with yellow wax.</l>

    
<l>“So now they had short respite, till the fire</l>
<l>might yield the heated course.</l>

    
<l>“Again they served</l>
<l>new wine, but mellow; and a second course:</l>
<l>sweet nuts, dried figs and wrinkled dates and plums,</l>
<l>and apples fragrant, in wide baskets heaped;</l>
<l>and, in a wreath of grapes from purple vines,</l>
<l>concealed almost, a glistening honey-comb;</l>
<l>and all these orchard dainties were enhanced</l>
<l>by willing service and congenial smiles.</l>

    
<l>“But while they served, the wine-bowl often drained,</l>
<l>as often was replenished, though unfilled,</l>
<l>and Baucis and Philemon, full of fear,</l>
<l>as they observed the wine spontaneous well,</l>
<l>increasing when it should diminish, raised</l>
<l>their hands in supplication, and implored</l>
<l>indulgence for their simple home and fare.</l>
<l>And now, persuaded by this strange event</l>
<l>such visitors were deities unknown,</l>
<l>this aged couple, anxious to bestow</l>
<l>their most esteemed possession, hastily</l>
<l>began to chase the only goose they had—</l>
<l>the faithful guardian of their little home —</l>
<l>which they would kill and offer to the Gods.</l>
<l>But swift of wing, at last it wearied them,</l>
<l>and fled for refuge to the smiling Gods.</l>
<l>At once the deities forbade their zeal,</l>
<l>and said, ‘A righteous punishment shall fall</l>
<l>severe upon this wicked neighborhood;</l>
<l>but by the might of our divinity,</l>
<l>no evil shall befall this humble home;</l>
<l>but you must come, and follow as we climb</l>
<l>the summit of this mountain!’</l>

    
<l>“Both obeyed,</l>
<l>and leaning on their staves toiled up the steep.</l>
<l>Not farther from the summit than the flight</l>
<l>of one swift arrow from a hunter's how,</l>
<l>they paused to view their little home once more;</l>
<l>and as they turned their eyes, they saw the fields</l>
<l>around their own engulfed in a morass,</l>
<l>although their own remained,—and while they wept</l>
<l>bewailing the sad fate of many friends,</l>
<l>and wondered at the change, they saw their home,</l>
<l>so old and little for their simple need—</l>
<l>put on new splendor, and as it increased</l>
<l>it changed into a temple of the gods.</l>
<l>Where first the frame was fashioned of rude stakes</l>
<l>columns of marble glistened, and the thatch</l>
<l>gleamed golden in the sun, and legends carved,</l>
<l>adorned the doors. And al] the ground shone white</l>
<l>with marble rich, and after this was done,</l>
<l>the Son of Saturn said with gentle voice,</l>
<l>‘Now tell us, good old man and you his wife,</l>
<l>worthy and faithful, what is your desire?’</l>

    
<l>“Philemon counselled with old Baucis first;</l>
<l>and then discovered to the listening Gods</l>
<l>their hearts' desire, ‘We pray you let us have</l>
<l>the care of your new temple; and since we</l>
<l>have passed so many years in harmony,</l>
<l>let us depart this life together— Let</l>
<l>the same hour take us both—I would not see</l>
<l>the tomb of my dear wife; and let me not</l>
<l>be destined to be buried by her hands!’</l>

    
<l>“At once their wishes were fulfilled. So long</l>
<l>as life was granted they were known to be</l>
<l>the temple's trusted keepers, and when age</l>
<l>had enervated them with many years,</l>
<l>as they were standing, by some chance, before</l>
<l>the sacred steps, and were relating all</l>
<l>these things as they had happened, Baucis saw</l>
<l>Philemon, her old husband, and he, too,</l>
<l>saw Baucis, as their bodies put forth leaves;</l>
<l>and while the tops of trees grew over them,</l>
<l>above their faces, — they spoke each to each;</l>
<l>as long as they could speak they said, ‘Farewell,</l>
<l>farewell, my own’—and while they said farewell;</l>
<l>new leaves and branches covered both at once.</l>

    
<l>“The people of Tyana still point out</l>
<l>two trees which grew there from a double trunk,</l>
<l>two forms made into one. Old truthful men,</l>
<l>who have no reason to deceive me, told</l>
<l>me truly all that I have told to you,</l>
<l>and I have seen the votive wreaths hung from</l>
<l>the branches of the hallowed double-tree.</l>
<l>And one time, as I hung fresh garlands there,</l>
<l>I said, ‘Those whom the Gods care for are Gods!</l>
<l>And those who worshiped are now worshiped here.’”</l>


Erysichthon. Fames.
PROTEUS

<l>He ceased, and this miraculous event,</l>
<l>and he who told it, had astonished them.</l>
<l>But Theseus above all. The hero asked</l>
<l>to hear of other wonders wrought by Gods.</l>
<l>The Calydonian River-God replied,</l>
<l>and leaning on one elbow, said to him:</l>

    
<l>“There are, O valiant hero, other things</l>
<l>whose forms once-changed as these, have so remained,</l>
<l>but there are some who take on many shapes,</l>
<l>as you have, Proteus, dweller of the deep—</l>
<l>the deep whose arms embrace the earth. For some</l>
<l>have seen you as a youth, then as a lion,</l>
<l>a furious boar one time, a serpent next,</l>
<l>so dreadful to the touch—and sometimes horns</l>
<l>have made you seem a bull—or now a stone,</l>
<l>or now a tree, or now a slipping stream,</l>
<l>or even—the foe of water—next a fire.”</l>

ERYSICHTHON AND MESTRA

<l>Now Erysichthon's daughter, Mestra, had</l>
<l>that power of Proteus—she was called the wife</l>
<l>of deft Autolycus.—Her father spurned</l>
<l>the majesty of all the Gods, and gave</l>
<l>no honor to their altars. It is said</l>
<l>he violated with an impious axe</l>
<l>the sacred grove of Ceres, and he cut</l>
<l>her trees with iron. Long-standing in her grove</l>
<l>there grew an ancient oak tree, spread so wide,</l>
<l>alone it seemed a standing forest; and</l>
<l>its trunk and branches held memorials,</l>
<l>as, fillets, tablets, garlands, witnessing</l>
<l>how many prayers the goddess Ceres granted.</l>
<l>And underneath it laughing Dryads loved</l>
<l>to whirl in festal dances, hand in hand,</l>
<l>encircling its enormous trunk, that thrice</l>
<l>five ells might measure; and to such a height</l>
<l>it towered over all the trees around,</l>
<l>as they were higher than the grass beneath.</l>

    
<l>But Erysichthon, heedless of all things,</l>
<l>ordered his slaves to fell the sacred oak,</l>
<l>and as they hesitated, in a rage</l>
<l>the wretch snatched from the hand of one an axe,</l>
<l>and said, “If this should be the only oak</l>
<l>loved by the goddess of this very grove,</l>
<l>or even were the goddess in this tree,</l>
<l>I'll level to the ground its leafy head.”</l>
<l>So boasted he, and while he swung on high</l>
<l>his axe to strike a slanting blow, the oak</l>
<l>beloved of Ceres, uttered a deep groan</l>
<l>and shuddered. Instantly its dark green leaves</l>
<l>turned pale, and all its acorns lost their green,</l>
<l>and even its long branches drooped their arms.</l>
<l>But when his impious hand had struck the trunk,</l>
<l>and cut its bark, red blood poured from the wound,—</l>
<l>as when a weighty sacrificial bull</l>
<l>has fallen at the altar, streaming blood</l>
<l>spouts from his stricken neck. All were amazed.</l>
<l>And one of his attendants boldly tried</l>
<l>to stay his cruel axe, and hindered him;</l>
<l>but Erysichthon, fixing his stern eyes</l>
<l>upon him, said, “Let this, then, be the price</l>
<l>of all your pious worship!” So he turned</l>
<l>the poised axe from the tree, and clove his head</l>
<l>sheer from his body, and again began</l>
<l>to chop the hard oak. From the heart of it</l>
<l>these words were uttered; “Covered by the bark</l>
<l>of this oak tree I long have dwelt a Nymph,</l>
<l>beloved of Ceres, and before my death</l>
<l>it has been granted me to prophesy,</l>
<l>that I may die contented. Punishment</l>
<l>for this vile deed stands waiting at your side.”</l>

    
<l>No warning could avert his wicked arm.</l>
<l>Much weakened by his countless blows, the tree,</l>
<l>pulled down by straining ropes, gave way at last</l>
<l>and leveled with its weight uncounted trees</l>
<l>that grew around it. Terrified and shocked,</l>
<l>the sister-dryads, grieving for the grove</l>
<l>and what they lost, put on their sable robes</l>
<l>and hastened unto Ceres, whom they prayed,</l>
<l>might rightly punish Erysichthon's crime;—</l>
<l>the lovely goddess granted their request,</l>
<l>and by the gracious movement of her head</l>
<l>she shook the fruitful, cultivated fields,</l>
<l>then heavy with the harvest; and she planned</l>
<l>an unexampled punishment deserved,</l>
<l>and not beyond his miserable crimes—</l>
<l>the grisly bane of famine; but because</l>
<l>it is not in the scope of Destiny,</l>
<l>that two such deities should ever meet</l>
<l>as Ceres and gaunt Famine,—calling forth</l>
<l>from mountain-wilds a rustic Oread,</l>
<l>the goddess Ceres, said to her, “There is</l>
<l>an ice-bound wilderness of barren soil</l>
<l>in utmost Scythia, desolate and bare</l>
<l>of trees and corn, where Torpid-Frost, White-Death</l>
<l>and Palsy and Gaunt-Famine, hold their haunts;</l>
<l>go there now, and command that Famine flit</l>
<l>from there; and let her gnawing-essence pierce</l>
<l>the entrails of this sacrilegious wretch,</l>
<l>and there be hidden—Let her vanquish me</l>
<l>and overcome the utmost power of food.</l>
<l>Heed not misgivings of the journey's length,</l>
<l>for you will guide my dragon-bridled car</l>
<l>through lofty ether.”</l>


    
<l>And she gave to her</l>
<l>the reins; and so the swiftly carried Nymph</l>
<l>arrived in Scythia. There, upon the told</l>
<l>of steepy Caucasus, when she had slipped</l>
<l>their tight yoke from the dragons' harnessed necks,</l>
<l>she searched for Famine in that granite land,</l>
<l>and there she found her clutching at scant herbs,</l>
<l>with nails and teeth. Beneath her shaggy hair</l>
<l>her hollow eyes glared in her ghastly face,</l>
<l>her lips were filthy and her throat was rough</l>
<l>and blotched, and all her entrails could be seen,</l>
<l>enclosed in nothing but her shriveled skin;</l>
<l>her crooked loins were dry uncovered bones,</l>
<l>and where her belly should be was a void;</l>
<l>her flabby breast was flat against her spine;</l>
<l>her lean, emaciated body made</l>
<l>her joints appear so large, her knobbled knees</l>
<l>seemed large knots, and her swollen ankle-bones</l>
<l>protruded.</l>

    
<l>When the Nymph, with keen sight, saw</l>
<l>the Famine-monster, fearing to draw near</l>
<l>she cried aloud the mandate she had brought</l>
<l>from fruitful Ceres, and although the time</l>
<l>had been but brief, and Famine far away,</l>
<l>such hunger seized the Nymph, she had to turn</l>
<l>her dragon-steeds, and flee through yielding air</l>
<l>and the high clouds;—at Thessaly she stopped.</l>

    
<l>Grim Famine hastened to obey the will</l>
<l>of Ceres, though their deeds are opposite,</l>
<l>and rapidly through ether heights was borne</l>
<l>to Erysichthon's home. When she arrived</l>
<l>at midnight, slumber was upon the wretch,</l>
<l>and as she folded him in her two wings,</l>
<l>she breathed her pestilential poison through</l>
<l>his mouth and throat and breast, and spread the curse</l>
<l>of utmost hunger in his aching veins.</l>

    
<l>When all was done as Ceres had decreed,</l>
<l>she left the fertile world for bleak abodes,</l>
<l>and her accustomed caves. While this was done</l>
<l>sweet Sleep with charming pinion soothed the mind</l>
<l>of Erysichthon. In a dreamful feast</l>
<l>he worked his jaws in vain, and ground his teeth,</l>
<l>and swallowed air as his imagined food;</l>
<l>till wearied with the effort he awoke</l>
<l>to hunger scorching as a fire, which burned</l>
<l>his entrails and compelled his raging jaws,</l>
<l>so he, demanding all the foods of sea</l>
<l>and earth and air, raged of his hunger, while</l>
<l>the tables groaned with heaps before him spread;</l>
<l>he, banqueting, sought banquets for more food,</l>
<l>and as he gorged he always wanted more.</l>

    
<l>The food of cities and a nation failed</l>
<l>to satisfy the cravings of one man.</l>
<l>The more his stomach gets, the more it needs —</l>
<l>even as the ocean takes the streams of earth,</l>
<l>although it swallows up great rivers drawn</l>
<l>from lands remote, it never can be filled</l>
<l>nor satisfied. And as devouring fire</l>
<l>its fuel refuses never, but consumes</l>
<l>unnumbered beams of wood, and burns for more</l>
<l>the more 'tis fed, and from abundance gains</l>
<l>increasing famine, so the raving jaws</l>
<l>of wretched Erysichthon, ever craved</l>
<l>all food in him, was on]y cause of food,</l>
<l>and what he ate made only room for more.</l>

    
<l>And after Famine through his gluttony</l>
<l>at last had wasted his ancestral wealth</l>
<l>his raging hunger suffered no decline,</l>
<l>and his insatiate gluttony increased.</l>
<l>When all his wealth at last was eaten up,</l>
<l>his daughter, worthy of a fate more kind,</l>
<l>alone was left to him and her he sold.</l>
<l>Descendant of a noble race, the girl</l>
<l>refusing to be purchased as a slave,</l>
<l>then hastened to the near shore of the sea,</l>
<l>and as she stretched her arms above the waves,</l>
<l>implored kind Neptune with her tears, “Oh, you</l>
<l>who have deprived me of virginity,</l>
<l>deliver me from such a master's power!”</l>

    
<l>Although the master, seeking her, had seen</l>
<l>her only at that moment, Neptune changed</l>
<l>her quickly from a woman to a man,</l>
<l>by giving her the features of a man</l>
<l>and garments proper to a fisher-man:</l>
<l>and there she stood. He even looked at her</l>
<l>and cried out, “Hey, there! Expert of the rod!</l>
<l>While you are casting forth the bit of brass,</l>
<l>concealed so deftly in its tiny bait,—</l>
<l>gods-willing! let the sea be smooth for you,</l>
<l>and let the foolish fishes swimming up,</l>
<l>never know danger till they snap the hook!</l>
<l>Now tell me where is she, who only now,</l>
<l>in tattered garment and wind-twisted hair,</l>
<l>was standing on this shore—for I am sure</l>
<l>I saw her standing on this shore, although</l>
<l>no footstep shows her flight.”</l>

    
<l>By this assured</l>
<l>the favor of the god protected her;</l>
<l>delighted to be questioned of herself,</l>
<l>she said, “No matter who you are, excuse me.</l>
<l>So busy have I been at catching fish,</l>
<l>I have not had the time to move my eyes</l>
<l>from this pool; and that you may be assured</l>
<l>I only tell the truth, may Neptune, God</l>
<l>of ocean witness it, I have not seen a man</l>
<l>where I am standing on this shore—myself</l>
<l>excepted—not a woman has stood here.”</l>

    
<l>Her master could not doubt it, and deceived</l>
<l>retraced his footsteps from the sandy shore.</l>
<l>As soon as he had disappeared, her form</l>
<l>unchanged, was given back to her. But when</l>
<l>her father knew his daughter could transform</l>
<l>her body and escape, he often sold</l>
<l>her first to one and then another—all</l>
<l>of whom she cheated— as a mare, bird,</l>
<l>a cow, or as a stag she got away; and so</l>
<l>brought food, dishonestly, to ease his greed.</l>

    
<l>And so he lived until the growing strength</l>
<l>of famine, gnawing at his vitals, had</l>
<l>consumed all he could get by selling her:</l>
<l>his anguish burned him with increasing heat.</l>
<l>He gnawed his own flesh, and he tore his limbs</l>
<l>and fed his body all he took from it. </l>

    
<l>ah, why should I dwell on the wondrous deeds</l>
<l>of others—Even I, O gathered youths,</l>
<l>have such a power I can often change</l>
<l>my body till my limit has been reached.</l>
<l>A while appearing in my real form,</l>
<l>another moment coiled up as a snake,</l>
<l>then as a monarch of the herd my strength</l>
<l>increases in my horns—my strength increased</l>
<l>in my two horns when I had two—but now</l>
<l>my forehead, as you see, has lost one horn.</l>
<l>And having ended with such words,—he groaned.</l>
