<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 6


Pallas et Arachne.
ARACHNE AND MINERVA

<l>All this Minerva heard; and she approved</l>
<l>their songs and their resentment; but her heart</l>
<l>was brooding thus, “It is an easy thing</l>
<l>to praise another, I should do as they:</l>
<l>no creature of the earth should ever slight</l>
<l>the majesty that dwells in me,—without</l>
<l>just retribution.”—So her thought was turned</l>
<l>upon the fortune of Arachne — proud,</l>
<l>who would not ever yield to her the praise</l>
<l>won by the art of deftly weaving wool,</l>
<l>a girl who had not fame for place of birth,</l>
<l>nor fame for birth, but only fame for skill!</l>

    
<l>For it was well known that her father dwelt</l>
<l>in Colophon; where, at his humble trade,</l>
<l>he dyed in Phocean purples, fleecy wool.</l>
<l>Her mother, also of the lower class,</l>
<l>had died. Arachne in a mountain town</l>
<l>by skill had grown so famous in the Land</l>
<l>of Lydia, that unnumbered curious nymphs</l>
<l>eager to witness her dexterity,</l>
<l>deserted the lush vineyards of Timolus;</l>
<l>or even left the cool and flowing streams</l>
<l>of bright Pactolus, to admire the cloth,</l>
<l>or to observe her deftly spinning wool.</l>

    
<l>So graceful was her motion then,—if she</l>
<l>was twisting the coarse wool in little balls,</l>
<l>or if she teased it with her finger-tips,</l>
<l>or if she softened the fine fleece, drawn forth</l>
<l>in misty films, or if she twirled the smooth</l>
<l>round spindle with her energetic thumb,</l>
<l>or if with needle she embroidered cloth;—</l>

    
<l>in all her motions one might well perceive</l>
<l>how much Minerva had instructed her:</l>
<l>but this she ever would deny, displeased</l>
<l>to share her fame; and said, “Let her contend</l>
<l>in art with me; and if her skill prevails,</l>
<l>I then will forfeit all!”</l>

    
<l>Minerva heard,</l>
<l>and came to her, disguised with long grey hair,</l>
<l>and with a staff to steady her weak limbs.</l>
<l>She seemed a feeble woman, very old,</l>
<l>and quavered as she said, “Old age is not</l>
<l>the cause of every ill; experience comes</l>
<l>with lengthened years; and, therefore, you should not</l>
<l>despise my words. It is no harm in you</l>
<l>to long for praise of mortals, when</l>
<l>your nimble hands are spinning the soft wool,—</l>
<l>but you should not deny Minerva's art—</l>
<l>and you should pray that she may pardon you,</l>
<l>for she will grant you pardon if you ask.”</l>

    
<l>Arachne, scowling with an evil face.</l>
<l>Looked at the goddess, as she dropped her thread.</l>
<l>She hardly could restrain her threatening hand,</l>
<l>and, trembling in her anger, she replied</l>
<l>to you, disguised Minerva:</l>

    
<l>“Silly fool,—</l>
<l>worn out and witless in your palsied age,</l>
<l>a great age is your great misfortune!— Let</l>
<l>your daughter and your son's wife—if the Gods</l>
<l>have blessed you—let them profit by your words;</l>
<l>within myself, my knowledge is contained</l>
<l>sufficient; you need not believe that your</l>
<l>advice does any good; for I am quite</l>
<l>unchanged in my opinion. Get you gone,—</l>
<l>advise your goddess to come here herself,</l>
<l>and not avoid the contest!”</l>

    
<l>Instantly,</l>
<l>the goddess said, “Minerva comes to you!”</l>
<l>And with those brief words, put aside the shape</l>
<l>of the old woman, and revealed herself,</l>
<l>Minerva, goddess.</l>

    
<l>All the other Nymphs</l>
<l>and matrons of Mygdonia worshiped her;</l>
<l>but not Arachne, who defiant stood;—</l>
<l>although at first she flushed up—then went pale—</l>
<l>then blushed again, reluctant.—So, at first,</l>
<l>the sky suffuses, as Aurora moves,</l>
<l>and, quickly when the glorious sun comes up,</l>
<l>pales into white.</l>

    
<l>She even rushed upon</l>
<l>her own destruction, for she would not give</l>
<l>from her desire to gain the victory.</l>
<l>Nor did the daughter of almighty Jove</l>
<l>decline: disdaining to delay with words,</l>
<l>she hesitated not.</l>

    
<l>And both, at once,</l>
<l>selected their positions, stretched their webs</l>
<l>with finest warp, and separated warp with sley.</l>
<l>The woof was next inserted in the web</l>
<l>by means of the sharp shuttles, which</l>
<l>their nimble fingers pushed along, so drawn</l>
<l>within the warp, and so the teeth notched in</l>
<l>the moving sley might strike them.—Both, in haste,</l>
<l>girded their garments to their breasts and moved</l>
<l>their skilful arms, beguiling their fatigue</l>
<l>in eager action.</l>

    
<l>Myriad tints appeared</l>
<l>besides the Tyrian purple—royal dye,</l>
<l>extracted in brass vessels.—As the bow,</l>
<l>that spans new glory in the curving sky,</l>
<l>its glittering rays reflected in the rain,</l>
<l>spreads out a multitude of blended tints,</l>
<l>in scintillating beauty to the sight</l>
<l>of all who gaze upon it; — so the threads,</l>
<l>inwoven, mingled in a thousand tints,</l>
<l>harmonious and contrasting; shot with gold:</l>
<l>and there, depicted in those shining webs,</l>
<l>were shown the histories of ancient days:—</l>

    
<l>Minerva worked the Athenian Hill of Mars,</l>
<l>where ancient Cecrops built his citadel,</l>
<l>and showed the old contention for the name</l>
<l>it should be given.—Twelve celestial Gods</l>
<l>surrounded Jupiter, on lofty thrones;</l>
<l>and all their features were so nicely drawn,</l>
<l>that each could be distinguished.—Jupiter</l>
<l>appeared as monarch of those judging Gods.</l>

    
<l>There Neptune, guardian of the sea, was shown</l>
<l>contending with Minerva. As he struck</l>
<l>the Rock with his long trident, a wild horse</l>
<l>sprang forth which he bequeathed to man. He claimed</l>
<l>his right to name the city for that gift.</l>

    
<l>And then she wove a portrait of herself,</l>
<l>bearing a shield, and in her hand a lance,</l>
<l>sharp-pointed, and a helmet on her head—</l>
<l>her breast well-guarded by her Aegis: there</l>
<l>she struck her spear into the fertile earth,</l>
<l>from which a branch of olive seemed to sprout,</l>
<l>pale with new clustered fruits.—And those twelve Gods,</l>
<l>appeared to judge, that olive as a gift</l>
<l>surpassed the horse which Neptune gave to man.</l>

    
<l>And, so Arachne, rival of her fame,</l>
<l>might learn the folly of her mad attempt,</l>
<l>from the great deeds of ancient histories,</l>
<l>and what award presumption must expect,</l>
<l>Minerva wove four corners with life scenes</l>
<l>of contest, brightly colored, but of size</l>
<l>diminutive.</l>


    
<l>In one of these was shown</l>
<l>the snow-clad mountains, Rhodope,</l>
<l>and Haemus, which for punishment were changed</l>
<l>from human beings to those rigid forms,</l>
<l>when they aspired to rival the high Gods.</l>
<l>And in another corner she described</l>
<l>that Pygmy, whom the angry Juno changed</l>
<l>from queen-ship to a crane; because she thought</l>
<l>herself an equal of the living Gods,</l>
<l>she was commanded to wage cruel wars</l>
<l>upon her former subjects. In the third,</l>
<l>she wove the story of Antigone,</l>
<l>who dared compare herself to Juno, queen</l>
<l>of Jupiter, and showed her as she was</l>
<l>transformed into a silly chattering stork,</l>
<l>that praised her beauty, with her ugly beak.—</l>
<l>Despite the powers of Ilion and her sire</l>
<l>Laomedon, her shoulders fledged white wings.</l>
<l>And so, the third part finished, there was left</l>
<l>one corner, where Minerva deftly worked</l>
<l>the story of the father, Cinyras;—</l>
<l>as he was weeping on the temple steps,</l>
<l>which once had been his daughter's living limbs.</l>
<l>And she adorned the border with designs</l>
<l>of peaceful olive—her devoted tree—</l>
<l>which having shown, she made an end of work.</l>

    
<l>Arachne, of Maeonia, wove, at first</l>
<l>the story of Europa, as the bull</l>
<l>deceived her, and so perfect was her art,</l>
<l>it seemed a real bull in real waves.</l>
<l>Europa seemed to look back towards the land</l>
<l>which she had left; and call in her alarm</l>
<l>to her companions—and as if she feared</l>
<l>the touch of dashing waters, to draw up</l>
<l>her timid feet, while she was sitting on</l>
<l>the bull's back.</l>

    
<l>And she wove Asteria seized</l>
<l>by the assaulting eagle; and beneath the swan's</l>
<l>white wings showed Leda lying by the stream:</l>

    
<l>and showed Jove dancing as a Satyr, when</l>
<l>he sought the beautiful Antiope,</l>
<l>to whom was given twins; and how he seemed</l>
<l>Amphitryon when he deceived Alcmena;</l>
<l>and how he courted lovely Danae</l>
<l>luring her as a gleaming shower of gold;</l>
<l>and poor Aegina, hidden in his flame,</l>
<l>jove as a shepherd with Mnemosyne;</l>
<l>and beautiful Proserpina, involved</l>
<l>by him, apparent as a spotted snake.</l>

    
<l>And in her web, Arachne wove the scenes</l>
<l>of Neptune:—who was shown first as a bull,</l>
<l>when he was deep in love with virgin Arne</l>
<l>then as Enipeus when the giant twins,</l>
<l>Aloidae, were begot; and as the ram</l>
<l>that gambolled with Bisaltis; as a horse</l>
<l>loved by the fruitful Ceres, golden haired,</l>
<l>all-bounteous mother of the yellow grain;</l>
<l>and as the bird that hovered round snake-haired</l>
<l>Medusa, mother of the winged horse;</l>
<l>and as the dolphin, sporting with the Nymph,</l>
<l>Melantho.—All of these were woven true</l>
<l>to life, in proper shades.</l>

    
<l>And there she showed</l>
<l>Apollo, when disguised in various forms:</l>
<l>as when he seemed a rustic; and as when</l>
<l>he wore hawk-wings, and then the tawny skin</l>
<l>of a great lion; and once more when he</l>
<l>deluded Isse, as a shepherd lad.</l>

    
<l>And there was Bacchus, when he was disguised</l>
<l>as a large cluster of fictitious grapes;</l>
<l>deluding by that wile the beautiful</l>
<l>Erigone;—and Saturn, as a steed,</l>
<l>begetter of the dual-natured Chiron.</l>

    
<l>And then Arachne, to complete her work,</l>
<l>wove all around the web a patterned edge</l>
<l>of interlacing flowers and ivy leaves.</l>

    
<l>Minerva could not find a fleck or flaw—</l>
<l>even Envy can not censure perfect art—</l>
<l>enraged because Arachne had such skill</l>
<l>she ripped the web, and ruined all the scenes</l>
<l>that showed those wicked actions of the Gods;</l>
<l>and with her boxwood shuttle in her hand,</l>
<l>struck the unhappy mortal on her head,—</l>
<l>struck sharply thrice, and even once again.</l>

    
<l>Arachne's spirit, deigning not to brook</l>
<l>such insult, brooded on it, till she tied</l>
<l>a cord around her neck, and hung herself.</l>

    
<l>Minerva, moved to pity at the sight,</l>
<l>sustained and saved her from that bitter death;</l>
<l>but, angry still, pronounced another doom:</l>
<l>“Although I grant you life, most wicked one,</l>
<l>your fate shall be to dangle on a cord,</l>
<l>and your posterity forever shall</l>
<l>take your example, that your punishment</l>
<l>may last forever!” Even as she spoke,</l>
<l>before withdrawing from her victim's sight,</l>
<l>she sprinkled her with juice—extract of herbs</l>
<l>of Hecate.</l>

    
<l>At once all hair fell off,</l>
<l>her nose and ears remained not, and her head</l>
<l>shrunk rapidly in size, as well as all</l>
<l>her body, leaving her diminutive.—</l>
<l>Her slender fingers gathered to her sides</l>
<l>as long thin legs; and all her other parts</l>
<l>were fast absorbed in her abdomen—whence</l>
<l>she vented a fine thread;—and ever since,</l>
<l>Arachne, as a spider, weaves her web.</l>


Niobe.
NIOBE

<l>All Lydia was astonished at her fate</l>
<l>the Rumor spread to Phrygia, soon the world</l>
<l>was filled with fear and wonder. Niobe</l>
<l>had known her long before,—when in Maeonia</l>
<l>near to Mount Sipylus; but the sad fate</l>
<l>which overtook Arachne, lost on her,</l>
<l>she never ceased her boasting and refused</l>
<l>to honor the great Gods.</l>

    
<l>So many things</l>
<l>increased her pride: She loved to boast</l>
<l>her husband's skill, their noble family,</l>
<l>the rising grandeur of their kingdom. Such</l>
<l>felicities were great delights to her;</l>
<l>but nothing could exceed the haughty way</l>
<l>she boasted of her children: and, in truth,</l>
<l>Niobe might have been adjudged on earth,</l>
<l>the happiest mother of mankind, if pride</l>
<l>had not destroyed her wit.</l>

    
<l>It happened then,</l>
<l>that Manto, daughter of Tiresias,</l>
<l>who told the future; when she felt the fire</l>
<l>of prophecy descend upon her, rushed</l>
<l>upon the street and shouted in the midst:</l>

    
<l>“You women of Ismenus! go and give</l>
<l>to high Latona and her children, twain,</l>
<l>incense and prayer. Go, and with laurel wreathe</l>
<l>your hair in garlands, as your sacred prayers</l>
<l>arise to heaven. Give heed, for by my speech</l>
<l>Latona has ordained these holy rites.”</l>

    
<l>At once, the Theban women wreathe their brows</l>
<l>with laurel, and they cast in hallowed flame</l>
<l>the grateful incense, while they supplicate</l>
<l>all favors of the ever-living Gods.</l>

    
<l>And while they worship, Niobe comes there,</l>
<l>surrounded with a troup that follow her,</l>
<l>and most conspicuous in her purple robe,</l>
<l>bright with inwoven threads of yellow gold.</l>
<l>Beautiful in her anger, she tosses back</l>
<l>her graceful head. The glory of her hair</l>
<l>shines on her shoulders. Standing forth,</l>
<l>she looks upon them with her haughty eyes,</l>
<l>and taunts them, “Madness has prevailed on you</l>
<l>to worship some imagined Gods of Heaven,</l>
<l>which you have only heard of; but the Gods</l>
<l>that truly are on earth, and can be seen,</l>
<l>are all neglected! Come, explain to me,</l>
<l>why is Latona worshiped and adored,</l>
<l>and frankincense not offered unto me?</l>
<l>For my divinity is known to you.</l>

    
<l>“Tantalus was my father, who alone</l>
<l>approached the tables of the Gods in heaven;</l>
<l>my mother, sister of the Pleiades,</l>
<l>was daughter of huge Atlas, who supports</l>
<l>the world upon his shoulders; I can boast</l>
<l>of Jupiter as father of my sire,</l>
<l>I count him also as my father-in-law.</l>
<l>The peoples of my Phrygia dread my power,</l>
<l>and I am mistress of the palace built</l>
<l>by Cadmus. By my husband, I am queen</l>
<l>of those great walls that reared themselves</l>
<l>to the sweet music of his sounding lyre.</l>
<l>We rule together all the people they</l>
<l>encompass and defend. And everywhere</l>
<l>my gaze is turned, an evidence of wealth</l>
<l>is witnessed.</l>

    
<l>“In my features you can see</l>
<l>the beauty of a goddess, but above</l>
<l>that majesty is all the glory due</l>
<l>to me, the mother of my seven sons</l>
<l>and daughters seven. And the time will come</l>
<l>when by their marriage they will magnify</l>
<l>the circle of my power invincible.</l>

    
<l>“All must acknowledge my just cause of pride</l>
<l>and must no longer worship, in despite</l>
<l>of my superior birth, this deity,</l>
<l>a daughter of ignoble Coeus, whom</l>
<l>one time the great Earth would not even grant</l>
<l>sufficient space for travail: whom the Heavens,</l>
<l>the Land, the Sea together once compelled</l>
<l>to wander, hopeless on all hostile shores!</l>
<l>Throughout the world she found herself rebuffed,</l>
<l>till Delos, sorry for the vagrant, said,</l>
<l>‘Homeless you roam the lands, and I the seas!’</l>
<l>And even her refuge always was adrift.</l>

    
<l>“And there she bore two children, who, compared</l>
<l>with mine, are but as one to seven. Who</l>
<l>denies my fortunate condition?—Who</l>
<l>can doubt my future?—I am surely safe.</l>

    
<l>“The wealth of my abundance is too strong</l>
<l>for Fortune to assail me. Let her rage</l>
<l>despoil me of large substance; yet so much</l>
<l>would still be mine, for I have risen above</l>
<l>the blight of apprehension. But, suppose</l>
<l>a few of my fair children should be taken!</l>
<l>Even so deprived, I could not be reduced</l>
<l>to only two, as this Latona, who,</l>
<l>might quite as well be childless.—Get you gone</l>
<l>from this insensate sacrifice. Make haste!</l>
<l>Cast off the wreathing laurels from your brows!”</l>

    
<l>They plucked the garlands from their hair, and left</l>
<l>the sacrifice, obedient to her will,</l>
<l>although in gentle murmurs they adored</l>
<l>the goddess Niobe had so defamed.</l>

    
<l>Latona, furious when she heard the speech,</l>
<l>flew swiftly to the utmost peak of Cynthus,</l>
<l>and spoke to her two children in these words:</l>

    
<l>“Behold your mother, proud of having borne</l>
<l>such glorious children! I will yield</l>
<l>prestige before no goddess—save alone</l>
<l>immortal Juno! I have been debased,</l>
<l>and driven for all ages from my own—</l>
<l>my altars, unto me devoted long,</l>
<l>and so must languish through eternity,</l>
<l>unless by you sustained. Nor is this all;.</l>
<l>That daughter of Tantalus, bold Niobe,</l>
<l>has added curses to her evil deeds,</l>
<l>and with a tongue as wicked as her sire's,</l>
<l>has raised her base-born children over mine.</l>
<l>Has even called me childless! A sad fate</l>
<l>more surely should be hers! Oh, I entreat”—</l>

    
<l>But Phoebus answered her, “No more complaint</l>
<l>is necessary, for it only serves</l>
<l>to hinder the swift sequel of her doom.”</l>
<l>And with the same words Phoebe answered her.</l>
<l>And having spoken, they descended through</l>
<l>the shielding shadows of surrounding clouds,</l>
<l>and hovered on the citadel of Cadmus.</l>


    
<l>There, far below them, was a level plain</l>
<l>which swept around those walls; where trampling steeds,</l>
<l>with horny hoofs, and multitudinous wheels,</l>
<l>had beaten a wide track. And on the field</l>
<l>the older sons of Niobe on steeds</l>
<l>emblazoned with bright dyes and harness rich</l>
<l>with studded gold were circling.—One of these,</l>
<l>Ismenus, first-born of his mother, while</l>
<l>controlling his fleet courser's foaming mouth,</l>
<l>cried out, “Ah wretched me!” A shaft had pierced</l>
<l>the middle of his breast; and as the reins</l>
<l>dropped slowly on the rapid courser's neck,</l>
<l>his drooping form fell forward to the ground.</l>

    
<l>Not far from him, his brother, Sipylus,</l>
<l>could hear the whistling of a fatal shaft,</l>
<l>and in his fright urged on the plunging steed:</l>
<l>as when the watchful pilot, sensible</l>
<l>of storms approaching, crowds on sail,</l>
<l>hoping to catch a momentary breeze,</l>
<l>so fled he, urging an impetuous flight;</l>
<l>but, while he fled the shaft, unerring, flew;</l>
<l>transfixed him with its quivering death; struck where</l>
<l>the neck supports the head and the sharp point</l>
<l>protruded from his throat. In his swift flight,</l>
<l>as he was leaning forward, he was struck;</l>
<l>and, rolling over the wild horse's neck</l>
<l>pitched to the ground, and stained it with his blood.</l>

    
<l>Unhappy Phaedimus, and Tantalus,</l>
<l>(So named from his maternal grandsire) now</l>
<l>had finished coursing on the track, and smooth.</l>
<l>Shining with oil, were wrestling in the field;</l>
<l>and while those brothers struggled—breast to breast—</l>
<l>another arrow, hurtling from the sky,</l>
<l>pierced them together, just as they were clinched.</l>
<l>The mingled sound that issued from two throats</l>
<l>was like a single groan. Convulsed with pain,</l>
<l>the wrestlers fell together on the ground,</l>
<l>where, stricken with a double agony,</l>
<l>rolling their eyeballs, they sobbed out their lives.</l>

    
<l>Alphenor saw them die—beating his breast</l>
<l>in agony—ran to lift in his arms</l>
<l>their lifeless bodies cold—while doing this</l>
<l>he fell upon them. Phoebus struck him so,</l>
<l>piercing his midriff in a vital part,</l>
<l>with fatal shot, which, when he pulled it forth,</l>
<l>dragged with its barb a torn clot of his lung—</l>
<l>his blood and life poured out upon the air.</l>

    
<l>The youthful Damasicthon next was struck,</l>
<l>not only once; an arrow pierced his leg</l>
<l>just where the sinews of the thigh begin,</l>
<l>and as he turned and stooped to pluck it out,</l>
<l>another keen shaft shot into his neck,</l>
<l>up to the fletching.—The blood drove it out,</l>
<l>and spouted after it in crimson jets.</l>

    
<l>Then, Ilioneus, last of seven sons,</l>
<l>lifted his unavailing arms in prayer,</l>
<l>and cried, “O Universal Deities,</l>
<l>gods of eternal heaven, spare my life!”—</l>
<l>Besought too late, Apollo of the Bow,</l>
<l>could not prevail against the deadly shaft,</l>
<l>already on its way: and yet his will,</l>
<l>compellant, acted to retard its flight,</l>
<l>so that it cut no deeper than his heart.</l>

    
<l>The rumors of an awful tragedy,—</l>
<l>the wailings of sad Niobe's loved friends,—</l>
<l>the terror of her grieving relatives,—</l>
<l>all gave some knowledge of her sudden loss:</l>
<l>but so bewildered and enraged her mind,</l>
<l>that she could hardly realize the Gods</l>
<l>had privilege to dare against her might.</l>
<l>Nor would she, till her lord, Amphion, thrust</l>
<l>his sword deep in his breast, by which his life</l>
<l>and anguish both were ended in dark night.</l>

    
<l>Alas, proud Niobe, once haughty queen!</l>
<l>Proud Niobe who but so lately drove</l>
<l>her people from Latona's altars, while,</l>
<l>moving majestic through the midst, she hears</l>
<l>their plaudits, now so bitterly debased,</l>
<l>her meanest enemy may pity her!—</l>

    
<l>She fell upon the bodies of her sons,</l>
<l>and in a frenzy of maternal grief,</l>
<l>kissed their unfeeling lips. Then unto Heaven</l>
<l>with arms accusing, railed upon her foe:</l>

<l>“Glut your revenge! Latona, glut your rage!</l>
<l>Yea, let my lamentations be your joy!</l>
<l>Go—satiate your flinty heart with death!</l>
<l>Are not my seven sons all dead? Am I</l>
<l>not waiting to be carried to my grave?—</l>
<l>exult and triumph, my victorious foe!</l>
<l>Victorious? Nay!—Much more remains to me</l>
<l>in all my utmost sorrow, than to you,</l>
<l>you gloater upon vengeance—Undismayed,</l>
<l>I stand victorious in my Field of Woe!”</l>

    
<l>no sooner had she spoken, than the cord</l>
<l>twanged from the ever-ready bow; and all</l>
<l>who heard the fatal sound, again were filled</l>
<l>with fear,—save Niobe, in misery bold,—</l>
<l>defiant in misfortune.—Clothed in black,</l>
<l>the sisters of the stricken brothers stood,</l>
<l>with hair disheveled, by the funeral biers.</l>

    
<l>And one while plucking from her brother's heart</l>
<l>a shaft, swooned unto death, fell on her face—</l>
<l>on her dear brother's corpse. Another girl,</l>
<l>while she consoled her mother, suddenly,</l>
<l>was stricken with an unseen, deadly wound;</l>
<l>and doubled in convulsions, closed her lips,</l>
<l>tight held them, till both breath and life were lost.</l>
<l>Another, vainly rushed away from death—</l>
<l>she met it, and pitched head-first to the ground;</l>
<l>and still another died upon her corse,</l>
<l>another vainly sought a secret death,</l>
<l>and, then another slipped beyond's life's edge.</l>
<l>So, altogether, six of seven died—</l>
<l>each victim, strickened in a different way.</l>

    
<l>One child remained. Then in a frenzy-fear</l>
<l>the mother, as she covered her with all</l>
<l>her garments and her body, wailed—“Oh, leave</l>
<l>me this one child! the youngest of them all!</l>
<l>My darling daughter—only leave me one!”</l>
<l>But even while she was entreating for its life—</l>
<l>the life was taken from her only child.</l>

    
<l>Childless— she crouched beside her slaughtered sons,</l>
<l>her lifeless daughters, and her husband's corpse.</l>
<l>The breeze not even moved her fallen hair,</l>
<l>a chill of marble spread upon her flesh,</l>
<l>beneath her pale, set brows, her eyes moved not,</l>
<l>her bitter tongue turned stiff in her hard jaws,</l>
<l>her lovely veins congealed, and her stiff neck</l>
<l>and rigid hands could neither bend nor move.—</l>
<l>her limbs and body, all were changed to stone.</l>

    
<l>Yet ever would she weep: and as her tears</l>
<l>were falling she was carried from the place,</l>
<l>enveloped in a storm and mighty wind,</l>
<l>far, to her native land, where fixed upon</l>
<l>a mountain summit she dissolves in tears,—</l>
<l>and to this day the marble drips with tears.</l>


Agrestes Lycii.
RUSTICS CHANGED TO FROGS

<l>All men and women, after this event,</l>
<l>feared to incur Latona's fateful wrath,</l>
<l>and worshiped with more zeal the Deity,</l>
<l>mother of twins.—And, as it is the way</l>
<l>of men to talk of many other things</l>
<l>after a strong occurrence, they recalled</l>
<l>what other deeds the goddess had performed;—</l>
<l>and one of them recited this event:</l>

    
<l>'Twas in the ancient days of long-ago,—</l>
<l>some rustics, in the fertile fields of Lycia,</l>
<l>heedless, insulted the goddess to their harm:—</l>
<l>perhaps you've never heard of this event,</l>
<l>because those country clowns were little known.</l>
<l>The event was wonderful, but I can vouch</l>
<l>the truth of it. I visited the place</l>
<l>and I have seen the pool of water, where</l>
<l>happened the miracle I now relate.</l>

    
<l>My good old father, then advanced in years,</l>
<l>incapable of travel, ordered me</l>
<l>to fetch some cattle—thoroughbreds—from there,</l>
<l>and had secured a Lycian for my guide,</l>

    
<l>as I traversed the pastures, with the man,</l>
<l>it chanced, I saw an ancient altar,—grimed</l>
<l>with sacrificial ashes—in the midst</l>
<l>of a large pool, with sedge and reeds around,</l>
<l>a-quiver in the breeze. And there my guide</l>
<l>stood on the marge, and with an awe-struck voice</l>
<l>began to whisper, “Be propitious, hear</l>
<l>my supplications, and forget not me!”</l>

    
<l>And I, observing him, echoed the words,</l>
<l>“Forget not me!” which, having done, I turned</l>
<l>to him and said, “Whose altar can this be?</l>
<l>Perhaps a sacred altar of the Fauns,</l>
<l>or of the Naiads, or a native God?”</l>

    
<l>To which my guide replied, “Young man, such Gods</l>
<l>may not be worshiped at this altar. She</l>
<l>whom once the royal Juno drove away</l>
<l>to wander a harsh world, alone permits</l>
<l>this altar to be used: that goddess whom</l>
<l>the wandering Isle of Delos, at the time</l>
<l>it drifted as the foam, almost refused</l>
<l>a refuge.</l>

    
<l>There Latona, as she leaned</l>
<l>against a palm-tree—and against the tree</l>
<l>most sacred to Minerva, brought forth twins,</l>
<l>although their harsh step-mother, Juno, strove</l>
<l>to interfere.—And from the island forced</l>
<l>to fly by jealous Juno, on her breast</l>
<l>she bore her children, twin Divinities.</l>

    
<l>At last, outwearied with the toil, and parched</l>
<l>with thirst—long-wandering in those heated days</l>
<l>over the arid land of Lycia, where</l>
<l>was bred the dire Chimaera— at the time</l>
<l>her parching breasts were drained, she saw this pool</l>
<l>of crystal water, shimmering in the vale.</l>

    
<l>Some countrymen were there to gather reeds,</l>
<l>and useful osiers, and the bulrush, found</l>
<l>with sedge in fenny pools. To them approached</l>
<l>Latona, and she knelt upon the merge</l>
<l>to cool her thirst, with some refreshing water.</l>
<l>But those clowns forbade her and the goddess cried,</l>
<l>as they so wickedly opposed her need:</l>

    
<l>“Why do you so resist my bitter thirst?</l>
<l>The use of water is the sacred right</l>
<l>of all mankind, for Nature has not made</l>
<l>the sun and air and water, for the sole</l>
<l>estate of any creature; and to Her</l>
<l>kind bounty I appeal, although of you</l>
<l>I humbly beg the use of it. Not here</l>
<l>do I intend to bathe my wearied limbs.</l>
<l>I only wish to quench an urgent thirst,</l>
<l>for, even as I speak, my cracking lips</l>
<l>and mouth so parched, almost deny me words.</l>
<l>A drink of water will be like a draught</l>
<l>of nectar, giving life; and I shall owe</l>
<l>to you the bounty and my life renewed.—</l>
<l>ah, let these tender infants, whose weak arms</l>
<l>implore you from my bosom, but incline</l>
<l>your hearts to pity!” And just as she spoke,</l>
<l>it chanced the children did stretch out their arms</l>
<l>and who would not be touched to hear such words,</l>
<l>as spoken by this goddess, and refuse?</l>

    
<l>But still those clowns persisted in their wrong</l>
<l>against the goddess; for they hindered her,</l>
<l>and threatened with their foul, abusive tongues</l>
<l>to frighten her away—and, worse than all,</l>
<l>they even muddied with their hands and feet</l>
<l>the clear pool; forcing the vile, slimy dregs</l>
<l>up from the bottom, in a spiteful way,</l>
<l>by jumping up and down.—Enraged at this,</l>
<l>she felt no further thirst, nor would she deign</l>
<l>to supplicate again; but, feeling all</l>
<l>the outraged majesty of her high state,</l>
<l>she raised her hands to Heaven, and exclaimed,</l>
<l>“Forever may you live in that mud-pool!”</l>

    
<l>The curse as soon as uttered took effect,</l>
<l>and every one of them began to swim</l>
<l>beneath the water, and to leap and plunge</l>
<l>deep in the pool.—Now, up they raise their heads,</l>
<l>now swim upon the surface, now they squat</l>
<l>themselves around the marshy margent, now</l>
<l>they plump again down to the chilly deeps.</l>
<l>And, ever and again, with croaking throats,</l>
<l>indulge offensive strife upon the banks,</l>
<l>or even under water, boom abuse.</l>

    
<l>Their ugly voices cause their bloated necks</l>
<l>to puff out; and their widened jaws are made</l>
<l>still wider in the venting of their spleen.</l>

    
<l>Their backs, so closely fastened to their heads,</l>
<l>make them appear as if their shrunken necks</l>
<l>have been cut off. Their backbones are dark green;</l>
<l>white are their bellies, now their largest part.—</l>

    
<l>Forever since that time, the foolish frogs</l>
<l>muddy their own pools, where they leap and dive.</l>


Marsyas. Pelops.
MARSYAS

<l>So he related how the clowns were changed</l>
<l>to leaping frogs; and after he was through,</l>
<l>another told the tale of Marsyas, in these words:</l>

    
<l>The Satyr Marsyas, when he played the flute</l>
<l>in rivalry against Apollo's lyre,</l>
<l>lost that audacious contest and, alas!</l>
<l>His life was forfeit; for, they had agreed</l>
<l>the one who lost should be the victor's prey.</l>
<l>And, as Apollo punished him, he cried,</l>
<l>“Ah-h-h! why are you now tearing me apart?</l>
<l>A flute has not the value of my life!”</l>

    
<l>Even as he shrieked out in his agony,</l>
<l>his living skin was ripped off from his limbs,</l>
<l>till his whole body was a flaming wound,</l>
<l>with nerves and veins and viscera exposed.</l>

    
<l>But all the weeping people of that land,</l>
<l>and all the Fauns and Sylvan Deities,</l>
<l>and all the Satyrs, and Olympus, his</l>
<l>loved pupil—even then renowned in song,</l>
<l>and all the Nymphs, lamented his sad fate;</l>
<l>and all the shepherds, roaming on the hills,</l>
<l>lamented as they tended fleecy flocks.</l>

    
<l>And all those falling tears, on fruitful Earth,</l>
<l>descended to her deepest veins, as drip</l>
<l>the moistening dews,—and, gathering as a fount,</l>
<l>turned upward from her secret-winding caves,</l>
<l>to issue, sparkling, in the sun-kissed air,</l>
<l>the clearest river in the land of Phrygia,—</l>
<l>through which it swiftly flows between steep banks</l>
<l>down to the sea: and, therefore, from his name,</l>
<l>'Tis called “The Marsyas” to this very day.</l>

    
<l>And after this was told, the people turned</l>
<l>and wept for Niobe's loved children dead,</l>
<l>and also, mourned Amphion, sorrow-slain.</l>

PELOPS

<l>The Theban people hated Niobe,</l>
<l>but Pelops, her own brother, mourned her death;</l>
<l>and as he rent his garment, and laid bare</l>
<l>his white left shoulder, you could see the part</l>
<l>composed of ivory.—At his birth 'twas all</l>
<l>of healthy flesh; but when his father cut</l>
<l>his limbs asunder, and the Gods restored</l>
<l>his life, all parts were rightly joined, except</l>
<l>part of one shoulder, which was wanting; so</l>
<l>to serve the purpose of the missing flesh,</l>
<l>a piece of ivory was inserted there,</l>
<l>making his body by such means complete.</l>


Procne et Philomela.
TEREUS AND PHILOMELA

<l>The lords of many cities that were near,</l>
<l>now met together and implored their kings</l>
<l>to mourn with Pelops those unhappy deeds.—</l>

    
<l>The lords of Argos; Sparta and Mycenae;</l>
<l>and Calydon, before it had incurred</l>
<l>the hatred of Diana, goddess of the chase;</l>
<l>fertile Orchomenus and Corinth, great</l>
<l>in wealth of brass; Patrae and fierce Messena;</l>
<l>Cleone, small; and Pylus and Troezen,</l>
<l>not ruled by Pittheus then,—and also, all</l>
<l>the other cities which are shut off by</l>
<l>the Isthmus there dividing by its two seas,</l>
<l>and all the cities which are seen from there.</l>

    
<l>What seemed most wonderful, of all those towns</l>
<l>Athens alone was wanting, for a war</l>
<l>had gathered from the distant seas, a host</l>
<l>of savage warriors had alarmed her walls,</l>
<l>and hindered her from mourning for the dead.</l>

    
<l>Now Tereus, then the mighty king of Thrace,</l>
<l>came to the aid of Athens as defense</l>
<l>from that fierce horde; and there by his great deeds</l>
<l>achieved a glorious fame. Since his descent</l>
<l>was boasted from the mighty Gradivus,</l>
<l>and he was gifted with enormous wealth,</l>
<l>Pandion, king of Athens, gave to him</l>
<l>in sacred wedlock his dear daughter, Procne.</l>

    
<l>But Juno, guardian of the sacred rites</l>
<l>attended not, nor Hymenaeus, nor</l>
<l>the Graces. But the Furies snatched up brands</l>
<l>from burning funeral pyres, and brandished them</l>
<l>as torches. They prepared the nuptial couch,—</l>
<l>a boding owl flew over the bride's room,</l>
<l>and then sat silently upon the roof.</l>

    
<l>With such bad omens Tereus married her,</l>
<l>sad Procne, and those omens cast a gloom</l>
<l>on all the household till the fateful birth</l>
<l>of their first born. All Thrace went wild with joy—</l>
<l>and even they, rejoicing, blessed the Gods,</l>
<l>when he, the little Itys, saw the light;</l>
<l>and they ordained each year their wedding day,</l>
<l>and every year the birthday of their child,</l>
<l>should be observed with festival and song:</l>
<l>so the sad veil of fate conceals from us</l>
<l>our future woes.</l>

    
<l>Now Titan had drawn forth</l>
<l>the changing seasons through five autumns, when,</l>
<l>in gentle accents, Procne spoke these words:</l>
<l>“My dearest husband, if you love me, let</l>
<l>me visit my dear sister, or consent</l>
<l>that she may come to us and promise her</l>
<l>that she may soon return. If you will but</l>
<l>permit me to enjoy her company</l>
<l>my heart will bless you as I bless the Gods.”</l>

    
<l>At once the monarch ordered his long ships</l>
<l>to launch upon the sea; and driven by sail,</l>
<l>and hastened by the swiftly sweeping oars,</l>
<l>they entered the deep port of Athens, where</l>
<l>he made fair landing on the fortified</l>
<l>Piraeus. There, when time was opportune</l>
<l>to greet his father-in-law and shake his hand,</l>
<l>they both exchanged their wishes for good health,</l>
<l>and Tereus told the reason why he came.</l>

    
<l>He was relating all his wife's desire.</l>
<l>Promising Philomela's safe return</l>
<l>from a brief visit, when Philomela appeared</l>
<l>rich in her costly raiment, yet more rich</l>
<l>in charm and beauty, just as if a fair</l>
<l>Dryad or Naiad should be so attired,</l>
<l>appearing radiant, from dark solitudes.</l>

    
<l>As if someone should kindle whitening corn</l>
<l>or the dry leaves, or hay piled in a stack;</l>
<l>so Tereus, when he saw the beautiful</l>
<l>and blushing virgin, was consumed with love.</l>

    
<l>Her modest beauty was a worthy cause</l>
<l>of worthy love; but by his heritage,</l>
<l>derived from a debasing clime, his love</l>
<l>was base; and fires unholy burned within</l>
<l>from his own lawless nature, just as fierce</l>
<l>as are the habits of his evil race.</l>

    
<l>In the wild frenzy of his wicked heart,</l>
<l>he thought he would corrupt her trusted maid,</l>
<l>her tried attendants, and corrupt even</l>
<l>her virtue with large presents: he would waste</l>
<l>his kingdom in the effort.—He prepared</l>
<l>to seize her at the risk of cruel war.</l>
<l>And he would do or dare all things to feed</l>
<l>his raging flame.—He could not brook delay.</l>

    
<l>With most impassioned words he begged for her,</l>
<l>pretending he gave voice to Procne's hopes.—</l>
<l>his own desire made him wax eloquent,</l>
<l>as often as his words exceeded bounds,</l>
<l>he pleaded he was uttering Procne's words.</l>

    
<l>His hypocritic eyes were filled with tears,</l>
<l>as though they represented her desire—</l>
<l>and, O you Gods above, what devious ways</l>
<l>are harbored in the hearts of mortals!  Through</l>
<l>his villainous desire he gathered praise,</l>
<l>and many lauded him for the great love</l>
<l>he bore his wife.</l>

    
<l>And even Philomela</l>
<l>desires her own undoing; and with fond</l>
<l>embraces nestles to her father, while</l>
<l>she pleads for his consent, that she may go</l>
<l>to visit her dear sister.—Tereus viewed</l>
<l>her pretty pleading, and in his hot heart,</l>
<l>imagined he was then embracing her;</l>
<l>and as he saw her kiss her father's lips,</l>
<l>her arms around his neck, it seemed that each</l>
<l>caress was his; and so his fire increased.</l>
<l>He even wished he were her father; though,</l>
<l>if it were so, his passion would no less</l>
<l>be impious.—Overcome at last by these</l>
<l>entreaties, her kind father gave consent.</l>
<l>Greatly she joyed and thanked him for her own</l>
<l>misfortune. She imagined a success,</l>
<l>instead of all the sorrow that would come.</l>

    
<l>The day declining, little of his toil</l>
<l>remained for Phoebus. Now his flaming steeds</l>
<l>were beating with their hoofs the downward slope</l>
<l>of high Olympus; and the regal feast</l>
<l>was set before the guests, and flashing wine</l>
<l>was poured in golden vessels, and the feast</l>
<l>went merrily, until the satisfied</l>
<l>assembly sought in gentle sleep their rest.</l>

    
<l>Not so, the love-hot Tereus, king of Thrace,</l>
<l>who, sleepless, imaged in his doting mind</l>
<l>the form of Philomela, recalled the shape</l>
<l>of her fair hands, and in his memory</l>
<l>reviewed her movements. And his flaming heart</l>
<l>pictured her beauties yet unseen.—He fed</l>
<l>his frenzy on itself, and could not sleep.</l>

    
<l>Fair broke the day; and now the ancient king,</l>
<l>Pandion, took his son-in-law's right hand</l>
<l>to bid farewell; and, as he wept,</l>
<l>commended his dear daughter, Philomela,</l>
<l>unto his guarding care. “And in your care,</l>
<l>my son-in-law, I trust my daughter's health.</l>
<l>Good reason, grounded on my love, compels</l>
<l>my sad approval. You have begged for her,</l>
<l>and both my daughters have persuaded me.</l>
<l>Wherefore, I do entreat you and implore</l>
<l>your honor, as I call upon the Gods,</l>
<l>that you will ever shield her with the love</l>
<l>of a kind father and return her safe,</l>
<l>as soon as may be—my last comfort given</l>
<l>to bless my doting age. And all delay</l>
<l>will agitate and vex my failing heart.</l>

    
<l>“And, O my dearest daughter, Philomela,</l>
<l>if you have any love for me, return</l>
<l>without too long delay and comfort me,</l>
<l>lest I may grieve; for it is quite enough</l>
<l>that I should suffer while your sister stays away.”</l>


    
<l>The old king made them promise, and he kissed</l>
<l>his daughter, while he wept. Then did he join</l>
<l>their hands in pledge of their fidelity,</l>
<l>and, as he gave his blessing, cautioned them</l>
<l>to kiss his absent daughter and her son</l>
<l>for his dear sake. Then as he spoke a last</l>
<l>farewell, his trembling voice was filled with sobs.</l>
<l>And he could hardly speak;—for a great fear</l>
<l>from some vague intuition of his mind,</l>
<l>surged over him, and he was left forlorn.</l>

    
<l>So soon as Philomela was safe aboard</l>
<l>the painted ship and as the sailors urged</l>
<l>the swiftly gliding keel across the deep</l>
<l>and the dim land fast-faded from their view,</l>
<l>then Tereus, in exultant humor, thought,</l>
<l>“Now all is well, the object of my love</l>
<l>sails with me while the sailors ply the oars.”,</l>

    
<l>He scarcely could control his barbarous</l>
<l>desire—with difficulty stayed his lust,</l>
<l>he followed all her actions with hot eyes. —</l>
<l>So, when the ravenous bird of Jupiter</l>
<l>has caught with crooked talons the poor hare,</l>
<l>and dropped it—ruthless,—in his lofty nest,</l>
<l>where there is no escape, his cruel eyes</l>
<l>gloat on the victim he anticipates.</l>

    
<l>And now, as Tereus reached his journey's end,</l>
<l>they landed from the travel-wearied ship,</l>
<l>safe on the shores of his own kingdom. Then</l>
<l>he hastened with the frightened Philomela</l>
<l>into most wild and silent solitudes</l>
<l>of an old forest; where, concealed among</l>
<l>deep thickets a forbidding old house stood:</l>
<l>there he immured the pale and trembling maid,</l>
<l>who, vainly in her fright, began to call</l>
<l>upon her absent sister,—and her tears</l>
<l>implored his pity. His obdurate mind</l>
<l>could not be softened by such piteous cries;</l>
<l>but even while her agonizing screams</l>
<l>implored her sister's and her father's aid,</l>
<l>and while she vainly called upon the Gods,</l>
<l>he overmastered her with brutal force.—</l>

    
<l>The poor child trembled as a frightened lamb,</l>
<l>which, just delivered from the frothing jaws</l>
<l>of a gaunt wolf, dreads every moving twig.</l>
<l>She trembled as a timid injured dove,</l>
<l>(her feathers dripping with her own life-blood)</l>
<l>that dreads the ravening talons of a hawk</l>
<l>from which some fortune has delivered her.</l>

    
<l>But presently, as consciousness returned,</l>
<l>she tore her streaming hair and beat her arms,</l>
<l>and, stretching forth her hands in frenzied grief,</l>
<l>cried out, “Oh, barbarous and brutal wretch!</l>
<l>Unnatural monster of abhorrent deeds!</l>
<l>Could not my anxious father's parting words,</l>
<l>nor his foreboding tears restrain your lust?</l>
<l>Have you no slight regard for your chaste wife,</l>
<l>my dearest sister, and are you without</l>
<l>all honor, so to spoil virginity </l>
<l>now making me invade my sister's claim,</l>
<l>you have befouled the sacred fount of life,—</l>
<l>you are a lawless bond of double sin!</l>

    
<l>“Oh, this dark punishment was not my due!</l>
<l>Come, finish with my murder your black deed,</l>
<l>so nothing wicked may remain undone.</l>
<l>But oh, if you had only slaughtered me</l>
<l>before your criminal embrace befouled</l>
<l>my purity, I should have had a shade</l>
<l>entirely pure, and free from any stain!</l>
<l>Oh, if there is a Majesty in Heaven,</l>
<l>and if my ruin has not wrecked the world,</l>
<l>then, you shall suffer for this grievous wrong</l>
<l>and time shall hasten to avenge my wreck.</l>

    
<l>“I shall declare your sin before the world,</l>
<l>and publish my own shame to punish you!</l>
<l>And if I'm prisoned in the solitudes,</l>
<l>my voice will wake the echoes in the wood</l>
<l>and move the conscious rocks. Hear me, O Heaven!</l>
<l>And let my imprecations rouse the Gods—</l>
<l>ah-h-h, if there can be a god in Heaven!”</l>

    
<l>Her cries aroused the dastard tyrant's wrath,</l>
<l>and frightened him, lest ever his foul deed</l>
<l>might shock his kingdom: and, roused at once</l>
<l>by rage and guilty fear; he seized her hair,</l>
<l>forced her weak arms against her back, and bound</l>
<l>them fast with brazen chains, then drew his sword.</l>

    
<l>When she first saw his sword above her head.</l>
<l>Flashing and sharp, she wished only for death,</l>
<l>and offered her bare throat: but while she screamed,</l>
<l>and, struggling, called upon her father's name,</l>
<l>he caught her tongue with pincers, pitiless,</l>

    
<l>And cut it with his sword.—The mangled root</l>
<l>still quivered, but the bleeding tongue itself,</l>
<l>fell murmuring on the blood-stained floor. As the tail</l>
<l>of a slain snake still writhes upon the ground,</l>
<l>so did the throbbing tongue; and, while it died,</l>
<l>moved up to her, as if to seek her feet.—</l>
<l>And, it is said that after this foul crime,</l>
<l>the monster violated her again.</l>

    
<l>And after these vile deeds, that wicked king</l>
<l>returned to Procne, who, when she first met</l>
<l>her brutal husband, anxiously inquired</l>
<l>for tidings of her sister; but with sighs</l>
<l>and tears, he told a false tale of her death,</l>
<l>and with such woe that all believed it true.</l>

    
<l>Then Procne, full of lamentation, took</l>
<l>her royal robe, bordered with purest gold,</l>
<l>and putting it away, assumed instead</l>
<l>garments of sable mourning; and she built</l>
<l>a noble sepulchre, and offered there</l>
<l>her pious gifts to an imagined shade;—</l>
<l>lamenting the sad death of her who lived.</l>

    
<l>A year had passed by since that awful date—</l>
<l>the sun had coursed the Zodiac's twelve signs.</l>
<l>But what could Philomela hope or do?</l>
<l>For like a jail the strong walls of the house</l>
<l>were built of massive stone, and guards around</l>
<l>prevented flight; and mutilated, she</l>
<l>could not communicate with anyone</l>
<l>to tell her injuries and tragic woe.</l>

    
<l>But even in despair and utmost grief,</l>
<l>there is an ingenuity which gives</l>
<l>inventive genius to protect from harm:</l>
<l>and now, the grief-distracted Philomela</l>
<l>wove in a warp with purple marks and white,</l>
<l>a story of the crime; and when 'twas done</l>
<l>she gave it to her one attendant there</l>
<l>and begged her by appropriate signs to take</l>
<l>it secretly to Procne. She took the web,</l>
<l>she carried it to Procne, with no thought</l>
<l>of words or messages by art conveyed.</l>

    
<l>The wife of that inhuman tyrant took</l>
<l>the cloth, and after she unwrapped it saw</l>
<l>and understood the mournful record sent.</l>
<l>She pondered it in silence and her tongue</l>
<l>could find no words to utter her despair;—</l>
<l>her grief and frenzy were too great for tears.—</l>
<l>In a mad rage her rapid mind counfounded</l>
<l>the right and wrong—intent upon revenge.</l>


    
<l>Since it was now the time of festival,</l>
<l>when all the Thracian matrons celebrate</l>
<l>the rites of Bacchus—every third year thus—</l>
<l>night then was in their secret; and at night</l>
<l>the slopes of Rhodope resounded loud</l>
<l>with clashing of shrill cymbals. So, at night</l>
<l>the frantic queen of Tereus left her home</l>
<l>and, clothed according to the well known rites</l>
<l>of Bacchus, hurried to the wilderness.</l>

    
<l>Her head was covered with the green vine leaves;</l>
<l>and from her left side native deer skin hung;</l>
<l>and on her shoulder rested a light spear.—</l>
<l>so fashioned, the revengeful Procne rushed</l>
<l>through the dark woods, attended by a host</l>
<l>of screaming followers, and wild with rage,</l>
<l>pretended it was Bacchus urged her forth.</l>

    
<l>At last she reached the lonely building, where</l>
<l>her sister, Philomela, was immured;</l>
<l>and as she howled and shouted “Ee-woh-ee-e!”,</l>
<l>She forced the massive doors; and having seized</l>
<l>her sister, instantly concealed her face</l>
<l>in ivy leaves, arrayed her in the trappings</l>
<l>of Bacchanalian rites. When this was done,</l>
<l>they rushed from there, demented, to the house</l>
<l>where as the Queen of Tereus, Procne dwelt.</l>

    
<l>When Philomela knew she had arrived</l>
<l>at that accursed house, her countenance,</l>
<l>though pale with grief, took on a ghastlier hue:</l>
<l>and, wretched in her misery and fright,</l>
<l>she shuddered in convulsions.—Procne took</l>
<l>the symbols, Bacchanalian, from her then,</l>
<l>and as she held her in a strict embrace</l>
<l>unveiled her downcast head. But she refused</l>
<l>to lift her eyes, and fixing her sad gaze</l>
<l>on vacant space, she raised her hand, instead;</l>
<l>as if in oath she called upon the Gods</l>
<l>to witness truly she had done no wrong,</l>
<l>but suffered a disgrace of violence.—</l>

    
<l>Lo, Procne, wild with a consuming rage,</l>
<l>cut short her sister's terror in these words,</l>
<l>“This is no time for weeping! awful deeds</l>
<l>demand a great revenge—take up the sword,</l>
<l>and any weapon fiercer than its edge!</l>
<l>My breast is hardened to the worst of crime</l>
<l>make haste with me! together let us put</l>
<l>this palace to the torch!</l>

    
<l>“Come, let us maim,</l>
<l>the beastly Tereus with revenging iron,</l>
<l>cut out his tongue, and quench his cruel eyes,</l>
<l>and hurl and burn him writhing in the flames!</l>
<l>Or, shall we pierce him with a grisly blade,</l>
<l>and let his black soul issue from deep wounds</l>
<l>a thousand.—Slaughter him with every death</l>
<l>imagined in the misery of hate!”</l>

    
<l>While Procne still was raving out such words,</l>
<l>Itys, her son, was hastening to his mother;</l>
<l>and when she saw him, her revengeful eyes</l>
<l>conceiving a dark punishment, she said,</l>
<l>“Aha! here comes the image of his father!”</l>
<l>She gave no other warning, but prepared</l>
<l>to execute a horrible revenge.</l>

    
<l>But when the tender child came up to her,</l>
<l>and called her “mother”, put his little arms</l>
<l>around her neck, and when he smiled and kissed</l>
<l>her often, gracious in his cunning ways,—</l>
<l>again the instinct of true motherhood</l>
<l>pulsed in her veins, and moved to pity, she</l>
<l>began to weep in spite of her resolve.</l>

    
<l>Feeling the tender impulse of her love</l>
<l>unnerving her, she turned her eyes from him</l>
<l>and looked upon her sister, and from her</l>
<l>glanced at her darling boy again. And so,</l>
<l>while she was looking at them both, by turns,</l>
<l>she said, “Why does the little one prevail</l>
<l>with pretty words, while Philomela stands</l>
<l>in silence always, with her tongue torn out?</l>
<l>She cannot call her sister, whom he calls</l>
<l>his mother! Oh, you daughter of Pandion,</l>
<l>consider what a wretch your husband is!</l>
<l>The wife of such a monster must be flint;</l>
<l>compassion in her heart is but a crime.”</l>

    
<l>No more she hesitated, but as swift</l>
<l>as the fierce tigress of the Ganges leaps,</l>
<l>seizes the suckling offspring of the hind,</l>
<l>and drags it through the forest to its lair;</l>
<l>so, Procne seized and dragged the frightened boy</l>
<l>to a most lonely section of the house;</l>
<l>and there she put him to the cruel sword,</l>
<l>while he, aware of his sad fate, stretched forth</l>
<l>his little hands, and cried, “Ah, mother,—ah!—”</l>
<l>And clung to her—clung to her, while she struck—</l>
<l>her fixed eyes, maddened, glaring horribly—</l>
<l>struck wildly, lopping off his tender limbs.</l>
<l>But Philomela cut through his tender throat.</l>

    
<l>Then they together, mangled his remains,</l>
<l>still quivering with the remnant of his life,</l>
<l>and boiled a part of him in steaming pots,</l>
<l>that bubbled over with the dead child's blood,</l>
<l>and roasted other parts on hissing spits.</l>

    
<l>And, after all was ready, Procne bade</l>
<l>her husband, Tereus, to the loathsome feast,</l>
<l>and with a false pretense of sacred rites,</l>
<l>according to the custom of her land,</l>
<l>by which, but one man may partake of it,</l>
<l>she sent the servants from the banquet hall.—</l>
<l>Tereus, majestic on his ancient throne</l>
<l>high in imagined state, devoured his son,</l>
<l>and gorged himself with flesh of his own flesh—</l>
<l>and in his rage of gluttony called out</l>
<l>for Itys to attend and share the feast!</l>

    
<l>Curst with a joy she could conceal no more,</l>
<l>and eager to gloat over his distress,</l>
<l>Procne cried out,</l>

    
<l>“Inside yourself, you have</l>
<l>the thing that you are asking for!” — Amazed,</l>
<l>he looked around and called his son again:—</l>

    
<l>that instant, Philomela sprang forth—her hair</l>
<l>disordered, and all stained with blood of murder,</l>
<l>unable then to speak, she hurled the head</l>
<l>of Itys in his father's fear-struck face,</l>
<l>and more than ever longed for fitting words.</l>

    
<l>The Thracian Tereus overturned the table,</l>
<l>and howling, called up from the Stygian pit,</l>
<l>the viperous sisters. Tearing at his breast,</l>
<l>in miserable efforts to disgorge</l>
<l>the half-digested gobbets of his son,</l>
<l>he called himself his own child's sepulchre,</l>
<l>and wept the hot tears of a frenzied man.</l>
<l>Then with his sword he rushed at the two sisters.</l>

    
<l>Fleeing from him, they seemed to rise on wings,</l>
<l>and it was true, for they had changed to birds.</l>
<l>Then Philomela, flitting to the woods,</l>
<l>found refuge in the leaves: but Procne flew</l>
<l>straight to the sheltering gables of a roof—</l>
<l>and always, if you look, you can observe</l>
<l>the brand of murder on the swallow's breast—</l>
<l>red feathers from that day. And Tereus, swift</l>
<l>in his great agitation, and his will</l>
<l>to wreak a fierce revenge, himself is turned</l>
<l>into a crested bird. His long, sharp beak</l>
<l>is given him instead of a long sword,</l>
<l>and so, because his beak is long and sharp,</l>
<l>he rightly bears the name of Hoopoe.</l>


Boreas. Zetes et Calais.

<l>Before the number of his years was told,</l>
<l>Pandion with the shades of Tartarus,</l>
<l>because of this, has wandered in sad dooms.</l>

ORITHYIA AND BOREAS

<l>Erectheus, next in line, with mighty sway</l>
<l>and justice, ruled all Athens on the throne</l>
<l>left vacant by the good Pandion's death.</l>
<l>Four daughters and four sons were granted him;</l>
<l>and of his daughters, two were beautiful,</l>
<l>and one of these was wed to Cephalus,</l>
<l>grandson of Aeolus. — But mighty Boreas</l>
<l>desired the hand of Orithyia, fair</l>
<l>and lovable.—King Tereus and the Thracians</l>
<l>were then such obstacles to Boreas</l>
<l>the god was long kept from his dear beloved.</l>
<l>Although the great king (who compels the cold</l>
<l>north-wind) had sought with prayers to win her hand,</l>
<l>and urged his love in gentleness, not force.</l>

    
<l>When quite aware his wishes were disdained,</l>
<l>he roughly said, with customary rage</l>
<l>and violence: “Away with sentimental talk!</l>

    
<l>My prayers and kind intentions are despised,</l>
<l>but I should blame nobody but myself;</l>
<l>then why should I, despising my great strength,</l>
<l>debase myself to weakness and soft prayers?—</l>
<l>might is my right, and violence my strength!—</l>
<l>by force I drive the force of gloomy clouds.</l>

    
<l>“Tremendous actions are the wine of life!—</l>
<l>monarch of Violence, rolling on clouds,</l>
<l>I toss wide waters, and I fell huge trees—</l>
<l>knotted old oaks—and whirled upon ice-wings,</l>
<l>I scatter the light snow, and pelt the Earth</l>
<l>with sleet and hail! I rush through boundless voids.</l>
<l>My thunders rumble in the hollow clouds—</l>
<l>and crash upon my brothers—fire to fire!</l>

    
<l>“Possessed of daemon-rage, I penetrate,</l>
<l>sheer to the utmost caverns of old Earth;</l>
<l>and straining, up from those unfathomed deeps,</l>
<l>scatter the terror-stricken shades of hell;</l>
<l>and hurl death-dealing earthquakes through the world!</l>

    
<l>“Such are the fateful powers I should use,</l>
<l>and never trust entreaties to prevail,</l>
<l>or win my bride—Force is the law of life!”</l>

    
<l>And now impetuous Boreas, having howled</l>
<l>resounding words, unrolled his rustling wings—</l>
<l>that fan the earth and ruffle the wide sea—</l>
<l>and, swiftly wrapping untrod mountain peaks</l>
<l>in whirling mantles of far-woven dust,</l>
<l>thence downward hovered to the darkened world;</l>
<l>and, canopied in artificial night</l>
<l>of swarthy overshadowing wings, caught up</l>
<l>the trembling Orithyia to his breast:</l>
<l>nor did he hesitate in airy course</l>
<l>until his huge wings fanned the chilling winds</l>
<l>around Ciconian Walls.</l>

    
<l>There, she was pledged</l>
<l>the wife of that cold, northern king of storms;</l>
<l>and unto him she gave those hero twins,</l>
<l>endowed with wings of their immortal sire,</l>
<l>and graceful in their mother's form and face.</l>

    
<l>Their bird-like wings were not fledged at their birth</l>
<l>and those twin boys, Zetes and Calais,</l>
<l>at first were void of feathers and soft down.</l>
<l>But when their golden hair and beards were grown,</l>
<l>wings like an eagle's came;—and feather-down</l>
<l>grew golden on their cheeks: and when from youth</l>
<l>they entered manhood, quick they were to join</l>
<l>the Argonauts, who for the Golden Fleece,</l>
<l>sought in that first ship, ventured on the sea.</l>
