<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 9


Achelous et Hercules.
HERCULES AND ACHELOUS

<l>To him the hero, who proclaimed himself</l>
<l>a favored son of Neptune, answered now;</l>
<l>“Declare the reason of your heavy sighs,</l>
<l>and how your horn was broken?” And at once</l>
<l>the Calydonian River-God replied,</l>
<l>binding with reeds his unadorned rough locks:</l>

    
<l>“It is a mournful task you have required,</l>
<l>for who can wish to tell his own disgrace?</l>
<l>But truly I shall speak without disguise,</l>
<l>for my defeat, if rightly understood,</l>
<l>should be my glory.—Even to have fought</l>
<l>in battle with a hero of such might,</l>
<l>affords me consolation.</l>

    
<l>“Deianira</l>
<l>(you may have heard some tales of her) was once</l>
<l>the envied hope of many. She was then</l>
<l>a lovely virgin.—I, among the rest</l>
<l>who loved this maiden, entered the fair home</l>
<l>of her great father Oeneus, and I said;</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Consider all my claims, Parthaon's son,</l>
<l>for I am come to plead your daughter's cause</l>
<l>and mine—So you may make me son-in-law.,—’</l>
<l>no sooner was it said, than Hercules</l>
<l>in such words also claimed the virgin's hand:</l>
<l>all others quickly yielded to our claims.</l>

    
<l>“He boasted his descent from Jupiter;</l>
<l>the glory of his labors and great deeds</l>
<l>performed at his unjust stepmother's wish.</l>

    
<l>“But as he was not then a God, it seemed</l>
<l>disgraceful if my state should yield my right;</l>
<l>so I contended with these haughty words,</l>
<l>‘Why should this alien of a foreign land,</l>
<l>contending for your daughter, match himself</l>
<l>to me! king of the waters in this realm!</l>
<l>For as I wind around, across your lands,</l>
<l>I must be of your people, and a part</l>
<l>of your great state. Oh, let it not be said,</l>
<l>because the jealous Juno had no thought</l>
<l>to punish me by labors, my descent</l>
<l>is not so regal! This tremendous boast,</l>
<l>that you, Alcmena's son, are sprung from Jove,</l>
<l>falls at the touch of truth;—or it reveals</l>
<l>the shame of a weak mother, who so gained</l>
<l>your doubtful glory of descent from Heaven!</l>
<l>Prove your descent from Jupiter is false,</l>
<l>or else confess you are the son of shame!’</l>

    
<l>“But Hercules, unable to control</l>
<l>the flame of his great wrath, scowled as I spoke.</l>
<l>He briefly answered me, ‘My hand excels</l>
<l>my tongue; let me now overcome in fight,</l>
<l>and I may suffer your offence of words.’</l>

    
<l>“Full of unvented rage he rushed on me,</l>
<l>but firm I stood, ashamed to yield a foot—</l>
<l>I had so largely boasted, no retreat was left,</l>
<l>and so I doffed my green robe—Striking guard,</l>
<l>with clenched hands doubled at my breast,</l>
<l>I stood my ground. He scooped up in his hand</l>
<l>fine, yellow dust; and tossed it on the air</l>
<l>so that the tawny powder sprinkled us;</l>
<l>quick-shifting then he sought to strike my neck,</l>
<l>or feint at my quick-moving legs, and turn</l>
<l>swift moving to attack me at all points.</l>
<l>But as a huge cliff in the sea remains</l>
<l>unmoved, unshaken by the sounding waves,</l>
<l>so my great size, against his vain attacks,</l>
<l>defended me securely—Back we went;</l>
<l>retiring for a space; then rushed again</l>
<l>together, furious, and with foot to foot,</l>
<l>determined not to yield, defiant stood,</l>
<l>till, forward-bending from my waist and hips,</l>
<l>I pressed my forehead against his and locked</l>
<l>his fingers into mine: so, have I seen</l>
<l>two strong bulls rush in combat for the good</l>
<l>of some smooth heifer in the pasture—while</l>
<l>the herd a-tremble and uncertain, wait;</l>
<l>ready to give allegiance to the one</l>
<l>most worthy of dominion.</l>

    
<l>“Thrice in vain</l>
<l>Hercules strove to push my breast from his,</l>
<l>but I pressed ever closer—till, the fourth</l>
<l>attempt succeeding, he unloosed my grip,</l>
<l>and breaking from my circling arms drew back,</l>
<l>and struck me such a buffet with his hand,</l>
<l>it twisted me about, and instantly</l>
<l>he clung with all his weight upon my back—</l>

    
<l>“Believe me I have not suppressed the truth.</l>
<l>Nor shall I try to gain applause not due:</l>
<l>I seemed to bear a mountain on my back. —</l>
<l>straining and dripping sweat, I broke his hold,—</l>
<l>with great exertion I unlocked his grip.</l>
<l>He pressed upon me, as I strained for breath,</l>
<l>preventing a renewal of my strength,</l>
<l>and seized upon my neck. Then at the last,</l>
<l>my bent knee went down on the gritty earth,</l>
<l>I bit the sand. So, worsted in my strength,</l>
<l>I sought diversion by an artifice,</l>
<l>and changed me to a serpent.—I then slipped</l>
<l>from his tight clutches my great length, and coiled</l>
<l>my body now transformed to snaky folds—</l>
<l>hissing I darted my divided tongue.</l>

    
<l>“But Hercules, Alcides, only laughed</l>
<l>and in derision of my scheming, said,</l>
<l>‘It was the pastime of my cradle days</l>
<l>to strangle better snakes than you—and though</l>
<l>your great length may excel all of your kind,</l>
<l>how small a part of that Lernaean snake</l>
<l>would you—one serpent be? It grew from wounds</l>
<l>I gave (at first it had one hundred heads)</l>
<l>and every time I severed one head from</l>
<l>its neck two grew there in the place of one,</l>
<l>by which its strength increased. This creature then</l>
<l>outbranching with strong serpents, sprung from death</l>
<l>and thriving on destruction, I destroyed.—</l>
<l>What do you think will then become of you,</l>
<l>disguised so in deceitful serpent-form,</l>
<l>wielding a borrowed weapon not your own</l>

    
<l>“And after he had ridiculed me thus,</l>
<l>he gouged his fingers underneath my jaws,</l>
<l>so that my throat was tortured, as if squeezed</l>
<l>with forceps, while I struggled in his grip.</l>

    
<l>“Twice was I vanquished, there remained to me</l>
<l>a third form so again I changed to seem</l>
<l>a savage bull, and with my limbs renewed</l>
<l>in that form fought once more. He threw his arms</l>
<l>about the left side of my ponderous neck,</l>
<l>and dragging on me followed as I ran.</l>
<l>He seized on my hard horns, and, tugging turned</l>
<l>and twisted me, until he fastened them</l>
<l>firm in the surface of the earth; and pushed</l>
<l>me, helpless, to the shifting sand beneath.</l>
<l>Not yet content he laid his fierce right hand</l>
<l>on my tough horn, and broke and tore it from</l>
<l>my mutilated head.—This horn, now heaped</l>
<l>with fruits delicious and sweet-smelling flowers,</l>
<l>the Naiads have held sacred from that hour,</l>
<l>devoted to the bounteous goddess Plenty.’</l>

    
<l>All this the River-god said; then a nymph,</l>
<l>a lovely nymph like fair Diana dressed,</l>
<l>whose locks were flowing down on either side,</l>
<l>came graceful to the board, and brought to them</l>
<l>of Autumn's plenty in an ample horn,</l>
<l>and gave to them selected apples for</l>
<l>a second course.</l>

    
<l>And now, as early dawn</l>
<l>appeared, and as the rising sunlight flashed</l>
<l>on golden summits of surrounding hills,</l>
<l>the young men waited not until the stream</l>
<l>subsiding, had resumed its peaceful way,</l>
<l>but all arose, reluctant, and went forth.</l>

    
<l>Then Achelous, in his moving waves,</l>
<l>hid his fine rustic features and his head,</l>
<l>scarred by the wound which gave the Horn of Plenty.</l>


Nessus. Herculis mors.
NESSUS AND THE DEATH OF HERCULES

<l>Loss of his horn had greatly humbled him,</l>
<l>it was so cherished though his only loss, —</l>
<l>but he could hide the sad disgrace with reeds</l>
<l>and willow boughs entwined about his head.</l>

    
<l>O, Nessus! your fierce passion for the same</l>
<l>maid utterly destroyed even you, pierced through</l>
<l>the body by a flying arrow-point.</l>

    
<l>Returning to the city of his birth</l>
<l>great Hercules, the son of Jupiter,</l>
<l>with his new bride, arrived upon the bank</l>
<l>of swift Evenus—after winter rains</l>
<l>had swollen it so far beyond its wont,</l>
<l>that, full of eddies, it was found to be</l>
<l>impassable. The hero stood there, brave</l>
<l>but anxious for his bride. Nessus, the centaur,</l>
<l>strong-limbed and well-acquainted with those fords,</l>
<l>came up to him and said, “Plunge in the flood</l>
<l>and swim with unimpeded strength—for with</l>
<l>my help she will land safely over there.”</l>

    
<l>And so the hero, with no thought of doubt,</l>
<l>trusted the damsel to the centaur's care,</l>
<l>though she was pale and trembling with her fear</l>
<l>of the swift river and the centaur's aid.</l>

    
<l>This done, the hero, burdened as he was</l>
<l>with quiver and the lion skin (for he</l>
<l>had tossed his club and curving bow across</l>
<l>the river to the other bank), declared,</l>
<l>“Since I have undertaken it, at once</l>
<l>this rushing water must be overcome.”</l>
<l>And instantly, he plunged in without thought</l>
<l>of where he might cross with most ease, for so</l>
<l>he scorned to take advantage of smooth water.</l>

    
<l>And after he had gained the other bank,</l>
<l>while picking up his bow which there was thrown,</l>
<l>he heard his wife's voice, anxious for his help.</l>
<l>He called to Nessus who was in the act</l>
<l>then to betray his trust: “Vain confidence!</l>
<l>You are not swift enough, vile ravisher!</l>
<l>You two-formed monster Nessus, I warn you!</l>
<l>Hear me, and never dare to come between</l>
<l>me and my love. If fear has no restraint,</l>
<l>your father's dreadful fate on whirling wheel,</l>
<l>should frighten you from this outrageous act:</l>
<l>for you cannot escape, although you trust</l>
<l>the fleet-foot effort of a rapid horse.</l>
<l>I cannot overtake you with my feet</l>
<l>but I can shoot and halt you with a wound.”</l>

    
<l>his deed sustained the final warning word.</l>
<l>He shot an arrow through the centaur's back,</l>
<l>so that the keen barb was exposed beyond</l>
<l>his bleeding breast. He tore it from both wounds,</l>
<l>and life-blood spurted instantly, mixed with</l>
<l>the deadly poison of Lernaean hydra.</l>
<l>This Nessus caught, and muttering, “I shall not</l>
<l>die unavenged”, he gave his tunic, soaked</l>
<l>with blood to Deianira as a gift;</l>
<l>and said, “Keep this to strengthen waning love.”</l>

    
<l>Now many years passed by, and all the deeds,</l>
<l>and labors of the mighty Hercules,</l>
<l>gave to the wide world his unequalled fame;</l>
<l>and finally appeased the hatred of</l>
<l>his fierce stepmother.</l>

    
<l>All victorious</l>
<l>returning from Oechalia, he prepared</l>
<l>to offer sacrifice, when at Cenaeum,</l>
<l>upon an altar he had built to Jupiter,</l>
<l>but tattling Rumor, swollen out of truth</l>
<l>from small beginning to a wicked lie,</l>
<l>declared brave Hercules, Amphitryon's son,</l>
<l>was burning for the love of Iole.</l>
<l>And Deianira—his fond wife—convinced</l>
<l>herself, the wicked rumor must be true.</l>

    
<l>Alarmed at the report of his new love,</l>
<l>at first, poor wife, she was dissolved in tears,</l>
<l>and then she sank in grievous misery.</l>
<l>But soon in angry mood, she rose and said:</l>

    
<l>“Why should I give up to my sorrow while</l>
<l>I drown my wretched spirit in weak tears?</l>
<l>Let me consider an effectual check—</l>
<l>while it is possible—even before</l>
<l>she comes, invader of my lawful bed:</l>
<l>shall I be silent or complain of it?</l>
<l>Must I go back to Calydon or stay?</l>
<l>Shall I depart unbidden, from my house?</l>
<l>Or, if no other method can prevail,</l>
<l>shall I oppose my rival's first approach?</l>
<l>O shade of Meleager, let me prove</l>
<l>I am yet worthy to be called your sister;</l>
<l>and in the desperate slaughter of this rival,</l>
<l>the world, astonished, may be taught to fear</l>
<l>the vengeance of an injured woman's rage.”</l>

    
<l>So, torn by many moods, at last her mind</l>
<l>fixed on one thought:—she might still keep his love,</l>
<l>could certainly restore it, if she sent</l>
<l>to him the tunic soaked in Nessus' blood.</l>

    
<l>Unknowingly, she gave the fatal cause</l>
<l>of her own woe to trusting Lichas, whom</l>
<l>she urged in gentle words to take the gift,</l>
<l>from her to her loved husband Hercules.</l>
<l>He, unsuspecting, put the tunic on,</l>
<l>all covered with Lernaean hydra's poison.</l>

    
<l>The hero then was casting frankincense</l>
<l>into the sacred flames, and pouring wine</l>
<l>on marble altars, as his holy prayers</l>
<l>were floating to the Gods. The hallowed heat</l>
<l>striking upon his poisoned vesture, caused</l>
<l>Echidna-bane to melt into his flesh.</l>

    
<l>As long as he was able he withstood</l>
<l>the torture. His great fortitude was strong.</l>
<l>But when at last his anguish overcame</l>
<l>even his endurance, he filled all the wild</l>
<l>of Oeta with his cries: he overturned</l>
<l>those hallowed altars, then in frenzied haste</l>
<l>he strove to pull the tunic from his back.</l>
<l>The poisoned garment, cleaving to him, ripped</l>
<l>his skin, heat-shriveled, from his burning flesh.</l>
<l>Or, tightening on him, as his great strength pulled,</l>
<l>stripped with it the great muscles from his limbs,</l>
<l>leaving his huge bones bare.</l>

    
<l>Even his blood</l>
<l>audibly hissed, as red-hot blades when they</l>
<l>are plunged in water, so the burning bane</l>
<l>boiled in his veins. Great perspiration streamed</l>
<l>from his dissolving body, as the heat</l>
<l>consumed his entrails; and his sinews cracked,</l>
<l>brittle when burnt. The marrow in his bones</l>
<l>dissolved, as it absorbed the venom-heat.</l>

<l>There was no limit to his misery;</l>
<l>raising both hands up towards the stars of heaven,</l>
<l>he cried, “Come Juno, feast upon my death;</l>
<l>feast on me, cruel one, look down from your</l>
<l>exalted seat; behold my dreadful end</l>
<l>and glut your savage heart! Oh, if I may</l>
<l>deserve some pity from my enemy,</l>
<l>from you I mean, this hateful life of mine</l>
<l>take from me—sick with cruel suffering</l>
<l>and only born for toil. The loss of life</l>
<l>will be a boon to me, and surely is</l>
<l>a fitting boon, such as stepmothers give!</l>

    
<l>“Was it for this I slew Busiris, who</l>
<l>defiled his temples with the strangers' blood?</l>
<l>For this I took his mother's strength from fierce</l>
<l>antaeus—that I did not show a fear</l>
<l>before the Spanish shepherd's triple form?</l>
<l>Nor did I fear the monstrous triple form</l>
<l>of Cerberus.—And is it possible</l>
<l>my hands once seized and broke the strong bull's horns?</l>
<l>And Elis knows their labor, and the waves</l>
<l>of Stymphalus, and the Parthenian woods.</l>
<l>For this the prowess of these hands secured</l>
<l>the Amazonian girdle wrought of gold;</l>
<l>and did my strong arms, gather all in vain</l>
<l>the fruit when guarded by the dragon's eyes.</l>
<l>The centaurs could not foil me, nor the boar</l>
<l>that ravaged in Arcadian fruitful fields.</l>
<l>Was it for this the hydra could not gain</l>
<l>double the strength from strength as it was lost?</l>
<l>And when I saw the steeds of Thrace, so fat</l>
<l>with human blood, and their vile mangers heaped</l>
<l>with mangled bodies, in a righteous rage</l>
<l>I threw them to the ground, and slaughtered them,</l>
<l>together with their master! In a cave</l>
<l>I crushed the Nemean monster with these arms;</l>
<l>and my strong neck upheld the wide-spread sky!</l>
<l>And even the cruel Juno, wife of Jove—</l>
<l>is weary of imposing heavy toils,</l>
<l>but I am not subdued performing them.</l>

    
<l>“A new calamity now crushes me,</l>
<l>which not my strength, nor valor, nor the use</l>
<l>of weapons can resist. Devouring flames</l>
<l>have preyed upon my limbs, and blasting heat</l>
<l>now shrivels the burnt tissue of my frame.</l>
<l>But still Eurystheus is alive and well!</l>
<l>And there are those who yet believe in Gods!”</l>

    
<l>Just as a wild bull, in whose body spears</l>
<l>are rankling, while the frightened hunter flies</l>
<l>away for safety, so the hero ranged</l>
<l>over sky-piercing Oeta; his huge groans,</l>
<l>his awful shrieks resounding in those cliffs.</l>
<l>At times he struggles with the poisoned robe.</l>
<l>Goaded to fury, he has razed great trees,</l>
<l>and scattered the vast mountain rocks around!</l>
<l>And stretched his arms towards his ancestral skies!</l>

    
<l>So, in his frenzy, as he wandered there,</l>
<l>he chanced upon the trembling Lichas, crouched</l>
<l>in the close covert of a hollow rock.</l>
<l>Then in a savage fury he cried out,</l>
<l>“Was it you, Lichas, brought this fatal gift?</l>
<l>Shall you be called the author of my death?”</l>
<l>Lichas, in terror, groveled at his feet,</l>
<l>and begged for mercy—“Only let me live!”</l>
<l>But seizing on him, the crazed Hero whirled</l>
<l>him thrice and once again about his head,</l>
<l>and hurled him, shot as by a catapult,</l>
<l>into the waves of the Euboic Sea.</l>

    
<l>While he was hanging in the air, his form</l>
<l>was hardened; as, we know, rain drops may first</l>
<l>be frozen by the cold air, and then change</l>
<l>to snow, and as it falls through whirling winds</l>
<l>may press, so twisted, into round hailstones:</l>
<l>even so has ancient lore declared that when</l>
<l>strong arms hurled Lichas through the mountain air</l>
<l>through fear, his blood was curdled in his veins.</l>
<l>No moisture left in him, he was transformed</l>
<l>into a flint-rock. Even to this day,</l>
<l>a low crag rising from the waves is seen</l>
<l>out of the deep Euboean Sea, and holds</l>
<l>the certain outline of a human form,</l>
<l>so sure]y traced, the wary sailors fear</l>
<l>to tread upon it, thinking it has life,</l>
<l>and they have called it Lichas ever since.</l>

    
<l>But, O illustrious son of Jupiter!</l>
<l>How many of the overspreading trees,</l>
<l>thick-growing on the lofty mountain-peak</l>
<l>of Oeta, did you level to the ground,</l>
<l>and heap into a pyre! And then you bade</l>
<l>obedient Philoctetes light a torch</l>
<l>beneath it, and then take in recompense</l>
<l>your bow with its capacious quiver full</l>
<l>of arrows, arms that now again would see</l>
<l>the realm of Troy. And as the pyre began</l>
<l>to kindle with the greedy flames, you spread</l>
<l>the Nemean lion skin upon the top,</l>
<l>and, club for pillow, you lay down to sleep,</l>
<l>as placid as if, with abounding cups</l>
<l>of generous wine and crowned with garlands, you</l>
<l>were safe, reclining on a banquet-couch.</l>

    
<l>And now on every side the spreading flames</l>
<l>were crackling fiercely, as they leaped from earth</l>
<l>upon the careless limbs of Hercules.</l>
<l>He scorned their power. The Gods felt fear</l>
<l>for earth's defender and their sympathy</l>
<l>gave pleasure to Saturnian Jove — he knew</l>
<l>their thought—and joyfully he said to them:</l>

    
<l>“Your sudden fear is surely my delight,</l>
<l>O heavenly Gods! my heart is lifted up</l>
<l>and joy prevails upon me, in the thought</l>
<l>that I am called the Father and the King</l>
<l>of all this grateful race of Gods. I know</l>
<l>my own beloved offspring is secure</l>
<l>in your declared protection: your concern</l>
<l>may justly evidence his worth, whose deeds</l>
<l>great benefits bestowed. Let not vain thoughts</l>
<l>alarm you, nor the rising flames of Oeta;</l>
<l>for Hercules who conquered everything,</l>
<l>shall conquer equally the spreading fires</l>
<l>which now you see: and all that part of him,</l>
<l>celestial — inherited of me—</l>
<l>immortal, cannot feel the power of death.</l>
<l>It is not subject to the poison-heat.</l>
<l>And therefore, since his earth-life is now lost,</l>
<l>him I'll translate, unshackled from all dross,</l>
<l>and purified, to our celestial shore.</l>
<l>I trust this action seems agreeable</l>
<l>to all the Deities surrounding me.</l>
<l>If any jealous god of heaven should grieve</l>
<l>at the divinity of Hercules,</l>
<l>he may begrudge the prize but he will know</l>
<l>at least 'twas given him deservedly,</l>
<l>and with this thought he must approve the deed.”</l>

    
<l>The Gods confirmed it: and though Juno seemed</l>
<l>to be contented and to acquiesce,</l>
<l>her deep vexation was not wholly hid,</l>
<l>when Jupiter with his concluding words</l>
<l>so plainly hinted at her jealous mind.</l>

    
<l>Now, while the Gods conversed, the mortal part</l>
<l>of Hercules was burnt by Mulciber;</l>
<l>but yet an outline of a spirit-form</l>
<l>remained. Unlike the well-known mortal shape</l>
<l>derived by nature of his mother, he</l>
<l>kept traces only of his father, Jove.</l>

    
<l>And as a serpent, when it is revived</l>
<l>from its old age, casts off the faded skin,</l>
<l>and fresh with vigor glitters in new scales,</l>
<l>so, when the hero had put off all dross,</l>
<l>his own celestial, wonderful appeared,</l>
<l>majestic and of godlike dignity.</l>

    
<l>And him, the glorious father of the Gods</l>
<l>in the great chariot drawn by four swift steeds,</l>
<l>took up above the wide-encircling clouds,</l>
<l>and set him there amid the glittering stars.</l>


Alcmene et Galanthis.
GALANTHIS

<l>Even Atlas felt the weight of Heaven increase,</l>
<l>but King Eurystheus, still implacable,</l>
<l>vented his baffled hatred on the sons</l>
<l>of the great hero. Then the Argive mother,</l>
<l>Alcmena, spent and anxious with long cares,</l>
<l>the burden of her old age and her fears,</l>
<l>could pass the weary hours with Iole</l>
<l>in garrulous narrations of his worth,</l>
<l>his mighty labors and her own sad days.</l>
<l>Iole, by command of Hercules,</l>
<l>had been betrothed to Hyllus, and by him</l>
<l>was gravid, burdened with a noble child.</l>
<l>And so to Iole, Alcmena told</l>
<l>this story of the birth of Hercules:—</l>

    
<l>“Ah, may the Gods be merciful to you</l>
<l>and give you swift deliverance in that hour</l>
<l>when needful of all help you must call out</l>
<l>for Ilithyia, the known goddess of</l>
<l>all frightened mothers in their travail, she</l>
<l>whom Juno's hatred overcame and made</l>
<l>so dreadful against me. For, when my hour</l>
<l>of bearing Hercules was very near,</l>
<l>and when the tenth sign of the zodiac</l>
<l>was traversed by the sun, my burden then</l>
<l>became so heavy, and the one I bore</l>
<l>so large, you certainly could tell that Jove</l>
<l>must be the father of the unborn child.</l>

    
<l>“At last, no longer able to endure—</l>
<l>ah me, a cold sweat seizes on me now;</l>
<l>only to think of it renews my pains!</l>
<l>Seven days in agony, as many nights,</l>
<l>exhausted in my dreadful misery,</l>
<l>I stretched my arms to heaven and invoked</l>
<l>Lucina and three Nixian deities</l>
<l>the guardians of birth. Lucina came;</l>
<l>but before then she had been pledged to give</l>
<l>my life to cruel Juno. While Lucina</l>
<l>sat on the altar near the door and listened,</l>
<l>with her right knee crossed over her left knee,</l>
<l>with fingers interlocked, she stopped the birth:</l>
<l>and in low muttered tones she chanted Charms</l>
<l>which there prevented my deliverance.</l>

    
<l>“I fiercely struggled, and insane with pain</l>
<l>shrieked vain revilings against Jupiter;</l>
<l>I longed for death, and my delirious words</l>
<l>then should have moved the most unfeeling rocks.</l>
<l>The Theban matrons, eager to help me,</l>
<l>stood near me while they asked the aid of Heaven.</l>

    
<l>“And there was present of the common class,</l>
<l>my maid Galanthis—with her red-gold hair—</l>
<l>efficient and most willing to obey</l>
<l>her worthy character deserved my love.</l>
<l>She felt assured, Juno unjustly worked</l>
<l>some spell of strong effect against my life.</l>
<l>And when this maid beheld Lucina perched</l>
<l>so strangely on the altar, with her fingers</l>
<l>inwoven on her knees and tightly pressed</l>
<l>together, in a gripping finger-comb,</l>
<l>she guessed that jealous Juno was the cause.</l>
<l>Quick-witted, in a ringing voice this maid</l>
<l>cried out, ‘Congratulations! All is well!</l>
<l>Alcmena is delivered—a fine child</l>
<l>so safely brought forth—her true prayers approved!’</l>

    
<l>“Lucina, who presides at birth, surprised</l>
<l>leaped up, unclenched her hands, as one amazed.</l>
<l>Just as her hands unfastened, and her knees</l>
<l>were parted from their stricture, I could feel</l>
<l>the bonds of stricture loosen; and without</l>
<l>more labor was delivered of my child.</l>

    
<l>“'Tis said, Galanthis laughed and ridiculed</l>
<l>the cheated deity; and as she laughed</l>
<l>the vixen goddess caught her by the hair</l>
<l>and dragging her upon the ground, while she</l>
<l>was struggling to arise, held her, and there</l>
<l>transformed both of her arms to animal</l>
<l>forelegs. Her old activity remained;</l>
<l>her hair was not changed, but she did not keep</l>
<l>her maiden form: and ever since that day,</l>
<l>because she aided with deceitful lips,</l>
<l>her offspring are brought forth through the same mouth.</l>
<l>Changed to a weasel she dwells now with me.”</l>


Dryope. Iolaus.

<l>When she had ended the sad tale, she heaved</l>
<l>a deep sigh, in remembrance of her tried,</l>
<l>beloved servant; and her daughter-in-law</l>
<l>Iole kindly answered in these words:</l>

DRYOPE

<l>“O my dear mother, if you weep because</l>
<l>of her who was your servant, now transformed</l>
<l>into a weasel, how can you support</l>
<l>the true narration of my sister's fate;</l>
<l>which I must tell to you, although my tears</l>
<l>and sorrows hinder and forbid my speech?</l>

    
<l>“Most beautiful of all Oechalian maids,</l>
<l>was Dryope, her mother's only child,</l>
<l>for you must know I am the daughter of</l>
<l>my father's second wife. She is not now</l>
<l>a maid; because, through violence of him</l>
<l>who rules at Delphi and at Delos, she</l>
<l>was taken by Andraemon, who since then</l>
<l>has been accounted happy in his wife.</l>

    
<l>“There is a lake surrounded by sweet lawns,</l>
<l>encircling beauties, where the upper slope</l>
<l>is crowned with myrtles in fair sunny groves.</l>
<l>Without a thought of danger Dryope</l>
<l>in worship one day went to gather flowers,</l>
<l>(who hears, has greater cause to be indignant)</l>
<l>delightful garlands, for the water-nymphs,</l>
<l>and, in her bosom, carried her dear son,</l>
<l>not yet a year old, whom she fed for love.</l>
<l>Not far from that dream-lake, in moisture grew</l>
<l>a lotus, beautiful in purple bloom,</l>
<l>the blossoms promising its fruit was near.</l>

    
<l>“At play with her sweet infant, Dryope</l>
<l>plucked them as toys for him. I, too, was there,</l>
<l>eagerly, also, I put forth my hand,</l>
<l>and was just ready to secure a spray,</l>
<l>when I was startled by some drops of blood</l>
<l>down-falling from the blossoms which were plucked;</l>
<l>and even the trembling branches shook in dread.</l>

    
<l>“Who wills, the truth of this may learn from all</l>
<l>quaint people of that land, who still relate</l>
<l>the Story of Nymph Lotis. She, they say,</l>
<l>while flying from the lust of Priapus,</l>
<l>was transformed quickly from her human shape,</l>
<l>into this tree, though she has kept her name.</l>

    
<l>“But ignorant of all this, Dryope,</l>
<l>alarmed, decided she must now return;</l>
<l>so, having first adored the hallowed nymphs,</l>
<l>upright she stood, and would have moved away,</l>
<l>but both her feet were tangled in a root.</l>
<l>There, as she struggled in its tightening hold,</l>
<l>she could move nothing save her upper parts;</l>
<l>and growing from that root, live bark began</l>
<l>to gather slowly upward from the ground,</l>
<l>spreading around her, till it touched her loins:</l>
<l>in terror when she saw the clinging growth,</l>
<l>she would have torn her hair out by the roots,</l>
<l>but, when she clutched at it, her hands were filled</l>
<l>with lotus leaves grown up from her changed head.</l>

    
<l>“Alas, her little son, Amphissos, felt</l>
<l>his mother's bosom harden to his touch,</l>
<l>and no life-stream refreshed his eager lips.</l>
<l>And while I saw your cruel destiny,</l>
<l>O my dear sister! and could give no help,</l>
<l>I clung to your loved body and around</l>
<l>the growing trunk and branches, hoping so</l>
<l>to stop their evil growth; and I confess,</l>
<l>endeavored there to hide beneath the bark.</l>

    
<l>“And, oh! Andraemon and her father, then</l>
<l>appeared to me while they were sadly seeking</l>
<l>for Dryope: so there I had to show</l>
<l>the lotus as it covered her, and they</l>
<l>gave kisses to the warm wood, and prostrate fell</l>
<l>upon the ground, and clung to growing roots</l>
<l>of their new darling tree, transformed from her.—</l>
<l>Dear sister, there was nothing of yourself</l>
<l>remaining but your face; and I could see</l>
<l>your tears drop slowly on the trembling leaves</l>
<l>which had so marvellously grown on you;</l>
<l>and while your lips remained uncovered, all</l>
<l>the air surrounding, echoed your complaint:—</l>

    
<l>“If oaths of wretched women can have force,</l>
<l>I swear I have not merited this fate!</l>
<l>Though innocent, to suffer punishment!</l>
<l>And if one word of my complaint is false,</l>
<l>I pray I may soon wither, and my leaves</l>
<l>fall from me as in blight, and let the axe</l>
<l>devote me, wretched to the flames. But take</l>
<l>this infant from my branches to a nurse;</l>
<l>and let him often play beneath his tree,—</l>
<l>his mother always. Let him drink his milk</l>
<l>beneath my shade. When he has learned to talk</l>
<l>let him salute me, and in sorrow say</l>
<l>“In this tree-trunk my mother is concealed.”</l>
<l>O, let him dread the fate that lurks in ponds,</l>
<l>and let him often play beneath his tree,—</l>
<l>and let him be persuaded every shrub</l>
<l>contains the body of a goddess. — Ah!</l>
<l>Farewell my husband,—sister, — and farewell</l>
<l>my father! If my love remain in you</l>
<l>remember to protect my life from harm,</l>
<l>so that the pruning-knife may never clip</l>
<l>my branches, and protect my foliage from</l>
<l>the browsing sheep.</l>

    
<l>“I cannot stoop to you;</l>
<l>0h, if you love me, lift your lips to mine,</l>
<l>and let me kiss you, if but once again,</l>
<l>before this growing lotus covers me.</l>
<l>Lift up my darling infant to my lips.</l>
<l>How can I hope to say much more to you?</l>
<l>The new bark now is creeping up my neck,</l>
<l>and creeping downward from my covered brow!</l>
<l>Ah, do not close my live eyes with your hands;</l>
<l>there is no need of it, for growing bark</l>
<l>will spread and darken them before I die!’</l>
<l>Such were the last words her poor smothered lips</l>
<l>could utter; for she was so quickly changed;</l>
<l>and long thereafter the new branches kept</l>
<l>the warmth of her lost body, so transformed.”</l>

IOLAUS

<l>And all the while that Iole told this,</l>
<l>tearful in sorrow for her sister's fate,</l>
<l>Alcmena weeping, tried to comfort her.</l>
<l>But as they wept together, suddenly</l>
<l>a wonderful event astonished them;</l>
<l>for, standing in the doorway, they beheld</l>
<l>the old man Iolaus, known to them,</l>
<l>but now transformed from age to youth, he seemed</l>
<l>almost a boy, with light down on his cheeks:</l>
<l>for Juno's daughter Hebe, had renewed</l>
<l>his years to please her husband, Hercules.</l>
<l>Just at the time when ready to make oath,</l>
<l>she would not grant such gifts to other men—</l>
<l>Themis had happily prevented her.</l>

    
<l>“For even now,” she said, “a civil strife</l>
<l>is almost ready to break forth in Thebes,</l>
<l>and Capaneus shall be invincible</l>
<l>to all save the strong hand of Jove himself;</l>
<l>and there two hostile brothers shall engage</l>
<l>in bloody conflict; and Amphiaraus</l>
<l>shall see his own ghost, deep in yawning earth.</l>

    
<l>“His own son, dutiful to him, shall be</l>
<l>both just and unjust in a single deed;</l>
<l>for he, in vengeance for his father's death,</l>
<l>shall slay his mother, and confounded lose</l>
<l>both home and reason,—persecuted both</l>
<l>by the grim Furies and the awful ghost</l>
<l>of his own murdered mother; this until</l>
<l>his wife, deluded, shall request of him</l>
<l>the fatal golden necklace, and until</l>
<l>the sword of Phegeus drains his kinsman's blood.</l>

    
<l>“And then at last his wife Callirhoe</l>
<l>shall supplicate the mighty Jupiter</l>
<l>to grant her infant sons the added years</l>
<l>of youthful manhood. Then shall Jupiter</l>
<l>let Hebe, guardian of ungathered days,</l>
<l>grant from the future to Callirhoe's sons,</l>
<l>the strength of manhood in their infancy.</l>
<l>Do not let their victorious father's death</l>
<l>be unavenged a long while. Jove prevailed</l>
<l>upon, will claim beforehand all the gifts</l>
<l>of Hebe, who is his known daughter-in-law,</l>
<l>and his step-daughter, and with one act change</l>
<l>Callirhoe's beardless boys to men of size.”</l>


Byblis.

<l>When Themis, prophesying future days,</l>
<l>had said these words, the Gods of Heaven complained</l>
<l>because they also could not grant the gift</l>
<l>of youth to many others in this way.</l>
<l>Aurora wept because her husband had</l>
<l>white hair; and Ceres then bewailed the age</l>
<l>of her Iasion, grey and stricken old;</l>
<l>and Mulciber demanded with new life</l>
<l>his Erichthonius might again appear;</l>
<l>and Venus, thinking upon future days,</l>
<l>said old Anchises' years must be restored.</l>

    
<l>And every god preferred some favorite,</l>
<l>until vexed with the clamor, Jupiter</l>
<l>implored, “If you can have regard for me,</l>
<l>consider the strange blessings you desire:</l>
<l>does any one of you believe he can</l>
<l>prevail against the settled will of Fate?</l>
<l>As Iolaus has returned by fate,</l>
<l>to those years spent by him; so by the Fates</l>
<l>Callirhoe's sons from infancy must grow</l>
<l>to manhood with no struggle on their part,</l>
<l>or force of their ambition. And you should</l>
<l>endure your fortune with contented minds:</l>
<l>I, also, must give all control to Fate.</l>

    
<l>“If I had power to change the course of Fate</l>
<l>I would not let advancing age break down</l>
<l>my own son Aeacus, nor bend his back</l>
<l>with weight of year; and Rhadamanthus should</l>
<l>retain an everlasting flower of youth,</l>
<l>together with my own son Minos, who</l>
<l>is now despised because of his great age,</l>
<l>so that his scepter has lost dignity.”</l>

    
<l>Such words of Jupiter controlled the Gods,</l>
<l>and none continued to complain, when they</l>
<l>saw Aeacus and Rhadamanthus old,</l>
<l>and Minos also, weary of his age.</l>
<l>And they remembered Minos in his prime,</l>
<l>had warred against great nations, till his name</l>
<l>if mentioned was a certain cause of fear.</l>
<l>But now, enfeebled by great age, he feared</l>
<l>Miletus, Deione's son, because</l>
<l>of his exultant youth and strength derived</l>
<l>from his great father Phoebus. And although</l>
<l>he well perceived Miletus' eye was fixed</l>
<l>upon his throne, he did not dare to drive</l>
<l>him from his kingdom.</l>

    
<l>But although not forced,</l>
<l>Miletus of his own accord did fly,</l>
<l>by swift ship, over to the Asian shore,</l>
<l>across the Aegean water, where he built</l>
<l>the city of his name.</l>

BYBLIS AND CAUNUS

<l>Cyane, who</l>
<l>was known to be the daughter of the stream</l>
<l>Maeander, which with many a twist and turn</l>
<l>flows wandering there—Cyane said to be</l>
<l>indeed most beautiful, when known by him,</l>
<l>gave birth to two; a girl called Byblis, who</l>
<l>was lovely, and the brother Caunus—twins.</l>

    
<l>Byblis is an example that the love</l>
<l>of every maiden must be within law.</l>
<l>Seized with a passion for her brother, she</l>
<l>loved him, descendant of Apollo, not</l>
<l>as sister loves a brother; not in such</l>
<l>a manner as the law of man permits.</l>

    
<l>At first she thought it surely was not wrong</l>
<l>to kiss him passionately, while her arms</l>
<l>were thrown around her brother's neck, and so</l>
<l>deceived herself. And, as the habit grew,</l>
<l>her sister-love degenerated, till</l>
<l>richly attired, she came to see her brother,</l>
<l>with all endeavors to attract his eye;</l>
<l>and anxious to be seen most beautiful,</l>
<l>she envied every woman who appeared</l>
<l>of rival beauty. But she did not know</l>
<l>or understand the flame, hot in her heart,</l>
<l>though she was agitated when she saw</l>
<l>the object of her swiftly growing love.</l>

    
<l>Now she began to call him lord, and now</l>
<l>she hated to say brother, and she said,</l>
<l>“Do call me Byblis—never call me sister!”</l>
<l>And yet while feeling love so, when awake</l>
<l>she does not dwell upon impure desire;</l>
<l>but when dissolved in the soft arms of sleep,</l>
<l>she sees the very object of her love,</l>
<l>and blushing, dreams she is embraced by him,</l>
<l>till slumber has departed. For a time</l>
<l>she lies there silent, as her mind recalls</l>
<l>the loved appearance of her lovely dream,</l>
<l>until her wavering heart, in grief exclaims:—</l>

    
<l>“What is this vision of the silent night?</l>
<l>Ah wretched me! I cannot count it true.</l>
<l>And, if he were not my own brother, he</l>
<l>why is my fond heart tortured with this dream?</l>
<l>He is so handsome even to envious eyes,</l>
<l>it is not strange he has filled my fond heart;</l>
<l>so surely would be worthy of my love.</l>
<l>But it is my misfortune I am his</l>
<l>own sister. Let me therefore strive, awake,</l>
<l>to stand with honor, but let sleep return</l>
<l>the same dream often to me.—There can be</l>
<l>no fear of any witness to a shade</l>
<l>which phantoms my delight.—O Cupid, swift</l>
<l>of love-wing with your mother, and O my</l>
<l>beloved Venus! wonderful the joys</l>
<l>of my experience in the transport. All</l>
<l>as if reality sustaining, lifted me</l>
<l>up to elysian pleasure, while in truth</l>
<l>I lay dissolving to my very marrow:</l>
<l>the pleasure was so brief, and Night, headlong</l>
<l>sped from me, envious of my coming joys.</l>

    
<l>“If I could change my name, and join to you,</l>
<l>how good a daughter I would prove to your</l>
<l>dear father, and how good a son would you</l>
<l>be to my father. If the Gods agreed,</l>
<l>then everything would be possessed by us</l>
<l>in common, but this must exclude ancestors.</l>
<l>For I should pray, compared with mine yours might</l>
<l>be quite superior. But, oh my love,</l>
<l>some other woman by your love will be</l>
<l>a mother; but because, unfortunate,</l>
<l>my parents are the same as yours, you must</l>
<l>be nothing but a brother. Sorrows, then,</l>
<l>shall be to us in common from this hour.</l>
<l>What have my night-born vision signified?</l>
<l>What weight have dreams? Do dreams have any weight?</l>
<l>The Gods forbid! The Gods have sisters! Truth</l>
<l>declares even Saturn married Ops, his own</l>
<l>blood-kin, Oceanus his Tethys, Jove,</l>
<l>Olympian his Juno. But the Gods</l>
<l>are so superior in their laws, I should</l>
<l>not measure human custom by the rights</l>
<l>established in the actions of divinities.</l>
<l>This passion must be banished from my heart,</l>
<l>or, if it cannot be so, I must pray</l>
<l>that I may perish, and be laid out dead</l>
<l>upon my couch so my dear brother there</l>
<l>may kiss my lips. But then he must consent,</l>
<l>and my delight would seem to him a crime.</l>

    
<l>“Tis known the sons of Aeolus embraced</l>
<l>their sisters —But why should I think of these?</l>
<l>Why should I take example from such lives?</l>
<l>Must I do as they did? Far from it! let</l>
<l>such lawless flames be quenched, until I feel</l>
<l>no evil love for him, although the pure</l>
<l>affection of a sister may be mine,</l>
<l>and cherished. If it should have happened first</l>
<l>that my dear brother had loved me—ah then,</l>
<l>I might have yielded love to his desire.</l>
<l>Why not now? I myself must woo him, since</l>
<l>I could not have rejected him, if he</l>
<l>had first wooed me. But is it possible</l>
<l>for me to speak of it, with proper words</l>
<l>describing such a strange confession? Love</l>
<l>will certainly compel and give me speech.</l>
<l>But, if shame seal my lips, then secret flame</l>
<l>in a sealed letter may be safely told.”</l>


    
<l>And after all this wavering, her mind</l>
<l>at last was satisfied; and as she leaned</l>
<l>on her left elbow, partly raised from her</l>
<l>half-dream position, she said, “Let him see:</l>
<l>let me at once confess my frantic passion</l>
<l>without repression! O my wretched heart!</l>
<l>What hot flame burns me!” But while speaking so,</l>
<l>she took an iron pen in her right hand,</l>
<l>and trembling wrote the heart-words as she could,</l>
<l>all on a clean wax tablet which she held</l>
<l>in her limp left hand. She begins and stops,</l>
<l>and hesitates—she loves and hates her hot</l>
<l>confession—writes, erases, changes here</l>
<l>and there, condemns, approves, disheartened throws</l>
<l>her tablets down and takes them up again:</l>
<l>her mind refuses everything she does,</l>
<l>and moves against each action as begun:</l>
<l>shame, fear and bold assurance mingled showed</l>
<l>upon her face, as she began to write,</l>
<l>“Your sister” but at once decided she</l>
<l>could not say sister, and commenced instead,</l>
<l>with other words on her amended wax.</l>

    
<l>“A health to you, which she who loves you fails</l>
<l>to have, unless you grant the same to her.</l>
<l>It shames me, oh I am ashamed to tell</l>
<l>my name to you, and so without my name,</l>
<l>I would I might plead well until the hopes</l>
<l>of my desires were realized, and then</l>
<l>you might know safely, Byblis is my name.</l>

    
<l>“You might have knowledge of my wounded heart,</l>
<l>because my pale, drawn face and down-cast eyes</l>
<l>so often tearful, and my sighs without</l>
<l>apparent cause have shown it — and my warm</l>
<l>embraces, and my frequent kisses, much</l>
<l>too tender for a sister. All of this</l>
<l>has happened, while with agitated heart</l>
<l>and in hot passion, I have tried all ways,</l>
<l>(I call upon the Gods to witness it!)</l>
<l>that I might force myself to sanity.</l>
<l>And I have struggled, wretched nights and days,</l>
<l>to overcome the cruelties of love,</l>
<l>too dreadful for a frail girl to endure,</l>
<l>for they most surely are all Cupid's art.</l>

    
<l>“I have been overborne and must confess</l>
<l>my passion, while with timid prayers I plead;</l>
<l>for only you can save me. You alone</l>
<l>may now destroy the one who loves you best:</l>
<l>so you must choose what will be the result.</l>
<l>The one who prays is not your enemy;</l>
<l>but one most closely joined to you, yet asks</l>
<l>to knit the tie more firmly. Let old men</l>
<l>be governed by propriety, and talk</l>
<l>of what is right and wrong, and hold to all</l>
<l>the nice distinctions of strict laws. But Love,</l>
<l>has no fixed law for those whose age is ours,</l>
<l>is heedless and compliant. And we have</l>
<l>not yet discovered what is right or wrong,</l>
<l>and all we should do is to imitate</l>
<l>the known example of the Gods. We have</l>
<l>no father's harsh rule, and we have no care</l>
<l>for reputation, and no fear that keeps</l>
<l>us from each other. But there may be cause</l>
<l>for fear, and we may hide our stolen love,</l>
<l>because a sister is at liberty</l>
<l>to talk with her dear brother—quite apart:</l>
<l>we may embrace and kiss each other, though</l>
<l>in public. What is wanting? Pity her</l>
<l>whose utmost love compels her to confess;</l>
<l>and let it not be written on her tomb,</l>
<l>her death was for your sake and love denied.”</l>

    
<l>Here when she dropped the tablet from her hand,</l>
<l>it was so full of fond words, which were doomed</l>
<l>to disappointment, that the last line traced</l>
<l>the edge: and without thinking of delay,</l>
<l>she stamped the shameful letter with her seal,</l>
<l>and moistened it with tears (her tongue failed her</l>
<l>for moisture). Then, hot-blushing, she called one</l>
<l>of her attendants, and with timid voice</l>
<l>said, coaxing, “My most trusted servant, take</l>
<l>these tablets to my—” after long delay</l>
<l>she said, “my brother.” While she gave the tablets</l>
<l>they suddenly slipped from her hands and fell.</l>

    
<l>Although disturbed by this bad omen, she</l>
<l>still sent the letter, which the servant found</l>
<l>an opportunity to carry off.</l>
<l>He gave the secret love-confession. This</l>
<l>her brother, grandson of Maeander, read</l>
<l>but partly, and with sudden passion threw</l>
<l>the tablets from him. He could barely hold</l>
<l>himself from clutching on the throat of her</l>
<l>fear-trembling servant; as, enraged, he cried,</l>
<l>“Accursed pander to forbidden lust,</l>
<l>be gone!—before the knowledge of your death</l>
<l>is added to this unforeseen disgrace!”</l>

    
<l>The servant fled in terror, and told all</l>
<l>her brother's actions and his fierce reply</l>
<l>to Byblis: and when she had heard her love</l>
<l>had been repulsed, her startled face went pale,</l>
<l>and her whole body trembled in the grip</l>
<l>of ice-chills. Quickly as her mind regained</l>
<l>its usual strength, her maddening love returned,</l>
<l>came back with equal force, and while she choked</l>
<l>with her emotion, gasping she said this:</l>

    
<l>“I suffer only from my folly! why did I</l>
<l>so rashly tell him of my wounded heart?</l>
<l>And why did I so hastily commit</l>
<l>to tablets all I should have kept concealed?</l>
<l>I should have edged my way by feeling first,</l>
<l>obscurely hinting till I knew his mind</l>
<l>and disposition towards me. And so that</l>
<l>my first voyage might get favorable wind,</l>
<l>I should have tested with a close-reefed sail,</l>
<l>and, knowing what the wind was, safely fared.</l>
<l>But now with sails full spread I have been tossed</l>
<l>by unexpected winds. And so my ship</l>
<l>is on the rocks; and, overwhelmed with all</l>
<l>the power of Ocean, I have not the strength</l>
<l>to turn back and recover what is lost.</l>

    
<l>“Surely clear omens warned me not to tell</l>
<l>my love so soon, because the tablets fell</l>
<l>just when I would have put them in the hand</l>
<l>of my picked servant — certainly a sign</l>
<l>my hasty hopes were destined to fall down.</l>
<l>Is it not clear I should have changed the day;</l>
<l>and even my intention? Rather say</l>
<l>should not the day have been postponed at once?</l>
<l>The god himself gave me unerring signs,</l>
<l>if I had not been so deranged with love.</l>
<l>I should have spoken to him, face to face;</l>
<l>and with my own lips have confessed it all;</l>
<l>and then my passion had been seen by him,</l>
<l>and, as my face was bathed in tears, I could</l>
<l>have told him so much more than words engraved</l>
<l>on tablets; and, while I was telling him</l>
<l>I could have thrown my arms around his neck,</l>
<l>and if rejected could have seemed almost</l>
<l>at point of death; as I embraced his feet,</l>
<l>while prostrate, even might have begged for life.</l>
<l>I could have tried so many plans, and they</l>
<l>together would have won his stubborn heart.</l>

    
<l>“Perhaps my stupid servant, in mistake,</l>
<l>did not approach him at a proper time,</l>
<l>and even sought an hour his mind was full</l>
<l>of other things.</l>

    
<l>“All this has harmed my case;</l>
<l>there is no other reason; he was not</l>
<l>born of a tigress, and his heart is not</l>
<l>of flint or solid iron, or of adamant;</l>
<l>and no she-lion suckled him. He shall</l>
<l>be won to my affection; and I must</l>
<l>attempt again, again, nor ever cease</l>
<l>so long as I have breath. If it were not</l>
<l>too late already to undo what has</l>
<l>been done, 'twere wiser not begun at all.</l>
<l>But since I have begun, it now is best</l>
<l>to end it with success. How can he help</l>
<l>remembering what I dared, although I should</l>
<l>abandon my design! In such a case,</l>
<l>because I gave up, I must be to him</l>
<l>weak, fickle-minded; or perhaps he may</l>
<l>believe I tried to tempt him with a snare.</l>
<l>But come what may, he will not think of me</l>
<l>as overcome by some god who inflames</l>
<l>and rules the heart. He surely will believe</l>
<l>I was so actuated by my lust.</l>

    
<l>“If I do nothing more, my innocence</l>
<l>is gone forever. I have written him</l>
<l>and wooed him also, in a way so rash</l>
<l>and unmistakable, that if I should</l>
<l>do nothing more than this, I should be held</l>
<l>completely guilty in my brother's sight—</l>
<l>but I have hope, and nothing worse to fear.”</l>


    
<l>Then back and forth she argues; and so great</l>
<l>is her uncertainty, she blames herself</l>
<l>for what she did, and is determined just</l>
<l>as surely to succeed.</l>

    
<l>She tries all arts,</l>
<l>but is repeatedly repulsed by him,</l>
<l>until unable to control her ways,</l>
<l>her brother in despair, fled from the shame</l>
<l>of her designs: and in another land</l>
<l>he founded a new city.</l>

    
<l>Then, they say,</l>
<l>the wretched daughter of Miletus lost</l>
<l>control of reason. She wrenched from her breast</l>
<l>her garments, and quite frantic, beat her arms,</l>
<l>and publicly proclaims unhallowed love.</l>
<l>Grown desperate, she left her hated home,</l>
<l>her native land, and followed the loved steps</l>
<l>of her departed brother. Just as those</l>
<l>crazed by your thyrsus, son of Semele!</l>
<l>The Bacchanals of Ismarus, aroused,</l>
<l>howl at your orgies, so her shrieks were heard</l>
<l>by the shocked women of Bubassus, where</l>
<l>the frenzied Byblis howled across the fields,</l>
<l>and so through Caria and through Lycia,</l>
<l>over the mountain Cragus and beyond</l>
<l>the town, Lymira, and the flowing stream</l>
<l>called Xanthus, and the ridge where dwelt</l>
<l>Chimaera, serpent-tailed and monstrous beast,</l>
<l>fire breathing from its lion head and neck.</l>

    
<l>She hurried through the forest of that ridge—</l>
<l>and there at last worn out with your pursuit,</l>
<l>O Byblis, you fell prostrate, with your hair</l>
<l>spread over the hard ground, and your wan face</l>
<l>buried in fallen leaves. Although the young,</l>
<l>still tender-hearted nymphs of Leleges,</l>
<l>advised her fondly how to cure her love,</l>
<l>and offered comfort to her heedless heart,</l>
<l>and even lifted her in their soft arms;</l>
<l>without an answer Byblis fell from them,</l>
<l>and clutched the green herbs with her fingers, while</l>
<l>her tears continued to fall on the grass.</l>
<l>They say the weeping Naiads gave to her</l>
<l>a vein of tears which always flows there from</l>
<l>her sorrows—nothing better could be done.</l>

    
<l>Immediately, as drops of pitch drip forth</l>
<l>from the gashed pine, or sticky bitumen</l>
<l>distils out from the rich and heavy earth,</l>
<l>or as the frozen water at the approach</l>
<l>of a soft-breathing wind melts in the sun;</l>
<l>so Byblis, sad descendant of the Sun,</l>
<l>dissolving in her own tears, was there changed</l>
<l>into a fountain; which to this late day,</l>
<l>in all those valleys has no name but hers,</l>
<l>and issues underneath a dark oak-tree.</l>


Iphis.
IPHIS AND IANTHE

<l>The tale of this unholy passion would</l>
<l>perhaps, have filled Crete's hundred cities then,</l>
<l>if Crete had not a wonder of its own</l>
<l>to talk of, in the change of Iphis. Once,</l>
<l>there lived at Phaestus, not far from the town</l>
<l>of Gnossus, a man Ligdus, not well known;</l>
<l>in fact obscure, of humble parentage,</l>
<l>whose income was no greater than his birth;</l>
<l>but he was held trustworthy and his life</l>
<l>had been quite blameless. When the time drew near</l>
<l>his wife should give birth to a child, he warned</l>
<l>her and instructed her, with words we quote:—</l>

    
<l>“There are two things which I would ask of Heaven:</l>
<l>that you may be delivered with small pain,</l>
<l>and that your child may surely be a boy.</l>
<l>Girls are such trouble, fair strength is denied</l>
<l>to them.—Therefore (may Heaven refuse the thought)</l>
<l>if chance should cause your child to be a girl,</l>
<l>(gods pardon me for having said the word!)</l>
<l>we must agree to have her put to death.”</l>

    
<l>And all the time he spoke such dreaded words,</l>
<l>their faces were completely bathed in tears;</l>
<l>not only hers but also his while he</l>
<l>forced on her that unnatural command.</l>
<l>Ah, Telethusa ceaselessly implored</l>
<l>her husband to give way to fortune's cast;</l>
<l>but Ligdus held his resolution fixed.</l>

    
<l>And now the expected time of birth was near,</l>
<l>when in the middle of the night she seemed</l>
<l>to see the goddess Isis, standing by</l>
<l>her bed, in company of serious spirit forms;</l>
<l>Isis had crescent horns upon her forehead,</l>
<l>and a bright garland made of golden grain</l>
<l>encircled her fair brow. It was a crown</l>
<l>of regal beauty: and beside her stood</l>
<l>the dog Anubis, and Bubastis, there</l>
<l>the sacred, dappled Apis, and the God</l>
<l>of silence with pressed finger on his lips;</l>
<l>the sacred rattles were there, and Osiris, known</l>
<l>the constant object of his worshippers' desire,</l>
<l>and there the Egyptian serpent whose quick sting</l>
<l>gives long-enduring sleep. She seemed to see</l>
<l>them all, and even to hear the goddess say</l>
<l>to her, “O Telethusa, one of my</l>
<l>remembered worshippers, forget your grief;</l>
<l>your husband's orders need not be obeyed;</l>
<l>and when Lucina has delivered you,</l>
<l>save and bring up your child, if either boy</l>
<l>or girl. I am the goddess who brings help</l>
<l>to all who call upon me; and you shall</l>
<l>never complain of me—that you adored</l>
<l>a thankless deity.” So she advised</l>
<l>by vision the sad mother, and left her.</l>

    
<l>The Cretan woman joyfully arose</l>
<l>from her sad bed, and supplicating, raised</l>
<l>ecstatic hands up towards the listening stars,</l>
<l>and prayed to them her vision might come true.</l>

    
<l>Soon, when her pains gave birth, the mother knew</l>
<l>her infant was a girl (the father had</l>
<l>no knowledge of it, as he was not there).</l>
<l>Intending to deceive, the mother said,</l>
<l>“Feed the dear boy.” All things had favored her</l>
<l>deceit—no one except the trusted nurse,</l>
<l>knew of it. And the father paid his vows,</l>
<l>and named the child after its grandfather, whose</l>
<l>name was honored Iphis. Hearing it so called,</l>
<l>the mother could not but rejoice, because</l>
<l>her child was given a name of common gender,</l>
<l>and she could use it with no more deceit.</l>

    
<l>She took good care to dress it as a boy,</l>
<l>and either as a boy or girl, its face</l>
<l>must always be accounted lovable.</l>

    
<l>And so she grew,—ten years and three had gone,</l>
<l>and then your father found a bride for you</l>
<l>O Iphis—promised you should take to wife</l>
<l>the golden-haired Ianthe, praised by all</l>
<l>the women of Phaestus for the dower</l>
<l>of her unequalled beauty, and well known,</l>
<l>the daughter of a Cretan named Telestes.</l>
<l>Of equal age and equal loveliness,</l>
<l>they had received from the same teachers, all</l>
<l>instruction in their childish rudiments.</l>
<l>So unsuspected love had filled their hearts</l>
<l>with equal longing—but how different!</l>

    
<l>Ianthe waits in confidence and hope</l>
<l>the ceremonial as agreed upon,</l>
<l>and is quite certain she will wed a man.</l>
<l>But Iphis is in love without one hope</l>
<l>of passion's ecstasy, the thought of which</l>
<l>only increased her flame; and she a girl</l>
<l>is burnt with passion for another girl!</l>
<l>She hardly can hold back her tears, and says:</l>

    
<l>“O what will be the awful dreaded end,</l>
<l>with such a monstrous love compelling me?</l>
<l>If the Gods should wish to save me, certainly</l>
<l>they should have saved me; but, if their desire</l>
<l>was for my ruin, still they should have given</l>

    
<l>some natural suffering of humanity.</l>
<l>The passion for a cow does not inflame a cow,</l>
<l>no mare has ever sought another mare.</l>
<l>The ram inflames the ewe, and every doe</l>
<l>follows a chosen stag; so also birds</l>
<l>are mated, and in all the animal world</l>
<l>no female ever feels love passion for</l>
<l>another female—why is it in me?</l>

    
<l>“Monstrosities are natural to Crete,</l>
<l>the daughter of the Sun there loved a bull—</l>
<l>it was a female's mad love for the male—</l>
<l>but my desire is far more mad than hers,</l>
<l>in strict regard of truth, for she had hope</l>
<l>of love's fulfillment. She secured the bull</l>
<l>by changing herself to a heifer's form;</l>
<l>and in that subtlety it was the male</l>
<l>deceived at last. Though all the subtleties</l>
<l>of all the world should be collected here;—</l>
<l>if Daedalus himself should fly back here</l>
<l>upon his waxen wings, what could he do?</l>
<l>What skillful art of his could change my sex,</l>
<l>a girl into a boy—or could he change</l>
<l>Ianthe? What a useless thought! Be bold</l>
<l>take courage Iphis, and be strong of soul.</l>
<l>This hopeless passion stultifies your heart;</l>
<l>so shake it off, and hold your memory</l>
<l>down to the clear fact of your birth: unless</l>
<l>your will provides deception for yourself:</l>
<l>do only what is lawful, and confine</l>
<l>strictly, your love within a woman's right.</l>

    
<l>“Hope of fulfillment can beget true love,</l>
<l>and hope keeps it alive. You are deprived</l>
<l>of this hope by the nature of your birth.</l>
<l>No guardian keeps you from her dear embrace,</l>
<l>no watchful jealous husband, and she has</l>
<l>no cruel father: she does not deny</l>
<l>herself to you. With all that liberty,</l>
<l>you can not have her for your happy wife,</l>
<l>though Gods and men should labor for your wish.</l>
<l>None of my prayers has ever been denied;</l>
<l>the willing Deities have granted me</l>
<l>whatever should be, and my father helps</l>
<l>me to accomplish everything I plan:</l>
<l>she and her father also, always help.</l>
<l>But Nature is more powerful than all,</l>
<l>and only Nature works for my distress.</l>

    
<l>“The wedding-day already is at hand;</l>
<l>the longed-for time is come; Ianthe soon</l>
<l>will be mine only—and yet, not my own:</l>
<l>with water all around me I shall thirst!</l>
<l>O why must Juno, goddess of sweet brides,</l>
<l>and why should Hymen also, favor us</l>
<l>when man with woman cannot join in wedlock,</l>
<l>but both are brides?” And so she closed her lips.</l>


    
<l>The other maiden flamed with equal love,</l>
<l>and often prayed for Hymen to appear.</l>
<l>But Telethusa, fearing that event,</l>
<l>the marriage which Ianthe keenly sought,</l>
<l>procrastinated, causing first delay</l>
<l>by some pretended illness; and then gave</l>
<l>pretence of omens and of visions seen,</l>
<l>sufficient for delay, until she had</l>
<l>exhausted every avenue of excuse,</l>
<l>and only one more day remained before</l>
<l>the fateful time, it was so near at hand.</l>

    
<l>Despairing then of finding other cause</l>
<l>which might prevent the fated wedding-day,</l>
<l>the mother took the circled fillets from</l>
<l>her own head, and her daughter's head, and prayed,</l>
<l>as she embraced the altar—her long hair</l>
<l>spread out upon the flowing breeze—and said:</l>

    
<l>“O Isis, goddess of Paraetonium,</l>
<l>the Mareotic fields, Pharos, and Nile</l>
<l>of seven horns divided—oh give help!</l>
<l>Goddess of nations! heal us of our fears!</l>
<l>I saw you, goddess, and your symbols once,</l>
<l>and I adored them all, the clashing sounds</l>
<l>of sistra and the torches of your train,</l>
<l>and I took careful note of your commands,</l>
<l>for which my daughter lives to see the sun,</l>
<l>and also I have so escaped from harm;—</l>
<l>all this is of your counsel and your gift;</l>
<l>oh, pity both of us—and give us aid!”</l>

    
<l>Tears emphasized her prayer; the goddess seemed</l>
<l>to move—in truth it was the altar moved;</l>
<l>the firm doors of the temple even shook—</l>
<l>and her horns, crescent, flashed with gleams of light,</l>
<l>and her loud sistrum rattled noisily.</l>
<l>Although not quite free of all fear, yet pleased</l>
<l>by that good omen, gladly the mother left</l>
<l>the temple with her daughter Iphis, who</l>
<l>beside her walked, but with a lengthened stride.</l>

    
<l>Her face seemed of a darker hue, her strength</l>
<l>seemed greater, and her features were more stern.</l>
<l>Her hair once long, was unadorned and short.</l>
<l>There is more vigor in her than she showed</l>
<l>in her girl ways. For in the name of truth,</l>
<l>Iphis, who was a girl, is now a man!</l>
<l>Make offerings at the temple and rejoice</l>
<l>without a fear!—They offer at the shrines,</l>
<l>and add a votive tablet, on which this</l>
<l>inscription is engraved:</l>

    
<l>these gifts are paid</l>
<l>by Iphis as a man which as a maid</l>
<l>he vowed to give.</l>

    
<l>The morrow's dawn</l>
<l>revealed the wide world; on the day agreed,</l>
<l>Venus, Juno and Hymen, all have met</l>
<l>our happy lovers at the marriage fires; </l>

    
<l>and Iphis, a new man, gained his Ianthe.</l>
