<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 10


Orpheus et Eurydice.
ORPHEUS AND EURYDICE

<l>Veiled in a saffron mantle, through the air</l>
<l>unmeasured, after the strange wedding, Hymen</l>
<l>departed swiftly for Ciconian land;</l>
<l>regardless and not listening to the voice</l>
<l>of tuneful Orpheus. Truly Hymen there</l>
<l>was present during the festivities</l>
<l>of Orpheus and Eurydice, but gave</l>
<l>no happy omen, neither hallowed words</l>
<l>nor joyful glances; and the torch he held</l>
<l>would only sputter, fill the eyes with smoke,</l>
<l>and cause no blaze while waving. The result</l>
<l>of that sad wedding, proved more terrible</l>
<l>than such foreboding fates.</l>

    
<l>While through the grass</l>
<l>delighted Naiads wandered with the bride,</l>
<l>a serpent struck its venomed tooth in her</l>
<l>soft ankle— and she died.—After the bard</l>
<l>of Rhodope had mourned, and filled the highs</l>
<l>of heaven with the moans of his lament,</l>
<l>determined also the dark underworld</l>
<l>should recognize the misery of death,</l>
<l>he dared descend by the Taenarian gate</l>
<l>down to the gloomy Styx. And there passed through</l>
<l>pale-glimmering phantoms, and the ghosts</l>
<l>escaped from sepulchres, until he found</l>
<l>Persephone and Pluto, master-king</l>
<l>of shadow realms below: and then began</l>
<l>to strike his tuneful lyre, to which he sang:—</l>

    
<l>“O deities of this dark world beneath</l>
<l>the earth! this shadowy underworld, to which</l>
<l>all mortals must descend! If it can be</l>
<l>called lawful, and if you will suffer speech</l>
<l>of strict truth (all the winding ways</l>
<l>of Falsity forbidden) I come not</l>
<l>down here because of curiosity</l>
<l>to see the glooms of Tartarus and have</l>
<l>no thought to bind or strangle the three necks</l>
<l>of the Medusan Monster, vile with snakes.</l>
<l>But I have come, because my darling wife</l>
<l>stepped on a viper that sent through her veins</l>
<l>death-poison, cutting off her coming years.</l>

    
<l>“If able, I would bear it, I do not</l>
<l>deny my effort—but the god of Love</l>
<l>has conquered me—a god so kindly known</l>
<l>in all the upper world. We are not sure</l>
<l>he can be known so well in this deep world,</l>
<l>but have good reason to conjecture he</l>
<l>is not unknown here, and if old report</l>
<l>almost forgotten, that you stole your wife</l>
<l>is not a fiction, Love united you</l>
<l>the same as others. By this Place of Fear</l>
<l>this huge void and these vast and silent realms,</l>
<l>renew the life-thread of Eurydice.</l>

    
<l>“All things are due to you, and though on earth</l>
<l>it happens we may tarry a short while,</l>
<l>slowly or swiftly we must go to one</l>
<l>abode; and it will be our final home.</l>
<l>Long and tenaciously you will possess</l>
<l>unquestioned mastery of the human race.</l>
<l>She also shall be yours to rule, when full</l>
<l>of age she shall have lived the days of her</l>
<l>allotted years. So I ask of you</l>
<l>possession of her few days as a boon.</l>
<l>But if the fates deny to me this prayer</l>
<l>for my true wife, my constant mind must hold</l>
<l>me always so that I can not return—</l>
<l>and you may triumph in the death of two!”</l>

    
<l>While he sang all his heart said to the sound</l>
<l>of his sweet lyre, the bloodless ghosts themselves</l>
<l>were weeping, and the anxious Tantalus</l>
<l>stopped clutching at return-flow of the wave,</l>
<l>Ixion's twisting wheel stood wonder-bound;</l>
<l>and Tityus' liver for a while escaped</l>
<l>the vultures, and the listening Belides</l>
<l>forgot their sieve-like bowls and even you,</l>
<l>O Sisyphus! sat idly on your rock!</l>

    
<l>Then Fame declared that conquered by the song</l>
<l>of Orpheus, for the first and only time</l>
<l>the hard cheeks of the fierce Eumenides</l>
<l>were wet with tears: nor could the royal queen,</l>
<l>nor he who rules the lower world deny</l>
<l>the prayer of Orpheus; so they called to them</l>
<l>Eurydice, who still was held among</l>
<l>the new-arriving shades, and she obeyed</l>
<l>the call by walking to them with slow steps,</l>
<l>yet halting from her wound. So Orpheus then</l>
<l>received his wife; and Pluto told him he</l>
<l>might now ascend from these Avernian vales</l>
<l>up to the light, with his Eurydice;</l>
<l>but, if he turned his eyes to look at her,</l>
<l>the gift of her delivery would be lost.</l>

    
<l>They picked their way in silence up a steep</l>
<l>and gloomy path of darkness. There remained</l>
<l>but little more to climb till they would touch</l>
<l>earth's surface, when in fear he might again</l>
<l>lose her, and anxious for another look</l>
<l>at her, he turned his eyes so he could gaze</l>
<l>upon her. Instantly she slipped away.</l>
<l>He stretched out to her his despairing arms,</l>
<l>eager to rescue her, or feel her form,</l>
<l>but could hold nothing save the yielding air.</l>
<l>Dying the second time, she could not say</l>
<l>a word of censure of her husband's fault;</l>
<l>what had she to complain of — his great love?</l>
<l>Her last word spoken was, “Farewell!” which he</l>
<l>could barely hear, and with no further sound</l>
<l>she fell from him again to Hades.—Struck</l>
<l>quite senseless by this double death of his</l>
<l>dear wife, he was as fixed from motion as</l>
<l>the frightened one who saw the triple necks</l>
<l>of Cerberus, that dog whose middle neck</l>
<l>was chained. The sight filled him with terror he</l>
<l>had no escape from, until petrified</l>
<l>to stone; or like Olenos, changed to stone,</l>
<l>because he fastened on himself the guilt</l>
<l>of his wife. O unfortunate Lethaea!</l>
<l>Too boastful of your beauty, you and he,</l>
<l>united once in love, are now two stones</l>
<l>upon the mountain Ida, moist with springs.</l>

    
<l>Orpheus implored in vain the ferryman</l>
<l>to help him cross the River Styx again,</l>
<l>but was denied the very hope of death.</l>
<l>Seven days he sat upon Death's river bank,</l>
<l>in squalid misery and without all food—</l>
<l>nourished by grief, anxiety, and tears—</l>
<l>complaining that the Gods of Erebus</l>
<l>were pitiless, at last he wandered back,</l>
<l>until he came to lofty Rhodope</l>
<l>and Haemus, beaten by the strong north wind.</l>

    
<l>Three times the Sun completed his full course</l>
<l>to watery Pisces, and in all that time,</l>
<l>shunning all women, Orpheus still believed</l>
<l>his love-pledge was forever. So he kept</l>
<l>away from women, though so many grieved,</l>
<l>because he took no notice of their love.</l>
<l>The only friendship he enjoyed was given</l>
<l>to the young men of Thrace.</l>


Arbores motae. Cyparissus.
ATTIS

<l>There was a hill</l>
<l>which rose up to a level plateau, high</l>
<l>and beautiful with green grass; and there was</l>
<l>not any shade for comfort on the top</l>
<l>and there on that luxuriant grass the bard,</l>
<l>while heaven-inspired reclined, and struck</l>
<l>such harmonies on his sweet lyre that shade</l>
<l>most grateful to the hill was spread around.</l>
<l>Strong trees came up there—the Chaonian oak</l>
<l>the Heliads' poplar, and the lofty-branched</l>
<l>deep mast-tree, the soft linden and the beech,</l>
<l>the brittle hazel, and the virgin laurel-tree,</l>
<l>the ash for strong spears, the smooth silver-fir,</l>
<l>the flex bent with acorns and the plane,</l>
<l>the various tinted maple and with those,</l>
<l>the lotus and green willows from their streams,</l>
<l>evergreen box and slender tamarisks,</l>
<l>rich myrtles of two colors and the tine,</l>
<l>bending with green-blue berries: and you, too,</l>
<l>the pliant-footed ivy, came along</l>
<l>with tendril-branching grape-vines, and the elm</l>
<l>all covered with twist-vines, the mountain-ash,</l>
<l>pitch-trees and arbute-trees of blushing fruit,</l>
<l>the bending-palm prized after victories,</l>
<l>the bare-trunk pine of tufted foliage,</l>
<l>bristled upon the top, a pleasant sight</l>
<l>delightful to the Mother of the Gods;</l>
<l>since Attis dear to Cybele, exchanged</l>
<l>his human form which hardened in that tree.</l>

CYPARISSUS

<l>In all the throng the cone-shaped cypress came;</l>
<l>a tree now, it was changed from a dear youth</l>
<l>loved by the god who strings the lyre and bow.</l>
<l>For there was at one time, a mighty stag</l>
<l>held sacred by those nymphs who haunt the fields</l>
<l>Carthaean. His great antlers spread so wide,</l>
<l>they gave an ample shade to his own head.</l>
<l>Those antlers shone with gold: from his smooth throat</l>
<l>a necklace, studded with a wealth of gems,</l>
<l>hung down to his strong shoulders—beautiful.</l>
<l>A silver boss, fastened with little thongs,</l>
<l>played on his forehead, worn there from his birth;</l>
<l>and pendants from both ears, of gleaming pearls,</l>
<l>adorned his hollow temples. Free of fear,</l>
<l>and now no longer shy, frequenting homes</l>
<l>of men he knew, he offered his soft neck</l>
<l>even to strangers for their petting hands.</l>

    
<l>But more than by all others, he was loved</l>
<l>by you, O Cyparissus, fairest youth</l>
<l>of all the lads of Cea. It was you</l>
<l>who led the pet stag to fresh pasturage,</l>
<l>and to the waters of the clearest spring.</l>
<l>Sometimes you wove bright garlands for his horns,</l>
<l>and sometimes, like a horseman on his back,</l>
<l>now here now there, you guided his soft mouth</l>
<l>with purple reins. It was upon a summer day,</l>
<l>at high noon when the Crab, of spreading claws,</l>
<l>loving the sea-shore, almost burnt beneath</l>
<l>the sun's hot burning rays; and the pet stag</l>
<l>was then reclining on the grassy earth</l>
<l>and, wearied of all action, found relief</l>
<l>under the cool shade of the forest trees;</l>
<l>that as he lay there Cyparissus pierced</l>
<l>him with a javelin: and although it was</l>
<l>quite accidental, when the shocked youth saw</l>
<l>his loved stag dying from the cruel wound</l>
<l>he could not bear it, and resolved on death.</l>
<l>What did not Phoebus say to comfort him?</l>
<l>He cautioned him to hold his grief in check,</l>
<l>consistent with the cause. But still the lad</l>
<l>lamented, and with groans implored the Gods</l>
<l>that he might mourn forever. His life force</l>
<l>exhausted by long weeping, now his limbs</l>
<l>began to take a green tint, and his hair,</l>
<l>which overhung his snow-white brow, turned up</l>
<l>into a bristling crest; and he became</l>
<l>a stiff tree with a slender top and pointed</l>
<l>up to the starry heavens. And the God,</l>
<l>groaning with sorrow, said; “You shall be mourned</l>
<l>sincerely by me, surely as you mourn</l>
<l>for others, and forever you shall stand</l>
<l>in grief, where others grieve.”</l>


Ganymedes. Hyacinthus.

<l>Such was the grove</l>
<l>by Orpheus drawn together; and he sat</l>
<l>surrounded by assembled animals,</l>
<l>and many strange Birds. When he tried the chords</l>
<l>by touching with his thumb, and was convinced</l>
<l>the notes were all in harmony, although</l>
<l>attuned to various melody, he raised</l>
<l>his voice and sang:</l>

    
<l>“Oh my loved mother, Muse,</l>
<l>from Jove inspire my song—for all things yield,</l>
<l>to the unequalled sway of Jove—oh, I</l>
<l>have sung so often Jupiter's great power</l>
<l>before this day, and in a wilder strain,</l>
<l>I've sung the giants and victorious bolts</l>
<l>hurled on Phlegraean plains. But now I need</l>
<l>the gentler touch; for I would sing of boys,</l>
<l>the favorites of Gods, and even of maids</l>
<l>who had to pay the penalty of wrong.”</l>

GANYMEDE

<l>The king of all the Gods once burned with love</l>
<l>for Ganymede of Phrygia. He found</l>
<l>a shape more pleasing even than his own.</l>
<l>Jove would not take the form of any bird,</l>
<l>except the eagle's, able to sustain</l>
<l>the weight of his own thunderbolts. Without</l>
<l>delay, Jove on fictitious eagle wings,</l>
<l>stole and flew off with that loved Trojan boy:</l>
<l>who even to this day, against the will</l>
<l>of Juno, mingles nectar in the cups</l>
<l>of his protector, mighty Jupiter.</l>

HYACINTHUS

<l>You also, Hyacinthus, would have been</l>
<l>set in the sky! if Phoebus had been given</l>
<l>time which the cruel fates denied for you.</l>
<l>But in a way you are immortal too.</l>
<l>Though you have died. Always when warm spring</l>
<l>drives winter out, and Aries (the Ram)</l>
<l>succeeds to Pisces (watery Fish), you rise</l>
<l>and blossom on the green turf. And the love</l>
<l>my father had for you was deeper than he felt</l>
<l>for others. Delphi center of the world,</l>
<l>had no presiding guardian, while the God</l>
<l>frequented the Eurotas and the land</l>
<l>of Sparta, never fortified with walls.</l>
<l>His zither and his bow no longer fill</l>
<l>his eager mind and now without a thought</l>
<l>of dignity, he carried nets and held</l>
<l>the dogs in leash, and did not hesitate</l>
<l>to go with Hyacinthus on the rough,</l>
<l>steep mountain ridges; and by all of such</l>
<l>associations, his love was increased.</l>

    
<l>Now Titan was about midway, betwixt</l>
<l>the coming and the banished night, and stood</l>
<l>at equal distance from those two extremes.</l>
<l>Then, when the youth and Phoebus were well stripped,</l>
<l>and gleaming with rich olive oil, they tried</l>
<l>a friendly contest with the discus. First</l>
<l>Phoebus, well-poised, sent it awhirl through air,</l>
<l>and cleft the clouds beyond with its broad weight;</l>
<l>from which at length it fell down to the earth,</l>
<l>a certain evidence of strength and skill.</l>
<l>Heedless of danger Hyacinthus rushed</l>
<l>for eager glory of the game, resolved</l>
<l>to get the discus. But it bounded back</l>
<l>from off the hard earth, and struck full against</l>
<l>your face, O Hyacinthus! Deadly pale</l>
<l>the God's face went — as pallid as the boy's.</l>
<l>With care he lifted the sad huddled form.</l>

    
<l>The kind god tries to warm you back to life,</l>
<l>and next endeavors to attend your wound,</l>
<l>and stay your parting soul with healing herbs.</l>
<l>His skill is no advantage, for the wound</l>
<l>is past all art of cure. As if someone,</l>
<l>when in a garden, breaks off violets,</l>
<l>poppies, or lilies hung from golden stems,</l>
<l>then drooping they must hang their withered heads,</l>
<l>and gaze down towards the earth beneath them; so,</l>
<l>the dying boy's face droops, and his bent neck,</l>
<l>a burden to itself, falls back upon</l>
<l>his shoulder: “You are fallen in your prime</l>
<l>defrauded of your youth, O Hyacinthus!”</l>
<l>Moaned Apollo. “I can see in your sad wound</l>
<l>my own guilt, and you are my cause of grief</l>
<l>and self-reproach. My own hand gave you death</l>
<l>unmerited — I only can be charged</l>
<l>with your destruction.—What have I done wrong?</l>
<l>Can it be called a fault to play with you?</l>
<l>Should loving you be called a fault? And oh,</l>
<l>that I might now give up my life for you!</l>
<l>Or die with you! But since our destinies</l>
<l>prevent us you shall always be with me,</l>
<l>and you shall dwell upon my care-filled lips.</l>
<l>The lyre struck by my hand, and my true songs</l>
<l>will always celebrate you. A new flower</l>
<l>you shall arise, with markings on your petals,</l>
<l>close imitation of my constant moans:</l>
<l>and there shall come another to be linked</l>
<l>with this new flower, a valiant hero shall</l>
<l>be known by the same marks upon its petals.”</l>

    
<l>And while Phoebus, Apollo, sang these words</l>
<l>with his truth-telling lips, behold the blood</l>
<l>of Hyacinthus, which had poured out on</l>
<l>the ground beside him and there stained the grass,</l>
<l>was changed from blood; and in its place a flower,</l>
<l>more beautiful than Tyrian dye, sprang up.</l>
<l>It almost seemed a lily, were it not</l>
<l>that one was purple and the other white.</l>

    
<l>But Phoebus was not satisfied with this.</l>
<l>For it was he who worked the miracle</l>
<l>of his sad words inscribed on flower leaves.</l>
<l>These letters AI, AI, are inscribed</l>
<l>on them. And Sparta certainly is proud</l>
<l>to honor Hyacinthus as her son;</l>
<l>and his loved fame endures; and every year</l>
<l>they celebrate his solemn festival.</l>


Cerastae et Propoetides.
THE CERASTAE AND PROPOETIDES

<l>If you should ask Amathus, which is rich</l>
<l>in metals, how can she rejoice and take</l>
<l>a pride in deeds of her Propoetides;</l>
<l>she would disclaim it and repudiate</l>
<l>them all, as well as those of transformed men,</l>
<l>whose foreheads were deformed by two rough horns,</l>
<l>from which their name Cerastae. By their gates</l>
<l>an altar unto Jove stood. If by chance</l>
<l>a stranger, not informed of their dark crimes,</l>
<l>had seen the horrid altar smeared with blood,</l>
<l>he would suppose that suckling calves and sheep</l>
<l>of Amathus, were sacrificed thereon—</l>
<l>it was in fact the blood of slaughtered guests!</l>

    
<l>Kind-hearted Venus, outraged by such deeds</l>
<l>of sacrifice, was ready to desert</l>
<l>her cities and her snake-infested plains;</l>
<l>“But how,” said she, “have their delightful lands</l>
<l>together with my well built cities sinned?</l>
<l>What crime have they done?—Those inhabitants</l>
<l>should pay the penalty of their own crimes</l>
<l>by exile or by death; or it may be</l>
<l>a middle course, between exile and death;</l>
<l>and what can that be, but the punishment</l>
<l>of a changed form?” And while she hesitates,</l>
<l>in various thoughts of what form they should take,</l>
<l>her eyes by chance, observed their horns,</l>
<l>and that decided her; such horns could well</l>
<l>be on them after any change occurred,</l>
<l>and she transformed their big and brutal bodies</l>
<l>to savage bulls.</l>

    
<l>But even after that,</l>
<l>the obscene Propoetides dared to deny</l>
<l>divinity of Venus, for which fault,</l>
<l>(and it is common fame) they were the first</l>
<l>to criminate their bodies, through the wrath</l>
<l>of Venus; and so blushing shame was lost,</l>
<l>white blood, in their bad faces grew so fast,</l>
<l>so hard, it was no wonder they were turned</l>
<l>with small change into hard and lifeless stones.</l>


Pygmalion.
PYGMALION AND THE STATUE

<l>Pygmalion saw these women waste their lives</l>
<l>in wretched shame, and critical of faults</l>
<l>which nature had so deeply planted through</l>
<l>their female hearts, he lived in preference,</l>
<l>for many years unmarried.—But while he</l>
<l>was single, with consummate skill, he carved</l>
<l>a statue out of snow-white ivory,</l>
<l>and gave to it exquisite beauty, which</l>
<l>no woman of the world has ever equalled:</l>
<l>she was so beautiful, he fell in love</l>
<l>with his creation. It appeared in truth</l>
<l>a perfect virgin with the grace of life,</l>
<l>but in the expression of such modesty</l>
<l>all motion was restrained—and so his art</l>
<l>concealed his art. Pygmalion gazed, inflamed</l>
<l>with love and admiration for the form,</l>
<l>in semblance of a woman, he had carved.</l>

    
<l>He lifts up both his hands to feel the work,</l>
<l>and wonders if it can be ivory,</l>
<l>because it seems to him more truly flesh. —</l>
<l>his mind refusing to conceive of it</l>
<l>as ivory, he kisses it and feels</l>
<l>his kisses are returned. And speaking love,</l>
<l>caresses it with loving hands that seem</l>
<l>to make an impress, on the parts they touch,</l>
<l>so real that he fears he then may bruise</l>
<l>her by his eager pressing. Softest tones</l>
<l>are used each time he speaks to her. He brings</l>
<l>to her such presents as are surely prized</l>
<l>by sweet girls; such as smooth round pebbles, shells,</l>
<l>and birds, and fragrant flowers of thousand tints,</l>
<l>lilies, and painted balls, and amber tears</l>
<l>of Heliads, which distill from far off trees.—</l>
<l>he drapes her in rich clothing and in gems:</l>
<l>rings on her fingers, a rich necklace round</l>
<l>her neck, pearl pendants on her graceful ears;</l>
<l>and golden ornaments adorn her breast.</l>
<l>All these are beautiful—and she appears</l>
<l>most lovable, if carefully attired,—</l>
<l>or perfect as a statue, unadorned.</l>

    
<l>He lays her on a bed luxurious, spread</l>
<l>with coverlets of Tyrian purple dye,</l>
<l>and naming her the consort of his couch,</l>
<l>lays her reclining head on the most soft</l>
<l>and downy pillows, trusting she could feel.</l>

    
<l>The festal day of Venus, known throughout</l>
<l>all Cyprus, now had come, and throngs were there</l>
<l>to celebrate. Heifers with spreading horns,</l>
<l>all gold-tipped, fell when given the stroke of death</l>
<l>upon their snow-white necks; and frankincense</l>
<l>was smoking on the altars. There, intent,</l>
<l>Pygmalion stood before an altar, when</l>
<l>his offering had been made; and although he</l>
<l>feared the result, he prayed: “If it is true,</l>
<l>O Gods, that you can give all things, I pray</l>
<l>to have as my wife—” but, he did not dare</l>
<l>to add “my ivory statue-maid,” and said,</l>
<l>“One like my ivory—.” Golden Venus heard,</l>
<l>for she was present at her festival,</l>
<l>and she knew clearly what the prayer had meant.</l>
<l>She gave a sign that her Divinity</l>
<l>favored his plea: three times the flame leaped high</l>
<l>and brightly in the air.</l>

    
<l>When he returned,</l>
<l>he went directly to his image-maid,</l>
<l>bent over her, and kissed her many times,</l>
<l>while she was on her couch; and as he kissed,</l>
<l>she seemed to gather some warmth from his lips.</l>
<l>Again he kissed her; and he felt her breast;</l>
<l>the ivory seemed to soften at the touch,</l>
<l>and its firm texture yielded to his hand,</l>
<l>as honey-wax of Mount Hymettus turns</l>
<l>to many shapes when handled in the sun,</l>
<l>and surely softens from each gentle touch.</l>

    
<l>He is amazed; but stands rejoicing in his doubt;</l>
<l>while fearful there is some mistake, again</l>
<l>and yet again, gives trial to his hopes</l>
<l>by touching with his hand. It must be flesh!</l>
<l>The veins pulsate beneath the careful test</l>
<l>of his directed finger. Then, indeed,</l>
<l>the astonished hero poured out lavish thanks</l>
<l>to Venus; pressing with his raptured lips</l>
<l>his statue's lips. Now real, true to life—</l>
<l>the maiden felt the kisses given to her,</l>
<l>and blushing, lifted up her timid eyes,</l>
<l>so that she saw the light and sky above,</l>
<l>as well as her rapt lover while he leaned</l>
<l>gazing beside her—and all this at once—</l>
<l>the goddess graced the marriage she had willed,</l>
<l>and when nine times a crescent moon had changed,</l>
<l>increasing to the full, the statue-bride</l>
<l>gave birth to her dear daughter Paphos. From</l>
<l>which famed event the island takes its name.</l>


Myrrha.
MYRRHA TRANSFORMED TO A TREE

<l>The royal Cinyras was sprung from her;</l>
<l>and if he had been father of no child,</l>
<l>might well have been accounted fortunate—</l>
<l>but I must sing of horrible events—</l>
<l>avoid it daughters! Parents! shun this tale!</l>
<l>But if my verse has charmed your thought,</l>
<l>do not give me such credit in this part;</l>
<l>convince yourself it cannot be true life;</l>
<l>or, if against my wish you hear and must</l>
<l>believe it, then be sure to notice how</l>
<l>such wickedness gets certain punishment.</l>

    
<l>And yet, if Nature could permit such crimes</l>
<l>as this to happen, I congratulate</l>
<l>Ismarian people and all Thrace as well,</l>
<l>and I congratulate this nation, which</l>
<l>we know is far away from the land where</l>
<l>this vile abomination did occur.</l>

    
<l>The land we call Panchaia may be rich</l>
<l>in balsam, cinnamon, and costum sweet</l>
<l>for ointment, frankincense distilled from trees,</l>
<l>with many flowers besides. All this large wealth</l>
<l>combined could never compensate the land</l>
<l>for this detestable, one crime: even though</l>
<l>the new Myrrh-Tree advanced on that rich soil.</l>

    
<l>Cupid declares his weapons never caused</l>
<l>an injury to Myrrha, and denies</l>
<l>his torches ever could have urged her crime.—</l>
<l>one of the three bad sisters kindled this,</l>
<l>with fire brand from the Styx, and poisoned you</l>
<l>with swollen vipers.—It is criminal</l>
<l>to hate a parent, but love such as hers</l>
<l>is certainly more criminal than hate.</l>

    
<l>The chosen princes of all lands desire</l>
<l>you now in marriage, and young men throughout</l>
<l>the Orient are vying for your hand.</l>
<l>Choose, Myrrha one from all of these for your</l>
<l>good husband; but exclude from such a thought</l>
<l>your father only. She indeed is quite</l>
<l>aware, and struggles bitterly against</l>
<l>her vile desires, and argues in her heart:—</l>

    
<l>“What am I tending to? O listening Gods</l>
<l>I pray for aid, I pray to Natural Love!</l>
<l>Ah, may the sacred rights of parents keep</l>
<l>this vile desire from me, defend me from</l>
<l>a crime so great—If it indeed is crime.</l>
<l>I am not sure it is—I have not heard</l>
<l>that any god or written law condemns</l>
<l>the union of a parent and his child.</l>
<l>All animals will mate as they desire—</l>
<l>a heifer may endure her sire, and who</l>
<l>condemns it? And the happy stud is not</l>
<l>refused by his mare-daughters: the he-goat</l>
<l>consorts unthought-of with the flock of which</l>
<l>he is the father; and the birds conceive</l>
<l>of those from whom they were themselves begot.</l>
<l>Happy are they who have such privilege!</l>
<l>Malignant men have given spiteful laws;</l>
<l>and what is right to Nature is decreed</l>
<l>unnatural, by jealous laws of men.</l>

    
<l>“But it is said there are some tribes today,</l>
<l>in which the mother marries her own son;</l>
<l>the daughter takes her father; and by this,</l>
<l>the love kind Nature gives them is increased</l>
<l>into a double bond.—Ah wretched me!</l>
<l>Why was it not my fortune to be born</l>
<l>in that love-blessed land? I must abide,</l>
<l>depressed by my misfortunes, in this place.</l>

    
<l>“Why do I dwell on these forbidden hopes?</l>
<l>Let me forget to think of lawless flame.</l>
<l>My father is most worthy of my love,</l>
<l>but only as a father.—If I were</l>
<l>not born the daughter of great Cinyras,</l>
<l>I might be joined to him; but, as it stands,</l>
<l>because he is mine he is never mine;</l>
<l>because near to me he is far from me.</l>

    
<l>“It would be better for me, if we were</l>
<l>but strangers to each other; for I then,</l>
<l>could wish to go, and leave my native land,</l>
<l>and so escape temptation to this crime:</l>
<l>but my unhappy passion holds me here,</l>
<l>that I may see Cinyras face to face,</l>
<l>and touch him, talk with him and even kiss him—</l>
<l>the best, if nothing else can be allowed.</l>

    
<l>“But what more could be asked for, by the most</l>
<l>depraved? Think of the many sacred ties</l>
<l>and loved names, you are dragging to the mire:</l>
<l>the rival of your mother, will you be</l>
<l>the mistress of your father, and be named</l>
<l>the sister of your son, and make yourself</l>
<l>the mother of your brother? And will you</l>
<l>not dread the sisters with black snakes for hair.</l>
<l>Whom guilty creatures, such as you, can see</l>
<l>brandish relentless flames before their eyes</l>
<l>and faces? While your body has not sinned</l>
<l>you must not let sin creep into your heart,</l>
<l>and violate great Nature's law with your</l>
<l>unlawful rovings. If you had the right</l>
<l>to long for his endearment, it could not</l>
<l>be possible. He is a virtuous man</l>
<l>and is regardful of the moral law—</l>
<l>oh how I wish my passion could be his!”</l>

    
<l>And so she argued and declared her love:</l>
<l>but Cinyras, her father, who was urged</l>
<l>by such a throng of suitors for her hand,</l>
<l>that he could make no choice, at last inquired</l>
<l>of her, so she might make her heart's wish known.</l>
<l>And as he named them over, asked her which</l>
<l>she fixed her gaze upon her father's face,</l>
<l>in doubtful agony what she could say,</l>
<l>while hot tears filled her eyes. Her father, sure</l>
<l>it all was of a virginal alarm,</l>
<l>as he is telling her she need not weep</l>
<l>dries her wet cheeks and kisses her sweet lips.</l>
<l>Too much delighted with his gentle words</l>
<l>and kind endearments, Myrrha, when he asked</l>
<l>again, which one might be her husband, said,</l>
<l>“The one just like yourself.”, And he replied</l>
<l>not understanding what her heart would say,</l>
<l>“You answer as a loving-daughter should.”</l>
<l>When she heard “loving-daughter” said, the girl</l>
<l>too conscious of her guilt, looked on the ground.</l>

    
<l>It was now midnight, peaceful sleep dissolved</l>
<l>the world-care of all mortals, but of her</l>
<l>who, sleepless through the night, burnt in the flame</l>
<l>of her misplaced affection. First despair</l>
<l>compels her to abandon every hope,</l>
<l>and then she changes and resolves to try;</l>
<l>and so she wavers from desire to shame,</l>
<l>for she could not adhere to any plan.</l>

    
<l>As a great tree, cut by the swinging axe</l>
<l>is chopped until the last blow has been struck,</l>
<l>then sways and threatens danger to all sides;</l>
<l>so does her weak mind, cut with many blows,</l>
<l>waver unsteadily—this way and that—</l>
<l>and turning back and forth it finds no rest</l>
<l>from passion, save the rest that lies in death.</l>

    
<l>The thought of death gave comfort to her heart.</l>
<l>Resolved to hang herself, she sat upright;</l>
<l>then, as she tied her girdle to a beam,</l>
<l>she said, “Farewell, beloved Cinyras,</l>
<l>and may you know the cause of my sad death.”</l>
<l>And while she spoke those words, her fingers fixed</l>
<l>the noosed rope close around her death-pale neck.</l>

    
<l>They say the murmur of despairing words</l>
<l>was heard by her attentive nurse who watched</l>
<l>outside the room. And, faithful as of old,</l>
<l>she opened the shut door. But, when she saw</l>
<l>the frightful preparations made for death,</l>
<l>the odd nurse screamed and beat and tore her breast,</l>
<l>then seized and snatched the rope from Myrrha's neck;</l>
<l>and after she had torn the noose apart,</l>
<l>at last she had the time to weep and time,</l>
<l>while she embraced the girl, to ask her why</l>
<l>the halter had been fastened round her neck.</l>
<l>The girl in stubborn silence only fixed</l>
<l>her eyes upon the ground—sad that her first</l>
<l>attempt at death, because too slow, was foiled.</l>
<l>The old nurse-woman urged and urged, and showed</l>
<l>her gray hair and her withered breasts, and begged</l>
<l>her by the memory of her cradle days,</l>
<l>and baby nourishment, to hide no more</l>
<l>from her long-trusted nurse what caused her grief.</l>
<l>The girl turned from her questions with a sigh.</l>
<l>The nurse, still more determined to know all,</l>
<l>promised fidelity and her best aid—</l>

    
<l>“Tell me,” she said, “and let me give you help;</l>
<l>my old age offers means for your relief:</l>
<l>if it be frantic passion, I have charms</l>
<l>and healing herbs; or, if an evil spell</l>
<l>was worked on you by someone, you shall be</l>
<l>cured to your perfect self by magic rites;</l>
<l>or, if your actions have enraged the Gods,</l>
<l>a sacrifice will satisfy their wrath.</l>
<l>What else could be the cause? Your family</l>
<l>and you are prosperous—your mother dear,</l>
<l>and your loved father are alive and well.”</l>
<l>And, when she heard her say the name of father,</l>
<l>a sigh heaved up from her distracted heart.</l>

    
<l>But even after that the nurse could not</l>
<l>conceive such evil in the girl's sick heart;</l>
<l>and yet she had a feeling it must be</l>
<l>only a love affair could cause the crime:</l>
<l>and with persistent purpose begged the cause.</l>
<l>She pressed the weeping girl against her breast;</l>
<l>and as she held her in her feeble arms,</l>
<l>she said, “Sweet heart, I know you are in love:</l>
<l>in this affair I am entirely yours</l>
<l>for your good service, you must have no fear,</l>
<l>your father cannot learn of it from me.,”</l>

    
<l>just like a mad girl, Myrrha sprang away,</l>
<l>and with her face deep-buried in a couch,</l>
<l>sobbed out, “Go from me or stop asking me</l>
<l>my cause of grief—it is a crime of shame—</l>
<l>I cannot tell it!” Horrified the nurse</l>
<l>stretched forth her trembling hands, palsied</l>
<l>with age and fear. She fell down at the feet</l>
<l>of her loved foster-child, and coaxing her</l>
<l>and frightening her, she threatened to disclose</l>
<l>her knowledge of the halter and of what</l>
<l>she knew of her attempted suicide;</l>
<l>and after all was said, she gave her word</l>
<l>to help the girl, when she had given to her</l>
<l>a true confession of her sad heart-love.</l>

    
<l>The girl just lifted up her face, and laid</l>
<l>it, weeping, on the bosom of her nurse.</l>
<l>She tried so often to confess, and just</l>
<l>as often checked her words, her shamed face hid</l>
<l>deep in her garment: “Oh”, at last she groans,</l>
<l>“O mother blessed in your husband—oh!”</l>
<l>Only that much she said and groaned. The nurse</l>
<l>felt a cold horror stealing through her heart</l>
<l>and frame, for she now understood it all.</l>
<l>And her white hair stood bristling on her head,</l>
<l>while with the utmost care of love and art</l>
<l>she strove to use appropriate words and deeds,</l>
<l>to banish the mad passion of the girl.</l>
<l>Though Myrrha knew that she was truly warned,</l>
<l>she was resolved to die, unless she could</l>
<l>obtain the object of her wicked love.</l>
<l>The nurse gave way at last as in defeat,</l>
<l>and said, “Live and enjoy—” but did not dare</l>
<l>to say, “your father”, did not finish, though,</l>
<l>she promised and confirmed it with an oath.</l>

    
<l>It was the time when matrons celebrate</l>
<l>the annual festival of Ceres. Then,</l>
<l>all robed in decent garments of snow-white,</l>
<l>they bring garlands of precious wheat, which are</l>
<l>first fruits of worship; and for nine nights they</l>
<l>must count forbidden every act of love,</l>
<l>and shun the touch of man. And in that throng,</l>
<l>Cenchreis, the king's wife, with constant care</l>
<l>attended every secret rite: and so</l>
<l>while the king's bed was lacking his true wife,</l>
<l>one of those nights,—King Cinyras was drunk</l>
<l>with too much wine,—the scheming nurse informed</l>
<l>him of a girl most beautiful, whose love</l>
<l>for him was passionate; in a false tale</l>
<l>she pictured a true passion. — When he asked</l>
<l>the maiden's age, she answered, “Just the same</l>
<l>as Myrrha's.” Bidden by the king to go</l>
<l>and fetch her, the officious old nurse, when</l>
<l>she found the girl, cried out; “Rejoice, my dear,</l>
<l>we have contrived it!” The unhappy girl</l>
<l>could not feel genuine joy in her amazed</l>
<l>and startled body. Her dazed mind was filled</l>
<l>with strange forebodings; but she did believe</l>
<l>her heart was joyful.—Great excitement filled</l>
<l>her wrecked heart with such inconsistencies.</l>

    
<l>Now was the time when nature is at rest;</l>
<l>between the Bears, Bootes turned his wain</l>
<l>down to the west, and the guilty Myrrha turns</l>
<l>to her enormity. The golden moon</l>
<l>flies from the heaven, and black clouds cover</l>
<l>the hiding stars and Night has lost her fires.</l>
<l>The first to hide were stars of Icarus</l>
<l>and of Erigone, in hallowed love</l>
<l>devoted to her father. Myrrha thrice</l>
<l>was warned by omen of her stumbling foot;</l>
<l>the funeral screech-owl also warned her thrice,</l>
<l>with dismal cry; yet Myrrha onward goes.</l>
<l>It seems to her the black night lessens shame.</l>
<l>She holds fast to her nurse with her left hand,</l>
<l>and with the other hand gropes through the dark.</l>
<l>And now they go until she finds the door.</l>
<l>Now at the threshold of her father's room,</l>
<l>she softly pushes back the door, her nurse</l>
<l>takes her within. The girl's knees trembling sink</l>
<l>beneath her. Her drawn bloodless face has lost</l>
<l>its color, and while she moves to the crime,</l>
<l>bad courage goes from her until afraid</l>
<l>of her bold effort, she would gladly turn</l>
<l>unrecognized. But as she hesitates,</l>
<l>the aged crone still holds her by the hand;</l>
<l>and leading her up to the high bed there</l>
<l>delivering Myrrha, says, “Now Cinyras,</l>
<l>you take her, she is yours;” and leaves the pair</l>
<l>doomed in their crime — the father to pollute</l>
<l>his own flesh in his own bed; where he tries</l>
<l>first to encourage her from maiden fears,</l>
<l>by gently talking to the timid girl.</l>
<l>He chanced to call her “daughter,” as a name</l>
<l>best suited to her age; and she in turn,</l>
<l>endearing, called him “father”, so no names</l>
<l>might be omitted to complete their guilt.</l>

    
<l>She staggered from his chamber with the crime</l>
<l>of her own father hidden in her womb,</l>
<l>and their guilt was repeated many nights;</l>
<l>till Cinyras — determined he must know</l>
<l>his mistress, after many meetings, brought</l>
<l>a light and knew his crime had harmed his daughter.</l>

    
<l>Speechless in shame he drew forth his bright sword</l>
<l>out from the scabbard where it hung near by.—</l>
<l>but frightened Myrrha fled, and so escaped</l>
<l>death in the shadows of dark night. Groping</l>
<l>her pathless way at random through the fields,</l>
<l>she left Arabia, famed for spreading palms,</l>
<l>and wandered through Panchaean lands. Until</l>
<l>after nine months of aimless wandering days,</l>
<l>she rested in Sabaea, for she could</l>
<l>not hold the burden she had borne so long.</l>

    
<l>Not knowing what to pray for, moved alike</l>
<l>by fear of death and weariness of life,</l>
<l>her wishes were expressed in prayer: “O Gods,</l>
<l>if you will listen to my prayer, I do</l>
<l>not shun a dreadful punishment deserved;</l>
<l>but now because my life offends the living,</l>
<l>and dying I offend the dead, drive me</l>
<l>from both conditions; change me, and refuse</l>
<l>my flesh both life and death!”</l>

    
<l>Some god did listen</l>
<l>to her unnatural prayer; her last petition</l>
<l>had answering gods. For even as she prayed,</l>
<l>the earth closed over her legs; roots grew out</l>
<l>and, stretching forth obliquely from her nails,</l>
<l>gave strong support to her up-growing trunk;</l>
<l>her bones got harder, and her marrow still</l>
<l>unchanged, kept to the center, as her blood</l>
<l>was changed to sap, as her outstretching arms</l>
<l>became long branches and her fingers twigs;</l>
<l>and as her soft skin hardened into bark:</l>
<l>and the fast-growing tree had closely bound</l>
<l>her womb, still heavy, and had covered her</l>
<l>soft bosom; and was spreading quickly up</l>
<l>to her neck.—She can not endure the strain,</l>
<l>and sinking down into the rising wood,</l>
<l>her whole face soon was hidden in the bark.</l>
<l>Although all sense of human life was gone,</l>
<l>as quickly as she lost her human form,</l>
<l>her weeping was continued, and warm drops</l>
<l>distilled from her (the tree) cease not to fall.</l>
<l>There is a virtue even in her tears—</l>
<l>the valued myrrh distilling from the trunk,</l>
<l>keeps to her name, by which she still is known,</l>
<l>and cannot be forgot of aging time.</l>

    
<l>The guilt-begotten child had growth while wood</l>
<l>was growing, and endeavored now to find</l>
<l>a way of safe birth. The tree-trunk was swelling</l>
<l>and tightened against Myrrha, who, unable</l>
<l>to express her torture, could not call upon</l>
<l>Lucina in the usual words of travail.</l>
<l>But then just like a woman in great pain,</l>
<l>the tree bends down and, while it groans, bedews</l>
<l>itself with falling tears. Lucina stood</l>
<l>in pity near the groaning branches, laid</l>
<l>her hands on them, and uttered charms to aid</l>
<l>the hindered birth. The tree cracked open then,</l>
<l>the bark was rent asunder, and it gave forth</l>
<l>its living weight, a wailing baby-boy.</l>
<l>The Naiads laid him on soft leaves, and they</l>
<l>anointed him with his own mother's tears.</l>

    
<l>Even Envy would not fail to praise the child,</l>
<l>as beautiful as naked cupids seen</l>
<l>in chosen paintings. Only give to him</l>
<l>a polished quiver, or take theirs from them,</l>
<l>and no keen eye could choose him from their midst.</l>


Venus et Adonis. Atalanta.

<l>Time gliding by without our knowledge cheats us,</l>
<l>and nothing can be swifter than the years.</l>
<l>That son of sister and grandfather, who</l>
<l>was lately hidden in his parent tree,</l>
<l>just lately born, a lovely baby-boy</l>
<l>is now a youth, now man more beautiful</l>
<l>than during growth. He wins the love of Venus</l>
<l>and so avenges his own mother's passion.</l>
<l>For while the goddess' son with quiver held</l>
<l>on shoulder, once was kissing his loved mother,</l>
<l>it chanced unwittingly he grazed her breast</l>
<l>with a projecting arrow. Instantly</l>
<l>the wounded goddess pushed her son away;</l>
<l>but the scratch had pierced her deeper than she thought</l>
<l>and even Venus was at first deceived.</l>

    
<l>Delighted with the beauty of the youth,</l>
<l>she does not think of her Cytherian shores</l>
<l>and does not care for Paphos, which is girt</l>
<l>by the deep sea, nor Cnidos, haunts of fish,</l>
<l>nor Amathus far-famed for precious ores.</l>

    
<l>Venus, neglecting heaven, prefers Adonis</l>
<l>to heaven, and so she holds close to his ways</l>
<l>as his companion, and forgets to rest</l>
<l>at noon-day in the shade, neglecting care</l>
<l>of her sweet beauty. She goes through the woods,</l>
<l>and over mountain ridges and wild fields,</l>
<l>rocky and thorn-set, bare to her white knees</l>
<l>after Diana's manner. And she cheers</l>
<l>the hounds, intent to hunt for harmless prey,</l>
<l>such as the leaping hare, or the wild stag,</l>
<l>high-crowned with branching antlers, or the doe.—</l>
<l>she keeps away from fierce wild boars, away</l>
<l>from ravenous wolves; and she avoids the bears</l>
<l>of frightful claws, and lions glutted with</l>
<l>the blood of slaughtered cattle.</l>

    
<l>She warns you,</l>
<l>Adonis, to beware and fear them. If her fears</l>
<l>for you were only heeded! “Oh be brave,”</l>
<l>she says, “against those timid animals</l>
<l>which fly from you; but courage is not safe</l>
<l>against the bold. Dear boy, do not be rash,</l>
<l>do not attack the wild beasts which are armed</l>
<l>by nature, lest your glory may cost me</l>
<l>great sorrow. Neither youth nor beauty nor</l>
<l>the deeds which have moved Venus have effect</l>
<l>on lions, bristling boars, and on the eyes</l>
<l>and tempers of wild beasts. Boars have the force</l>
<l>of lightning in their curved tusks, and the rage</l>
<l>of tawny lions is unlimited.</l>
<l>I fear and hate them all.”</l>

    
<l>When he inquires</l>
<l>the reason, she says: “I will tell it; you</l>
<l>will be surprised to learn the bad result</l>
<l>caused by an ancient crime.—But I am weary</l>
<l>with unaccustomed toil; and see! a poplar</l>
<l>convenient, offers a delightful shade</l>
<l>and this lawn gives a good couch. Let us rest</l>
<l>ourselves here on the grass.” So saying, she</l>
<l>reclined upon the turf and, pillowing</l>
<l>her head against his breast and mingling kisses</l>
<l>with her words, she told him the following tale:</l>


ATALANTA

<l>Perhaps you may have heard of a swift maid,</l>
<l>who ran much faster than swift-footed men</l>
<l>contesting in the race. What they have told</l>
<l>is not an idle tale.—She did excel</l>
<l>them all—and you could not have said</l>
<l>whether her swift speed or her beauty was</l>
<l>more worthy of your praise. When this maid once</l>
<l>consulted with an oracle, of her</l>
<l>fate after marriage, the god answered her:</l>
<l>“You, Atalanta, never will have need</l>
<l>of husband, who will only be your harm.</l>
<l>For your best good you should avoid the tie;</l>
<l>but surely you will not avoid your harm;</l>
<l>and while yet living you will lose yourself.”</l>

    
<l>She was so frightened by the oracle,</l>
<l>she lived unwedded in far shaded woods;</l>
<l>and with harsh terms repulsed insistent throngs</l>
<l>of suitors. “I will not be won,” she said,</l>
<l>“Till I am conquered first in speed. Contest</l>
<l>the race with me. A wife and couch shall both</l>
<l>be given to reward the swift, but death</l>
<l>must recompense the one who lags behind.</l>
<l>This must be the condition of a race.”</l>
<l>Indeed she was that pitiless, but such</l>
<l>the power of beauty, a rash multitude</l>
<l>agreed to her harsh terms.</l>

    
<l>Hippomenes</l>
<l>had come, a stranger, to the cruel race,</l>
<l>with condemnation in his heart against</l>
<l>the racing young men for their headstrong love;</l>
<l>and said, “Why seek a wife at such a risk?”</l>
<l>But when he saw her face, and perfect form</l>
<l>disrobed for perfect running, such a form</l>
<l>as mine, Adonis, or as yours—if you</l>
<l>were woman—he was so astonished he</l>
<l>raised up his hands and said, “Oh pardon me</l>
<l>brave men whom I was blaming, I could not</l>
<l>then realize the value of the prize</l>
<l>you strove for.” And as he is praising her,</l>
<l>his own heart leaping with love's fire, he hopes</l>
<l>no young man may outstrip her in the race;</l>
<l>and, full of envy, fears for the result.</l>

    
<l>“But why,” he cries, “is my chance in the race</l>
<l>untried? Divinity helps those who dare.”</l>
<l>But while the hero weighed it in his mind</l>
<l>the virgin flew as if her feet had wings.</l>
<l>Although she seemed to him in flight as swift</l>
<l>as any Scythian arrow, he admired</l>
<l>her beauty more; and her swift speed appeared</l>
<l>in her most beautiful. The breeze bore back</l>
<l>the streamers on her flying ankles, while</l>
<l>her hair was tossed back over her white shoulders;</l>
<l>the bright trimmed ribbons at her knees were fluttering,</l>
<l>and over her white girlish body came</l>
<l>a pink flush, just as when a purple awning</l>
<l>across a marble hall gives it a wealth</l>
<l>of borrowed hues. And while Hippomenes</l>
<l>in wonder gazed at her, the goal was reached;</l>
<l>and Atalanta crowned victorious</l>
<l>with festal wreath.—But all the vanquished youths</l>
<l>paid the death-penalty with sighs and groans,</l>
<l>according to the stipulated bond.</l>

    
<l>Not frightened by the fate of those young men,</l>
<l>he stood up boldly in the midst of all;</l>
<l>and fixing his strong eyes upon the maiden, said:</l>
<l>“Where is the glory in an easy victory</l>
<l>over such weaklings? Try your fate with me!</l>
<l>If fortune fail to favor you, how could</l>
<l>it shame you to be conquered by a man?</l>
<l>Megareus of Onchestus is my father,</l>
<l>his grandsire, Neptune, god of all the seas.</l>
<l>I am descendant of the King of Waves:</l>
<l>and add to this, my name for manly worth</l>
<l>has not disgraced the fame of my descent.</l>
<l>If you should prove victorious against</l>
<l>this combination, you will have achieved</l>
<l>a great enduring name—the only one</l>
<l>who ever bested great Hippomenes.”</l>

    
<l>While he was speaking, Atalanta's gaze</l>
<l>grew softer, in her vacillating hopes</l>
<l>to conquer and be conquered; till at last,</l>
<l>her heart, unbalanced, argued in this way:</l>

    
<l>“It must be some god envious of youth,</l>
<l>wishing to spoil this one prompts him to seek</l>
<l>wedlock with me and risk his own dear life.</l>
<l>I am not worth the price, if I may judge.</l>
<l>His beauty does not touch me—but I could</l>
<l>be moved by it—I must consider he</l>
<l>is but a boy. It is not he himself</l>
<l>who moves me, but his youth. Sufficient cause</l>
<l>for thought are his great courage and his soul</l>
<l>fearless of death. What of his high descent;—</l>
<l>great grandson of the King of all the seas?</l>
<l>What of his love for me that has such great</l>
<l>importance, he would perish if his fate</l>
<l>denied my marriage to him? O strange boy,</l>
<l>go from me while you can; abandon hope</l>
<l>of this alliance stained with blood—A match</l>
<l>with me is fatal. Other maids will not</l>
<l>refuse to wed you, and a wiser girl</l>
<l>will gladly seek your love.—But what concern</l>
<l>is it of mine, when I but think of those</l>
<l>who have already perished! Let him look</l>
<l>to it himself; and let him die. Since he</l>
<l>is not warned by his knowledge of the fate</l>
<l>of many other suitors, he declares</l>
<l>quite plainly, he is weary of his life.—</l>

    
<l>“Shall he then die, because it must be his</l>
<l>one hope to live with me? And suffer death</l>
<l>though undeserved, for me because he loves?</l>
<l>My victory will not ward off the hate,</l>
<l>the odium of the deed! But it is not</l>
<l>a fault of mine.—Oh fond, fond man, I would</l>
<l>that you had never seen me! But you are</l>
<l>so madly set upon it, I could wish</l>
<l>you may prove much the swifter! Oh how dear</l>
<l>how lovable is his young girlish face!—</l>
<l>ah, doomed Hippomenes, I only wish</l>
<l>mischance had never let you see me! You</l>
<l>are truly worthy of a life on earth.</l>
<l>If I had been more fortunate, and not</l>
<l>denied a happy marriage day; I would</l>
<l>not share my bed with any man but you.”</l>

    
<l>All this the virgin Atalanta said;</l>
<l>and knowing nothing of the power of love,</l>
<l>she is so ignorant of what she does,</l>
<l>she loves and does not know she is in love.</l>

    
<l>Meanwhile her father and the people, all</l>
<l>loudly demanded the accustomed race.</l>
<l>A suppliant, the young Hippomenes</l>
<l>invoked me with his anxious voice, “I pray</l>
<l>to you, O Venus, Queen of Love, be near</l>
<l>and help my daring—smile upon the love</l>
<l>you have inspired!” The breeze, not envious,</l>
<l>wafted this prayer to me; and I confess,</l>
<l>it was so tender it did move my heart—</l>
<l>I had but little time to give him aid.</l>

    
<l>There is a field there which the natives call</l>
<l>the Field Tamasus—the most prized of all</l>
<l>the fertile lands of Cyprus. This rich field,</l>
<l>in ancient days, was set apart for me,</l>
<l>by chosen elders who decreed it should</l>
<l>enrich my temples yearly. In this field</l>
<l>there grows a tree, with gleaming golden leaves,</l>
<l>and all its branches crackle with bright gold.</l>
<l>Since I was coming from there, by some chance,</l>
<l>I had three golden apples in my hand,</l>
<l>which I had plucked. With them I planned to aid</l>
<l>Hippomenes. While quite invisible</l>
<l>to all but him, I taught him how to use</l>
<l>those golden apples for his benefit.</l>


    
<l>The trumpet soon gave signal for the race</l>
<l>and both of them crouching flashed quickly forth</l>
<l>and skimmed the surface of the sandy course</l>
<l>with flying feet. You might even think those two</l>
<l>could graze the sea with unwet feet and pass</l>
<l>over the ripened heads of standing grain.</l>

    
<l>Shouts of applause gave courage to the youth:</l>
<l>the cheering multitude cried out to him:—</l>
<l>“Now is the time to use your strength. Go on!</l>
<l>Hippomenes! Bend to the work! You're sure</l>
<l>to win!” It must be doubted who was most</l>
<l>rejoiced by those brave words, Megareus' son,</l>
<l>or Schoeneus' daughter. Oh, how often, when</l>
<l>she could have passed him, she delayed her speed;</l>
<l>and after gazing long upon his face</l>
<l>reluctantly again would pass him! Now</l>
<l>dry panting breath came from his weary throat—</l>
<l>the goal still far away.—Then Neptune's scion</l>
<l>threw one of three gold apples. Atalanta</l>
<l>with wonder saw it—eager to possess</l>
<l>the shining fruit, she turned out of her course,</l>
<l>picked up the rolling gold. Hippomenes</l>
<l>passed by her, while spectators roared applause.</l>
<l>Increasing speed, she overcame delay,</l>
<l>made up for time lost, and again she left</l>
<l>the youth behind. She was delayed again</l>
<l>because he tossed another golden apple.</l>
<l>She followed him, and passed him in the race.</l>

    
<l>The last part of the course remained. He cried</l>
<l>“Be near me, goddess, while I use your gift.”</l>
<l>With youthful might he threw the shining gold,</l>
<l>in an oblique direction to the side,</l>
<l>so that pursuit would mean a slow return.</l>
<l>The virgin seemed to hesitate, in doubt</l>
<l>whether to follow after this third prize.</l>

    
<l>I forced her to turn for it; take it up;</l>
<l>and, adding weight to the gold fruit, she held,</l>
<l>impeded her with weight and loss of time.</l>
<l>For fear my narrative may stretch beyond</l>
<l>the race itself,—the maiden was outstripped;</l>
<l>Hippomenes then led his prize away.</l>

    
<l>Adonis, did I not deserve his thanks</l>
<l>with tribute of sweet incense? But he was</l>
<l>ungrateful, and, forgetful of my help,</l>
<l>he gave me neither frankincense nor thanks.</l>
<l>Such conduct threw me into sudden wrath,</l>
<l>and, fretting at the slight, I felt I must</l>
<l>not be despised at any future time.</l>
<l>I told myself 'twas only right to make</l>
<l>a just example of them. They were near</l>
<l>a temple, hidden in the forest, which</l>
<l>glorious Echion in remembered time</l>
<l>had built to Rhea, Mother of the gods,</l>
<l>in payment of a vow. So, wearied from</l>
<l>the distance traveled, they were glad to have</l>
<l>a needed rest. Hippomenes while there,</l>
<l>was seized with love his heart could not control.—</l>
<l>a passion caused by my divinity.</l>

    
<l>Quite near the temple was a cave-like place,</l>
<l>covered with pumice. It was hallowed by</l>
<l>religious veneration of the past.</l>
<l>Within the shadows of that place, a priest</l>
<l>had stationed many wooden images</l>
<l>of olden gods. The lovers entered there</l>
<l>and desecrated it. The images</l>
<l>were scandalized, and turned their eyes away.</l>
<l>The tower-crowned Mother, Cybele, at first</l>
<l>prepared to plunge the guilty pair beneath</l>
<l>the waves of Styx, but such a punishment</l>
<l>seemed light. And so their necks, that had been smooth.</l>
<l>Were covered instantly with tawny manes;</l>
<l>their fingers bent to claws; their arms were changed</l>
<l>to fore-legs; and their bosoms held their weight;</l>
<l>and with their tails they swept the sandy ground.</l>

    
<l>Their casual glance is anger, and instead</l>
<l>of words they utter growls. They haunt the woods,</l>
<l>a bridal-room to their ferocious taste.</l>
<l>And now fierce lions they are terrible</l>
<l>to all of life; except to Cybele;</l>
<l>whose harness has subdued their champing jaws.</l>

    
<l>My dear Adonis keep away from all</l>
<l>such savage animals; avoid all those</l>
<l>which do not turn their fearful backs in flight</l>
<l>but offer their bold breasts to your attack,</l>
<l>lest courage should be fatal to us both.</l>

ADONIS TRANSFORMED

<l>Indeed she warned him. — Harnessing her swans,</l>
<l>she traveled swiftly through the yielding air;</l>
<l>but his rash courage would not heed advice.</l>
<l>By chance his dogs, which followed a sure track,</l>
<l>aroused a wild boar from his hiding place;</l>
<l>and, as he rushed out from his forest lair,</l>
<l>Adonis pierced him with a glancing stroke.</l>

    
<l>Infuriate, the fierce boar's curved snout</l>
<l>first struck the spear-shaft from his bleeding side;</l>
<l>and, while the trembling youth was seeking where</l>
<l>to find a safe retreat, the savage beast</l>
<l>raced after him, until at last he sank</l>
<l>his deadly tusk deep in Adonis' groin;</l>
<l>and stretched him dying on the yellow sand.</l>

    
<l>And now sweet Aphrodite, borne through air</l>
<l>in her light chariot, had not yet arrived</l>
<l>at Cyprus, on the wings of her white swans.</l>
<l>Afar she recognized his dying groans,</l>
<l>and turned her white birds towards the sound. And when</l>
<l>down looking from the lofty sky, she saw</l>
<l>him nearly dead, his body bathed in blood,</l>
<l>she leaped down—tore her garment—tore her hair —</l>
<l>and beat her bosom with distracted hands.</l>
<l>And blaming Fate said, “But not everything</l>
<l>is at the mercy of your cruel power.</l>
<l>My sorrow for Adonis will remain,</l>
<l>enduring as a lasting monument.</l>
<l>Each passing year the memory of his death</l>
<l>shall cause an imitation of my grief.</l>

    
<l>“Your blood, Adonis, will become a flower</l>
<l>perennial. Was it not allowed to you</l>
<l>Persephone, to transform Menthe's limbs</l>
<l>into sweet fragrant mint? And can this change</l>
<l>of my loved hero be denied to me?”</l>

    
<l>Her grief declared, she sprinkled his blood with</l>
<l>sweet-smelling nectar, and his blood as soon</l>
<l>as touched by it began to effervesce,</l>
<l>just as transparent bubbles always rise</l>
<l>in rainy weather. Nor was there a pause</l>
<l>more than an hour, when from Adonis, blood,</l>
<l>exactly of its color, a loved flower</l>
<l>sprang up, such as pomegranates give to us,</l>
<l>small trees which later hide their seeds beneath</l>
<l>a tough rind. But the joy it gives to man</l>
<l>is short-lived, for the winds which give the flower</l>
<l>its name, Anemone, shake it right down,</l>
<l>because its slender hold, always so weak,</l>
<l>lets it fall to the ground from its frail stem.</l>
