<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 4


Minyeides.
THE DAUGHTERS OF KING MINYAS TRANSFORMED TO BATS

<l>Alcithoe, daughter of King Minyas,</l>
<l>consents not to the orgies of the God;</l>
<l>denies that Bacchus is the son of Jove,</l>
<l>and her two sisters join her in that crime.</l>

    
<l>'Twas festal-day when matrons and their maids,</l>
<l>keeping it sacred, had forbade all toil.—</l>
<l>And having draped their bosoms with wild skins,</l>
<l>they loosed their long hair for the sacred wreaths,</l>
<l>and took the leafy thyrsus in their hands;—</l>
<l>for so the priest commanded them. Austere</l>
<l>the wrath of Bacchus if his power be scorned.</l>

    
<l>Mothers and youthful brides obeyed the priest;</l>
<l>and putting by their wickers and their webs,</l>
<l>dropt their unfinished toils to offer up</l>
<l>frankincense to the God; invoking him</l>
<l>with many names:—“O Bacchus! O Twice-born!</l>
<l>O Fire-begot! Thou only child Twice-mothered!</l>
<l>God of all those who plant the luscious grape!</l>
<l>O Liber!” All these names and many more,</l>
<l>for ages known—throughout the lands of Greece.</l>

    
<l>“Thy youth is not consumed by wasting time;</l>
<l>and lo, thou art an ever-youthful boy,</l>
<l>most beautiful of all the Gods of Heaven,</l>
<l>smooth as a virgin when thy horns are hid.—</l>
<l>The distant east to tawny India's clime,</l>
<l>where rolls remotest Ganges to the sea,</l>
<l>was conquered by thy might.—O Most-revered!</l>
<l>Thou didst destroy the doubting Pentheus,</l>
<l>and hurled the sailors' bodies in the deep,</l>
<l>and smote Lycurgus, wielder of the ax.</l>

    
<l>“And thou dost guide thy lynxes, double-yoked,</l>
<l>with showy harness.—Satyrs follow thee;</l>
<l>and Bacchanals, and old Silenus, drunk,</l>
<l>unsteady on his staff; jolting so rough</l>
<l>on his small back-bent ass; and all the way</l>
<l>resounds a youthful clamour; and the screams</l>
<l>of women! and the noise of tambourines!</l>
<l>And the hollow cymbals! and the boxwood flutes,—</l>
<l>fitted with measured holes.—Thou art implored</l>
<l>by all Ismenian women to appear</l>
<l>peaceful and mild; and they perform thy rites.”</l>

    
<l>Only the daughters of King Minyas</l>
<l>are carding wool within their fastened doors,</l>
<l>or twisting with their thumbs the fleecy yarn,</l>
<l>or working at the web. So they corrupt</l>
<l>the sacred festival with needless toil,</l>
<l>keeping their hand-maids busy at the work.</l>

    
<l>And one of them, while drawing out the thread</l>
<l>with nimble thumb, anon began to speak;</l>
<l>“While others loiter and frequent these rites</l>
<l>fantastic, we the wards of Pallas, much</l>
<l>to be preferred, by speaking novel thoughts</l>
<l>may lighten labour. Let us each in turn,</l>
<l>relate to an attentive audience,</l>
<l>a novel tale; and so the hours may glide.”</l>
<l>it pleased her sisters, and they ordered her</l>
<l>to tell the story that she loved the most.</l>

    
<l>So, as she counted in her well-stored mind</l>
<l>the many tales she knew, first doubted she</l>
<l>whether to tell the tale of Derceto,—</l>
<l>that Babylonian, who, aver the tribes</l>
<l>of Palestine, in limpid ponds yet lives,—</l>
<l>her body changed, and scales upon her limbs;</l>
<l>or how her daughter, having taken wings,</l>
<l>passed her declining years in whitened towers.</l>
<l>Or should she tell of Nais, who with herbs,</l>
<l>too potent, into fishes had transformed</l>
<l>the bodies of her lovers, till she met</l>
<l>herself the same sad fate; or of that tree</l>
<l>which sometime bore white fruit, but now is changed</l>
<l>and darkened by the blood that stained its roots.—</l>
<l>Pleased with the novelty of this, at once</l>
<l>she tells the tale of Pyramus and Thisbe;—</l>
<l>and swiftly as she told it unto them,</l>
<l>the fleecy wool was twisted into threads.</l>


Pyramus et Thisbe.
PYRAMUS AND THISBE

<l>When Pyramus and Thisbe, who were known</l>
<l>the one most handsome of all youthful men,</l>
<l>the other loveliest of all eastern girls,—</l>
<l>lived in adjoining houses, near the walls</l>
<l>that Queen Semiramis had built of brick</l>
<l>around her famous city, they grew fond,</l>
<l>and loved each other—meeting often there—</l>
<l>and as the days went by their love increased.</l>

    
<l>They wished to join in marriage, but that joy</l>
<l>their fathers had forbidden them to hope;</l>
<l>and yet the passion that with equal strength</l>
<l>inflamed their minds no parents could forbid.</l>
<l>No relatives had guessed their secret love,</l>
<l>for all their converse was by nods and signs;</l>
<l>and as a smoldering fire may gather heat,</l>
<l>the more 'tis smothered, so their love increased.</l>

    
<l>Now, it so happened, a partition built</l>
<l>between their houses, many years ago,</l>
<l>was made defective with a little chink;</l>
<l>a small defect observed by none, although</l>
<l>for ages there; but what is hid from love?</l>
<l>Our lovers found the secret opening,</l>
<l>and used its passage to convey the sounds</l>
<l>of gentle, murmured words, whose tuneful note</l>
<l>passed oft in safety through that hidden way.</l>

    
<l>There, many a time, they stood on either side,</l>
<l>thisbe on one and Pyramus the other,</l>
<l>and when their warm breath touched from lip to lip,</l>
<l>their sighs were such as this: “Thou envious wall</l>
<l>why art thou standing in the way of those</l>
<l>who die for love? What harm could happen thee</l>
<l>shouldst thou permit us to enjoy our love?</l>
<l>But if we ask too much, let us persuade</l>
<l>that thou wilt open while we kiss but once:</l>
<l>for, we are not ungrateful; unto thee</l>
<l>we own our debt; here thou hast left a way</l>
<l>that breathed words may enter loving ears.,”</l>
<l>so vainly whispered they, and when the night</l>
<l>began to darken they exchanged farewells;</l>
<l>made presence that they kissed a fond farewell</l>
<l>vain kisses that to love might none avail.</l>

    
<l>When dawn removed the glimmering lamps of night,</l>
<l>and the bright sun had dried the dewy grass</l>
<l>again they met where they had told their love;</l>
<l>and now complaining of their hapless fate,</l>
<l>in murmurs gentle, they at last resolved,</l>
<l>away to slip upon the quiet night,</l>
<l>elude their parents, and, as soon as free,</l>
<l>quit the great builded city and their homes.</l>

    
<l>Fearful to wander in the pathless fields,</l>
<l>they chose a trysting place, the tomb of Ninus,</l>
<l>where safely they might hide unseen, beneath</l>
<l>the shadow of a tall mulberry tree,</l>
<l>covered with snow-white fruit, close by a spring.</l>

    
<l>All is arranged according to their hopes:</l>
<l>and now the daylight, seeming slowly moved,</l>
<l>sinks in the deep waves, and the tardy night</l>
<l>arises from the spot where day declines.</l>

    
<l>Quickly, the clever Thisbe having first</l>
<l>deceived her parents, opened the closed door.</l>
<l>She flitted in the silent night away;</l>
<l>and, having veiled her face, reached the great tomb,</l>
<l>and sat beneath the tree; love made her bold.</l>

    
<l>There, as she waited, a great lioness</l>
<l>approached the nearby spring to quench her thirst:</l>
<l>her frothing jaws incarnadined with blood</l>
<l>of slaughtered oxen. As the moon was bright,</l>
<l>Thisbe could see her, and affrighted fled</l>
<l>with trembling footstep to a gloomy cave;</l>
<l>and as she ran she slipped and dropped her veil,</l>
<l>which fluttered to the ground. She did not dare</l>
<l>to save it. Wherefore, when the savage beast</l>
<l>had taken a great draft and slaked her thirst,</l>
<l>and thence had turned to seek her forest lair,</l>
<l>she found it on her way, and full of rage,</l>
<l>tore it and stained it with her bloody jaws:</l>
<l>but Thisbe, fortunate, escaped unseen.</l>

    
<l>Now Pyramus had not gone out so soon</l>
<l>as Thisbe to the tryst; and, when he saw</l>
<l>the certain traces of that savage beast,</l>
<l>imprinted in the yielding dust, his face</l>
<l>went white with fear; but when he found the veil</l>
<l>covered with blood, he cried; “Alas, one night</l>
<l>has caused the ruin of two lovers! Thou</l>
<l>wert most deserving of completed days,</l>
<l>but as for me, my heart is guilty! I</l>
<l>destroyed thee! O my love! I bade thee come</l>
<l>out in the dark night to a lonely haunt,</l>
<l>and failed to go before. Oh! whatever lurks</l>
<l>beneath this rock, though ravenous lion, tear</l>
<l>my guilty flesh, and with most cruel jaws</l>
<l>devour my cursed entrails! What? Not so;</l>
<l>it is a craven's part to wish for death!”</l>

    
<l>So he stopped briefly; and took up the veil;</l>
<l>went straightway to the shadow of the tree;</l>
<l>and as his tears bedewed the well-known veil,</l>
<l>he kissed it oft and sighing said, “Kisses</l>
<l>and tears are thine, receive my blood as well.”</l>

    
<l>And he imbrued the steel, girt at his side,</l>
<l>deep in his bowels; and plucked it from the wound,</l>
<l>a-faint with death. As he fell back to earth,</l>
<l>his spurting blood shot upward in the air;</l>
<l>so, when decay has rift a leaden pipe</l>
<l>a hissing jet of water spurts on high.—</l>

    
<l>By that dark tide the berries on the tree</l>
<l>assumed a deeper tint, for as the roots</l>
<l>soaked up the blood the pendent mulberries</l>
<l>were dyed a purple tint.</l>

    
<l>Thisbe returned,</l>
<l>though trembling still with fright, for now she thought</l>
<l>her lover must await her at the tree,</l>
<l>and she should haste before he feared for her.</l>
<l>Longing to tell him of her great escape</l>
<l>she sadly looked for him with faithful eyes;</l>
<l>but when she saw the spot and the changed tree,</l>
<l>she doubted could they be the same, for so</l>
<l>the colour of the hanging fruit deceived.</l>

    
<l>While doubt dismayed her, on the ground she saw</l>
<l>the wounded body covered with its blood;—</l>
<l>she started backward, and her face grew pale</l>
<l>and ashen; and she shuddered like the sea,</l>
<l>which trembles when its face is lightly skimmed</l>
<l>by the chill breezes;—and she paused a space;—</l>
<l>but when she knew it was the one she loved,</l>
<l>she struck her tender breast and tore her hair.</l>
<l>Then wreathing in her arms his loved form,</l>
<l>she bathed the wound with tears, mingling her grief</l>
<l>in his unquenched blood; and as she kissed</l>
<l>his death-cold features wailed; “Ah Pyramus,</l>
<l>what cruel fate has taken thy life away?</l>
<l>Pyramus! Pyramus! awake! awake!</l>
<l>It is thy dearest Thisbe calls thee! Lift</l>
<l>thy drooping head! Alas,”—At Thisbe's name</l>
<l>he raised his eyes, though languorous in death,</l>
<l>and darkness gathered round him as he gazed.</l>

    
<l>And then she saw her veil; and near it lay</l>
<l>his ivory sheath—but not the trusty sword </l>
<l>and once again she wailed; “Thy own right hand,</l>
<l>and thy great passion have destroyed thee!—</l>
<l>And I? my hand shall be as bold as thine—</l>
<l>my love shall nerve me to the fatal deed—</l>
<l>thee, I will follow to eternity—</l>
<l>though I be censured for the wretched cause,</l>
<l>so surely I shall share thy wretched fate:—</l>
<l>alas, whom death could me alone bereave,</l>
<l>thou shalt not from my love be reft by death!</l>
<l>And, O ye wretched parents, mine and his,</l>
<l>let our misfortunes and our pleadings melt</l>
<l>your hearts, that ye no more deny to those</l>
<l>whom constant love and lasting death unite—</l>
<l>entomb us in a single sepulchre.</l>

    
<l>“And, O thou tree of many-branching boughs,</l>
<l>spreading dark shadows on the corpse of one,</l>
<l>destined to cover twain, take thou our fate</l>
<l>upon thy head; mourn our untimely deaths;</l>
<l>let thy fruit darken for a memory,</l>
<l>an emblem of our blood.” No more she said;</l>
<l>and having fixed the point below her breast,</l>
<l>she fell on the keen sword, still warm with his red blood.</l>

    
<l>But though her death was out of Nature's law</l>
<l>her prayer was answered, for it moved the Gods</l>
<l>and moved their parents. Now the Gods have changed</l>
<l>the ripened fruit which darkens on the branch:</l>
<l>and from the funeral pile their parents sealed</l>
<l>their gathered ashes in a single urn.</l>


Venus et Mars. Leucothoe. Clytie.
MARS AND VENUS

<l>So ended she; at once Leuconoe</l>
<l>took the narrator's thread; and as she spoke</l>
<l>her sisters all were silent.</l>

    
<l>“Even the Sun</l>
<l>that rules the world was captive made of Love.</l>
<l>My theme shall be a love-song of the Sun.</l>
<l>'Tis said the Lord of Day, whose wakeful eye</l>
<l>beholds at once whatever may transpire,</l>
<l>witnessed the loves of Mars and Venus. Grieved</l>
<l>to know the wrong, he called the son of Juno,</l>
<l>Vulcan, and gave full knowledge of the deed,</l>
<l>showing how Mars and Venus shamed his love,</l>
<l>as they defiled his bed. Vulcan amazed,—</l>
<l>the nimble-thoughted Vulcan lost his wits,</l>
<l>so that he dropped the work his right hand held.</l>

    
<l>But turning from all else at once he set</l>
<l>to file out chains of brass, delicate, fine,</l>
<l>from which to fashion nets invisible,</l>
<l>filmy of mesh and airy as the thread</l>
<l>of insect-web, that from the rafter swings.—</l>

    
<l>Implicit woven that they yielded soft</l>
<l>the slightest movement or the gentlest touch,</l>
<l>with cunning skill he drew them round the bed</l>
<l>where they were sure to dally. Presently</l>
<l>appeared the faithless wife, and on the couch</l>
<l>lay down to languish with her paramour.—</l>
<l>Meshed in the chains they could not thence arise,</l>
<l>nor could they else but lie in strict embrace,—</l>
<l>cunningly thus entrapped by Vulcan's wit.—</l>

    
<l>At once the Lemnian cuckold opened wide</l>
<l>the folding ivory doors and called the Gods,—</l>
<l>to witness. There they lay disgraced and bound.</l>
<l>I wot were many of the lighter Gods</l>
<l>who wished themselves in like disgraceful bonds.—</l>
<l>The Gods were moved to laughter: and the tale</l>
<l>was long most noted in the courts of Heaven.</l>

    
<l>The Cytherean Venus brooded on</l>
<l>the Sun's betrayal of her stolen joys,</l>
<l>and thought to torture him in passion's pains,</l>
<l>and wreak requital for the pain he caused.</l>

LEUCOTHEA AND CLYTIE

<l>Son of Hyperion! what avails thy light?</l>
<l>What is the profit of thy glowing heat?</l>
<l>Lo, thou whose flames have parched innumerous lands,</l>
<l>thyself art burning with another flame!</l>
<l>And thou whose orb should joy the universe</l>
<l>art gazing only on Leucothea's charms.</l>

    
<l>Thy glorious eye on one fair maid is fixed,</l>
<l>forgetting all besides. Too early thou</l>
<l>art rising from thy bed of orient skies,</l>
<l>too late thy setting in the western waves;</l>
<l>so taking time to gaze upon thy love,</l>
<l>thy frenzy lengthens out the wintry hour!</l>

    
<l>And often thou art darkened in eclipse,</l>
<l>dark shadows of this trouble in thy mind,</l>
<l>unwonted aspect, casting man perplexed</l>
<l>in abject terror. Pale thou art, though not</l>
<l>betwixt thee and the earth the shadowous moon</l>
<l>bedims thy devious way. Thy passion gives</l>
<l>to grief thy countenance—for her thy heart</l>
<l>alone is grieving—Clymene and Rhodos,</l>
<l>and Persa, mother of deluding Circe,</l>
<l>are all forgotten for thy doting hope;</l>
<l>even Clytie, who is yearning for thy love,</l>
<l>no more can charm thee; thou art so foredone.</l>

    
<l>Leucothea is the cause of many tears,</l>
<l>Leucothea, daughter of Eurynome,</l>
<l>most beauteous matron of Arabia's strand,</l>
<l>where spicey odours blow. Eurynome</l>
<l>in youthful prime excelled her mother's grace,</l>
<l>and, save her daughter, all excelled besides.</l>
<l>Leucothea's father, Orchamas was king</l>
<l>where Achaemenes whilom held the sway;</l>
<l>and Orchamas from ancient Belus' death</l>
<l>might count his reign the seventh in descent.</l>

    
<l>The dark-night pastures of Apollo's steeds</l>
<l>are hid below the western skies; when there,</l>
<l>and spent with toil, in lieu of nibbling herbs</l>
<l>they take ambrosial food: it gives their limbs</l>
<l>restoring strength and nourishes anew.</l>

    
<l>Now while these coursers eat celestial food</l>
<l>and Night resumes his reign, the god appears</l>
<l>disguised, unguessed, as old Eurynome</l>
<l>to fair Leucothea as she draws the threads,</l>
<l>all smoothly twisted from her spindle. There</l>
<l>she sits with twice six hand-maids ranged around,</l>
<l>and as the god beholds her at the door</l>
<l>he kisses her, as if a child beloved</l>
<l>and he her mother. And he spoke to her:</l>

<l>“Let thy twelve hand-maids leave us undisturbed,</l>
<l>for I have things of close import to tell,</l>
<l>and seemly, from a mother to her child.”,</l>
<l>so when they all withdrew the god began,</l>
<l>“Lo, I am he who measures the long year;</l>
<l>I see all things, and through me the wide world</l>
<l>may see all things; I am the glowing eye</l>
<l>of the broad universe! Thou art to me</l>
<l>the glory of the earth!” Filled with alarm,</l>
<l>from her relaxed fingers she let fall</l>
<l>the distaff and the spindle, but, her fear</l>
<l>so lovely in her beauty seemed, the God</l>
<l>no longer brooked delay: he changed his form</l>
<l>back to his wonted beauty and resumed</l>
<l>his bright celestial. Startled at the sight</l>
<l>the maid recoiled a space; but presently</l>
<l>the glory of the god inspired her love;</l>
<l>and all her timid doubts dissolved away;</l>
<l>without complaint she melted in his arms.</l>

    
<l>So ardently the bright Apollo loved,</l>
<l>that Clytie, envious of Leucothea's joy,</l>
<l>where evil none was known, a scandal made;</l>
<l>and having published wide their secret love,</l>
<l>leucothea's father also heard the tale.</l>
<l>Relentlessly and fierce, his cruel hand</l>
<l>buried his living daughter in the ground,</l>
<l>who, while her arms implored the glowing Sun,</l>
<l>complained. “For love of thee my life is lost.”</l>
<l>And as she wailed her father sowed her there.</l>

    
<l>Hyperion's Son began with piercing heat</l>
<l>to scatter the loose sand, a way to open,</l>
<l>that she might look with beauteous features forth</l>
<l>too late! for smothered by the compact earth,</l>
<l>thou canst not lift thy drooping head; alas!</l>
<l>A lifeless corse remains.</l>

    
<l>No sadder sight</l>
<l>since Phaethon was blasted by the bolt,</l>
<l>down-hurled by Jove, had ever grieved the God</l>
<l>who daily drives his winged steeds. In vain</l>
<l>he strives with all the magic of his rays</l>
<l>to warm her limbs anew. — The deed is done—</l>
<l>what vantage gives his might if fate deny?</l>
<l>He sprinkles fragrant nectar on her grave,</l>
<l>and lifeless corse, and as he wails exclaims,</l>
<l>“But naught shall hinder you to reach the skies.”</l>

    
<l>At once the maiden's body, steeped in dews</l>
<l>of nectar, sweet and odourate, dissolves</l>
<l>and adds its fragrant juices to the earth:</l>
<l>slowly from this a sprout of Frankincense</l>
<l>takes root in riched soil, and bursting through</l>
<l>the sandy hillock shows its top.</l>

    
<l>No more</l>
<l>to Clytie comes the author of sweet light,</l>
<l>for though her love might make excuse of grief,</l>
<l>and grief may plead to pardon jealous words,</l>
<l>his heart disdains the schemist of his woe;</l>
<l>and she who turned to sour the sweet of love,</l>
<l>from that unhallowed moment pined away.</l>
<l>Envious and hating all her sister Nymphs,</l>
<l>day after day,—and through the lonely nights,</l>
<l>all unprotected from the chilly breeze,</l>
<l>her hair dishevelled, tangled, unadorned,</l>
<l>she sat unmoved upon the bare hard ground.</l>

    
<l>Nine days the Nymph was nourished by the dews,</l>
<l>or haply by her own tears' bitter brine;—</l>
<l>all other nourishment was naught to her.—</l>
<l>She never raised herself from the bare ground,</l>
<l>though on the god her gaze was ever fixed;—</l>
<l>she turned her features towards him as he moved:</l>
<l>they say that afterwhile her limbs took root</l>
<l>and fastened to the around.</l>

    
<l>A pearly white</l>
<l>overspread her countenance, that turned as pale</l>
<l>and bloodless as the dead; but here and there</l>
<l>a blushing tinge resolved in violet tint;</l>
<l>and something like the blossom of that name</l>
<l>a flower concealed her face. Although a root</l>
<l>now holds her fast to earth, the Heliotrope</l>
<l>turns ever to the Sun, as if to prove</l>
<l>that all may change and love through all remain.</l>


Salmacis.

<l>Thus was the story ended. All were charmed</l>
<l>to hear recounted such mysterious deeds.</l>
<l>While some were doubting whether such were true</l>
<l>others affirmed that to the living Gods</l>
<l>is nothing to restrain their wondrous works,</l>
<l>though surely of the Gods, immortal, none</l>
<l>accorded Bacchus even thought or place.</l>

    
<l>When all had made an end of argument,</l>
<l>they bade Alcithoe take up the word:</l>
<l>she, busily working on the pendent web,</l>
<l>still shot the shuttle through the warp and said;</l>
<l>“The amours of the shepherd Daphnis, known</l>
<l>to many of you, I shall not relate;</l>
<l>the shepherd Daphnis of Mount Ida, who</l>
<l>was turned to stone obdurate, for the Nymph</l>
<l>whose love he slighted—so the rivalry</l>
<l>of love neglected rouses to revenge:</l>
<l>neither shall I relate the story told</l>
<l>of Scython, double-sexed, who first was man,</l>
<l>then altered to a woman: so I pass</l>
<l>the tale of Celmus turned to adamant,</l>
<l>who reared almighty Jove from tender youth:</l>
<l>so, likewise the Curetes whom the rain</l>
<l>brought forth to life: Smilax and Crocus, too,</l>
<l>transpeciated into little flowers:</l>
<l>all these I pass to tell a novel tale,</l>
<l>which haply may resolve in pleasant thoughts.</l>

HERMAPHRODITUS

<l>Learn how the fountain, Salmacis, became</l>
<l>so infamous; learn how it enervates</l>
<l>and softens the limbs of those who chance to bathe.</l>
<l>Although the fountain's properties are known,</l>
<l>the cause is yet unknown. The Naiads nursed</l>
<l>an infant son of Hermes, surely his</l>
<l>of Aphrodite gotten in the caves</l>
<l>of Ida, for the child resembled both</l>
<l>the god and goddess, and his name was theirs.</l>

    
<l>The years passed by, and when the boy had reached</l>
<l>the limit of three lustrums, he forsook</l>
<l>his native mountains; for he loved to roam</l>
<l>through unimagined places, by the banks</l>
<l>of undiscovered rivers; and the joy</l>
<l>of finding wonders made his labour light.</l>

    
<l>Leaving Mount Ida, where his youth was spent,</l>
<l>he reached the land of Lycia, and from thence</l>
<l>the verge of Caria, where a pretty pool</l>
<l>of soft translucent water may be seen,</l>
<l>so clear the glistening bottom glads the eye:</l>
<l>no barren sedge, no fenny reeds annoy,</l>
<l>no rushes with their sharpened arrow-points,</l>
<l>but all around the edges of that pool</l>
<l>the softest grass engirdles with its green.</l>

    
<l>A Nymph dwells there, unsuited to the chase,</l>
<l>unskilled to bend the bow, slothful of foot,</l>
<l>the only Naiad in the world unknown</l>
<l>to rapid-running Dian. Whensoever</l>
<l>her Naiad sisters pled in winged words,</l>
<l>“Take up the javelin, sister Salmacis,</l>
<l>take up the painted quiver and unite</l>
<l>your leisure with the action of the chase;”</l>
<l>she only scorned the javelin and the quiver,</l>
<l>nor joined her leisure to the active chase.</l>

    
<l>Rather she bathes her smooth and shapely limbs;</l>
<l>or combs her tresses with a boxwood comb,</l>
<l>Citorian; or looking in the pool</l>
<l>consults the glassed waters of effects</l>
<l>increasing beauty; or she decks herself</l>
<l>in gauzy raiment, and reposing lolls</l>
<l>on cushioned leaves, or grass-enverdured beds;</l>
<l>or gathers posies from the spangled lawns.</l>
<l>Now, haply as she culled the sweetest flowers</l>
<l>she saw the youth, and longing in her heart</l>
<l>made havoc as her greedy eyes beheld.</l>

    
<l>Although her love could scarcely brook delay,</l>
<l>she waited to enhance her loveliness,</l>
<l>in beauty hoping to allure his love.</l>
<l>All richly dight she scanned herself and robes,</l>
<l>to know that every charm should fair appear,</l>
<l>and she be worthy: wherefore she began:</l>

<l>“O godlike youth! if thou art of the skies,</l>
<l>thou art no other than the god of Love;</l>
<l>if mortal, blest are they who gave thee birth;</l>
<l>happy thy brother; happy, fortunate</l>
<l>thy sister; happy, fortunate and blest</l>
<l>the nurse that gave her bosom; but the joys</l>
<l>surpassing all, dearest and tenderest,</l>
<l>are hers whom thou shalt wed. So, let it be</l>
<l>if thou so young have deigned to marry, let</l>
<l>my joys be stolen; if unmarried, join</l>
<l>with me in wedlock.” So she spoke, and stood</l>
<l>in silence waiting for the youth's reply.</l>

    
<l>He knows nor cares for love—with loveliness</l>
<l>the mounting blushes tinge his youthful cheeks,</l>
<l>as blush-red tint of apples on the tree,</l>
<l>ripe in the summer sun, or as the hue</l>
<l>of painted ivory, or the round moon</l>
<l>red-blushing in her splendour, when the clash</l>
<l>of brass resounds in vain. And long the Nymph</l>
<l>implored; almost clung on his neck, as smooth</l>
<l>and white as ivory; unceasingly</l>
<l>imploring him to kiss her, though as chaste</l>
<l>as kisses to a sister; but the youth</l>
<l>outwearied, thus:</l>

<l>“I do beseech you make</l>
<l>an end of this; or must I fly the place</l>
<l>and leave you to your tears?” Affrighted then</l>
<l>said Salmacis, “To you I freely give—</l>
<l>good stranger here remain.” Although she made</l>
<l>fair presence to retire, she hid herself,</l>
<l>that from a shrub-grown covert, on her knees</l>
<l>she might observe unseen.</l>

    
<l>As any boy</l>
<l>that heedless deems his mischief unobserved,</l>
<l>now here now there, he rambled on the green;</l>
<l>now in the bubbly ripples dipped his feet,</l>
<l>now dallied in the clear pool ankle-deep;—</l>
<l>the warm-cool feeling of the liquid then,</l>
<l>so pleased him, that without delay he doffed</l>
<l>his fleecy garments from his tender limbs.</l>

    
<l>Ah, Salmacis, amazement is thy meed!</l>
<l>Thou art consumed to know his naked grace!</l>
<l>As the hot glitters of the round bright sun</l>
<l>collected, sparkle from the polished plate,</l>
<l>thine eyes are glistened with delirious fires.</l>

    
<l>Delay she cannot; panting for his joy,</l>
<l>languid for his caressing, crazed, distract,</l>
<l>her passion difficult is held in check.—</l>

    
<l>He claps his body with his hollow palms</l>
<l>and lightly vaults into the limped wave,</l>
<l>and darting through the water hand over hand</l>
<l>shines in the liquid element, as though</l>
<l>should one enhance a statue's ivorine,</l>
<l>or glaze the lily in a lake of glass.</l>

    
<l>And thus the Naiad, “I have gained my suit;</l>
<l>his love is mine,—is mine!” Quickly disrobed,</l>
<l>she plunged into the yielding wave—seized him,</l>
<l>caressed him, clung to him a thousand ways,</l>
<l>kissed him, thrust down her hands and touched his breast:</l>
<l>reluctant and resisting he endeavours</l>
<l>to make escape, but even as he struggles</l>
<l>she winds herself about him, as entwines</l>
<l>the serpent which the royal bird on high</l>
<l>holds in his talons; —as it hangs, it coils</l>
<l>in sinuous folds around the eagle's feet;—</l>
<l>twisting its coils around his head and wings:</l>
<l>or as the ivy clings to sturdy oaks;</l>
<l>or as the polypus beneath the waves,</l>
<l>by pulling down, with suckers on all sides,</l>
<l>tenacious holds its prey. And yet the youth,</l>
<l>descendant of great Atlas, not relents</l>
<l>nor gives the Naiad joy. Pressing her suit</l>
<l>she winds her limbs around him and exclaims,</l>
<l>“You shall not scape me, struggle as you will,</l>
<l>perverse and obstinate! Hear me, ye Gods!</l>
<l>Let never time release the youth from me;</l>
<l>time never let me from the youth release!”</l>


    
<l>Propitious deities accord her prayers:</l>
<l>the mingled bodies of the pair unite</l>
<l>and fashion in a single human form.</l>
<l>So one might see two branches underneath</l>
<l>a single rind uniting grow as one:</l>
<l>so, these two bodies in a firm embrace</l>
<l>no more are twain, but with a two-fold form</l>
<l>nor man nor woman may be called—Though both</l>
<l>in seeming they are neither one of twain.</l>

    
<l>When that Hermaphroditus felt the change,</l>
<l>so wrought upon him by the languid fount,</l>
<l>considered that he entered it a man,</l>
<l>and now his limbs relaxing in the stream</l>
<l>he is not wholly male, but only half,—</l>
<l>he lifted up his hands and thus implored,</l>
<l>albeit with no manly voice; “Hear me</l>
<l>O father! hear me mother! grant to me</l>
<l>this boon; to me whose name is yours, your son;</l>
<l>whoso shall enter in this fount a man</l>
<l>must leave its waters only half a man.”</l>
<l>Moved by the words of their bi-natured son</l>
<l>both parents yield assent: they taint the fount</l>
<l>with essences of dual-working powers.</l>

    
<l>Now though the daughters of King Minyas</l>
<l>have made an end of telling tales, they make</l>
<l>no end of labour; for they so despise</l>
<l>the deity, and desecrate his feast.</l>

    
<l>While busily engaged, with sudden beat</l>
<l>they hear resounding tambourines; and pipes</l>
<l>and crooked horns and tinkling brass renew,</l>
<l>unseen, the note; saffron and myrrh dissolve</l>
<l>in dulcet odours; and, beyond belief,</l>
<l>the woven webs, dependent on the loom,</l>
<l>take tints of green, put forth new ivy leaves,</l>
<l>or change to grape-vines verdant. There the thread</l>
<l>is twisted into tendrils, there the warp</l>
<l>is fashioned into many-moving leaves—</l>
<l>the purple lends its splendour to the grape.</l>

    
<l>And now the day is past; it is the hour</l>
<l>when night ambiguous merges into day,</l>
<l>which dubious owns nor light nor dun obscure;</l>
<l>and suddenly the house begins to shake,</l>
<l>and torches oil-dipped seem to flare around,</l>
<l>and fires a-glow to shine in every room,</l>
<l>and phantoms, feigned of savage beasts, to howl.—</l>

    
<l>Full of affright amid the smoking halls</l>
<l>the sisters vainly hide, and wheresoever</l>
<l>they deem security from flaming fires,</l>
<l>fearfully flit. And while they seek to hide,</l>
<l>a membrane stretches over every limb,</l>
<l>and light wings open from their slender arms.</l>

    
<l>In the weird darkness they are unaware</l>
<l>what measure wrought to change their wonted shape.</l>
<l>No plumous vans avail to lift their flight,</l>
<l>yet fair they balance on membraneous wing.</l>
<l>Whenever they would speak a tiny voice,</l>
<l>diminutive, apportioned to their size,</l>
<l>in squeaking note complains. Adread the light,</l>
<l>their haunts avoid by day the leafy woods,</l>
<l>for sombre attics, where secure they rest</l>
<l>till forth the dun obscure their wings may stretch</l>
<l>at hour of Vesper;—this accords their name.</l>


Athamas et Ino.
ATHAMAS AND INO

<l>Throughout the land of Thebes miraculous</l>
<l>the power of Bacchus waxed; and far and wide</l>
<l>Ino, his aunt, reported the great deeds</l>
<l>by this divinity performed. Of all</l>
<l>her sisters only she escaped unharmed,</l>
<l>when Fate destroyed them, and she knew not grief—</l>
<l>only for sorrow of her sisters' woes.—</l>

    
<l>While Ino vaunted of her mother-joys,</l>
<l>and of her kingly husband, Athamas,</l>
<l>and of the mighty God, her foster-child;</l>
<l>Juno, disdaining her in secret, said;</l>
<l>“How shall the offspring of a concubine</l>
<l>transform Maeonian mariners, overwhelm</l>
<l>them in the ocean, sacrifice a son</l>
<l>to his deluded mother, who insane,</l>
<l>tears out his entrails; how shall he invent</l>
<l>wings for three daughters of King Minyas,</l>
<l>while Juno unavenged, bewails despite?—</l>
<l>Is it the end? the utmost of my power?</l>
<l>His deeds instruct the way; true wisdom heeds</l>
<l>an enemy's device; by the strange death</l>
<l>of Pentheus, all that madness could perform</l>
<l>was well revealed to all; what then denies</l>
<l>a frenzy may unravel Ino's course</l>
<l>to such a fate as wrought her sisters' woe?”</l>

    
<l>A shelving path in shadows of sad yew</l>
<l>through utter silence to the deep descends,</l>
<l>infernal, where the languid Styx exhales</l>
<l>vapours; and there the shadows of the dead,</l>
<l>descend, after they leave their sacred urns,</l>
<l>and ghostly forms invade: and far and wide,</l>
<l>those dreary regions Horror and bleak Cold</l>
<l>obtain.</l>

    
<l>The ghosts, arrived, not know the way,—</l>
<l>which leadeth to the Stygian city-gates,—</l>
<l>not know the melancholy palace where</l>
<l>the swarthy Pluto stays, though streets and ways</l>
<l>a thousand to that city lead, and gates</l>
<l>out-swing from every side: and as the sea</l>
<l>with never-seen increase engulfs the streams</l>
<l>unnumbered of the world, that realm enfolds</l>
<l>the souls of men, nor ever is it filled.</l>

    
<l>Around the shadowy spirits go; bloodless</l>
<l>boneless and bodiless; they throng the place</l>
<l>of judgment, or they haunt the mansion where</l>
<l>abides the Utmost Tyrant, or they tend</l>
<l>to various callings, as their whilom way; —</l>
<l>appropriate punishment confines to pain</l>
<l>the multitude condemned.</l>

    
<l>To this abode,</l>
<l>impelled by rage and hate, from habitation</l>
<l>celestial, Juno, of Saturn born, descends,</l>
<l>submissive to its dreadful element.</l>

    
<l>No sooner had she entered the sad gates,</l>
<l>than groans were uttered by the threshold, pressed</l>
<l>by her immortal form, and Cerberus</l>
<l>upraising his three-visaged mouths gave vent</l>
<l>to triple-barking howls.—She called to her</l>
<l>the sisters, Night-begot, implacable,</l>
<l>terrific Furies. They did sit before</l>
<l>the prison portals, adamant confined,</l>
<l>combing black vipers from their horrid hair.</l>

    
<l>When her amid the night-surrounding shades</l>
<l>they recognized, those Deities uprose.</l>
<l>O dread confines! dark seat of wretched vice!</l>
<l>Where stretched athwart nine acres, Tityus,</l>
<l>must thou endure thine entrails to be torn!</l>
<l>O Tantalus, thou canst not touch the wave,</l>
<l>and from thy clutch the hanging branches rise!</l>
<l>O Sisyphus, thou canst not stay the stone,</l>
<l>catching or pushing, it must fall again!</l>
<l>O thou Ixion! whirled around, around,</l>
<l>thyself must follow to escape thyself!</l>
<l>And, O Belides, (plotter of sad death</l>
<l>upon thy cousins) thou art always doomed</l>
<l>to dip forever ever-spilling waves!</l>

    
<l>When that the daughter of Saturnus fixed</l>
<l>a stern look on those wretches, first her glance</l>
<l>arrested on Ixion; but the next</l>
<l>on Sisyphus; and thus the goddess spoke;—</l>

<l>“For why should he alone of all his kin</l>
<l>suffer eternal doom, while Athamas,</l>
<l>luxurious in a sumptuous palace reigns;</l>
<l>and, haughty with his wife, despises me.”</l>
<l>So grieved she, and expressed the rage of hate</l>
<l>that such descent inspired, beseeching thus,</l>
<l>no longer should the House of Cadmus stand,</l>
<l>so that the sister Furies plunge in crime</l>
<l>overweening Athamas.—Entreating them,</l>
<l>she mingled promises with her commands.—</l>

    
<l>When Juno ended speech, Tisiphone,</l>
<l>whose locks entangled are not ever smooth,</l>
<l>tossed them around, that backward from her face</l>
<l>such crawling snakes were thrown;—then answered she:</l>
<l>“Since what thy will decrees may well be done,</l>
<l>why need we to consult with many words?</l>
<l>Leave thou this hateful region and convey</l>
<l>thyself, contented, to a better realm.”</l>

    
<l>Rejoicing Juno hastens to the clouds—</l>
<l>before she enters her celestial home,</l>
<l>Iris, the child of Thaumas, purifies</l>
<l>her limbs in sprinkled water.</l>


    
<l>Waiting not,</l>
<l>Tisiphone, revengeful, takes a torch;—</l>
<l>besmeared with blood, and vested in a robe,</l>
<l>dripping with crimson gore, and twisting-snakes</l>
<l>engirdled, she departs her dire abode—</l>
<l>with twitching Madness, Terror, Fear and Woe:</l>
<l>and when she had arrived the destined house,</l>
<l>the door-posts shrank from her, the maple doors</l>
<l>turned ashen grey: the Sun amazed fled.</l>

    
<l>Affrighted, Athamas and Ino viewed</l>
<l>and fled these prodigies; but suddenly</l>
<l>that baneful Fury stood across the way,</l>
<l>blocking the passage— There she stands with arms</l>
<l>extended, and alive with twisting vipers.—</l>
<l>She shakes her hair; the moving serpents hiss;</l>
<l>they cling upon her shoulders, and they glide</l>
<l>around her temples, dart their fangs, and vomit</l>
<l>corruption.—Plucking from the midst two snakes,</l>
<l>she hurls them with her pestilential hand</l>
<l>upon her victims, Athamas and Ino, whom,</l>
<l>although the vipers strike upon their breasts,</l>
<l>no injury attacks their mortal parts;—</l>
<l>only their minds are stricken with wild rage,</l>
<l>inciting to mad violence and crime.</l>

    
<l>And with a monstrous composite of foam—</l>
<l>once gathered from the mouth of Cerberus,</l>
<l>the venom of Echidna, purposeless</l>
<l>aberrances, crimes, tears, hatred—the lust</l>
<l>of homicide, and the dark vapourings</l>
<l>of foolish brains; a liquid poison, mixed,</l>
<l>and mingled with fresh blood, in hollow brass,</l>
<l>and boiled, and stirred up with a slip of hemlock—</l>
<l>she took of it, and as they trembled, threw</l>
<l>that mad-mixed poison on them; and it scorched</l>
<l>their inmost vitals—and she waved her torch</l>
<l>repeatedly, within a circle's rim—</l>
<l>and added flame to flame.—</l>

    
<l>Then, confident</l>
<l>of having executed her commands,</l>
<l>the Fury hastened to the void expanse</l>
<l>where Pluto reigns, and swiftly put aside</l>
<l>the serpents that were wreathed around her robes.</l>

    
<l>At once, the son of Aeolus, enraged,</l>
<l>shouts loudly in his palace; “Ho, my lads!</l>
<l>Spread out your nets! a savage lioness</l>
<l>and her twin whelps are lurking in the wood;—</l>
<l>behold them!” In his madness he believes</l>
<l>his wife a savage beast. He follows her,</l>
<l>and quickly from her bosom snatches up</l>
<l>her smiling babe, Learchus, holding forth</l>
<l>his tiny arms, and whirls him in the air,</l>
<l>times twice and thrice, as whirls the whizzing sling,</l>
<l>and dashes him in pieces on the rocks; —</l>
<l>cracking his infant bones.</l>

    
<l>The mother, roused</l>
<l>to frenzy (who can tell if grief the cause,</l>
<l>or fires of scattered poison?) yells aloud,</l>
<l>and with her torn hair tangled, running mad,</l>
<l>she carries swiftly in her clutching arms,</l>
<l>her little Melicerta! and begins</l>
<l>to shout, “Evoe, Bacche!”—Juno hears</l>
<l>the shouted name of Bacchus, and she laughs,</l>
<l>and taunts her;—“Let thy foster-child award!”</l>

    
<l>There is a crag, out-jutting on the deep,</l>
<l>worn hollow at the base by many waves,</l>
<l>where not the rain may ripple on that pool;—</l>
<l>high up the rugged summit overhangs</l>
<l>its ragged brows above the open sea:</l>
<l>there, Ino climbs with frenzy-given strength,</l>
<l>and fearless, with her burden in her arms,</l>
<l>leaps in the waves where whitening foams arise.</l>

    
<l>Venus takes pity on her guiltless child,</l>
<l>unfortunate grand-daughter, and begins</l>
<l>to soothe her uncle Neptune with these words;—</l>

<l>“O Neptune, ruler of the deep, to whom,</l>
<l>next to the Power in Heaven, was given sway,</l>
<l>consider my request! Open thy heart</l>
<l>to my descendants, which thine eyes behold,</l>
<l>tossed on the wild Ionian Sea! I do implore thee,</l>
<l>remember they are thy true Deities—</l>
<l>are thine as well as mine—for it is known</l>
<l>my birth was from the white foam of thy sea;—</l>
<l>a truth made certain by my Grecian name.”</l>

    
<l>Neptune regards her prayer: he takes from them</l>
<l>their mortal dross: he clothes in majesty,</l>
<l>and hallows their appearance. Even their names</l>
<l>and forms are altered; Melicerta, changed,</l>
<l>is now Palaemon called, and Ino, changed,</l>
<l>Leucothoe called, are known as Deities.</l>

    
<l>When her Sidonian attendants traced</l>
<l>fresh footprints to the last verge of the rock,</l>
<l>and found no further vestige, they declared</l>
<l>her dead, nor had they any doubt of it.</l>
<l>They tore their garments and their hair—and wailed</l>
<l>the House of Cadmus— and they cursed at Juno,</l>
<l>for the sad fate of the wretched concubine.</l>

    
<l>That goddess could no longer brook their words,</l>
<l>and thus made answer, “I will make of you</l>
<l>eternal monuments of my revenge!”</l>

    
<l>Her words were instantly confirmed—The one</l>
<l>whose love for Ino was the greatest, cried;</l>
<l>“Into the deep; look—look—I seek my queen.”</l>
<l>But even as she tried to leap, she stood</l>
<l>fast-rooted to the ever-living rock;</l>
<l>another, as she tried to beat her breast</l>
<l>with blows repeated, noticed that her arms</l>
<l>grew stiff and hard; another, as by chance,</l>
<l>was petrified with hands stretched over the waves:</l>
<l>another could be seen, as suddenly</l>
<l>her fingers hardened, clutching at her hair</l>
<l>to tear it from the roots.—And each remained</l>
<l>forever in the posture first assumed.—</l>
<l>But others of those women, sprung from Cadmus,</l>
<l>were changed to birds, that always with wide wings</l>
<l>skim lightly the dark surface of that sea.</l>


Cadmus et Harmonia.
CADMUS AND HARMONIA

<l>Unwitting that his daughter and his son</l>
<l>are Ocean deities, Agenor's son,—</l>
<l>depressed by sorrow and unnumbered woes,</l>
<l>calamities, and prodigies untold,—</l>
<l>the founder fled the city he had built,</l>
<l>as though fatalities that gathered round</l>
<l>that city grieved him deeper than the fate</l>
<l>of his own family; and thence, at last</l>
<l>arrived the confines of Illyria;</l>
<l>in exile with his wife.—</l>

    
<l>Weighted with woe,</l>
<l>bowed down with years, their minds recalled the time</l>
<l>when first disaster fell upon their House:—</l>
<l>relating their misfortunes, Cadmus spoke;</l>
<l>“Was that a sacred dragon that my spear</l>
<l>impaled, when on the way from Sidon's gates</l>
<l>I planted in the earth those dragon-teeth,</l>
<l>unthought-of seed? If haply 'tis the Gods,</l>
<l>(whose rage unerring, gives me to revenge)</l>
<l>I only pray that I may lengthen out,</l>
<l>as any serpent.” Even as he spoke,</l>
<l>he saw and felt himself increase in length.</l>
<l>His body coiled into a serpent's form;</l>
<l>bright scale's enveloped his indurate skin,</l>
<l>and azure macules in speckled pride,</l>
<l>enriched his glowing folds; and as he fell</l>
<l>supinely on his breast, his legs were joined,</l>
<l>and gradually tapered as a serpent's tail.—</l>

    
<l>Some time his arms remained, which stretching forth</l>
<l>while tears rolled down his human face, not changed</l>
<l>as yet, he said; “Hither, O hapless one!</l>
<l>Come hither my unhappy wife, while aught</l>
<l>is left of manhood; touch me, take my hand,</l>
<l>unchanged as yet—ah, soon this serpent-form</l>
<l>will cover me!”</l>

    
<l>So did he speak, nor thought</l>
<l>to make an end; but suddenly his tongue</l>
<l>became twin-forked. As often as he tried,</l>
<l>a hissing sound escaped; the only voice</l>
<l>that Nature left him. —</l>

    
<l>And his wife bewailed,</l>
<l>and smote her breast, “Ah, Cadmus, ah!</l>
<l>Most helpless one, put off that monster-shape!</l>
<l>Your feet, your shoulders and your hands are gone;</l>
<l>your manly form, your very colour gone; all—all</l>
<l>is changed!—Oh, why not, ye celestial Gods,</l>
<l>me likewise, to a serpent-shape transform!”—</l>

    
<l>So ended her complaint. Cadmus caressed</l>
<l>her gently with his tongue; and slid to her</l>
<l>dear bosom, just as if he knew his wife;</l>
<l>and he embraced her, and he touched her neck.</l>

    
<l>All their attendants, who had seen the change,</l>
<l>were filled with fear; but when as crested snakes</l>
<l>the twain appeared in brightly glistening mail,</l>
<l>their grief was lightened: and the pair, enwreathed</l>
<l>in twisting coils, departed from that place,</l>
<l>and sought a covert in the nearest grove.—</l>
<l>There, then, these gentle serpents never shun</l>
<l>mankind, nor wound, nor strike with poisoned fangs;</l>
<l>for they are always conscious of the past.</l>


Perseus. Atlas. Andromeda.
PERSEUS AND ATLAS

<l>The fortune of their grandson, Bacchus, gave</l>
<l>great comfort to them—as a god adored</l>
<l>in conquered India; by Achaia praised</l>
<l>in stately temples. — But Acrisius</l>
<l>the son of Abas, of the Cadmean race,</l>
<l>remained to banish Bacchus from the walls</l>
<l>of Argos, and to lift up hostile arms</l>
<l>against that deity, who he denied</l>
<l>was born to Jove. He would not even grant</l>
<l>that Perseus from the loins of Jupiter</l>
<l>was got of Danae in the showering gold.</l>

    
<l>So mighty is the hidden power of truth,</l>
<l>Acrisius soon lamented that affront</l>
<l>to Bacchus, and that ever he refused</l>
<l>to own his grandson; for the one achieved</l>
<l>high heaven, and the other, (as he bore</l>
<l>the viperous monster-head) on sounding wings</l>
<l>hovered a conqueror in the fluent air,</l>
<l>over sands, Libyan, where the Gorgon-head</l>
<l>dropped clots of gore, that, quickening on the ground,</l>
<l>became unnumbered serpents; fitting cause</l>
<l>to curse with vipers that infested land.</l>

    
<l>Thence wafted by the never-constant winds</l>
<l>through boundless latitudes, now here now there,</l>
<l>as flits a vapour-cloud in dizzy flight,</l>
<l>down-looking from the lofty skies on earth,</l>
<l>removed far, so compassed he the world.</l>

    
<l>Three times did he behold the frozen Bears,</l>
<l>times thrice his gaze was on the Crab's bent arms.</l>
<l>Now shifting to the west, now to the east,</l>
<l>how often changed his course? Time came, when day</l>
<l>declining, he began to fear the night,</l>
<l>by which he stopped his flight far in the west—</l>
<l>the realm of Atlas—where he sought repose</l>
<l>till Lucifer might call Aurora's fires;</l>
<l>Aurora chariot of the Day.</l>

    
<l>There dwelt</l>
<l>huge Atlas, vaster than the race of man:</l>
<l>son of Iapetus, his lordly sway</l>
<l>extended over those extreme domains,</l>
<l>and over oceans that command their waves</l>
<l>to take the panting coursers of the Sun,</l>
<l>and bathe the wearied Chariot of the Day.</l>

    
<l>For him a thousand flocks, a thousand herds</l>
<l>overwandered pasture fields; and neighbour tribes</l>
<l>might none disturb that land. Aglint with gold</l>
<l>bright leaves adorn the trees,—boughs golden-wrought</l>
<l>bear apples of pure gold. And Perseus spoke</l>
<l>to Atlas, “O my friend, if thou art moved</l>
<l>to hear the story of a noble race,</l>
<l>the author of my life is Jupiter;</l>
<l>if valiant deeds perhaps are thy delight</l>
<l>mine may deserve thy praise.—Behold of thee</l>
<l>kind treatment I implore—a place of rest.”</l>

    
<l>But Atlas, mindful of an oracle</l>
<l>since by Themis, the Parnassian, told,</l>
<l>recalled these words, “O Atlas! mark the day</l>
<l>a son of Jupiter shall come to spoil;</l>
<l>for when thy trees been stripped of golden fruit,</l>
<l>the glory shall be his.”</l>

    
<l>Fearful of this,</l>
<l>Atlas had built solid walls around</l>
<l>his orchard, and secured a dragon, huge,</l>
<l>that kept perpetual guard, and thence expelled</l>
<l>all strangers from his land. Wherefore he said,</l>
<l>“Begone! The glory of your deeds is all</l>
<l>pretense; even Jupiter, will fail your need.”</l>

    
<l>With that he added force and strove to drive</l>
<l>the hesitating Alien from his doors;</l>
<l>who pled reprieve or threatened with bold words.</l>
<l>Although he dared not rival Atlas' might,</l>
<l>Perseus made this reply; “For that my love</l>
<l>you hold in light esteem, let this be yours.”</l>
<l>He said no more, but turning his own face,</l>
<l>he showed upon his left Medusa's head,</l>
<l>abhorrent features.—Atlas, huge and vast,</l>
<l>becomes a mountain—His great beard and hair</l>
<l>are forests, and his shoulders and his hands</l>
<l>mountainous ridges, and his head the top</l>
<l>of a high peak;—his bones are changed to rocks.</l>

    
<l>Augmented on all sides, enormous height</l>
<l>attains his growth; for so ordained it, ye,</l>
<l>O mighty Gods! who now the heavens' expanse</l>
<l>unnumbered stars, on him command to rest.</l>

PERSEUS AND ANDROMEDA

<l>In their eternal prison, Aeous,</l>
<l>grandson of Hippotas, had shut the winds;</l>
<l>and Lucifer, reminder of our toil,</l>
<l>in splendour rose upon the lofty sky:</l>
<l>and Perseus bound his wings upon his feet,</l>
<l>on each foot bound he them; his sword he girt</l>
<l>and sped wing-footed through the liquid air.</l>

    
<l>Innumerous kingdoms far behind were left,</l>
<l>till peoples Ethiopic and the lands</l>
<l>of Cepheus were beneath his lofty view.</l>

    
<l>There Ammon, the Unjust, had made decree</l>
<l>Andromeda, the Innocent, should grieve</l>
<l>her mother's tongue. They bound her fettered arms</l>
<l>fast to the rock. When Perseus her beheld</l>
<l>as marble he would deem her, but the breeze</l>
<l>moved in her hair, and from her streaming eyes</l>
<l>the warm tears fell. Her beauty so amazed</l>
<l>his heart, unconscious captive of her charms,</l>
<l>that almost his swift wings forgot to wave.—</l>

    
<l>Alighted on the ground, he thus began;</l>
<l>“O fairest! whom these chains become not so,</l>
<l>but worthy are for links that lovers bind,</l>
<l>make known to me your country's name and your's</l>
<l>and wherefore bound in chains.” A moment then,</l>
<l>as overcome with shame, she made no sound:</l>
<l>were not she fettered she would surely hide</l>
<l>her blushing head; but what she could perform</l>
<l>that did she do—she filled her eyes with tears.</l>

    
<l>So pleaded he that lest refusal seem</l>
<l>implied confession of a crime, she told</l>
<l>her name, her country's name, and how her charms</l>
<l>had been her mother's pride. But as she spoke</l>
<l>the mighty ocean roared. Over the waves</l>
<l>a monster fast approached, its head held high,</l>
<l>abreast the wide expanse.—The virgin shrieked;—</l>
<l>no aid her wretched father gave, nor aid</l>
<l>her still more wretched mother; but they wept</l>
<l>and mingled lamentations with their tears—</l>
<l>clinging distracted to her fettered form.</l>

    
<l>And thus the stranger spoke to them, “Time waits</l>
<l>for tears, but flies the moment of our need:</l>
<l>were I, who am the son of Regal Jove</l>
<l>and her whom he embraced in showers of gold,</l>
<l>leaving her pregnant in her brazen cell, —</l>
<l>I, Perseus, who destroyed the Gorgon, wreathed</l>
<l>with snake-hair, I, who dared on waving wings</l>
<l>to cleave etherial air—were I to ask</l>
<l>the maid in marriage, I should be preferred</l>
<l>above all others as your son-in-law.</l>
<l>Not satisfied with deeds achieved, I strive</l>
<l>to add such merit as the Gods permit;</l>
<l>now, therefore, should my velour save her life,</l>
<l>be it conditioned that I win her love.”</l>

    
<l>To this her parents gave a glad assent,</l>
<l>for who could hesitate? And they entreat,</l>
<l>and promise him the kingdom as a dower.</l>


    
<l>As a great ship with steady prow speeds on;</l>
<l>forced forwards by the sweating arms of youth</l>
<l>it plows the deep; so, breasting the great waves,</l>
<l>the monster moved, until to reach the rock</l>
<l>no further space remained than might the whirl</l>
<l>of Balearic string encompass, through</l>
<l>the middle skies, with plummet-mold of lead.</l>

    
<l>That instant, spurning with his feet the ground,</l>
<l>the youth rose upwards to a cloudy height;</l>
<l>and when the shadow of the hero marked</l>
<l>the surface of the sea, the monster sought</l>
<l>vainly to vent his fury on the shade.</l>

    
<l>As the swift bird of Jove, when he beholds</l>
<l>a basking serpent in an open field,</l>
<l>exposing to the sun its mottled back,</l>
<l>and seizes on its tail; lest it shall turn</l>
<l>to strike with venomed fang, he fixes fast</l>
<l>his grasping talons in the scaly neck;</l>
<l>so did the winged youth, in rapid flight</l>
<l>through yielding elements, press down</l>
<l>on the great monster's back, and thrust his sword,</l>
<l>sheer to the hilt, in its right shoulder—loud</l>
<l>its frightful torture sounded over the waves.—</l>
<l>So fought the hero-son of Inachus.</l>

    
<l>Wild with the grievous wound, the monster rears</l>
<l>high in the air, or plunges in the waves;—</l>
<l>or wheels around as turns the frightened boar</l>
<l>shunning the hounds around him in full cry.</l>

    
<l>The hero on his active wings avoids</l>
<l>the monster's jaws, and with his crooked sword</l>
<l>tortures its back wherever he may pierce</l>
<l>its mail of hollow shell, or strikes betwixt</l>
<l>the ribs each side, or wounds its lashing tail,</l>
<l>long, tapered as a fish.</l>

    
<l>The monster spouts</l>
<l>forth streams—incarnadined with blood—</l>
<l>that spray upon the hero's wings; who drenched,</l>
<l>and heavy with the spume, no longer dares</l>
<l>to trust existence to his dripping wings;</l>
<l>but he discerns a rock, which rises clear</l>
<l>above the water when the sea is calm,</l>
<l>but now is covered by the lashing waves.</l>
<l>On this he rests; and as his left hand holds</l>
<l>firm on the upmost ledge, he thrusts his sword,</l>
<l>times more than three, unswerving in his aim,</l>
<l>sheer through the monster's entrails.—Shouts of praise</l>
<l>resound along the shores, and even the Gods</l>
<l>may hear his glory in their high abodes.</l>

    
<l>Her parents, Cepheus and Cassiope,</l>
<l>most joyfully salute their son-in-law;</l>
<l>declaring him the saviour of their house.</l>
<l>And now, her chains struck off, the lovely cause</l>
<l>and guerdon of his toil, walks on the shore.</l>

    
<l>The hero washes his victorious hands</l>
<l>in water newly taken from the sea:</l>
<l>but lest the sand upon the shore might harm</l>
<l>the viper-covered head, he first prepared</l>
<l>a bed of springy leaves, on which he threw</l>
<l>weeds of the sea, produced beneath the waves.</l>
<l>On them he laid Medusa's awful face,</l>
<l>daughter of Phorcys;—and the living weeds,</l>
<l>fresh taken from the boundless deep, imbibed</l>
<l>the monster's poison in their spongy pith:</l>
<l>they hardened at the touch, and felt in branch</l>
<l>and leaf unwonted stiffness. Sea-Nymphs, too,</l>
<l>attempted to perform that prodigy</l>
<l>on numerous other weeds, with like result:</l>
<l>so pleased at their success, they raised new seeds,</l>
<l>from plants wide-scattered on the salt expanse.</l>

    
<l>Even from that day the coral has retained</l>
<l>such wondrous nature, that exposed to air</l>
<l>it hardens.—Thus, a plant beneath the waves</l>
<l>becomes a stone when taken from the sea.</l>

    
<l>Three altars to three Gods he made of turf.</l>
<l>To thee, victorious Virgin, did he build</l>
<l>an altar on the right, to Mercury</l>
<l>an altar on the left, and unto Jove</l>
<l>an altar in the midst. He sacrificed</l>
<l>a heifer to Minerva, and a calf</l>
<l>to Mercury, the Wingfoot, and a bull</l>
<l>to thee, O greatest of the Deities.</l>

    
<l>Without a dower he takes Andromeda,</l>
<l>the guerdon of his glorious victory,</l>
<l>nor hesitates.—Now pacing in the van,</l>
<l>both Love and Hymen wave the flaring torch,</l>
<l>abundant perfumes lavished in the flames.</l>

    
<l>The houses are bedecked with wreathed flowers;</l>
<l>and lyres and flageolets resound, and songs—</l>
<l>felicit notes that happy hearts declare.</l>
<l>The portals opened, sumptuous halls display</l>
<l>their golden splendours, and the noble lords</l>
<l>of Cepheus' court take places at the feast,</l>
<l>magnificently served.</l>

    
<l>After the feast,</l>
<l>when every heart was warming to the joys of genial Bacchus,</l>
<l>then, Lyncidian Perseus asked about the land and its ways</l>
<l>about the customs and the character of its heroes.</l>
<l>Straightway one of the dinner-companions made reply,</l>
<l>and asked in turn, “ Now, valiant Perseus, pray</l>
<l>tell the story of the deed, that all may know,</l>
<l>and what the arts and power prevailed, when you</l>
<l>struck off the serpent-covered head.”</l>

    
<l>“There is,”</l>
<l>continued Perseus of the house of Agenor,</l>
<l>“There is a spot beneath cold Atlas, where</l>
<l>in bulwarks of enormous strength, to guard</l>
<l>its rocky entrance, dwelt two sisters, born</l>
<l>of Phorcys. These were wont to share in turn</l>
<l>a single eye between them: this by craft</l>
<l>I got possession of, when one essayed</l>
<l>to hand it to the other.—I put forth</l>
<l>my hand and took it as it passed between:</l>
<l>then, far, remote, through rocky pathless crags,</l>
<l>over wild hills that bristled with great woods,</l>
<l>I thence arrived to where the Gorgon dwelt.</l>

    
<l>“Along the way, in fields and by the roads,</l>
<l>I saw on all sides men and animals—</l>
<l>like statues—turned to flinty stone at sight</l>
<l>of dread Medusa's visage. Nevertheless</l>
<l>reflected on the brazen shield, I bore</l>
<l>upon my left, I saw her horrid face.</l>

    
<l>“When she was helpless in the power of sleep</l>
<l>and even her serpent-hair was slumber-bound,</l>
<l>I struck, and took her head sheer from the neck.—</l>
<l>To winged Pegasus the blood gave birth,</l>
<l>his brother also, twins of rapid wing.”</l>

    
<l>So did he speak, and truly told besides</l>
<l>the perils of his journey, arduous</l>
<l>and long—He told of seas and lands that far</l>
<l>beneath him he had seen, and of the stars</l>
<l>that he had touched while on his waving wings.</l>

    
<l>And yet, before they were aware, the tale</l>
<l>was ended; he was silent. Then rejoined</l>
<l>a noble with enquiry why alone</l>
<l>of those three sisters, snakes were interspersed</l>
<l>in dread Medusa's locks. And he replied:—</l>

<l>“Because, O Stranger, it is your desire</l>
<l>to learn what worthy is for me to tell,</l>
<l>hear ye the cause: Beyond all others she</l>
<l>was famed for beauty, and the envious hope</l>
<l>of many suitors. Words would fail to tell</l>
<l>the glory of her hair, most wonderful</l>
<l>of all her charms—A friend declared to me</l>
<l>he saw its lovely splendour. Fame declares</l>
<l>the Sovereign of the Sea attained her love</l>
<l>in chaste Minerva's temple. While enraged</l>
<l>she turned her head away and held her shield</l>
<l>before her eyes. To punish that great crime</l>
<l>minerva changed the Gorgon's splendid hair</l>
<l>to serpents horrible. And now to strike</l>
<l>her foes with fear, she wears upon her breast</l>
<l>those awful vipers—creatures of her rage.</l>
