<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 11

Orphei mors.
DEATH OF ORPHEUS

<l>While with his songs, Orpheus, the bard of Thrace,</l>
<l>allured the trees, the savage animals,</l>
<l>and even the insensate rocks, to follow him;</l>
<l>Ciconian matrons, with their raving breasts</l>
<l>concealed in skins of forest animals,</l>
<l>from the summit of a hill observed him there,</l>
<l>attuning love songs to a sounding harp.</l>
<l>One of those women, as her tangled hair</l>
<l>was tossed upon the light breeze shouted, “See!</l>
<l>Here is the poet who has scorned our love!”</l>
<l>Then hurled her spear at the melodious mouth</l>
<l>of great Apollo's bard: but the spear's point,</l>
<l>trailing in flight a garland of fresh leaves,</l>
<l>made but a harmless bruise and wounded not.</l>

    
<l>The weapon of another was a stone,</l>
<l>which in the very air was overpowered</l>
<l>by the true harmony of his voice and lyre,</l>
<l>and so disabled lay before his feet,</l>
<l>as asking pardon for that vain attempt.</l>

    
<l>The madness of such warfare then increased.</l>
<l>All moderation is entirely lost, </l>
<l>and a wild Fury overcomes the right.—</l>
<l>although their weapons would have lost all force,</l>
<l>subjected to the power of Orpheus' harp,</l>
<l>the clamorous discord of their boxwood pipes,</l>
<l>the blaring of their horns, their tambourines</l>
<l>and clapping hands and Bacchanalian yells,</l>
<l>with hideous discords drowned his voice and harp.—</l>
<l>at last the stones that heard his song no more</l>
<l>fell crimson with the Thracian poet's blood.</l>

    
<l>Before his life was taken, the maenads turned</l>
<l>their threatening hands upon the many birds,</l>
<l>which still were charmed by Orpheus as he sang,</l>
<l>the serpents, and the company of beasts—</l>
<l>fabulous audience of that worshipped bard.</l>
<l>And then they turned on him their blood-stained hands:</l>
<l>and flocked together swiftly, as wild birds,</l>
<l>which, by some chance, may see the bird of night</l>
<l>beneath the sun. And as the savage dogs</l>
<l>rush on the doomed stag, loosed some bright fore-noon,</l>
<l>on blood-sand of the amphitheatre;</l>
<l>they rushed against the bard, with swift</l>
<l>hurled thyrsi which, adorned with emerald leaves</l>
<l>had not till then been used for cruelty.</l>

    
<l>And some threw clods, and others branches torn</l>
<l>from trees; and others threw flint stones at him,</l>
<l>and, that no lack of weapons might restrain</l>
<l>their savage fury then, not far from there</l>
<l>by chance they found some oxen which turned up</l>
<l>the soil with ploughshares, and in fields nearby</l>
<l>were strong-armed peasants, who with eager sweat</l>
<l>worked for the harvest as they dug hard fields;</l>
<l>and all those peasants, when they saw the troop</l>
<l>of frantic women, ran away and left</l>
<l>their implements of labor strown upon</l>
<l>deserted fields—harrows and heavy rakes</l>
<l>and their long spades</l>

    
<l>after the savage mob</l>
<l>had seized upon those implements, and torn</l>
<l>to pieces oxen armed with threatening horns,</l>
<l>they hastened to destroy the harmless bard,</l>
<l>devoted Orpheus; and with impious hate,</l>
<l>murdered him, while his out-stretched hands implored</l>
<l>their mercy—the first and only time his voice</l>
<l>had no persuasion. O great Jupiter!</l>
<l>Through those same lips which had controlled the rocks</l>
<l>and which had overcome ferocious beasts,</l>
<l>his life breathed forth, departed in the air.</l>

    
<l>The mournful birds, the stricken animals,</l>
<l>the hard stones and the weeping woods, all these</l>
<l>that often had followed your inspiring voice,</l>
<l>bewailed your death; while trees dropped their green leaves,</l>
<l>mourning for you, as if they tore their hair.</l>
<l>They say sad rivers swelled with their own tears—</l>
<l>naiads and dryads with dishevelled hair</l>
<l>wore garments of dark color.</l>

    
<l>His torn limbs</l>
<l>were scattered in strange places. Hebrus then</l>
<l>received his head and harp—and, wonderful!</l>
<l>While his loved harp was floating down the stream,</l>
<l>it mourned for him beyond my power to tell.</l>
<l>His tongue though lifeless, uttered a mournful sound</l>
<l>and mournfully the river's banks replied:</l>
<l>onward borne by the river to the sea</l>
<l>they left their native stream and reached the shore</l>
<l>of Lesbos at Methymna. Instantly,</l>
<l>a furious serpent rose to attack the head</l>
<l>of Orpheus, cast up on that foreign sand—</l>
<l>the hair still wet with spray. Phoebus at last</l>
<l>appeared and saved the head from that attack:</l>
<l>before the serpent could inflict a sting,</l>
<l>he drove it off, and hardened its wide jaws</l>
<l>to rigid stone.</l>

    
<l>Meanwhile the fleeting shade</l>
<l>of Orpheus had descended under earth:</l>
<l>remembering now those regions that he saw</l>
<l>when there before, he sought Eurydice</l>
<l>through fields frequented by the blest; and when</l>
<l>he found her, folded her in eager arms.</l>
<l>Then lovingly they wandered side by side,</l>
<l>or he would follow when she chose to lead,</l>
<l>or at another time he walked in front,</l>
<l>looking back, safely,—at Eurydice.</l>

    
<l>Bacchus would not permit the wickedness</l>
<l>of those who slaughtered Orpheus to remain</l>
<l>unpunished. Grieving for the loss of his</l>
<l>loved bard of sacred rites, at once he bound</l>
<l>with twisted roots the feet of everyone</l>
<l>of those Edonian women who had caused</l>
<l>the crime of Orpheus' death.</l>

    
<l>Their toes grew long.</l>
<l>He thrust the sharp points in the solid earth.</l>
<l>As when a bird entangled in a snare,</l>
<l>hid by the cunning fowler, knows too late</l>
<l>that it is held, then vainly beats its wings,</l>
<l>and fluttering only makes more tight the noose</l>
<l>with every struggle; so each woman-fiend</l>
<l>whose feet were sinking in the soil, when she</l>
<l>attempted flight, was held by deepening roots.</l>
<l>And while she looks down where her toes and nails</l>
<l>and feet should be, she sees wood growing up</l>
<l>from them and covering all her graceful legs.</l>
<l>Full of delirious grief, endeavoring</l>
<l>to smite with right hand on her changing thigh,</l>
<l>she strikes on solid oak. Her tender breast</l>
<l>and shoulders are transformed to rigid oak.</l>
<l>You would declare that her extended arms</l>
<l>are real branches of a forest tree,</l>
<l>and such a thought would be the very truth.</l>


Midas aureus.
BACCHUS AND MIDAS

<l>And not content with this, Bacchus resolved</l>
<l>to leave that land, and with a worthier train</l>
<l>went to the vineyards of his own Tmolus</l>
<l>and to Pactolus, though the river was</l>
<l>not golden, nor admired for precious sands.</l>
<l>His usual throng of Satyrs and of Bacchanals</l>
<l>surrounded him; but not Silenus, who</l>
<l>was then detained from him. The Phrygian folk</l>
<l>had captured him, as he was staggering, faint</l>
<l>with palsied age and wine. And after they</l>
<l>bound him in garlands, they led him to their king</l>
<l>Midas, to whom with the Cecropian</l>
<l>Eumolpus, Thracian Orpheus had shown all</l>
<l>the Bacchic rites. When Midas recognized</l>
<l>his old time friend Silenus, who had been</l>
<l>so often his companion in the rites</l>
<l>of Bacchus, he kept joyful festival,</l>
<l>with his old comrade, twice five days and nights.</l>

    
<l>Upon the eleventh day, when Lucifer</l>
<l>had dimmed the lofty multitude of stars,</l>
<l>King Midas and Silenus went from there</l>
<l>joyful together to the Lydian lands.</l>
<l>There Midas put Silenus carefully</l>
<l>under the care of his loved foster-child,</l>
<l>young Bacchus. He with great delight, because</l>
<l>he had his foster-father once again,</l>
<l>allowed the king to choose his own reward—</l>
<l>a welcome offer, but it led to harm.</l>
<l>And Midas made this ill-advised reply:</l>
<l>“Cause whatsoever I shall touch to change</l>
<l>at once to yellow gold.” Bacchus agreed</l>
<l>to his unfortunate request, with grief 	</l>
<l>that Midas chose for harm and not for good.</l>
<l>The Berecynthian hero, king of Phrygia,</l>
<l>with joy at his misfortune went away,</l>
<l>and instantly began to test the worth</l>
<l>of Bacchus' word by touching everything.</l>

    
<l>Doubtful himself of his new power, he pulled</l>
<l>a twig down from a holm-oak, growing on</l>
<l>a low hung branch. The twig was turned to gold.</l>
<l>He lifted up a dark stone from the ground</l>
<l>and it turned pale with gold. He touched a clod</l>
<l>and by his potent touch the clod became</l>
<l>a mass of shining gold. He plucked some ripe,</l>
<l>dry spears of grain, and all that wheat he touched</l>
<l>was golden. Then he held an apple which</l>
<l>he gathered from a tree, and you would think</l>
<l>that the Hesperides had given it.</l>
<l>If he but touched a lofty door, at once</l>
<l>each door-post seemed to glisten. When he washed</l>
<l>his hands in liquid streams, the lustrous drops</l>
<l>upon his hands might have been those which once</l>
<l>astonished Danae. He could not now</l>
<l>conceive his large hopes in his grasping mind,</l>
<l>as he imagined everything of gold.</l>

    
<l>And, while he was rejoicing in great wealth,</l>
<l>his servants set a table for his meal,</l>
<l>with many dainties and with needful bread:</l>
<l>but when he touched the gift of Ceres with</l>
<l>his right hand, instantly the gift of Ceres</l>
<l>stiffened to gold; or if he tried to bite</l>
<l>with hungry teeth a tender bit of meat,</l>
<l>the dainty, as his teeth but touched it, shone</l>
<l>at once with yellow shreds and flakes of gold.</l>
<l>And wine, another gift of Bacchus, when</l>
<l>he mixed it in pure water, can be seen</l>
<l>in his astonished mouth as liquid gold.</l>

    
<l>Confounded by his strange misfortune—rich</l>
<l>and wretched—he was anxious to escape</l>
<l>from his unhappy wealth. He hated all</l>
<l>he had so lately longed for. Plenty could</l>
<l>not lessen hunger and no remedy</l>
<l>relieved his dry, parched throat. The hated gold</l>
<l>tormented him no more than he deserved.</l>
<l>Lifting his hands and shining arms to heaven,</l>
<l>he moaned. “Oh pardon me, father Lenaeus!</l>
<l>I have done wrong, but pity me, I pray,</l>
<l>and save me from this curse that looked so fair.”</l>

    
<l>How patient are the gods! Bacchus forthwith,</l>
<l>because King Midas had confessed his fault,</l>
<l>restored him and annulled the promise given,</l>
<l>annulled the favor granted, and he said:</l>

    
<l>“That you may not be always cased in gold,</l>
<l>which you unhappily desired, depart</l>
<l>to the stream that flows by that great town of Sardis</l>
<l>and upward trace its waters, as they glide</l>
<l>past Lydian heights, until you find their source.</l>
<l>Then, where the spring leaps out from mountain rock,</l>
<l>plunge head and body in the snowy foam.</l>
<l>At once the flood will take away your curse.”</l>

    
<l>King Midas did as he was told and plunged</l>
<l>beneath the water at the river's source.</l>
<l>And the gold virtue granted by the god,</l>
<l>as it departed from his body, tinged</l>
<l>the stream with gold. And even to this hour</l>
<l>adjoining fields, touched by this ancient vein</l>
<l>of gold, are hardened where the river flows</l>
<l>and colored with the gold that Midas left.</l>


Midae aures.
THE MUSICAL CONTEST OF PAN AND APOLLO

<l>Abhorring riches he inhabited</l>
<l>the woods and fields, and followed Pan who dwells</l>
<l>always in mountain-caves: but still obtuse</l>
<l>remained, from which his foolish mind again,</l>
<l>by an absurd decision, harmed his life.</l>
<l>He followed Pan up to the lofty mount</l>
<l>Tmolus, which from its great height looks far</l>
<l>across the sea. Steep and erect it stands</l>
<l>between great Sardis and the small Hypaepa.</l>

    
<l>While Pan was boasting there to mountain nymphs</l>
<l>of his great skill in music, and while he</l>
<l>was warbling a gay tune upon the reeds,</l>
<l>cemented with soft wax, in his conceit</l>
<l>he dared to boast to them how he despised</l>
<l>Apollo's music when compared with his—.</l>
<l>At last to prove it, he agreed to stand</l>
<l>against Apollo in a contest which</l>
<l>it was agreed should be decided by</l>
<l>Tmolus as their umpire.</l>

    
<l>This old god</l>
<l>sat down on his own mountain, and first eased</l>
<l>his ears of many mountain growing trees,</l>
<l>oak leaves were wreathed upon his azure hair</l>
<l>and acorns from his hollow temples hung.</l>
<l>First to the Shepherd-god Tmolus spoke:</l>

    
<l>“My judgment shall be yours with no delay.</l>
<l>Pan made some rustic sounds on his rough reeds,</l>
<l>delighting Midas with his uncouth notes;</l>
<l>for Midas chanced to be there when he played.</l>

    
<l>When Pan had ceased, divine Tmolus turned</l>
<l>to Phoebus, and the forest likewise turned</l>
<l>just as he moved. Apollo's golden locks</l>
<l>were richly wreathed with fresh Parnassian laurel;</l>
<l>his robe of Tyrian purple swept the ground;</l>
<l>his left hand held his lyre, adorned with gems</l>
<l>and Indian ivory. His right hand held</l>
<l>the plectrum—as an artist he stood there</l>
<l>before Tmolus, while his skilful thumb</l>
<l>touching the strings made charming melody.</l>

    
<l>Delighted with Apollo's artful touch,</l>
<l>Tmolus ordered Pan to hold his reeds</l>
<l>excelled by beauty of Apollo's lyre.</l>
<l>That judgment of the sacred mountain god</l>
<l>pleased all those present, all but Midas, who</l>
<l>blaming Tmolus called the award unjust.</l>

    
<l>The Delian god forbids his stupid ears</l>
<l>to hold their native human shape;</l>
<l>and, drawing them out to a hideous length,</l>
<l>he fills them with gray hairs, and makes them both</l>
<l>unsteady, wagging at the lower part:</l>
<l>still human, only this one part condemned,</l>
<l>Midas had ears of a slow-moving ass.</l>

    
<l>Midas, careful to hide his long ears, wore</l>
<l>a purple turban over both, which hid</l>
<l>his foul disgrace from laughter. But one day</l>
<l>a servant, who was chosen to cut his hair</l>
<l>with steel, when it was long, saw his disgrace.</l>
<l>He did not dare reveal what he had seen,</l>
<l>but eager, to disclose the secret, dug</l>
<l>a shallow hole, and in a low voice told</l>
<l>what kind of ears were on his master's head.</l>
<l>All this he whispered in the hollow earth</l>
<l>he dug, and then he buried all he said</l>
<l>by throwing back the loose earth in the hole</l>
<l>so everything was silent when he left.</l>

    
<l>A grove thick set with quivering reeds</l>
<l>began to grow there, and when it matured,</l>
<l>about twelve months after that servant left,</l>
<l>the grove betrayed its planter. For, moved by</l>
<l>a gentle South Wind, it repeated all</l>
<l>the words which he had whispered, and disclosed</l>
<l>from earth the secret of his master's ears.</l>


Laomedon. Hesione.
HESIONE

<l>His vengence now complete, Latona's son</l>
<l>borne through the liquid air, departed from</l>
<l>Tmolus, and then rested on the land</l>
<l>of Laomedon, this side the narrow sea</l>
<l>dividing Phrygia from the land of Thrace.</l>
<l>The promontory of Sigaeum right</l>
<l>and on the left Rhoetaeum loftily arose;</l>
<l>and at that place an ancient altar had</l>
<l>been dedicated to great Jove, the god</l>
<l>Panomphaean. And near that place he saw</l>
<l>laomedon, beginning then to build</l>
<l>the walls of famous Troy. He was convinced</l>
<l>the task exceeded all the power of man,</l>
<l>requiring great resource. Together with</l>
<l>the trident-bearing father of the deep,</l>
<l>he assumed a mortal form: and those two gods</l>
<l>agreed to labor for a sum of gold</l>
<l>and built the mighty wall. But that false king</l>
<l>refused all payment, adding perjury</l>
<l>to his false bargaining. Neptune, enraged,</l>
<l>said, “You shall not escape your punishment.”</l>
<l>And he drove all his waters high upon</l>
<l>the shores of Troy—built there through perfidy.</l>

    
<l>The sad land seemed a sea: the hard-earned wealth</l>
<l>of all its farmers was destroyed</l>
<l>and overwhelmed by furious waves.</l>
<l>This awful punishment was not enough.</l>
<l>The daughter of the king was soon required</l>
<l>as food for a sea-monster—. Hesione</l>
<l>was chained to rugged rocks. But Hercules</l>
<l>delivered from all harm the royal maid</l>
<l>and justly he demanded of the king,</l>
<l>her father, payment of the promised steeds;</l>
<l>but that perfidious king refused to keep</l>
<l>his promise. Hercules enraged, because</l>
<l>all payment was denied to him for his</l>
<l>great service, captured the twice-perjured walls</l>
<l>of conquered Troy. And as a fair reward,</l>
<l>he gave to Telamon, who fought for him,</l>
<l>Hesione, loved daughter of that king.</l>
<l>For Peleus had a goddess as his bride</l>
<l>and he was prouder of his father-in-law</l>
<l>than of his grandsire. Since not he alone</l>
<l>was grandson of great Jove, but he alone</l>
<l>was honored with a goddess for a wife.</l>


Peleus et Thetis.
PELEUS AND THETIS. BIRTH OF ACHILLES.

<l>To Thetis, aged Proteus once had said,</l>
<l>“Oh goddess of the waves, you shall conceive,</l>
<l>and you shall be the mother of a youth</l>
<l>who by heroic actions will surpass</l>
<l>the deeds of his own father, and your son</l>
<l>shall be superior to his father's power.”</l>
<l>So Jupiter, although the flame of love</l>
<l>for Thetis burned his breast, would not embrace</l>
<l>the lovely daughter of the sea, and urged</l>
<l>his grandson Peleus, son of Aeacus,</l>
<l>to wed the green haired maid without delay.</l>

    
<l>There is a curved bay of Haemonia,</l>
<l>where like an arch, two bending arms</l>
<l>project out in the waves, as if to form</l>
<l>a harbor; but the water is not deep—</l>
<l>although enough to hide a shoal of sand.</l>
<l>It has a firm shore which will not retain</l>
<l>a foot's impression, nor delay the step—</l>
<l>no seaweeds grow in that vicinity.</l>

    
<l>There is a grove of myrtle near that place</l>
<l>thick-hung with berries, blended of twin shades.</l>
<l>A cave within the middle of that grove</l>
<l>is found, and whether it was formed by art</l>
<l>or nature is not known, although it seems</l>
<l>a work of art. There Thetis often went,</l>
<l>quite naked, seated on her dolphin, which</l>
<l>was harnessed. Peleus seized her there when she</l>
<l>was fast asleep: and after he had tried</l>
<l>to win her by entreaties, while she long</l>
<l>continued to resist him, he resolved</l>
<l>to conquer her by violence, and seized</l>
<l>her neck with both arms. She resorted then</l>
<l>to all her usual art, and often changed:	</l>
<l>her shape as it was known, so that he failed</l>
<l>in his attempt. At first she was a bird,</l>
<l>but while she seemed a bird he held her fast;</l>
<l>and then she changed herself to a large tree,</l>
<l>and Peleus clung with ardor to the tree;</l>
<l>her third disguise was as a spotted tigress,</l>
<l>which frightened him so that he lost his hold.</l>

    
<l>Then, as he poured wine on the heaving sea,</l>
<l>he prayed unto the sea green gods and gave</l>
<l>them sacrifice of sheep entrails, and smoke</l>
<l>of frankincense. He ceased not, till at last</l>
<l>the prophet of Carpathia, as he rose</l>
<l>up from a deep wave, said, “Hark unto me,</l>
<l>O son of Aeacus! and you shall have</l>
<l>the bride your heart desires: when she at rest</l>
<l>lies sleeping in the cool wave, you must bind</l>
<l>her while she is unwary, with strong cords</l>
<l>and complicated bonds, And never let</l>
<l>her arts deceive you when she imitates</l>
<l>a hundred varied forms, but hold her fast,</l>
<l>whatever she may seem, until she shall</l>
<l>at length assume the shape she had at first.”</l>
<l>So Proteus cautioned him, and hid his face</l>
<l>beneath the waves as his last words were said.</l>

    
<l>Now Titan was descending and the pole</l>
<l>of his bright chariot as it downward bent</l>
<l>illuminated the Hesperian main;</l>
<l>and at that time the lovely Nereid,</l>
<l>Thetis, departing from her ocean wave,</l>
<l>entered the cavern for desired repose.</l>

    
<l>Peleus was waiting there. Immediately,</l>
<l>just as he seized upon the virgin's limbs,</l>
<l>she changed her shape and perservered</l>
<l>until convinced she could not overcome </l>
<l>his hold—for her two arms were forced apart—</l>
<l>she groaned and said, “You could not overcome</l>
<l>me in this way, but some divinity</l>
<l>has given you the power.” Then she appeared</l>
<l>as Thetis: and, when Peleus saw her now</l>
<l>deprived of all deceptions, he embraced</l>
<l>her and was father of the great Achilles.</l>


Peleus apud Ceycem.
DAEDALION CHANGED TO A HAWK	

<l>Great Peleus' heart was filled with happiness;</l>
<l>because of his great son and Thetis his</l>
<l>dear wife: he was blest in everything, except</l>
<l>in killing Phocus. The Trachinian land</l>
<l>received him guilty of his brother's blood;</l>
<l>when he fled, banished from his native home.</l>
<l>There Ceyx, who had the fine countenance</l>
<l>of Lucifer his father, reigned as king,</l>
<l>without the cost of violence or blood.</l>
<l>Before this time his days had always given</l>
<l>him joy and comfort, but all now was changed,</l>
<l>for he was mourning a loved brother's death.</l>

    
<l>Peleus, outwearied with his journey's length.</l>
<l>Left his fine flock of sheep and all the herds</l>
<l>he had brought with him, not far from the walls</l>
<l>of that city, where Ceyx long had reigned.</l>
<l>He entered with an olive branch all swathed</l>
<l>in woolen fillets, symbol of good will,</l>
<l>and with a suppliant hand disclosed his name.</l>
<l>He told the monarch who he was, also</l>
<l>his father's name. But he concealed his crime,</l>
<l>giving untruthful reasons for his flight:</l>
<l>and begged a refuge either in town or field.</l>

    
<l>The king of Trachyn answered with kind words:</l>
<l>“Ah, Peleus, even the lowest ranks enjoy</l>
<l>our bounties and our hospitality,</l>
<l>and you bring with you powers which compell</l>
<l>attention and respect. Your name is so</l>
<l>illustrious, and is not Jupiter</l>
<l>your grandsire? Do not lose your time by such</l>
<l>entreaties. Everything you may desire</l>
<l>is yours as soon as known, and all you see</l>
<l>is partly yours, but in how sad a state!”</l>

    
<l>And then he wept. When Peleus and his friends</l>
<l>asked him the reason of his grief he said,</l>
<l>“Perchance you deem that bird which lives on prey,</l>
<l>which is the terror of all other birds,</l>
<l>had always feathered wings? It was a man.</l>
<l>And now the vigor of its courage is</l>
<l>as great as when well known by his man's name,</l>
<l>Daedalion, bold in wars and strong and harsh,</l>
<l>and not afraid to hazard violence.</l>
<l>His father was unequalled Lucifer,</l>
<l>star of the Morning, who at dawn brings forth</l>
<l>Aurora, and withdraws the last of all</l>
<l>the shining stars of heaven.—My brother named</l>
<l>daedalion, son of that great star, was fond</l>
<l>of cruel warfare, while I cherished peace</l>
<l>and loved the quiet of my married life.</l>
<l>This brother, powerful in the art of war,</l>
<l>subdued strong kings and nations.—And 'tis he</l>
<l>transformed from manhood, now a bird of prey,</l>
<l>that so relentlessly pursues the doves,</l>
<l>known as the pride of Thisbe's citizens.</l>

    
<l>“My brother had a daughter Chione</l>
<l>so beautiful she pleased a thousand men,</l>
<l>when she had reached the marriageable age</l>
<l>of twice seven years. It happened by some chance</l>
<l>that Phoebus and the son of Maia, who</l>
<l>returned—one from his Delphi, the other from</l>
<l>Cyllene's heights—beheld this lovely maid</l>
<l>both at the same time, and were both inflamed</l>
<l>with passion. Phoebus waited till the night.</l>

    
<l>Hermes could not endure delay and with</l>
<l>the magic of his wand, that causes sleep,</l>
<l>he touched the virgin's face; and instantly,</l>
<l>as if entranced, she lay there fast asleep,</l>
<l>and suffered violence from the ardent god.</l>
<l>When night bespangled the wide heaven with stars,</l>
<l>Phoebus became an aged crone and gained</l>
<l>the joy he had deferred until that hour.</l>

    
<l>“When her mature womb had completed time</l>
<l>Autolycus was born, a crafty son,</l>
<l>who certainly inherited the skill</l>
<l>of wingfoot Mereury, his artful sire,</l>
<l>notorious now; for every kind of theft.</l>
<l>In fact, Autolycus with Mercury's craft,</l>
<l>loved to make white of black, and black of white.</l>

    
<l>“But Phoebus' child, for Chione bore twins, </l>
<l>was named Philammon, like his sire, well known.</l>
<l>To all men for the beauty of his song.</l>
<l>And famous for his handling of the lyre.</l>

    
<l>“What benefit in life did she obtain</l>
<l>because she pleased! two gods and bore such twins?</l>
<l>Was she blest by good fortune then because </l>
<l>she was the daughter of a valiant father,</l>
<l>and even the grandchild of the Morning Star?</l>
<l>Can glory be a curse? Often it is.</l>

    
<l>“And surely it was so for Chione.</l>
<l>It was a prejudice that harmed her days</l>
<l>because she vaunted that she did surpass</l>
<l>Diana's beauty and decried her charms:</l>
<l>the goddess in hot anger answered her,</l>
<l>sarcastically, ‘If my face cannot</l>
<l>give satisfaction, let me try my deeds.’ </l>

    
<l>“Without delay Diana bent her bow,</l>
<l>and from the string an arrow swiftly flew, </l>
<l>and pierced the vaunting tongue of Chione.</l>
<l>Her tongue was silenced, and she tried in vain</l>
<l>to speak or make a sound, and while she tried</l>
<l>her life departed with the flowing blood.</l>

    
<l>“Embracing her, I shared her father's grief.</l>
<l>I spoke consoling words to my dear brother,</l>
<l>he heard them as a cliff might hear the sea.</l>
<l>And he lamented bitterly the loss</l>
<l>of his dear daughter, snatched away from him.</l>

    
<l>“Ah! when he saw her burning, he was filled</l>
<l>with such an uncontrolled despair, he rushed</l>
<l>four times to leap upon the blazing pyre;</l>
<l>and after he had been four times repulsed,</l>
<l>he turned and rushed away in headlong flight</l>
<l>through trackless country, as a bullock flees,</l>
<l>his swollen neck pierced with sharp hornet-stings,</l>
<l>it seemed to me he ran beyond the speed</l>
<l>of any human being. You would think</l>
<l>his feet had taken wings, he left us far</l>
<l>behind and swift in his desire for death</l>
<l>he stood at last upon Parnassus' height.</l>

    
<l>“Apollo pitied him.—And when Daedalion</l>
<l>leaped over the steep cliff, Apollo's power</l>
<l>transformed him to a bird; supported him</l>
<l>while he was hovering in the air upon</l>
<l>uncertain wings, of such a sudden growth.</l>
<l>Apollo, also, gave him a curved beak,</l>
<l>and to his slender toes gave crooked claws.</l>
<l>His former courage still remains, with strength</l>
<l>greater than usual in birds. He changed</l>
<l>to a fierce hawk; cruel to all, he vents</l>
<l>his rage on other birds. Grieving himself</l>
<l>he is a cause of grief to all his kind.”</l>

PELEUS AND THE WOLF

<l>While Ceyx, the royal son of Lucifer,</l>
<l>told these great wonders of his brother's life;</l>
<l>Onetor, who had watched the while those herds</l>
<l>which Peleus had assigned to him, ran up</l>
<l>with panting speed; and cried out as he ran,</l>
<l>“Peleus, Peleus! I bring you dreadful news!”</l>
<l>Peleus asked him to tell what had gone wrong</l>
<l>and with King Ceyx he listened in suspense.</l>


    
<l>“I drove the weary bullocks to the shore,”</l>
<l>Onetor then began, “About the time</l>
<l>when the high burning Sun in middle course,</l>
<l>could look back on as much as might be seen</l>
<l>remaining: and some cattle had then bent</l>
<l>their knees on yellow sand; and as they lay</l>
<l>might view the expanse of water stretched beyond.</l>
<l>Some with slow steps were wandering here and there,</l>
<l>and others swimming, stretched their lofty necks</l>
<l>above the waves. A temple near that sea</l>
<l>was fair to view, although 'twas not adorned</l>
<l>with gold nor marble. It was richly made</l>
<l>of beams, and shaded with an ancient grove.</l>

    
<l>“A sailor, while he dried his nets upon</l>
<l>the shore nearby, declared that aged Nereus</l>
<l>possessed it with his Nereids, as the gods</l>
<l>who ruled the neighboring waters. Very near</l>
<l>it is a marsh, made by the encroaching waves,</l>
<l>all thickly covered with low willow trees.</l>

    
<l>“From there a loud uncanny crashing sound</l>
<l>alarms the neighborhood. A monster-wolf!</l>
<l>All stained with mud he breaks forth from the marsh,</l>
<l>his thundering jaws thick-covered with vile foam</l>
<l>and clotted blood—his fierce eyes flashing flames</l>
<l>of crimson: and though he was raging, both</l>
<l>with fury and with hunger, the true cause</l>
<l>of his fierce passions was Ferocity.</l>

    
<l>“He never paused to sate his ravenous hunger</l>
<l>with the first cattle that he fell upon,</l>
<l>but mangled the whole herd, as if at war.</l>
<l>And some of us, while we defended them,</l>
<l>were wounded with his fatal bite and killed.—</l>
<l>the shore and nearest waves were red with blood,</l>
<l>and marshy fens were filled with mournful sounds—</l>
<l>the longings of our cattle.—This delay</l>
<l>is dangerous. We must not hesitate.</l>
<l>We must unite before all is destroyed!</l>
<l>Take up your arms. Arm! and unite, I say!</l>
<l>And bear our weapons for the cause of Right!”</l>

    
<l>So spoke the countryman, and yet the loss</l>
<l>had no effect on Peleus, though severe,</l>
<l>for he, remembering his red crime, believed</l>
<l>the Nereid had given him that loss—</l>
<l>a just misfortune, as an offering</l>
<l>to the departed Phocus. After this,</l>
<l>King Ceyx, while he put his armor on,</l>
<l>ordered his men to arm themselves with their</l>
<l>best weapons, and to follow his command.</l>
<l>But his fond wife, Halcyone, aroused</l>
<l>by such a tumult, ran to him in haste;</l>
<l>in such haste that her hair was still unfinished,</l>
<l>and such as had been done, she threw</l>
<l>in wild disorder.—Clinging to the neck</l>
<l>of her loved husband, she entreated him</l>
<l>with words and tears, to send his men along.</l>
<l>But keep himself at home and so to save</l>
<l>two lives in one.</l>

    
<l>But Peleus said “O queen,</l>
<l>'Tis sweet and commendable in you to fear</l>
<l>but needless. Though you promise generous aid,</l>
<l>my hope lies not in fighting with the beast,</l>
<l>I must appease a goddess of the sea.</l>
<l>And the divinity of ocean must</l>
<l>be properly adored.”</l>

    
<l>A lofty tower</l>
<l>is near there, and upon its extreme height</l>
<l>a signal-fire is burning night and day,</l>
<l>known to the grateful ships. They all went there;</l>
<l>and from its summit they beheld with sighs,</l>
<l>the mangled cattle scattered on the shore,</l>
<l>and saw the ravager among the herd,</l>
<l>his blood-stained jaws and long hair dripping blood.</l>

    
<l>Then Peleus stretched his arms out towards the sea,</l>
<l>and he implored the azure Psamathe</l>
<l>to lay aside her wrath and give him aid.</l>
<l>But she was deaf to any word of Peleus</l>
<l>entreating her, and would not offer aid,</l>
<l>till Thetis, interceding on behalf</l>
<l>of her afflicted husband, moved her will.</l>

    
<l>The monster-wolf persisted in his rage,</l>
<l>even when the sea nymph bade him turn aside.</l>
<l>His keen ferocity increased by taste</l>
<l>of new sweet blood; till Psamathe, while he</l>
<l>was seizing the last mangled heifer's neck,</l>
<l>transformed him to hard marble. Every part</l>
<l>of that ferocious monster's shape remained</l>
<l>but it was changed to marble colored stone,</l>
<l>which showed the monster was no more a wolf,</l>
<l>and should no longer be a cause of fear.</l>

    
<l>But still, the guiding Fates did not permit</l>
<l>the banished Peleus to continue there,</l>
<l>in this land governed by the friendly king.</l>
<l>A wandering exile, he proceeded north</l>
<l>into Magnesia; and was purified</l>
<l>of guilt by King Acastus of that land.</l>


Ceyx et Alcyone. Somnus.
CEYX AND HALCYONE

<l>King Ceyx, disturbed by his loved brother's fate</l>
<l>and prodigies which happened since that time,</l>
<l>prepared to venture to the Clarian god,</l>
<l>that he might there consult the oracle,</l>
<l>so sanctified to consolation of distress:</l>
<l>for then the way to Delphi was unsafe</l>
<l>because of Phorbas and his Phlegyans.</l>
<l>Before he went he told his faithful queen,</l>
<l>his dear Halcyone. She felt at once</l>
<l>terror creep through the marrow of her bones,</l>
<l>pallor of boxwood overspread her face,</l>
<l>and her two cheeks were wet with gushing tears.</l>
<l>Three times she tried to speak while tears and sobs</l>
<l>delayed her voice, until at last she said:—</l>

    
<l>“What fault of mine, my dearest, has so changed</l>
<l>your usual thoughts? Where is that care for me</l>
<l>that always has stood first? Can you leave me</l>
<l>for this long journey with no anxious fear—</l>
<l>Halcyone, forsaken in these halls?</l>
<l>Will this long journey be a pleasant change</l>
<l>because far from you I should be more dear?</l>
<l>Perhaps you think you will go there by land,</l>
<l>and I shall only grieve, and shall not fear</l>
<l>the sea affrights me with its tragic face.</l>
<l>Just lately I observed some broken planks</l>
<l>upon our seashore, and I've read and read</l>
<l>the names of seamen on their empty tombs!</l>

    
<l>“Oh, let no false assurance fill your mind</l>
<l>because your father-in-law is Aeolus.</l>
<l>Who in a dungeon shuts the stormful winds</l>
<l>and smoothes at will the troubled ocean waves</l>
<l>soon as the winds get freedom from his power,</l>
<l>they take entire possession of the deep,</l>
<l>and nothing is forbidden their attack;</l>
<l>and all the rights of every land and sea</l>
<l>are disregarded by them. They insult</l>
<l>even the clouds of heaven and their wild</l>
<l>concussions urge the lightnings to strike fires.</l>
<l>The more I know of them, for I knew</l>
<l>them in my childhood and I often saw</l>
<l>them from my father's home, the more I fear.</l>

    
<l>“But, O dear husband! if this new resolve</l>
<l>can not be altered by my prayers and fears,</l>
<l>and if you are determined, take me, too:</l>
<l>some comfort may be gained, if in the storms</l>
<l>we may be tossed together. I shall fear</l>
<l>only the ills that really come to us,</l>
<l>together we can certainly endure</l>
<l>discomforts till we gain that distant land.”</l>

    
<l>Such words and tears of the daughter of Aeolus</l>
<l>gave Ceyx, famed son of the Morning Star,</l>
<l>much thought and sorrow; for the flame of love</l>
<l>burned in his heart as strongly as in hers.</l>

    
<l>Reluctant to give up the voyage, even more</l>
<l>to make Halcyone his partner on</l>
<l>the dangerous sea, he answered her complaints</l>
<l>in many ways to pacify her breast,</l>
<l>but could not comfort her until at last</l>
<l>he said, “This separation from your love</l>
<l>will be most sorrowful; and so I swear</l>
<l>to you, as witnessed by the sacred fire</l>
<l>of my Star-father, if the fates permit</l>
<l>my safe return, I will come back to you</l>
<l>before the moon has rounded twice her orb.”</l>

    
<l>These promises gave hope of his return.</l>
<l>Without delay he ordered a ship should</l>
<l>be drawn forth from the dock, launched in the sea,</l>
<l>and properly supplied against the needs</l>
<l>of travel.—Seeing this, Halcyone,</l>
<l>as if aware of future woe, shuddered,</l>
<l>wept, and embraced him, and in extreme woe</l>
<l>said with a sad voice, “Ah—Farewell!” and then,</l>
<l>her nerveless body sank down to the ground.</l>

    
<l>While Ceyx longed for some pretext to delay,</l>
<l>the youthful oarsmen, chosen for their strength,</l>
<l>in double rows began to draw the oars</l>
<l>back towards their hardy breasts, cutting the waves</l>
<l>with equal strokes. She raised her weeping eyes</l>
<l>and saw her husband on the high-curved stern.</l>
<l>He by his waving hand made signs to her,</l>
<l>and she returned his signals. Then the ship</l>
<l>moved farther from the shore until her eyes</l>
<l>could not distinguish his loved countenance.</l>
<l>Still, while she could, she followed with her gaze</l>
<l>the fading hull; and, when that too was lost</l>
<l>far in the distance, she remained and gazed</l>
<l>at the white topsails, waving from the mast.</l>
<l>But, when she could no longer see the sails,</l>
<l>with anxious heart she sought her lonely couch</l>
<l>and laid herself upon it. Couch and room</l>
<l>renewed her sorrow and reminded her</l>
<l>how much of life was absent on the sea.</l>

    
<l>The ship had left the harbor, and the breeze</l>
<l>shook the taut rigging. Now the captain bade</l>
<l>the idle oars be drawn up to the sides.</l>
<l>They ran the pointed sailyards up the mast</l>
<l>and with spread canvas caught the coming breeze.</l>

    
<l>Perhaps the ship had not sailed half her course,</l>
<l>on every side the land was out of sight</l>
<l>in fact at a great distance, when, towards dark</l>
<l>the sea grew white with its increasing waves,</l>
<l>while boisterous east winds blew with violence.—</l>
<l>prompt in his duty, the captain warns his crew,</l>
<l>“Lower the top sails—quick—furl all the sails</l>
<l>tight to the yards!”—He ordered, but the storm</l>
<l>bore all his words away, his voice could not</l>
<l>be heard above the roaring of the sea.</l>

    
<l>But of their own accord some sailors rushed</l>
<l>to draw the oars in, others to secure</l>
<l>the sides from danger, and some strove to pull</l>
<l>the sails down from the wind. One pumps the waves</l>
<l>up from the hold, and pours the rushing sea</l>
<l>again into the sea; another takes</l>
<l>the yards off.—While such things are being done</l>
<l>without command or order, the wild storm</l>
<l>increases, and on every side fierce winds</l>
<l>wage a destructive warfare, which stirs up</l>
<l>the furious waters to their utmost power.</l>

    
<l>Even the captain, terrified, confessed</l>
<l>he did not know the status of the ship,</l>
<l>and could not order nor forbid the men—</l>
<l>so great the storm, so far beyond his skill.</l>

    
<l>Then he gave up control, while frightened men</l>
<l>shouted above the rattled cordage shocks,</l>
<l>and heavy waves were dashed against huge waves,</l>
<l>and ail the sky reverberated with</l>
<l>terrific thunders. The deep sea upturned</l>
<l>tremendous billows, which appeared to reach</l>
<l>so near the heaven they touched the heavy clouds</l>
<l>with foam of their tossed waters.—At one time,</l>
<l>while the great billows churned up yellow sand</l>
<l>from off the bottom, the wild rolling waves</l>
<l>were of that color. At another time</l>
<l>they were more black than water of the Styx.</l>
<l>Sometimes they levelled, white with lashing foam.</l>


    
<l>The ship was tossed about in the wild storm:</l>
<l>aloft as from a mountain peak it seemed</l>
<l>to look down on the valley and the depth</l>
<l>of Acheron; and, when sunk down in a trough</l>
<l>of waves engulfing, it appeared to look</l>
<l>up at the zenith from infernal seas.</l>
<l>Often the waves fell on the sides with crash</l>
<l>as terrible as when a flying stone</l>
<l>or iron ram shatters a citadel.</l>

    
<l>As lions, mustering up their strength anew,</l>
<l>might hurl their breasts against the spears</l>
<l>and outstretched arms of huntsmen, so the waves,</l>
<l>upon the rising of the winds, rushed forth</l>
<l>against the battered sides of the tossed ship</l>
<l>and rose much higher than the slanting masts.</l>

    
<l>The ship-bolts lost their grip, the loosened planks,</l>
<l>despoiled of covering wax, gave open seams,</l>
<l>through which streamed water of the fatal waves.—</l>
<l>vast sheets of rain pour from dissolving clouds,</l>
<l>so suddenly, it seemed that all the heavens</l>
<l>were flung into the deep, while swelling seas</l>
<l>ascended to the emptied fields of heaven!</l>

    
<l>The sails are drenched with rain, the salt sea waves</l>
<l>are mingled with the waters of the skies.</l>
<l>The firmament is black without a star,</l>
<l>and night is doubly dark with its own gloom</l>
<l>and blackness of the storm. Quick lightning makes</l>
<l>the black skies glitter, and the waves are fired</l>
<l>with flames of thunder-bolts. Now floods leap up</l>
<l>into the very middle of the ship.</l>

    
<l>Just as a soldier, more courageous than</l>
<l>the rest of his brave fellows, after he</l>
<l>has often charged against the embattled walls</l>
<l>of a defended city, gains at length</l>
<l>the place which he has fought for; all inflamed</l>
<l>with his desire of glory, scales the wall</l>
<l>and stands alone among a thousand foes;</l>
<l>so, when destructive waves have beat against</l>
<l>the ship's high sides, the tenth wave with known power,</l>
<l>rushes more furious than the nine before,</l>
<l>nor ceases to attack the failing ship,</l>
<l>until dashed high above the captured walls</l>
<l>it surges in the hold. Part of the sea</l>
<l>is still attempting to get in the ship,</l>
<l>and part is in it. All are panic stricken,</l>
<l>like men within a doomed and shaken town;</l>
<l>who see some foes attack the walls without,</l>
<l>and others hold possession of the walls</l>
<l>within the city. Every art has failed,</l>
<l>their courage sinks. With every coming wave</l>
<l>another death seems rushing in upon them.</l>

    
<l>One sailor yields in tears; another falls</l>
<l>down, stupefied; another calls those blest</l>
<l>whom funeral rites await; another prays,</l>
<l>addressing trusted gods, lifting his hands</l>
<l>up to that heaven unseen, as vainly he</l>
<l>implores some aid divine, and one in fright</l>
<l>recalls his brothers and his parent, while</l>
<l>another names his children and his home:</l>
<l>each frightened sailor thinks of all he left.</l>

    
<l>King Ceyx thinks only of Halcyone,</l>
<l>no other name is on his lips but hers:</l>
<l>and though he longs for her, yet he is glad</l>
<l>that she is safe at home. Ah, how he tried</l>
<l>to look back to the shore of his loved land,</l>
<l>to turn his last gaze towards his wife and home.</l>
<l>But he has lost direction.—The tossed sea</l>
<l>is raging in a hurricane so vast,</l>
<l>and all the sky is hidden by the gloom</l>
<l>of thickened storm-clouds, doubled in pitch-black.</l>

    
<l>The mast is shattered by the violence</l>
<l>of drenching tempests, and the useless helm</l>
<l>is broken. One undaunted giant wave</l>
<l>stands over wreck and spoil, and looks down like</l>
<l>a conqueror upon the other waves:</l>
<l>then falls as heavily as if some god</l>
<l>should hurl Mount Athos or Mount Pindus, torn</l>
<l>from rock foundations, into that wide sea:</l>
<l>so, with down-rushing weight and violence</l>
<l>it struck and plunged the ship to the lowest deeps.</l>
<l>And as the ship sank, many of the crew</l>
<l>sank overwhelmed in deep surrounding waves,</l>
<l>never to rise from suffocating death:</l>
<l>but some in desperation, clung for life</l>
<l>to broken timbers and escaped that fate.</l>

    
<l>King Ceyx clung to a fragment of the wreck</l>
<l>with that majestic hand which often before</l>
<l>had proudly swayed the sceptre. And in vain,</l>
<l>alas, he called upon his father's name,</l>
<l>alas, he begged his father-in-law's support.</l>
<l>But, while he swam, his lips most frequently</l>
<l>pronounced that dearest name, “Halcyone!”</l>
<l>He longs to have his body carried by waves</l>
<l>to her dear gaze and have at last,</l>
<l>entombment by the hands of his loved friends.</l>
<l>Swimming, he called Halcyone—far off,</l>
<l>as often as the billows would allow</l>
<l>his lips to open, and among the waves</l>
<l>his darling's name was murmured, till at last</l>
<l>a night-black arch of water swept above</l>
<l>the highest waves and buried him beneath</l>
<l>engulfing billows.</l>

    
<l>Lucifer was dim</l>
<l>past recognition when the dawn appeared</l>
<l>and, since he never could depart from heaven,</l>
<l>soon hid his grieving countenance in clouds.</l>

    
<l>Meanwhile, Halcyone, all unaware</l>
<l>of his sad wreck, counts off the passing nights</l>
<l>and hastens to prepare for him his clothes</l>
<l>that he may wear as soon as he returns to her;</l>
<l>and she is choosing what to wear herself,</l>
<l>and vainly promises his safe return—</l>
<l>all this indeed, while she in hallowed prayer</l>
<l>is giving frankincense to please the gods:</l>
<l>and first of loving adorations, she</l>
<l>paid at the shrine of Juno. There she prayed</l>
<l>for Ceyx—after he had suffered death,</l>
<l>that he might journey safely and return</l>
<l>and might love her above all other women,</l>
<l>this one last prayer alone was granted to her</l>

    
<l>but Juno could not long accept as hers</l>
<l>these supplications on behalf of one</l>
<l>then dead; and that she might persuade Halcyone</l>
<l>to turn her death-polluted hands away</l>
<l>from hallowed altars, Juno said in haste,</l>
<l>“O, Iris, best of all my messengers,</l>
<l>go quickly to the dreadful court of Sleep,</l>
<l>and in my name command him to despatch</l>
<l>a dream in the shape of Ceyx, who is dead,</l>
<l>and tell Halcyone the woeful truth.”</l>

    
<l>So she commanded.—Iris instantly</l>
<l>assumed a garment of a thousand tints;</l>
<l>and as she marked the high skies with her arch,</l>
<l>went swiftly thence as ordered, to the place</l>
<l>where Sleep was then concealed beneath a rock.</l>


    
<l>Near the Cimmerian Land there is a cave,</l>
<l>with a long entrance, in a hallowed mountain,</l>
<l>the home of slothful Sleep. To that dark cave</l>
<l>the Sun, when rising or in middle skies,</l>
<l>or setting, never can approach with light.</l>
<l>There dense fogs, mingled with the dark, exhale</l>
<l>darkness from the black soil—and all that place</l>
<l>is shadowed in a deep mysterious gloom.</l>

    
<l>No wakeful bird with visage crested high</l>
<l>calls forth the morning's beauty in clear notes;</l>
<l>nor do the watchful dogs, more watchful geese,</l>
<l>nor wild beasts, cattle, nor the waving trees,</l>
<l>make sound or whisper; and the human voice</l>
<l>is never heard there—silent Rest is there.</l>
<l>But, from the bottom of a rock beneath,</l>
<l>Lethean waters of a stream ooze forth,</l>
<l>sounds of a rivulet, which trickle with</l>
<l>soft murmuring amid the pebbles and</l>
<l>invite soft sleep. Before the cavern doors</l>
<l>most fertile poppies and a wealth of herbs</l>
<l>bloom in abundance, from the juice of which</l>
<l>the humid night-hours gather sleep and spread</l>
<l>it over darkened Earth. No door is in</l>
<l>that cavern-home and not a hinge's noise</l>
<l>nor guarding porter's voice disturbs the calm.</l>
<l>But in the middle is a resting-couch,</l>
<l>raised high on night-black ebony and soft</l>
<l>with feathered cushions, all jet black, concealed</l>
<l>by a rich coverlet as dark as night,</l>
<l>on which the god of sleep, dissolved in sloth</l>
<l>lies with unmoving limbs. Around him there</l>
<l>in all directions, unsubstantial dreams</l>
<l>recline in imitation of all shapes—</l>
<l>as many as the uncounted ears of corn</l>
<l>at harvest—as the myriad leaves of trees—</l>
<l>or tiny sand grains spread upon the shore.</l>

    
<l>As soon as Iris entered that dread gloom,</l>
<l>she pushed aside the visions in her way</l>
<l>with her fair glowing hands; and instantly,</l>
<l>that sacred cavern of the god of Sleep</l>
<l>was all illuminated with the glow</l>
<l>and splendor of her garment.—Out of himself</l>
<l>the god with difficulty lifted up</l>
<l>his lanquid eyes. From this small sign of life</l>
<l>relapsing many times to languid sloth,</l>
<l>while nodding, with his chin he struck his breast</l>
<l>again and again. At last he roused himself</l>
<l>from gloom and slumber; and, while raised upon</l>
<l>his elbow, he enquired of Iris why</l>
<l>she came to him.—He knew her by her name.</l>

    
<l>She answered him, “O, Sleep, divine repose</l>
<l>of all things! Gentlest of the deities!</l>
<l>Peace to the troubled mind, from which you drive</l>
<l>the cares of life, restorer of men's strength</l>
<l>when wearied with the toils of day, command</l>
<l>a vision that shall seem the actual form</l>
<l>of royal Ceyx to visit Trachin famed</l>
<l>for Hercules and tell Halcyone</l>
<l>his death by shipwreck. It is Juno's wish.”</l>

    
<l>Iris departed after this was said.</l>
<l>For she no longer could endure the effect</l>
<l>of slumber-vapor; and as soon as she</l>
<l>knew sleep was creeping over her tired limbs</l>
<l>she flew from there—and she departed by</l>
<l>the rainbow, over which she came before.</l>

    
<l>Out of the multitude—his thousand sons—</l>
<l>the god of sleep raised Morpheus by his power.</l>
<l>Most skillful of his sons, who had the art</l>
<l>of imitating any human shape;</l>
<l>and dexterously could imitate in men</l>
<l>the gait and countenance, and every mode</l>
<l>of speaking. He could simulate the dress</l>
<l>and customary words of any man</l>
<l>he chose to represent—but he could not</l>
<l>assume the form of anything but man.</l>

    
<l>Such was his art. Another of Sleep's sons</l>
<l>could imitate all kinds of animals;</l>
<l>such as a wild beast or a flying bird,</l>
<l>or even a serpent with its twisted shape;</l>
<l>and that son, by the gods above was called</l>
<l>Icelos—but the inhabitants of earth</l>
<l>called him Phobetor—and a third son, named</l>
<l>Phantasos, cleverly could change himself</l>
<l>into the forms of earth that have no life;</l>
<l>into a statue, water, or a tree.</l>

    
<l>It was the habit of these three to show</l>
<l>themselves at night to kings and generals;</l>
<l>and other sons would frequently appear</l>
<l>among the people of the common class.</l>
<l>All such the aged god of Sleep passed by.</l>
<l>Selecting only Morpheus from among</l>
<l>the many brothers to accomplish this,</l>
<l>and execute what Iris had desired.</l>
<l>And after all that work, he dropped his head,</l>
<l>and sank again in languid drowsiness,</l>
<l>shrinking to sloth within his lofty couch.</l>

    
<l>Morpheus at once flew through the night</l>
<l>of darkness, on his wings that make no sound,</l>
<l>and in brief space of intervening time,</l>
<l>arrived at the Haemonian city walls;</l>
<l>and there he laid aside his wings, and took</l>
<l>the face and form of Ceyx. In that form</l>
<l>as one deprived of life, devoid of clothes,</l>
<l>wan and ghastly, he stood beside the bed</l>
<l>of the sad wife. The hero's beard seemed dripping,</l>
<l>sea water streamed down from his drenching hair.</l>

    
<l>Then leaning on the bed, while dropping tears</l>
<l>were running down his cheeks, he said these words:</l>
<l>“Most wretched wife, can you still recognize</l>
<l>your own loved Ceyx, or have my looks changed:</l>
<l>so much with death you can not?—Look at me,</l>
<l>and you will be assured I am your own:</l>
<l>but here instead of your dear husband, you</l>
<l>will find only his ghost. Your faithful prayers</l>
<l>did not avail, Halcyone, and I</l>
<l>have perished. Give up all deluding hopes</l>
<l>of my return. The stormy Southwind caught</l>
<l>my ship while sailing the Aegean sea;</l>
<l>and there, tossed by the mighty wind, my ship</l>
<l>was dashed to pieces. While I vainly called</l>
<l>upon your name, the angry waters closed</l>
<l>above my drowning head and it is no</l>
<l>uncertain messenger that tells you this</l>
<l>and nothing from vague rumors has been told.</l>
<l>But it is I myself, come from the wreck,</l>
<l>now telling you my fate. Come then, arise</l>
<l>shed tears, and put on mourning; do not send</l>
<l>me unlamented, down to Tartarus.”</l>

    
<l>And Morpheus added to these words a voice</l>
<l>which she would certainly believe was her</l>
<l>beloved husband's; and he seemed to be</l>
<l>shedding fond human tears; and even his hands</l>
<l>were moved in gestures that Ceyx often used.</l>

    
<l>Halcyone shed tears and groaned aloud,</l>
<l>and, as she moved her arms and caught at his</l>
<l>dear body, she embraced the vacant air</l>
<l>she cried out loudly, “Stay, oh stay with me!</l>
<l>Why do you hurry from me? We will go</l>
<l>together!” Agitated by her own</l>
<l>excited voice; and by what seemed to be</l>
<l>her own dear husband, she awoke from sleep.</l>
<l>And first looked all about her to persuade</l>
<l>herself that he whom she had lately seen</l>
<l>must yet be with her, for she had aroused</l>
<l>the servants who in haste brought lights desired.</l>

    
<l>When she could find him nowhere, in despair</l>
<l>she struck her face and tore her garment from</l>
<l>her breast and beat her breast with mourning hands.</l>
<l>She did not wait to loosen her long hair;</l>
<l>but tore it with her hands and to her nurse,</l>
<l>who asked the cause of her wild grief, she cried:</l>
<l>“Alas, Halcyone is no more! no more! </l>
<l>with her own Ceyx she is dead! is dead!</l>
<l>Away with words of comfort, he is lost</l>
<l>by shipwreck! I have seen him, and I knew</l>
<l>him surely—as a ghost he came to me;</l>
<l>and when desirous to detain him, I</l>
<l>stretched forth my arms to him, his ghost left me—</l>
<l>it vanished from me; but it surely was</l>
<l>the ghost of my dead husband. If you ask</l>
<l>description of it, I must truly say</l>
<l>he did not have his well known features—he</l>
<l>was not so cheerful as he was in life!</l>
<l>Alas, I saw him pale and naked, with</l>
<l>his hair still dripping—his ghost from the waves</l>
<l>stood on this very spot:” and while she moaned</l>
<l>she sought his footprints on the floor. “Alas,</l>
<l>this was my fear, and this is what my mind</l>
<l>shuddered to think of, when I begged that you</l>
<l>would not desert me for the wind's control.</l>
<l>But how I wish, since you were sailing forth</l>
<l>to perish, that you had but taken me</l>
<l>with you. If I had gone with you, it would</l>
<l>have been advantage to me, for I should</l>
<l>have shared the whole course of my life with you</l>
<l>and you would not have met a separate death.</l>
<l>I linger here but I have met my death,</l>
<l>I toss on waves, and drift upon the sea.</l>

    
<l>“My heart would be more cruel than the waves,</l>
<l>if it should ask me to endure this life—</l>
<l>if I should struggle to survive such grief.</l>
<l>I will not strive nor leave you so forlorn,</l>
<l>at least I'll follow you to death. If not</l>
<l>the urn at least the lettered stone</l>
<l>shall keep us still together. If your bones</l>
<l>are not united with my bones, 'tis sure</l>
<l>our names must be united.”Overcome</l>
<l>with grief, she could not say another word—</l>
<l>but she continued wailing, and her groans</l>
<l>were heaved up from her sorrow-stricken breast.</l>

    
<l>At early dawn, she went from her abode</l>
<l>down to the seashore, where most wretchedly,</l>
<l>she stood upon the spot from which he sailed,</l>
<l>and sadly said; “He lingered here while he</l>
<l>was loosening the cables, and he kissed</l>
<l>me on this seashore when he left me here.”</l>
<l>And while she called to recollection all</l>
<l>that she had seen when standing there, and while</l>
<l>she looked far out on flowing waves from there,</l>
<l>she noticed floating on the distant sea—</l>
<l>what shall I say? At first even she could not</l>
<l>be sure of what she saw. But presently</l>
<l>although still distant—it was certainly</l>
<l>a floating corpse. She could not see what man</l>
<l>he might be, but because it seemed to her</l>
<l>it surely was a shipwrecked body, she</l>
<l>was moved as at an omen and began</l>
<l>to weep; and, moaning as she stood there, said:—</l>
<l>“Ah wretched one, whoever it may be,</l>
<l>ah, wretched is the wife whom you have left!”</l>

    
<l>As driven by the waves the body came</l>
<l>still nearer to her, she was less and less</l>
<l>the mistress of herself, the more she looked</l>
<l>upon it; and, when it was close enough</l>
<l>for her to see its features, she beheld</l>
<l>her husband. “It is he,” she cried and then</l>
<l>she tore her face, her hair, her royal robe</l>
<l>and then, extending both her trembling hands</l>
<l>towards Ceyx, “So dearest one! So do you come</l>
<l>to me again?” She cried, “O luckless mate.”</l>

    
<l>A mole, made by the craft of man, adjoins</l>
<l>the sea and breaks the shoreward rush of waves.</l>
<l>To this she leaped—it seemed impossible—</l>
<l>and then, while beating the light air with wings</l>
<l>that instant formed upon her, she flew on,</l>
<l>a mourning bird, and skimmed above the waves.</l>
<l>And while she lightly flew across the sea</l>
<l>her clacking mouth with its long slender bill,</l>
<l>full of complaining, uttered moaning sounds:</l>
<l>but when she touched the still and pallied form,</l>
<l>embracing his dear limbs with her new wings,</l>
<l>she gave cold kisses with her hardened bill.</l>

    
<l>All those who saw it doubted whether Ceyx</l>
<l>could feel her kisses; and it seemed to them</l>
<l>the moving waves had raised his countenance.</l>
<l>But he was truly conscious of her grief;</l>
<l>and through the pity of the gods above,</l>
<l>at last they both were changed to flying birds,</l>
<l>together in their fate. Their love lived on,</l>
<l>nor in these birds were marriage bonds dissolved,</l>
<l>and they soon coupled and were parent birds.</l>
<l>Each winter during seven full days of calm</l>
<l>Halcyone broods on her floating nest—</l>
<l>her nest that sails upon a halcyon sea:</l>
<l>the passage of the deep is free from storms,</l>
<l>throughout those seven full days; and Aeolus</l>
<l>restraining harmful winds, within their cave,</l>
<l>for his descendants' sake gives halcyon seas.</l>


Aesacos.
HESPERIA AND AESACUS

<l>An old man saw the two birds fly across</l>
<l>the wide extended sea and praised their love,</l>
<l>undying to the end. His old friend who</l>
<l>stood near him, said, “There is another bird,</l>
<l>which you can see skimming above the waves</l>
<l>with folded legs drawn up;” and as he spoke,</l>
<l>he pointed at a divedapper, which had</l>
<l>a long throat, and continued, “It was first</l>
<l>the son of a great king, as Ceyx, was:</l>
<l>and if you wish to know his ancestry,</l>
<l>I can assure you he descended from</l>
<l>Ilus, Assaracus, and Ganymede—</l>
<l>taken by Jupiter, and old Laomedon,</l>
<l>and Priam, ruler at the fall of Troy.</l>

    
<l>“Aesacus was the brother of the great</l>
<l>illustrious Hector; and, if he had not</l>
<l>been victimized by a strange fate in youth,</l>
<l>he would have equalled Hector's glorious fame,</l>
<l>Hector was child of Hecuba, who was</l>
<l>daughter of Dymas. Alexirhoe,</l>
<l>the daughter of the two-horned Granicus,</l>
<l>so rumor has it, secretly brought forth</l>
<l>Aesacus, hidden under Ida's shade.</l>

    
<l>“He loathed the city and away from court,</l>
<l>frequented lonely mountains and the fields</l>
<l>of unambitious peasants. Rarely he</l>
<l>was seen among the throngs of Ilium.—</l>
<l>yet, neither churlish nor impregnable</l>
<l>to love's appeal, he saw Hesperia,</l>
<l>the daughter of Cebrenus, while she was</l>
<l>once resting on the velvet-shaded banks</l>
<l>of her sire's cherished stream. Aesacus had</l>
<l>so often sought for her throughout the woods.</l>

    
<l>“Just when he saw her, while she rested there,</l>
<l>her hair spread on her shoulders to the sun,</l>
<l>she saw him, and without delay she fled,</l>
<l>even as the frightened deer runs from the wolf</l>
<l>or as the water-duck, when she has left</l>
<l>her favored stream, surprised, flies from the hawk.</l>
<l>Aesacus followed her, as swift with love</l>
<l>as she was swift with fear. But in the grass</l>
<l>a lurking snake struck at her rosy heel</l>
<l>and left its venom in her flesh.—And so,</l>
<l>her flight was ended by untimely death.</l>

    
<l>“Oh, frantic, he embraced her breathless form,</l>
<l>and cried: ‘Alas, alas, that I pursued!</l>
<l>I did not dream of such a dreadful fate!</l>
<l>Success was not worth such a price</l>
<l>I and the snake together caused your death—</l>
<l>the serpent gave the wound, I was the cause.</l>
<l>Mine is the greater guilt, and by my death</l>
<l>I'll give you consolation for your death!’ ”</l>

    
<l>“He said those words and leaped on a high rock,</l>
<l>which years of sounding waves had undermined,</l>
<l>and hurled himself into the sea below.</l>

    
<l>“Tethys was moved with pity for his fall,</l>
<l>received him softly, and then covered him</l>
<l>with feathers, as he swam among the waves.</l>
<l>The death he sought for was not granted him.</l>
<l>At this the lover was wroth. Against his will,</l>
<l>he was obliged to live in his distress,</l>
<l>with opposition to his spirit that desired</l>
<l>departure from the wretched pain of life.</l>

    
<l>“As he assumed upon his shoulders wings</l>
<l>newformed, he flew aloft and from that height</l>
<l>again he plunged his body in the waves</l>
<l>his feathers broke all danger of that fall—</l>
<l>and this new bird, Aesacus, plunged headlong</l>
<l>into the deep, and tried incessantly</l>
<l>that method of destruction. His great love</l>
<l>unsatisfied, made his sad body lean,</l>
<l>till even the spaces fixed between the joints</l>
<l>of his legs have grown long; his neck is long;</l>
<l>so that his head is far away from his</l>
<l>lean body. Still he hunts the sea</l>
<l>and takes his name from diving in the waves.</l>
