<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 12

Graeci Aulide. Fama.
EVENTS IN AULIS

<l>Sadly his father, Priam, mourned for him,</l>
<l>not knowing that young Aesacus had assumed</l>
<l>wings on his shoulders, and was yet alive.</l>
<l>Then also Hector with his brothers made</l>
<l>complete but unavailing sacrifice,</l>
<l>upon a tomb which bore his carved name.</l>
<l>Paris was absent. But soon afterwards,</l>
<l>he brought into that land a ravished wife,</l>
<l>Helen, the cause of a disastrous war,</l>
<l>together with a thousand ships, and all</l>
<l>the great Pelasgian nation.</l>

    
<l>Vengeance would</l>
<l>not long have been delayed, but the fierce winds</l>
<l>raged over seas impassable, and held</l>
<l>the ships at fishy Aulis. They could not</l>
<l>be moved from the Boeotian land. Here, when</l>
<l>a sacrifice had been prepared to Jove,</l>
<l>according to the custom of their land,</l>
<l>and when the ancient altar glowed with fire,</l>
<l>the Greeks observed an azure colored snake</l>
<l>crawling up in a plane tree near the place</l>
<l>where they had just begun their sacrifice.</l>
<l>Among the highest branches was a nest,</l>
<l>with twice four birds—and those the serpent seized</l>
<l>together with the mother-bird as she</l>
<l>was fluttering round her loss. And every bird</l>
<l>the serpent buried in his greedy maw.</l>
<l>All stood amazed: but Calchas, who perceived</l>
<l>the truth, exclaimed, “Rejoice Pelasgian men,</l>
<l>for we shall conquer; Troy will fall; although</l>
<l>the toil of war must long continue—so</l>
<l>the nine birds equal nine long years of war.”</l>
<l>And while he prophesied, the serpent, coiled</l>
<l>about the tree, was transformed to a stone,</l>
<l>curled crooked as a snake. </l>

    
<l>but Nereus stormed</l>
<l>in those Aonian waves, and not a ship</l>
<l>moved forward. Some declared that Neptune thus</l>
<l>was aiding Troy, because he built the walls</l>
<l>of that great city. Not so Calchas, son</l>
<l>of Thestor! He knew all the truth, and told</l>
<l>them plainly that a virgin's blood</l>
<l>alone might end a virgin goddess' wrath.</l>

    
<l>The public good at last prevailed above</l>
<l>affection, and the duty of a king</l>
<l>at last proved stronger than a father's love:</l>
<l>when Iphigenia as a sacrifice,</l>
<l>stood by the altar with her weeping maids</l>
<l>and was about to offer her chaste blood,</l>
<l>the goddess, moved by pity, spread a mist</l>
<l>before their eyes, amid the sacred rites</l>
<l>and mournful supplications. It is said</l>
<l>she left a hind there in the maiden's place</l>
<l>and carried Iphigenia away. The hind,</l>
<l>as it was fitting, calmed Diana's rage</l>
<l>and also calmed the anger of the sea.</l>
<l>The thousand ships received the winds astern</l>
<l>and gained the Phrygian shore.</l>

THE HOUSE OF FAME AND THE TROJAN CYGNUS

<l>There is a spot</l>
<l>convenient in the center of the world,</l>
<l>between the land and sea and the wide heavens,</l>
<l>the meeting of the threefold universe.</l>
<l>From there is seen all things that anywhere</l>
<l>exist, although in distant regions far;</l>
<l>and there all sounds of earth and space are heard.</l>

    
<l>Fame is possessor of this chosen place,</l>
<l>and has her habitation in a tower,</l>
<l>which aids her view from that exalted highs.</l>
<l>And she has fixed there numerous avenues,</l>
<l>and openings, a thousand, to her tower</l>
<l>and no gates with closed entrance, for the house</l>
<l>is open, night and day, of sounding brass,</l>
<l>reechoing the tones of every voice.</l>
<l>It must repeat whatever it may hear;</l>
<l>and there's no rest, and silence in no part.</l>
<l>There is no clamor; but the murmuring sound</l>
<l>of subdued voices, such as may arise</l>
<l>from waves of a far sea, which one may hear</l>
<l>who listens at a distance; or the sound</l>
<l>which ends a thunderclap, when Jupiter</l>
<l>has clashed black clouds together. Fickle crowds</l>
<l>are always in that hall, that come and go,</l>
<l>and myriad rumors—false tales mixed with true—</l>
<l>are circulated in confusing words.</l>
<l>Some fill their empty ears with all this talk,</l>
<l>and some spread elsewhere all that's told to them.</l>
<l>The volume of wild fiction grows apace,</l>
<l>and each narrator adds to what he hears.</l>

    
<l>Credulity is there and rash Mistake,</l>
<l>and empty Joy, and coward Fear alarmed</l>
<l>by quick Sedition, and soft Whisper—all</l>
<l>of doubtful life. Fame sees what things are done</l>
<l>in heaven and on the sea, and on the earth.</l>
<l>She spies all things in the wide universe.</l>


Achilles et Cygnus.

<l>Fame now had spread the tidings, a great fleet</l>
<l>of Greek ships was at that time on its way,</l>
<l>an army of brave men. The Trojans stood,</l>
<l>all ready to prevent the hostile Greeks</l>
<l>from landing on their shores. By the decree</l>
<l>of Fate, the first man killed of the invaders' force</l>
<l>was strong Protesilaus, by the spear</l>
<l>of valiant Hector, whose unthought-of power</l>
<l>at that time was discovered by the Greeks</l>
<l>to their great cost. The Phyrgians also learned,</l>
<l>at no small cost of blood, what warlike strength</l>
<l>came from the Grecian land. The Sigean shores</l>
<l>grew red with death-blood: Cygnus, Neptune's son,</l>
<l>there slew a thousand men: for which, in wrath,</l>
<l>Achilles pressed his rapid chariot</l>
<l>straight through the Trojan army; making a lane</l>
<l>with his great spear, shaped from a Pelion tree.</l>
<l>And as he sought through the fierce battle's press,</l>
<l>either for Cygnus or for Hector, he</l>
<l>met Cygnus and engaged at once with him</l>
<l>(Fate had preserved great Hector from such foe</l>
<l>till ten years from that day).</l>

    
<l>Cheering his steeds,</l>
<l>their white necks pressed upon the straining yoke,</l>
<l>he steered the chariot towards his foe,</l>
<l>and, brandishing the spear with his strong arm,</l>
<l>he cried, “Whoever you may be, you have</l>
<l>the consolation of a glorious death</l>
<l>you die by me, Haemonian Achilles!”</l>

    
<l>His heavy spear flew after the fierce words.</l>
<l>Although the spear was whirled direct and true,</l>
<l>yet nothing it availed with sharpened point.</l>
<l>It only bruised, as with a blunted stroke,</l>
<l>the breast of Cygnus! “By report we knew</l>
<l>of you before this battle, goddess born.”</l>
<l>The other answered him, “But why are you</l>
<l>surprised that I escape the threatened wound?”</l>
<l>(Achilles was surprised). “This helmet crowned,</l>
<l>great with its tawny horse-hair, and this shield,</l>
<l>broad-hollowed, on my left arm, are not held</l>
<l>for help in war: they are but ornament,</l>
<l>as Mars wears armor. All of them shall be</l>
<l>put off, and I will fight with you unhurt.</l>
<l>It is a privilege that I was born</l>
<l>not as you, of a Nereid but of him</l>
<l>whose powerful rule is over Nereus,</l>
<l>his daughters and their ocean.” So, he spoke.</l>

    
<l>Immediately he threw his spear against Achilles,</l>
<l>destined to pierce the curving shield through brass,</l>
<l>and through nine folds of tough bull's hide.</l>
<l>It stopped there, for it could not pierce the tenth.</l>
<l>The hero wrenched it out, and hurled again</l>
<l>a quivering spear at Cygnus, with great strength.</l>
<l>The Trojan stood unwounded and unharmed.</l>
<l>Nor did a third spear injure Cygnus, though</l>
<l>he stood there with his body all exposed.</l>
<l>Achilles raged at this, as a wild bull</l>
<l>in open circus, when with dreadful horns</l>
<l>he butts against the hanging purple robes</l>
<l>which stir his wrath and there observes how they</l>
<l>evade him, quite unharmed by his attack.</l>

    
<l>Achilles then examined his good spear,</l>
<l>to see if by some chance the iron point</l>
<l>was broken from it, but the point was firm,</l>
<l>fixed on the wooden shaft. “My hand is weak,”</l>
<l>he said, “but is it possible its strength</l>
<l>forsook me though it never has before?</l>
<l>For surely I had my accustomed strength,</l>
<l>when first I overthrew Lyrnessus' walls,</l>
<l>or when I won the isle of Tenedos</l>
<l>or Thebes (then under King Eetion)</l>
<l>and I drenched both with their own peoples' blood,</l>
<l>or when the river Caycus ran red</l>
<l>with slaughter of its people, or, when twice</l>
<l>Telephus felt the virtue of my spear.</l>
<l>On this field also, where such heaps lie slain,</l>
<l>my right hand surely has proved its true might;</l>
<l>and it is mighty.”</l>

    
<l>So he spoke of strength,</l>
<l>remembered. But as if in proof against</l>
<l>his own distrust, he hurled a spear against</l>
<l>Menoetes, a soldier in the Lycian ranks.</l>
<l>The sharp spear tore the victim's coat of mail</l>
<l>and pierced his breast beneath. Achilles, when</l>
<l>he saw his dying head strike on the earth</l>
<l>wrenched the same spear from out the reeking wound,</l>
<l>and said, “This is the hand, and this the spear</l>
<l>I conquered with; and I will use the same</l>
<l>against him who in luck escaped their power;</l>
<l>and the result should favor as I pray</l>
<l>the helpful gods.”</l>

    
<l>And, as he said such words,</l>
<l>in haste he hurled his ashen spear, again</l>
<l>at Cygnus. It went straight and struck unshunned.</l>
<l>Resounding on the shoulder of that foe,</l>
<l>it bounced back as if it hit a wall</l>
<l>or solid cliff. Yet when Achilles saw</l>
<l>just where the spear struck, Cygnus there</l>
<l>was stained with blood. He instantly rejoiced;</l>
<l>but vainly, for it was Menoetes' blood!</l>
<l>Then in a sudden rage, Achilles leaped</l>
<l>down headlong from his lofty chariot;</l>
<l>and, seeking his god-favored foe, he struck</l>
<l>in conflict fiercely, with his gleaming sword.</l>
<l>Although he saw that he had pierced both shield</l>
<l>and helmet through, he did not harm the foe—</l>
<l>his sword was even blunted on the flesh.</l>

    
<l>Achilles could not hold himself for rage,</l>
<l>but furious, with his sword-hilt and his shield</l>
<l>he battered wildly the uncovered face</l>
<l>and hollow-temples of his Trojan foe.</l>
<l>Cygnus gave way; Achilles rushed on him,</l>
<l>buffeting fiercely, so that he could not</l>
<l>recover from the shock. Fear seized upon</l>
<l>Cygnus, and darkness swam before his eyes.</l>
<l>Then, as he moved back with retreating steps,</l>
<l>a large stone hindered him and blocked his way.</l>
<l>His back pushed against this, Achilles seized</l>
<l>and dashed him violently to the ground.</l>
<l>Then pressing with buckler and hard knees the breast</l>
<l>of Cygnus, he unlaced the helmet thongs,</l>
<l>wound them about the foeman's neck and drew</l>
<l>them tightly under his chin, till Cygnus' throat</l>
<l>could take no breath of life. Achilles rose</l>
<l>eager to strip his conquered foe but found</l>
<l>his empty armor, for the god of ocean</l>
<l>had changed the victim into that white bird</l>
<l>whose name he lately bore.</l>


Caeneus.
CAENEUS TRANSFORMED INTO A BIRD

<l>There was a truce</l>
<l>for many days after this opening fight</l>
<l>while both sides resting, laid aside their arms.</l>
<l>A watchful guard patroled the Phrygian walls;</l>
<l>the Grecian trenches had their watchful guard.</l>
<l>Then, on a festal day, Achilles gave</l>
<l>the blood of a slain heifer to obtain</l>
<l>the favor of Athena for their cause.</l>
<l>The entrails burned upon the altar, while</l>
<l>the odor, grateful to the deities,</l>
<l>was mounting to the skies. When sacred rites</l>
<l>were done, a banquet for the heroes was</l>
<l>served on their tables. There the Grecian chiefs</l>
<l>reclined on couches; while they satisfied</l>
<l>themselves with roasted flesh, and banished cares:</l>
<l>and thirst with wine. Nor harp nor singing voice</l>
<l>nor long pipe made of boxwood pierced with holes,</l>
<l>delighted them. They talked of their own deeds</l>
<l>and valor, all that thrilling night: and even</l>
<l>the strength of enemies whom they had met</l>
<l>and overcome. What else could they admit</l>
<l>or think of, while the great Achilles spoke</l>
<l>or listened to them? But especially</l>
<l>the recent victory over Cygnus held</l>
<l>them ardent. Wonderful it seemed to them</l>
<l>that such a youth could be composed of flesh</l>
<l>not penetrable by the sharpest spear;</l>
<l>of flesh which blunted even hardened steel,</l>
<l>and never could be wounded. All the Greeks,</l>
<l>and even Achilles wondered at the thought.</l>

    
<l>Then Nestor said to them: “During your time,</l>
<l>Cygnus has been the only man you knew</l>
<l>who could despise all weapons and whose flesh</l>
<l>could not be pierced by thrust of sword or spear.</l>
<l>But long ago I saw another man</l>
<l>able to bear unharmed a thousand strokes,</l>
<l>Caeneus of Thessaly, Caeneus who lived</l>
<l>upon Mt. Othrys. He was famed in war</l>
<l>yet, strange to say, by birth he was a woman!”</l>

    
<l>Then all expressed the greatest wonderment,</l>
<l>and begged to hear the story of his life.</l>
<l>Achilles cried, “O eloquent old man!</l>
<l>The wisdom of our age! All of us wish</l>
<l>to hear, who was this Caeneus? Why was he</l>
<l>changed to the other sex? in what campaigns,</l>
<l>and in what wars was he so known to you?</l>
<l>Who conquered him, if any ever did?”</l>

    
<l>The aged man replied to them with care:—</l>
<l>“Although my great age is a harm to me,</l>
<l>and many actions of my early days</l>
<l>escape my memory; yet, most of them</l>
<l>are well remembered. Nothing of old days,</l>
<l>amid so many deeds of war and peace,</l>
<l>can be more firmly fixed upon my mind</l>
<l>than the strange story I shall tell of him.</l>

    
<l>“If long extent of years made anyone</l>
<l>a witness of most wonderful events</l>
<l>and many, truly I may say to you</l>
<l>that I have lived two hundred years; and now</l>
<l>have entered my third century.</l>
<l>The daughter of Elatus, Caenis, was</l>
<l>remarkable for charm—most beautiful</l>
<l>of all Thessalian maidens—many sighed</l>
<l>for her in vain through all the neighboring towns</l>
<l>and yours, Achilles, for that was her home.</l>
<l>But Peleus did not try to win her love,</l>
<l>for he was either married at that time</l>
<l>to your dear mother, or was pledged to her.</l>

    
<l>“Caenis never became the willing bride</l>
<l>of any suitor; but report declares,</l>
<l>while she was walking on a lonely shore,</l>
<l>the god of ocean saw and ravished her.</l>
<l>And in the joy of that love Neptune said,</l>
<l>‘Request of me whatever you desire,  </l>
<l>and nothing shall deny your dearest wish!’—</l>
<l>the story tells us that he made this pledge.</l>
<l>And Caenis said to Neptune, ‘The great wrong,</l>
<l>which I have suffered from you justifies</l>
<l>the wonderful request that I must make;</l>
<l>I ask that I may never suffer such</l>
<l>an injury again. Grant I may be</l>
<l>no longer woman, and I'll ask no more.’</l>

    
<l>while she was speaking to him, the last words</l>
<l>of her strange prayer were uttered in so deep,</l>
<l>in such a manly tone, it seemed indeed</l>
<l>they must be from a man.—That was a fact:</l>
<l>Neptune not only had allowed her prayer  </l>
<l>but made the new man proof against all wounds</l>
<l>of spear or sword. Rejoicing in the gift</l>
<l>he went his way as Caeneus Atracides,</l>
<l>spent years in every manful exercise,</l>
<l>and roamed the plains of northern Thessaly.</l>


Centaurorum et Lapitharum pugna.

<l>“The son of bold Ixion, Pirithous</l>
<l>wedding Hippodame, had asked as guests</l>
<l>the cloud-born centaurs to recline around</l>
<l>the ordered tables, in a cool cave, set</l>
<l>under some shading trees. Thessalian chiefs</l>
<l>were there and I myself was with them there.</l>
<l>The festal place resounded with the rout</l>
<l>in noisy clamor, singing nuptial verse;</l>
<l>and in the great room, filled with smoking fire,</l>
<l>the maiden came escorted by a crowd</l>
<l>of matrons and young married women; she</l>
<l>most beautiful of all that lovely throng.</l>

    
<l>“And so Pirithous, the fortunate son,</l>
<l>of bold Ixion, was so praised by all,</l>
<l>for his pure joy and lovely wife,</l>
<l>it seemed his very blessings must have led</l>
<l>to fatal harm: for savage Eurytus,</l>
<l>wildest of the wild centaurs, now inflamed</l>
<l>with sudden envy, drunkenness, and lust,</l>
<l>upset the tables and made havoc there</l>
<l>so dreadful, that the banquet suddenly</l>
<l>was changed from love to uproar. Seized by the hair,</l>
<l>the bride was violently dragged away.</l>
<l>When Eurytus caught up Hippodame</l>
<l>each one of all the centaurs took at will</l>
<l>the maid or matron that he longed for most.</l>
<l>The palace, seeming like a captured town,</l>
<l>resounded with affrighted shrieks of women.</l>
<l>At once we all sprang up. And Theseus cried,</l>

    
<l>“What madness, Eurytus, has driven you</l>
<l>to this vile wickedness! While I have life,</l>
<l>you dare attack Pirithous. You know</l>
<l>not what you do, for one wrong injures both!’</l>
<l>The valiant hero did not merely talk:</l>
<l>he pushed them off as they were pressing on,</l>
<l>and rescued her whom Eurytus had seized.</l>
<l>Since Eurytus could not defend such deeds</l>
<l>with words, he turned and beat with violent hands</l>
<l>the face of him who saved the bride and struck</l>
<l>his generous breast. By chance, an ancient bowl</l>
<l>was near at hand. This rough with figures carved,</l>
<l>the son of Aegeus caught and hurled it full</l>
<l>in that vile centaur's face. He, spouting out</l>
<l>thick gouts of blood, and bleeding from his wounds—</l>
<l>his brains and wine mixed,—kicked the blood-soaked sand.</l>

    
<l>His double membered centaur brothers, wild</l>
<l>with passion at his death, all shouted out,</l>
<l>‘To arms! to arms!’ Their courage raised by wine!</l>
<l>In their first onset, hurled cups flew about,</l>
<l>and shattered wine casks, hollow basins—things</l>
<l>before adapted to a banquet, now</l>
<l>for death and carnage in the furious fight.</l>

    
<l>Amycus first (Opinion's son) began to spoil</l>
<l>the inner sanctuary of its gifts.</l>
<l>He snatched up from that shrine a chandelier,</l>
<l>adorned with glittering lamps, and lifted high,</l>
<l>with all the force of one who strives to break</l>
<l>the bull s white neck with sacrificial axe,</l>
<l>he dashed it at the head of Celadon,</l>
<l>one of the Lapithae, and crushed his skull</l>
<l>into the features of his face. His eyes</l>
<l>leaped from his sockets, and the shattered bones</l>
<l>of his smashed face gave way so that his nose</l>
<l>was driven back and fastened in his throat.</l>
<l>But Belates of Pella tore away</l>
<l>a table-leg of maple wood and felled</l>
<l>Amycus to the ground; his sunken chin</l>
<l>cast down upon his breast; and, as he spat</l>
<l>his teeth out mixed with blood, a second blow</l>
<l>despatched him to the shades of Tartarus.</l>

    
<l>“Gryneus, seeing a smoking altar, cried,</l>
<l>‘Good use for this,’ with which words he raised up</l>
<l>that heavy, blazing altar. Hurling it</l>
<l>into the middle of the Lapithae,</l>
<l>he struck down Broteas and Orius:</l>
<l>Mycale, mother of that Orius,</l>
<l>was famous for her incantations,</l>
<l>which she had often used to conjure down</l>
<l>the shining twin-horns of the unwilling moon.</l>
<l>Exadius threatened, ‘You shall not escape!</l>
<l>Let me but have a weapon!’ And with that,</l>
<l>he whirled the antlers of a votive stag,</l>
<l>which he found there, hung on a tall pine-tree;</l>
<l>and with that double-branching horn he pierced</l>
<l>the eyes of Gryneus, and he gouged them out.</l>
<l>One eye stuck to the horn; the other rolled</l>
<l>down on his beard, to which it strictly clung</l>
<l>in dreadful clotted gore.</l>

    
<l>Then Rhoetus snatched</l>
<l>a blazing brand of plum-wood from an altar</l>
<l>and whirling it upon the right, smashed through</l>
<l>the temples of Charaxus, wonderful</l>
<l>with golden hair. Seized by the violent flames,</l>
<l>his yellow locks burned fiercely, as a field</l>
<l>of autumn grain; and even the scorching blood</l>
<l>gave from the sore wound a terrific noise</l>
<l>as a red-hot iron in pincers which the smith</l>
<l>lifts out and plunges in the tepid pool,</l>
<l>hissing and sizzling. Charaxus shook</l>
<l>the fire from his burnt locks; and heaved up on</l>
<l>his shoulders a large threshold stone torn from</l>
<l>the ground—a weight sufficient for a team</l>
<l>of oxen. The vast weight impeded him,</l>
<l>so that it could not even touch his foe—</l>
<l>and yet, the massive stone did hit his friend,</l>
<l>Cometes, who was standing near to him,</l>
<l>and crushed him down. Then Rhoetus, crazed with joy,</l>
<l>exulting yelled, ‘I pray that all of you</l>
<l>may be so strong!’ Wielding his half-burnt stake</l>
<l>with heavy blows again and again, he broke</l>
<l>the sutures of his enemy's skull, until</l>
<l>the bones were mingled with his oozing brains.</l>

    
<l>“Victorious, then rushed he upon Evagrus,</l>
<l>and Corythus and Dryas. First of these</l>
<l>was youthful Corythus, whose cheeks were then</l>
<l>just covered with soft down. When he fell dead,</l>
<l>Evagrus cried, ‘What glory do you get,</l>
<l>killing a boy?’ But Rhoetus did not give</l>
<l>him time for uttering one word more. He pushed</l>
<l>the red hot stake into the foeman's mouth,</l>
<l>while he still spoke, and down into his lungs.</l>
<l>He then pursued the savage Dryas, while</l>
<l>whirling the red fire fast about his head;</l>
<l>but not with like success, for, while he still</l>
<l>rejoiced in killings, Dryas turned and pierced</l>
<l>him with a stake where neck and shoulder meet.</l>

    
<l>“Rhoetus groaned and with a great effort pulled</l>
<l>the stake out from the bone, then fled away,</l>
<l>drenched in his blood. And Orneus followed him.</l>
<l>Lycabas fled, and Medon with a wound</l>
<l>in his right shoulder. Thaumas and Pisenor</l>
<l>and Mermerus fled with them. Mermerus,</l>
<l>who used to excell all others in a race,</l>
<l>ran slowly, crippled by a recent wound.</l>
<l>Pholus and Melaneus ran for their lives</l>
<l>and with them Abas, hunter of wild boars</l>
<l>and Asbolus, the augur, who in vain</l>
<l>had urged his friends to shun that hapless fight.</l>
<l>As Nessus joined the rout, he said to him,</l>
<l>‘You need not flee, for you shall be reserved</l>
<l>a victim for the bow of Hercules!’</l>

    
<l>but neither Lycidas, Eurynomus</l>
<l>nor Areos, nor Imbreus had escaped</l>
<l>from death: for all of these the strong right hand</l>
<l>of Dryas pierced, as they confronted him.</l>
<l>Crenaeus there received a wound in front.</l>
<l>Although he turned in flight, as he looked back,</l>
<l>a heavy javelin between his eyes</l>
<l>pierced through him, where his nose and forehead joined.</l>


    
<l>“In all this uproar, Aphidas lay flat,</l>
<l>in endless slumber from the wine he drank,</l>
<l>incessant, and his nerveless hand still held</l>
<l>the cup of mixed wine, as he lay full stretched,</l>
<l>upon a shaggy bear-skin from Mount Ossa.</l>
<l>When Phorbas saw him, harmless in that sleep,</l>
<l>he laid his fingers in his javelin's thong,</l>
<l>and shouted loudly, ‘Mix your wine, down there,</l>
<l>with waters of the Styx!’ And stopping talk,</l>
<l>let fly his javelin at the sleeping youth—</l>
<l>the ashen shaft, iron-tipped, was driven through</l>
<l>his neck, exposed, as he by chance lay there—</l>
<l>his head thrown back. He did not even feel</l>
<l>a touch of death—and from his deep-pierced throat</l>
<l>his crimson blood flowed out upon the couch,</l>
<l>and in the wine-bowl still grasped in his hand.</l>

    
<l>“I saw Petraeus when he strove to tear</l>
<l>up from the earth, an acorn-bearing oak.</l>
<l>And, while he struggled with it, back and forth,</l>
<l>and was just ready to wrench up the trunk,</l>
<l>Pirithous hurled a well aimed spear at him,</l>
<l>transfixed his ribs, and pinned his body tight,</l>
<l>writhing, to that hard oak: and Lycus fell</l>
<l>and Chromis fell, before Pirithous.</l>

    
<l>“They gave less glory to the conqueror</l>
<l>than Helops or than Dictys. Helops was</l>
<l>killed by a javelin, which pierced his temples</l>
<l>from the right side, clear through to his left ear.</l>
<l>And Dictys, running in a desperate haste,</l>
<l>hoping in vain, to escape Ixion's son,</l>
<l>slipped on the steep edge of a precipice;</l>
<l>and, as he fell down headlong crashed into</l>
<l>the top of a huge ash-tree, which impaled</l>
<l>his dying body on its broken spikes.</l>

    
<l>“Aphareus, eager to avenge him tried</l>
<l>to lift a rock from that steep mountain side;</l>
<l>but as he heaved, the son of Aegeus struck</l>
<l>him squarely with an oaken club; and smashed,</l>
<l>and broke the huge bones of that centaur's arm.</l>
<l>He has no time, and does not want to give</l>
<l>that useless foe to death. He leaps upon</l>
<l>the back of tall Bienor, never trained</l>
<l>to carry riders, and he fixed his knees</l>
<l>firm in the centaur's ribs, and holding tight</l>
<l>to the long hair, seized by his left hand, struck</l>
<l>and shattered the hard features and fierce face</l>
<l>and bony temples with his club of gnarled</l>
<l>strong oak. And with it, he struck to the ground</l>
<l>Nedymnus and Lycopes, dart expert,</l>
<l>and Hippasus, whose beard hid all his breast.</l>
<l>And Rhipheus taller than the highest trees</l>
<l>and Thereus, who would carry home alive</l>
<l>the raging bears, caught in Thessalian hills.</l>

    
<l>Demoleon could no longer stand and look</l>
<l>on Theseus and his unrestrained success.</l>
<l>He struggled with vast effort to tear up</l>
<l>an old pine, trunk and all, with its long roots,</l>
<l>and, failing shortly in that first attempt,</l>
<l>he broke it off and hurled it at his foe.</l>
<l>But Theseus saw the pine tree in its flight</l>
<l>and, warned by Pallas, got beyond its range—</l>
<l>his boast was, Pallas had directed him!</l>
<l>And yet, the missle was not launched in vain.</l>
<l>It sheared the left shoulder and the breast</l>
<l>from tall Crantor. He, Achilles, was</l>
<l>your father's armor bearer and was given</l>
<l>by King Amyntor, when he sued for peace.</l>

    
<l>“When Peleus at a distance saw him torn</l>
<l>and mangled, he exclaimed, ‘At least receive</l>
<l>this sacrifice, O Crantor! most beloved!</l>
<l>Dearest of young men!’ And with sturdy arm</l>
<l>and all his strength of soul as well, he hurled</l>
<l>his ashen lance against Demoleon,</l>
<l>which piercing through his shivered ribs, hung there</l>
<l>and quivered in the bones. The centaur wrenched</l>
<l>the wooden shaft out, with his frenzied hands,</l>
<l>but could not move the pointed head, which stuck</l>
<l>within his lungs. His very anguish gave</l>
<l>him such a desperation, that he rose</l>
<l>against his foe and trampled and beat down</l>
<l>the hero with his hoofs, Peleus allowed</l>
<l>the blows to fall on helm and ringing shield.</l>
<l>Protected so, he watched his time and thrust</l>
<l>up through the centaur's shoulder. By one stroke</l>
<l>he pierced two breasts, where horse and man-form met.</l>

    
<l>Before this, Peleus with the spear had killed</l>
<l>both Myles and Phlegraeus and with the sword</l>
<l>Iphinous and Clanis. Now he killed</l>
<l>Dorylas, who was clad in a wolfskin cap</l>
<l>and fought with curving bull's horns dripping blood.</l>

    
<l>“To him I said, for courage gave me strength,</l>
<l>‘Your horns! how much inferior to my steel!’—</l>
<l>and threw my spear. Since he could not avoid</l>
<l>the gleaming point, he held up his right hand</l>
<l>to shield his forehead from the threatened wound.</l>
<l>His hand was pierced and pinned against his forehead.</l>
<l>He shouted madly. Peleus, near him while</l>
<l>he stood there pinned and helpless with his wound,</l>
<l>struck him with sharp sword in the belly deep.</l>
<l>He leaped forth fiercely, as he trailed his bowels</l>
<l>upon the ground, with his entangled legs</l>
<l>treading upon them, bursting them, he fell</l>
<l>with empty belly, lifeless to the earth.</l>

    
<l>“Cyllarus, beauty did not save your life—</l>
<l>if beauty is in any of your tribe—</l>
<l>your golden beard was in its early growth,</l>
<l>your golden hair came flowing to your shoulders. </l>
<l>in your bright face there was a pleasing glance.</l>
<l>The neck and shoulders and the hands and breast,:</l>
<l>and every aspect of his human form</l>
<l>resembled those admired statues which</l>
<l>our gifted artists carve. Even the shape</l>
<l>of the fine horse beneath the human form</l>
<l>was perfect too. Give him the head and neck</l>
<l>of a full-blooded horse, and he would seem</l>
<l>a steed for Castor, for his back was shaped</l>
<l>so comfortable to be sat upon</l>
<l>and muscle swelled upon his arching chest.</l>
<l>His lustrous body was as black as pitch,</l>
<l>and yet his legs and flowing tail</l>
<l>were white as snow.</l>

    
<l>Many a female of his kind</l>
<l>loved him, but only Hylonome gained</l>
<l>his love. There was no other centaur maid</l>
<l>so beautiful as she within the woods.</l>
<l>By coaxing ways she had won Cyllarus,</l>
<l>by loving and confessing love. By daintiness,</l>
<l>so far as that was possible in one</l>
<l>of such a form, she held his love; for now</l>
<l>she smoothed her long locks with a comb; and now</l>
<l>she decked herself with rosemary and now</l>
<l>with violets or with roses in her hair;</l>
<l>and sometimes she wore lilies, white as snow;</l>
<l>and twice each day she bathed her lovely face,</l>
<l>in the sweet stream that falls down from the height</l>
<l>of wooded Pagasa; and daily, twice</l>
<l>she dipped her body in the stream. She wore</l>
<l>upon her shoulders and left side a skin,</l>
<l>greatly becoming, of selected worth.</l>

    
<l>“Their love was equal, and together they</l>
<l>would wander over mountain-sides, and rest</l>
<l>together in cool caves; and so it was,</l>
<l>they went together to that palace-cave,</l>
<l>known to the Lapithae. Together they</l>
<l>fought fiercely in this battle, side by side.</l>
<l>Thrown by an unknown hand, a javelin pierced</l>
<l>Cyllarus, just below the fatal spot</l>
<l>where the chest rises to the neck—his heart,</l>
<l>though only slightly wounded, grew quite cold,</l>
<l>and his whole body felt cold, afterwards,</l>
<l>as quickly as the weapon was drawn out.</l>
<l>Then Hylonome held in her embrace</l>
<l>the dying body; fondled the dread wound</l>
<l>and, fixing her lips closely to his lips</l>
<l>endeavored to hold back his dying breath.</l>
<l>But soon she saw that he indeed was dead.</l>
<l>With mourning words, which clamor of the fight</l>
<l>prevented me from hearing, she threw herself</l>
<l>on the spear that pierced her Cyllarus and fell</l>
<l>upon his breast, embracing him in death.</l>


    
<l>“Another sight still comes before my eyes,</l>
<l>the centaur Phaeocomes with his log.</l>
<l>He wore six lion skins well wrapped around</l>
<l>his body, and with fixed connecting knots</l>
<l>they covered him, both horse and man. He hurled</l>
<l>a trunk two yokes of oxen scarce could move</l>
<l>and struck the hapless son of Olenus</l>
<l>a crushing blow upon the head. The broad</l>
<l>round dome was shattered, and his dying brains</l>
<l>oozed out through hollow nostrils, mouth, and ears,</l>
<l>as curdled milk seeps down through oaken twigs;</l>
<l>or other liquors, crushed out under weights,</l>
<l>flow through a well-pierced sieve and, thick,</l>
<l>squeeze out through numerous holes.</l>

    
<l>As he began</l>
<l>to spoil his victim—and your father can</l>
<l>affirm the truth of this—I thrust my sword</l>
<l>deep in the wretch's groin. Chthonius, too,</l>
<l>and Teleboas fell there by my sword.</l>
<l>The former had a two-pronged stick as his</l>
<l>sole weapon, and the other had a spear,</l>
<l>with which the wounded me. You see the scar.</l>
<l>The old scar still is surely visible!</l>

    
<l>“Those were my days of youth and strength, and then</l>
<l>I ought to have warred against the citadel</l>
<l>of Pergama. I could have checked, or even</l>
<l>vanquished, the arms of Hector: but, alas,</l>
<l>Hector had not been born, or was perhaps</l>
<l>a boy. Old age has dulled my youthful strength.</l>
<l>What use is it, to speak of Periphas,</l>
<l>who overcame Pyretus, double-formed?</l>
<l>Why tell of Ampyx, who with pointless shaft,</l>
<l>victorious thrust Echeclus through the face?</l>
<l>Macareus, hurling a heavy crowbar pierced</l>
<l>Erigdupus and laid him low.</l>
<l>A hunting spear that Nessus strongly hurled,</l>
<l>was buried in the groin of Cymelus.</l>
<l>Do not believe that Mopsus, son of Ampycus,</l>
<l>was merely a prophet of events to come,</l>
<l>he slew a daring two-formed monster there.</l>
<l>Hodites tried in vain to speak, before</l>
<l>his death, but could not, for his tongue was nailed</l>
<l>against his chin, his chin against his throat.</l>

    
<l>“Five of the centaurs Caeneus put to death:</l>
<l>Styphelus, Bromus, and Antimachus,</l>
<l>Elymus, and Pyracmos with his axe.</l>
<l>I have forgot their wounds but noted well</l>
<l>their names and number. Latreus, huge of limb,</l>
<l>had killed and stripped Emathian Halesus.</l>
<l>Now in his armor he came rushing out,</l>
<l>in years he was between old age and youth;</l>
<l>but he retained the vigor of his youth;</l>
<l>his temples showed his hair was mixed with grey.</l>
<l>Conspicuous for his Macedonian lance</l>
<l>and sword and shield, facing both sides—each way,</l>
<l>he insolently clashed his arms; and while</l>
<l>he rode poured out these words in empty air.</l>

    
<l>“ ‘Shall I put up with one like you, O Caeneus?</l>
<l>For you are still a woman in my sight.</l>
<l>Have you forgot your birth or that disgrace</l>
<l>by which you won reward—at what a price</l>
<l>you got the false resemblance to a man?!</l>
<l>Consider both your birth, and what you have</l>
<l>submitted to! Take up a distaff, and</l>
<l>wool basket! Twist your threads with practiced thumb!</l>
<l>Leave warfare to your men!’</l>

    
<l>“While puffed-up pride</l>
<l>was vaunting out such nonsense, Caeneus hurled</l>
<l>a spear and pierced the stretched out running side,</l>
<l>just where the man was joined upon the horse.</l>

    
<l>“The Centaur, Latreus, raved with pain and struck</l>
<l>with his great pike, the face of Caeneus.</l>
<l>His pike rebounded as the hail that slants</l>
<l>up from the roof; or as a pebble might</l>
<l>rebound from hollow drum. Then coming near,</l>
<l>he tried to drive a sword into the hard side</l>
<l>of Caeneus, but it could not make a wound.</l>
<l>‘Aha!’ he cried, ‘this will not get you off.</l>
<l>The good edge of my sword will take your life,</l>
<l>although the point is blunt!’ He turned the edge</l>
<l>against the flank of Caeneus and swung round</l>
<l>the hero's loins with his long, curving arm.</l>
<l>The flesh resounded like a marble block,</l>
<l>the keen blade shattered on the unyielding skin.</l>

    
<l>“And, after Caeneus had exposed his limbs</l>
<l>unhurt to Latreus, who stood there amazed,</l>
<l>‘Come now,’ he said, ‘and let us try my steel</l>
<l>against your body!’ And, clear to the hilt,</l>
<l>down through the monster's shoulder-blade he plunged</l>
<l>his deadly sword and, turning it again,</l>
<l>deep in the Centaur's entrails, made new wounds</l>
<l>within his wound.</l>

    
<l>“Then, quite beside themselves,</l>
<l>the double-natured monsters rushed against</l>
<l>that single-handed youth with huge uproar,</l>
<l>and thrust and hurled their weapons all at him.</l>
<l>Their blunted weapons fell and he remained</l>
<l>unharmed and without even a mark.”</l>

    
<l>“That strange sight left them speechless. ‘Oh what shame!’</l>
<l>at length cried Monychus, ‘Our mighty host,—</l>
<l>a nation of us, are defeated and defied</l>
<l>by one who hardly is a man. Although</l>
<l>indeed, he is a man, and we have proved,</l>
<l>by our weak actions, we are certainly</l>
<l>what he was! Shame on us! Oh, what if we</l>
<l>have twofold strength, of what avail our huge</l>
<l>and mighty limbs, doubly united in</l>
<l>the strongest, hugest bodies in this world?</l>
<l>And how can I believe that we were born</l>
<l>of any goddess? It is surely vain</l>
<l>to claim descent of great Ixion, who</l>
<l>high-souled, sought Juno for his mighty mate;</l>
<l>imagine it, while we are conquered by</l>
<l>an enemy, who is but half a man!</l>
<l>Wake up! and let us heap tree-trunks and stones</l>
<l>and mountains on him! Crush his stubborn life!</l>
<l>Let forests smother him to death! Their weight</l>
<l>will be as deadly as a hundred wounds!’</l>

    
<l>“While he was raving, by some chance he found</l>
<l>a tree thrown down there by the boisterous wind:</l>
<l>example to the rest, he threw that tree</l>
<l>against the powerful foe; and in short time</l>
<l>Othrys was bare of trees, and Pelion had no shade.</l>
<l>Buried under that mountainous forest heap,</l>
<l>Caeneus heaved up against the weight of oaks</l>
<l>upon his brawny shoulders piled. But, as</l>
<l>the load increased above his face and head,</l>
<l>he could not draw a breath. Gasping for life,</l>
<l>he strove to lift his head into the air,</l>
<l>and sometimes he convulsed the towering mass,</l>
<l>as if great Ida, now before our eyes,</l>
<l>should tremble with some heaving of the earth.</l>

    
<l>“What happened to him could not well be known.</l>
<l>Some thought his body was borne down by weight</l>
<l>into the vast expanse of Tartarus.</l>
<l>The son of Ampycus did not agree,</l>
<l>for from the middle of the pile we saw</l>
<l>a bird with golden wings mount high in air.</l>
<l>Before or since, I never saw the like.</l>

    
<l>“When Mopsus was aware of that bird's flight—</l>
<l>it circled round the camp on rustling wings—</l>
<l>with eyes and mind he followed it and shouted aloud:</l>
<l>‘Hail, glory of the Lapithaean race,</l>
<l>their greatest hero, now a bird unique!’</l>
<l>and we believed the verdict of the seer.</l>

    
<l>“Our grief increased resentment, and we bore</l>
<l>it with disgust that one was overwhelmed</l>
<l>by such a multitude. Then in revenge</l>
<l>we plied our swords, till half our foes were dead,</l>
<l>and only flight and darkness saved the rest.”</l>


Periclymenus.
PERICLYMENUS IN COMBAT WITH HERCULES

<l>Nestor had hardly told this marvellous tale</l>
<l>of bitter strife betwixt the Lapithae</l>
<l>and those half-human, vanquished Centaurs, when</l>
<l>Tlepolemus, incensed because no word</l>
<l>of praise was given to Hercules, replied</l>
<l>in this way; “Old sir, it is very strange,</l>
<l>you have neglected to say one good word</l>
<l>in praise of Hercules. My father told</l>
<l>me often, that he overcame in battle</l>
<l>those cloud born centaurs.”</l>

    
<l>Nestor, very loth,</l>
<l>replied, “Why force me to recall old wrongs,</l>
<l>to uncover sorrow buried by the years,</l>
<l>that made me hate your father? It is true</l>
<l>his deeds were wonderful beyond belief,</l>
<l>heaven knows, and filled the earth with well earned praise</l>
<l>which I should rather wish might be denied.</l>
<l>Deiphobus, the wise Polydamas, and even</l>
<l>great Hector get no praise from me.</l>
<l>Your father, I recall once overthrew</l>
<l>Messene's walls and with no cause destroyed</l>
<l>Elis and Pylos and with fire and sword</l>
<l>ruined my own loved home. I cannot name</l>
<l>all whom he killed. But there were twelve of us,</l>
<l>the sons of Neleus and all warrior youths,</l>
<l>and all those twelve but me alone he killed.</l>
<l>Ten of them met the common fate of war,</l>
<l>but sadder was the death of Periclymenus.</l>

    
<l>“Neptune, the founder of my family,</l>
<l>had granted him a power to assume</l>
<l>whatever shape he chose, and when he wished</l>
<l>to lay that shape aside. When he, in vain,</l>
<l>had been transformed to many other shapes</l>
<l>he turned into the form of that bird, which</l>
<l>is wont to carry in his crooked talons</l>
<l>the forked lightnings, favorite bird of Jove.</l>
<l>With wings and crooked bill and sharp-hooked talons,</l>
<l>he assailed and tore the face of Hercules.</l>
<l>But, when he soared away on eagle wings</l>
<l>up to the clouds and hovered, poised in air,</l>
<l>that hero aimed his too unerring bow</l>
<l>and hit him where the new wing joined his side.</l>
<l>The wound was not large, but his sinews cut</l>
<l>failed to uphold him, and denied his wings</l>
<l>their strength and motion. He fell down to earth;</l>
<l>his weakened pinions could not catch the air.</l>
<l>And the sharp arrow, which had lightly pierced</l>
<l>the wing, was driven upward through the side</l>
<l>into the left part of my brother's neck.</l>

    
<l>“O noble leader of the Rhodian fleet,</l>
<l>why should I sing the praise of Hercules?</l>
<l>But for my brothers I take no revenge</l>
<l>except withholding praise of his great deeds.</l>
<l>With you, my friendship will remain secure.”</l>

THE DEATH OF ACHILLES

<l>When Nestor with his honied tongue had told</l>
<l>these tales of old, they all took wine again</l>
<l>and they arose and gave the night to sleep.</l>


Achillis mors.

<l>But Neptune, who commands the ocean waves,</l>
<l>lamented with a father's grief his son,</l>
<l>whose person he had changed into a bird—</l>
<l>the swan of Phaethon, and towards Achilles,</l>
<l>grim victor in the fight, his lasting hate</l>
<l>made him pursue resentment far beyond</l>
<l>the ordinary manner of the gods.</l>
<l>After nine years of war he spoke these words,</l>
<l>addressing long haired Sminthean Apollo:</l>

    
<l>“O nephew the most dear to me of all</l>
<l>my brother's sons, with me you built in vain</l>
<l>the walls of Troy: you must be lost in grief,</l>
<l>when you look on those towers so soon to fall?</l>
<l>Or do you not lament the multitudes</l>
<l>slain in defence of them—To name but one:</l>

    
<l>“Does not the ghost of Hector, dragged around</l>
<l>his Pergama, appear to you? And yet</l>
<l>the fierce Achilles, who is bloodstained more</l>
<l>than slaughtering war, lives on this earth,</l>
<l>for the destruction of our toil. Let him</l>
<l>once get into my power, and I will make</l>
<l>him feel the action of my triple spear.</l>
<l>But, since I may not meet him face to face,</l>
<l>do you with sudden arrow give him death.”</l>

    
<l>The Delian god, Apollo, gave assent,</l>
<l>both for his own hate and his uncle's rage.</l>
<l>Veiled in a cloud, he found the Trojan host</l>
<l>and, there, while bloody strife went on, he saw</l>
<l>the hero Paris shoot at intervals</l>
<l>his arrows at the nameless host of Greeks.</l>
<l>Revealing his divinity, he said:</l>

    
<l>“Why spend your arrows on the common men</l>
<l>if you would serve your people, take good aim</l>
<l>at great Achilles and at last avenge</l>
<l>your hapless brothers whom he gave to death.”</l>
<l>He pointed out Achilles—laying low</l>
<l>the Trojan warriors with his mighty spear.</l>
<l>On him he turned the Trojan's willing bow</l>
<l>and guided with his hand the fatal shaft.</l>
<l>It was the first joy that old Priam knew</l>
<l>since Hector's death. So then Achilles you,</l>
<l>who overcame the mighty, were subdued</l>
<l>by a coward who seduced a Grecian wife!</l>
<l>Ah, if you could not die by manly hands,</l>
<l>your choice had been the axe.</l>

    
<l>Now that great terror of the Trojan race,</l>
<l>the glory and defence of the Pelasgians,</l>
<l>Achilles, first in war, lay on the pyre.</l>
<l>The god of Fire first armed, then burned, his limbs.</l>
<l>And now he is but ashes; and of him, so great,</l>
<l>renowned and mighty, but a pitiful</l>
<l>handful of small dust insufficient for</l>
<l>a little urn! But all his glory lives</l>
<l>enough to fill the world—a great reward.</l>
<l>And in that glory is his real life:</l>
<l>in a true sense he will never know the void</l>
<l>of Tartarus.</l>

    
<l>But soon his very shield—</l>
<l>that men might know to whom it had belonged—</l>
<l>brings war, and arms are taken for his arms.</l>
<l>Neither Diomed nor Ajax called the less</l>
<l>ventured to claim the hero's mighty shield.</l>
<l>Menelaus and other warlike chiefs,</l>
<l>even Agamemnon, all withdrew their claims.</l>
<l>Only the greater Ajax and Ulysses</l>
<l>had such assurance that they dared contest</l>
<l>for that great prize. Then Agamemnon chose</l>
<l>to avoid the odium of preferring one.</l>
<l>He bade the Argolic chieftains take their seats</l>
<l>within the camp and left to all of them</l>
<l>the hearing and decision of the cause.</l>
