<text>
    
Achelous et Hercules.
HERCULES AND ACHELOUS

To him the hero, who proclaimed himself<lb/>
a favored son of Neptune, answered now;<lb/>
“Declare the reason of your heavy sighs,<lb/>
and how your horn was broken?” And at once<lb/>
the Calydonian River-God replied,<lb/>
binding with reeds his unadorned rough locks:<lb/>

    
“It is a mournful task you have required,<lb/>
for who can wish to tell his own disgrace?<lb/>
But truly I shall speak without disguise,<lb/>
for my defeat, if rightly understood,<lb/>
should be my glory.—Even to have fought<lb/>
in battle with a hero of such might,<lb/>
affords me consolation.<lb/>

    
“Deianira<lb/>
(you may have heard some tales of her) was once<lb/>
the envied hope of many. She was then<lb/>
a lovely virgin.—I, among the rest<lb/>
who loved this maiden, entered the fair home<lb/>
of her great father Oeneus, and I said;<lb/>

    
“ ‘Consider all my claims, Parthaon's son,<lb/>
for I am come to plead your daughter's cause<lb/>
and mine—So you may make me son-in-law.,—’<lb/>
no sooner was it said, than Hercules<lb/>
in such words also claimed the virgin's hand:<lb/>
all others quickly yielded to our claims.<lb/>

    
“He boasted his descent from Jupiter;<lb/>
the glory of his labors and great deeds<lb/>
performed at his unjust stepmother's wish.<lb/>

    
“But as he was not then a God, it seemed<lb/>
disgraceful if my state should yield my right;<lb/>
so I contended with these haughty words,<lb/>
‘Why should this alien of a foreign land,<lb/>
contending for your daughter, match himself<lb/>
to me! king of the waters in this realm!<lb/>
For as I wind around, across your lands,<lb/>
I must be of your people, and a part<lb/>
of your great state. Oh, let it not be said,<lb/>
because the jealous Juno had no thought<lb/>
to punish me by labors, my descent<lb/>
is not so regal! This tremendous boast,<lb/>
that you, Alcmena's son, are sprung from Jove,<lb/>
falls at the touch of truth;—or it reveals<lb/>
the shame of a weak mother, who so gained<lb/>
your doubtful glory of descent from Heaven!<lb/>
Prove your descent from Jupiter is false,<lb/>
or else confess you are the son of shame!’<lb/>

    
“But Hercules, unable to control<lb/>
the flame of his great wrath, scowled as I spoke.<lb/>
He briefly answered me, ‘My hand excels<lb/>
my tongue; let me now overcome in fight,<lb/>
and I may suffer your offence of words.’<lb/>

    
“Full of unvented rage he rushed on me,<lb/>
but firm I stood, ashamed to yield a foot—<lb/>
I had so largely boasted, no retreat was left,<lb/>
and so I doffed my green robe—Striking guard,<lb/>
with clenched hands doubled at my breast,<lb/>
I stood my ground. He scooped up in his hand<lb/>
fine, yellow dust; and tossed it on the air<lb/>
so that the tawny powder sprinkled us;<lb/>
quick-shifting then he sought to strike my neck,<lb/>
or feint at my quick-moving legs, and turn<lb/>
swift moving to attack me at all points.<lb/>
But as a huge cliff in the sea remains<lb/>
unmoved, unshaken by the sounding waves,<lb/>
so my great size, against his vain attacks,<lb/>
defended me securely—Back we went;<lb/>
retiring for a space; then rushed again<lb/>
together, furious, and with foot to foot,<lb/>
determined not to yield, defiant stood,<lb/>
till, forward-bending from my waist and hips,<lb/>
I pressed my forehead against his and locked<lb/>
his fingers into mine: so, have I seen<lb/>
two strong bulls rush in combat for the good<lb/>
of some smooth heifer in the pasture—while<lb/>
the herd a-tremble and uncertain, wait;<lb/>
ready to give allegiance to the one<lb/>
most worthy of dominion.<lb/>

    
“Thrice in vain<lb/>
Hercules strove to push my breast from his,<lb/>
but I pressed ever closer—till, the fourth<lb/>
attempt succeeding, he unloosed my grip,<lb/>
and breaking from my circling arms drew back,<lb/>
and struck me such a buffet with his hand,<lb/>
it twisted me about, and instantly<lb/>
he clung with all his weight upon my back—<lb/>

    
“Believe me I have not suppressed the truth.<lb/>
Nor shall I try to gain applause not due:<lb/>
I seemed to bear a mountain on my back. —<lb/>
straining and dripping sweat, I broke his hold,—<lb/>
with great exertion I unlocked his grip.<lb/>
He pressed upon me, as I strained for breath,<lb/>
preventing a renewal of my strength,<lb/>
and seized upon my neck. Then at the last,<lb/>
my bent knee went down on the gritty earth,<lb/>
I bit the sand. So, worsted in my strength,<lb/>
I sought diversion by an artifice,<lb/>
and changed me to a serpent.—I then slipped<lb/>
from his tight clutches my great length, and coiled<lb/>
my body now transformed to snaky folds—<lb/>
hissing I darted my divided tongue.<lb/>

    
“But Hercules, Alcides, only laughed<lb/>
and in derision of my scheming, said,<lb/>
‘It was the pastime of my cradle days<lb/>
to strangle better snakes than you—and though<lb/>
your great length may excel all of your kind,<lb/>
how small a part of that Lernaean snake<lb/>
would you—one serpent be? It grew from wounds<lb/>
I gave (at first it had one hundred heads)<lb/>
and every time I severed one head from<lb/>
its neck two grew there in the place of one,<lb/>
by which its strength increased. This creature then<lb/>
outbranching with strong serpents, sprung from death<lb/>
and thriving on destruction, I destroyed.—<lb/>
What do you think will then become of you,<lb/>
disguised so in deceitful serpent-form,<lb/>
wielding a borrowed weapon not your own<lb/>

    
“And after he had ridiculed me thus,<lb/>
he gouged his fingers underneath my jaws,<lb/>
so that my throat was tortured, as if squeezed<lb/>
with forceps, while I struggled in his grip.<lb/>

    
“Twice was I vanquished, there remained to me<lb/>
a third form so again I changed to seem<lb/>
a savage bull, and with my limbs renewed<lb/>
in that form fought once more. He threw his arms<lb/>
about the left side of my ponderous neck,<lb/>
and dragging on me followed as I ran.<lb/>
He seized on my hard horns, and, tugging turned<lb/>
and twisted me, until he fastened them<lb/>
firm in the surface of the earth; and pushed<lb/>
me, helpless, to the shifting sand beneath.<lb/>
Not yet content he laid his fierce right hand<lb/>
on my tough horn, and broke and tore it from<lb/>
my mutilated head.—This horn, now heaped<lb/>
with fruits delicious and sweet-smelling flowers,<lb/>
the Naiads have held sacred from that hour,<lb/>
devoted to the bounteous goddess Plenty.’<lb/>

    
All this the River-god said; then a nymph,<lb/>
a lovely nymph like fair Diana dressed,<lb/>
whose locks were flowing down on either side,<lb/>
came graceful to the board, and brought to them<lb/>
of Autumn's plenty in an ample horn,<lb/>
and gave to them selected apples for<lb/>
a second course.<lb/>

    
And now, as early dawn<lb/>
appeared, and as the rising sunlight flashed<lb/>
on golden summits of surrounding hills,<lb/>
the young men waited not until the stream<lb/>
subsiding, had resumed its peaceful way,<lb/>
but all arose, reluctant, and went forth.<lb/>

    
Then Achelous, in his moving waves,<lb/>
hid his fine rustic features and his head,<lb/>
scarred by the wound which gave the Horn of Plenty.<lb/>


Nessus. Herculis mors.
NESSUS AND THE DEATH OF HERCULES

Loss of his horn had greatly humbled him,<lb/>
it was so cherished though his only loss, —<lb/>
but he could hide the sad disgrace with reeds<lb/>
and willow boughs entwined about his head.<lb/>

    
O, Nessus! your fierce passion for the same<lb/>
maid utterly destroyed even you, pierced through<lb/>
the body by a flying arrow-point.<lb/>

    
Returning to the city of his birth<lb/>
great Hercules, the son of Jupiter,<lb/>
with his new bride, arrived upon the bank<lb/>
of swift Evenus—after winter rains<lb/>
had swollen it so far beyond its wont,<lb/>
that, full of eddies, it was found to be<lb/>
impassable. The hero stood there, brave<lb/>
but anxious for his bride. Nessus, the centaur,<lb/>
strong-limbed and well-acquainted with those fords,<lb/>
came up to him and said, “Plunge in the flood<lb/>
and swim with unimpeded strength—for with<lb/>
my help she will land safely over there.”<lb/>

    
And so the hero, with no thought of doubt,<lb/>
trusted the damsel to the centaur's care,<lb/>
though she was pale and trembling with her fear<lb/>
of the swift river and the centaur's aid.<lb/>

    
This done, the hero, burdened as he was<lb/>
with quiver and the lion skin (for he<lb/>
had tossed his club and curving bow across<lb/>
the river to the other bank), declared,<lb/>
“Since I have undertaken it, at once<lb/>
this rushing water must be overcome.”<lb/>
And instantly, he plunged in without thought<lb/>
of where he might cross with most ease, for so<lb/>
he scorned to take advantage of smooth water.<lb/>

    
And after he had gained the other bank,<lb/>
while picking up his bow which there was thrown,<lb/>
he heard his wife's voice, anxious for his help.<lb/>
He called to Nessus who was in the act<lb/>
then to betray his trust: “Vain confidence!<lb/>
You are not swift enough, vile ravisher!<lb/>
You two-formed monster Nessus, I warn you!<lb/>
Hear me, and never dare to come between<lb/>
me and my love. If fear has no restraint,<lb/>
your father's dreadful fate on whirling wheel,<lb/>
should frighten you from this outrageous act:<lb/>
for you cannot escape, although you trust<lb/>
the fleet-foot effort of a rapid horse.<lb/>
I cannot overtake you with my feet<lb/>
but I can shoot and halt you with a wound.”<lb/>

    
his deed sustained the final warning word.<lb/>
He shot an arrow through the centaur's back,<lb/>
so that the keen barb was exposed beyond<lb/>
his bleeding breast. He tore it from both wounds,<lb/>
and life-blood spurted instantly, mixed with<lb/>
the deadly poison of Lernaean hydra.<lb/>
This Nessus caught, and muttering, “I shall not<lb/>
die unavenged”, he gave his tunic, soaked<lb/>
with blood to Deianira as a gift;<lb/>
and said, “Keep this to strengthen waning love.”<lb/>

    
Now many years passed by, and all the deeds,<lb/>
and labors of the mighty Hercules,<lb/>
gave to the wide world his unequalled fame;<lb/>
and finally appeased the hatred of<lb/>
his fierce stepmother.<lb/>

    
All victorious<lb/>
returning from Oechalia, he prepared<lb/>
to offer sacrifice, when at Cenaeum,<lb/>
upon an altar he had built to Jupiter,<lb/>
but tattling Rumor, swollen out of truth<lb/>
from small beginning to a wicked lie,<lb/>
declared brave Hercules, Amphitryon's son,<lb/>
was burning for the love of Iole.<lb/>
And Deianira—his fond wife—convinced<lb/>
herself, the wicked rumor must be true.<lb/>

    
Alarmed at the report of his new love,<lb/>
at first, poor wife, she was dissolved in tears,<lb/>
and then she sank in grievous misery.<lb/>
But soon in angry mood, she rose and said:<lb/>

    
“Why should I give up to my sorrow while<lb/>
I drown my wretched spirit in weak tears?<lb/>
Let me consider an effectual check—<lb/>
while it is possible—even before<lb/>
she comes, invader of my lawful bed:<lb/>
shall I be silent or complain of it?<lb/>
Must I go back to Calydon or stay?<lb/>
Shall I depart unbidden, from my house?<lb/>
Or, if no other method can prevail,<lb/>
shall I oppose my rival's first approach?<lb/>
O shade of Meleager, let me prove<lb/>
I am yet worthy to be called your sister;<lb/>
and in the desperate slaughter of this rival,<lb/>
the world, astonished, may be taught to fear<lb/>
the vengeance of an injured woman's rage.”<lb/>

    
So, torn by many moods, at last her mind<lb/>
fixed on one thought:—she might still keep his love,<lb/>
could certainly restore it, if she sent<lb/>
to him the tunic soaked in Nessus' blood.<lb/>

    
Unknowingly, she gave the fatal cause<lb/>
of her own woe to trusting Lichas, whom<lb/>
she urged in gentle words to take the gift,<lb/>
from her to her loved husband Hercules.<lb/>
He, unsuspecting, put the tunic on,<lb/>
all covered with Lernaean hydra's poison.<lb/>

    
The hero then was casting frankincense<lb/>
into the sacred flames, and pouring wine<lb/>
on marble altars, as his holy prayers<lb/>
were floating to the Gods. The hallowed heat<lb/>
striking upon his poisoned vesture, caused<lb/>
Echidna-bane to melt into his flesh.<lb/>

    
As long as he was able he withstood<lb/>
the torture. His great fortitude was strong.<lb/>
But when at last his anguish overcame<lb/>
even his endurance, he filled all the wild<lb/>
of Oeta with his cries: he overturned<lb/>
those hallowed altars, then in frenzied haste<lb/>
he strove to pull the tunic from his back.<lb/>
The poisoned garment, cleaving to him, ripped<lb/>
his skin, heat-shriveled, from his burning flesh.<lb/>
Or, tightening on him, as his great strength pulled,<lb/>
stripped with it the great muscles from his limbs,<lb/>
leaving his huge bones bare.<lb/>

    
Even his blood<lb/>
audibly hissed, as red-hot blades when they<lb/>
are plunged in water, so the burning bane<lb/>
boiled in his veins. Great perspiration streamed<lb/>
from his dissolving body, as the heat<lb/>
consumed his entrails; and his sinews cracked,<lb/>
brittle when burnt. The marrow in his bones<lb/>
dissolved, as it absorbed the venom-heat.<lb/>

There was no limit to his misery;<lb/>
raising both hands up towards the stars of heaven,<lb/>
he cried, “Come Juno, feast upon my death;<lb/>
feast on me, cruel one, look down from your<lb/>
exalted seat; behold my dreadful end<lb/>
and glut your savage heart! Oh, if I may<lb/>
deserve some pity from my enemy,<lb/>
from you I mean, this hateful life of mine<lb/>
take from me—sick with cruel suffering<lb/>
and only born for toil. The loss of life<lb/>
will be a boon to me, and surely is<lb/>
a fitting boon, such as stepmothers give!<lb/>

    
“Was it for this I slew Busiris, who<lb/>
defiled his temples with the strangers' blood?<lb/>
For this I took his mother's strength from fierce<lb/>
antaeus—that I did not show a fear<lb/>
before the Spanish shepherd's triple form?<lb/>
Nor did I fear the monstrous triple form<lb/>
of Cerberus.—And is it possible<lb/>
my hands once seized and broke the strong bull's horns?<lb/>
And Elis knows their labor, and the waves<lb/>
of Stymphalus, and the Parthenian woods.<lb/>
For this the prowess of these hands secured<lb/>
the Amazonian girdle wrought of gold;<lb/>
and did my strong arms, gather all in vain<lb/>
the fruit when guarded by the dragon's eyes.<lb/>
The centaurs could not foil me, nor the boar<lb/>
that ravaged in Arcadian fruitful fields.<lb/>
Was it for this the hydra could not gain<lb/>
double the strength from strength as it was lost?<lb/>
And when I saw the steeds of Thrace, so fat<lb/>
with human blood, and their vile mangers heaped<lb/>
with mangled bodies, in a righteous rage<lb/>
I threw them to the ground, and slaughtered them,<lb/>
together with their master! In a cave<lb/>
I crushed the Nemean monster with these arms;<lb/>
and my strong neck upheld the wide-spread sky!<lb/>
And even the cruel Juno, wife of Jove—<lb/>
is weary of imposing heavy toils,<lb/>
but I am not subdued performing them.<lb/>

    
“A new calamity now crushes me,<lb/>
which not my strength, nor valor, nor the use<lb/>
of weapons can resist. Devouring flames<lb/>
have preyed upon my limbs, and blasting heat<lb/>
now shrivels the burnt tissue of my frame.<lb/>
But still Eurystheus is alive and well!<lb/>
And there are those who yet believe in Gods!”<lb/>

    
Just as a wild bull, in whose body spears<lb/>
are rankling, while the frightened hunter flies<lb/>
away for safety, so the hero ranged<lb/>
over sky-piercing Oeta; his huge groans,<lb/>
his awful shrieks resounding in those cliffs.<lb/>
At times he struggles with the poisoned robe.<lb/>
Goaded to fury, he has razed great trees,<lb/>
and scattered the vast mountain rocks around!<lb/>
And stretched his arms towards his ancestral skies!<lb/>

    
So, in his frenzy, as he wandered there,<lb/>
he chanced upon the trembling Lichas, crouched<lb/>
in the close covert of a hollow rock.<lb/>
Then in a savage fury he cried out,<lb/>
“Was it you, Lichas, brought this fatal gift?<lb/>
Shall you be called the author of my death?”<lb/>
Lichas, in terror, groveled at his feet,<lb/>
and begged for mercy—“Only let me live!”<lb/>
But seizing on him, the crazed Hero whirled<lb/>
him thrice and once again about his head,<lb/>
and hurled him, shot as by a catapult,<lb/>
into the waves of the Euboic Sea.<lb/>

    
While he was hanging in the air, his form<lb/>
was hardened; as, we know, rain drops may first<lb/>
be frozen by the cold air, and then change<lb/>
to snow, and as it falls through whirling winds<lb/>
may press, so twisted, into round hailstones:<lb/>
even so has ancient lore declared that when<lb/>
strong arms hurled Lichas through the mountain air<lb/>
through fear, his blood was curdled in his veins.<lb/>
No moisture left in him, he was transformed<lb/>
into a flint-rock. Even to this day,<lb/>
a low crag rising from the waves is seen<lb/>
out of the deep Euboean Sea, and holds<lb/>
the certain outline of a human form,<lb/>
so sure]y traced, the wary sailors fear<lb/>
to tread upon it, thinking it has life,<lb/>
and they have called it Lichas ever since.<lb/>

    
But, O illustrious son of Jupiter!<lb/>
How many of the overspreading trees,<lb/>
thick-growing on the lofty mountain-peak<lb/>
of Oeta, did you level to the ground,<lb/>
and heap into a pyre! And then you bade<lb/>
obedient Philoctetes light a torch<lb/>
beneath it, and then take in recompense<lb/>
your bow with its capacious quiver full<lb/>
of arrows, arms that now again would see<lb/>
the realm of Troy. And as the pyre began<lb/>
to kindle with the greedy flames, you spread<lb/>
the Nemean lion skin upon the top,<lb/>
and, club for pillow, you lay down to sleep,<lb/>
as placid as if, with abounding cups<lb/>
of generous wine and crowned with garlands, you<lb/>
were safe, reclining on a banquet-couch.<lb/>

    
And now on every side the spreading flames<lb/>
were crackling fiercely, as they leaped from earth<lb/>
upon the careless limbs of Hercules.<lb/>
He scorned their power. The Gods felt fear<lb/>
for earth's defender and their sympathy<lb/>
gave pleasure to Saturnian Jove — he knew<lb/>
their thought—and joyfully he said to them:<lb/>

    
“Your sudden fear is surely my delight,<lb/>
O heavenly Gods! my heart is lifted up<lb/>
and joy prevails upon me, in the thought<lb/>
that I am called the Father and the King<lb/>
of all this grateful race of Gods. I know<lb/>
my own beloved offspring is secure<lb/>
in your declared protection: your concern<lb/>
may justly evidence his worth, whose deeds<lb/>
great benefits bestowed. Let not vain thoughts<lb/>
alarm you, nor the rising flames of Oeta;<lb/>
for Hercules who conquered everything,<lb/>
shall conquer equally the spreading fires<lb/>
which now you see: and all that part of him,<lb/>
celestial — inherited of me—<lb/>
immortal, cannot feel the power of death.<lb/>
It is not subject to the poison-heat.<lb/>
And therefore, since his earth-life is now lost,<lb/>
him I'll translate, unshackled from all dross,<lb/>
and purified, to our celestial shore.<lb/>
I trust this action seems agreeable<lb/>
to all the Deities surrounding me.<lb/>
If any jealous god of heaven should grieve<lb/>
at the divinity of Hercules,<lb/>
he may begrudge the prize but he will know<lb/>
at least 'twas given him deservedly,<lb/>
and with this thought he must approve the deed.”<lb/>

    
The Gods confirmed it: and though Juno seemed<lb/>
to be contented and to acquiesce,<lb/>
her deep vexation was not wholly hid,<lb/>
when Jupiter with his concluding words<lb/>
so plainly hinted at her jealous mind.<lb/>

    
Now, while the Gods conversed, the mortal part<lb/>
of Hercules was burnt by Mulciber;<lb/>
but yet an outline of a spirit-form<lb/>
remained. Unlike the well-known mortal shape<lb/>
derived by nature of his mother, he<lb/>
kept traces only of his father, Jove.<lb/>

    
And as a serpent, when it is revived<lb/>
from its old age, casts off the faded skin,<lb/>
and fresh with vigor glitters in new scales,<lb/>
so, when the hero had put off all dross,<lb/>
his own celestial, wonderful appeared,<lb/>
majestic and of godlike dignity.<lb/>

    
And him, the glorious father of the Gods<lb/>
in the great chariot drawn by four swift steeds,<lb/>
took up above the wide-encircling clouds,<lb/>
and set him there amid the glittering stars.<lb/>
</text>
