<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>Book 3

Cadmus.
CADMUS AND THE DRAGONTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS

Now Jupiter had not revealed himself,<lb/>
nor laid aside the semblance of a bull,<lb/>
until they stood upon the plains of Crete.<lb/>

    
But not aware of this, her father bade<lb/>
her brother Cadmus search through all the world,<lb/>
until he found his sister, and proclaimed<lb/>
him doomed to exile if he found her not;—<lb/>
thus was he good and wicked in one deed.<lb/>
When he had vainly wandered over the earth<lb/>
(for who can fathom the deceits of Jove?)<lb/>
Cadmus, the son of King Agenor, shunned<lb/>
his country and his father's mighty wrath.<lb/>

    
But he consulted the famed oracles<lb/>
of Phoebus, and enquired of them what land<lb/>
might offer him a refuge and a home.<lb/>
And Phoebus answered him; “When on the plains<lb/>
a heifer, that has never known the yoke,<lb/>
shall cross thy path go thou thy way with her,<lb/>
and follow where she leads; and when she lies,<lb/>
to rest herself upon the meadow green,<lb/>
there shalt thou stop, as it will be a sign<lb/>
for thee to build upon that plain the walls<lb/>
of a great city: and its name shall be<lb/>
the City of Boeotia.”<lb/>

    
Cadmus turned;<lb/>
but hardly had descended from the cave,<lb/>
Castalian, ere he saw a heifer go<lb/>
unguarded, gentle-paced, without the scars<lb/>
of labour on her neck. He followed close<lb/>
upon her steps (and silently adored<lb/>
celestial Phoebus, author of his way)<lb/>
till over the channel that Cephissus wears<lb/>
he forded to the fields of Panope<lb/>
and even over to Boeotia.—<lb/>
there stood the slow-paced heifer, and she raised<lb/>
her forehead, broad with shapely horns, towards Heaven;<lb/>
and as she filled the air with lowing, stretched<lb/>
her side upon the tender grass, and turned<lb/>
her gaze on him who followed in her path.<lb/>

    
Cadmus gave thanks and kissed the foreign soil,<lb/>
and offered salutation to the fields<lb/>
and unexplored hills. Then he prepared<lb/>
to make large sacrifice to Jupiter,<lb/>
and ordered slaves to seek the living springs<lb/>
whose waters in libation might be poured.<lb/>

    
There was an ancient grove, whose branching trees<lb/>
had never known the desecrating ax,<lb/>
where hidden in the undergrowth a cave,<lb/>
with oziers bending round its low-formed arch,<lb/>
was hollowed in the jutting rocks—deep-found<lb/>
in the dark center of that hallowed grove—<lb/>
beneath its arched roof a beauteous stream<lb/>
of water welled serene. Its gloom concealed<lb/>
a dragon, sacred to the war-like Mars;<lb/>
crested and gorgeous with radescent scales,<lb/>
and eyes that sparkled as the glow of coals.<lb/>
A deadly venom had puffed up his bulk,<lb/>
and from his jaws he darted forth three tongues,<lb/>
and in a triple row his sharp teeth stood.<lb/>

    
Now those who ventured of the Tyrian race,<lb/>
misfortuned followers of Cadmus, took<lb/>
the path that led them to this grove; and when<lb/>
they cast down-splashing in the springs an urn,<lb/>
the hidden dragon stretched his azure head<lb/>
out from the cavern's gloom, and vented forth<lb/>
terrific hissings. Horrified they dropped<lb/>
their urns. A sudden trembling shook their knees;<lb/>
and their life-blood was ice within their veins.<lb/>

    
The dragon wreathed his scales in rolling knots,<lb/>
and with a spring, entwisted in great folds,<lb/>
reared up his bulk beyond the middle rings,<lb/>
high in the air from whence was given his gaze<lb/>
the extreme confines of the grove below.<lb/>
A size prodigious, his enormous bulk,<lb/>
if seen extended where was naught to hide,<lb/>
would rival in its length the Serpent's folds,<lb/>
involved betwixt the planes of the Twin Bears.<lb/>
The terrified Phoenicians, whether armed<lb/>
for conflict, or in flight precipitate,<lb/>
or whether held incapable from fear,<lb/>
he seized with sudden rage; stung them to death,<lb/>
or crushed them in the grasp of crushing folds,<lb/>
or blasted with the poison of his breath.<lb/>

    
High in the Heavens the sun small shadow made<lb/>
when Cadmus, wondering what detained his men,<lb/>
prepared to follow them. Clothed in a skin<lb/>
torn from a lion, he was armed, complete,<lb/>
with lance of glittering steel; and with a dart:<lb/>
but passing these he had a dauntless soul.<lb/>

    
When he explored the grove and there beheld<lb/>
the lifeless bodies, and above them stretched<lb/>
the vast victorious dragon licking up<lb/>
the blood that issued from their ghastly wounds;<lb/>
his red tongues dripping gore; then Cadmus filled<lb/>
with rage and grief; “Behold, my faithful ones!<lb/>
I will avenge your deaths or I will share it!”<lb/>

    
He spoke; and lifted up a mill-stone huge,<lb/>
in his right hand, and having poised it, hurled<lb/>
with a tremendous effort dealing such<lb/>
a blow would crush the strongest builded walls;<lb/>
yet neither did the dragon flinch the shock<lb/>
nor was he wounded, for his armour-scales,<lb/>
fixed in his hard and swarthy hide, repelled<lb/>
the dreadful impact. Not the javelin thus,<lb/>
so surely by his armoured skin was foiled,<lb/>
for through the middle segment of his spine<lb/>
the steel point pierced, and sank beneath the flesh,<lb/>
deep in his entrails. Writhing in great pain<lb/>
he turned his head upon his bleeding back,<lb/>
twisting the shaft, with force prodigious shook<lb/>
it back and forth, and wrenched it from the wound;<lb/>
with difficulty wrenched it. But the steel<lb/>
remained securely fastened in his bones.<lb/>
Such agony but made increase of rage:<lb/>
his throat was swollen with great knotted veins;<lb/>
a white froth gathered on his poisonous jaws;<lb/>
the earth resounded with his rasping scales;<lb/>
he breathed upon the grass a pestilence,<lb/>
steaming mephitic from his Stygian mouth.<lb/>

    
His body writhes up in tremendous gyres;<lb/>
his folds, now straighter than a beam, untwist;<lb/>
he rushes forward on his vengeful foe,<lb/>
his great breast crushing the deep-rooted trees.<lb/>

    
Small space gave Cadmus to the dragon's rage,<lb/>
for by the lion's spoil he stood the shock,<lb/>
and thrusting in his adversary's jaws<lb/>
the trusted lance gave check his mad career.<lb/>
Wild in his rage the dragon bit the steel<lb/>
and fixed his teeth on the keen-biting point:<lb/>
out from his poisoned palate streams of gore<lb/>
spouted and stained the green with sanguine spray.<lb/>
Yet slight the wound for he recoiled in time,<lb/>
and drew his wounded body from the spear;<lb/>
by shrinking from the sharp steel saved his throat<lb/>
a mortal wound. But Cadmus as he pressed<lb/>
the spear-point deeper in the serpent's throat,<lb/>
pursued him till an oak-tree barred the way;<lb/>
to this he fixed the dragon through the neck:<lb/>
the stout trunk bending with the monster's weight,<lb/>
groaned at the lashing of his serpent tail.<lb/>


    
While the brave victor gazed upon the bulk<lb/>
enormous of his vanquished foe, a voice<lb/>
was heard—from whence was difficult to know,<lb/>
but surely heard—“Son of Agenor, why<lb/>

    
art thou here standing by this carcase-worm,<lb/>
for others shall behold thy body changed<lb/>
into a serpent?” Terrified, amazed,<lb/>
he lost his colour and his self-control;<lb/>
his hair stood upright from the dreadful fright.<lb/>

    
But lo, the hero's watchful Deity,<lb/>
Minerva, from the upper realms of air<lb/>
appeared before him. She commanded him<lb/>
to sow the dragon's teeth in mellowed soil,<lb/>
from which might spring another race of men.<lb/>
And he obeyed: and as he plowed the land,<lb/>
took care to scatter in the furrowed soil<lb/>
the dragon's teeth; a seed to raise up man.<lb/>

    
'Tis marvelous but true, when this was done<lb/>
the clods began to move. A spear-point first<lb/>
appeared above the furrows, followed next<lb/>
by helmet-covered heads, nodding their cones;<lb/>
their shoulders, breasts and arms weighted with spears;<lb/>
and largely grew the shielded crop of men.—<lb/>
so is it in the joyful theaters<lb/>
when the gay curtains, rolling from the floor,<lb/>
are upward drawn until the scene is shown,—<lb/>
it seems as if the figures rise to view:<lb/>
first we behold their faces, then we see<lb/>
their bodies, and their forms by slow degrees<lb/>
appear before us on the painted cloth.<lb/>

    
Cadmus, affrighted by this host, prepared<lb/>
to arm for his defence; but one of those<lb/>
from earth created cried; “Arm not! Away<lb/>
from civil wars!” And with his trenchant sword<lb/>
he smote an earth-born brother, hand to hand;<lb/>
even as the vanquished so the victor fell,<lb/>
pierced by a dart some distant brother hurled;<lb/>
and likewise he who cast that dart was slain:<lb/>
both breathing forth their lives upon the air<lb/>
so briefly theirs, expired together. All<lb/>
as if demented leaped in sudden rage,<lb/>
each on the other, dealing mutual wounds.<lb/>

    
So, having lived the space allotted them,<lb/>
the youthful warriors perished as they smote<lb/>
the earth (their blood-stained mother) with their breasts:<lb/>
and only five of all the troop remained;<lb/>
of whom Echion, by Minerva warned,<lb/>
called on his brothers to give up the fight,<lb/>
and cast his arms away in pledge of faith.—<lb/>
when Cadmus, exiled from Sidonia's gates,<lb/>
builded the city by Apollo named,<lb/>
these five were trusted comrades in his toil.<lb/>

ACTAEONTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS

Now Thebes is founded, who can deem thy days<lb/>
unhappy in shine exile, Cadmus? Thou,<lb/>
the son-in-law of Mars and Venus; thou,<lb/>
whose glorious wife has borne to shine embrace<lb/>
daughters and sons? And thy grandchildren join<lb/>
around thee, almost grown to man's estate.—<lb/>
nor should we say, “He leads a happy life,”<lb/>
Till after death the funeral rites are paid.<lb/>


Actaeon.

Thy grandson, Cadmus, was the first to cast<lb/>
thy dear felicity in sorrow's gloom.<lb/>
Oh, it was pitiful to witness him,<lb/>
his horns outbranching from his forehead, chased<lb/>
by dogs that panted for their master's blood!<lb/>
If thou shouldst well inquire it will be shown<lb/>
his sorrow was the crime of Fortune—not<lb/>
his guilt—for who maintains mistakes are crimes?<lb/>

    
Upon a mountain stained with slaughtered game,<lb/>
the young Hyantian stood. Already day,<lb/>
increasing to meridian, made decrease<lb/>
the flitting shadows, and the hot sun shone<lb/>
betwixt extremes in equal distance. Such<lb/>
the hour, when speaking to his fellow friends,<lb/>
the while they wandered by those lonely haunts,<lb/>
actaeon of Hyantis kindly thus;<lb/>

“Our nets and steel are stained with slaughtered game,<lb/>
the day has filled its complement of sport;<lb/>
now, when Aurora in her saffron car<lb/>
brings back the light of day, we may again<lb/>
repair to haunts of sport. Now Phoebus hangs<lb/>
in middle sky, cleaving the fields with heat.—<lb/>
enough of toil; take down the knotted nets.”—<lb/>
all did as he commanded; and they sought<lb/>
their needed rest.<lb/>

    
There is a valley called<lb/>
Gargaphia; sacred to Diana, dense<lb/>
with pine trees and the pointed cypress, where,<lb/>
deep in the woods that fringed the valley's edge,<lb/>
was hollowed in frail sandstone and the soft<lb/>
white pumice of the hills an arch, so true<lb/>
it seemed the art of man; for Nature's touch<lb/>
ingenious had so fairly wrought the stone,<lb/>
making the entrance of a grotto cool.<lb/>
Upon the right a limpid fountain ran,<lb/>
and babbled, as its lucid channel spread<lb/>
into a clear pool edged with tender grass.<lb/>
Here, when a-wearied with exciting sport,<lb/>
the Sylvan goddess loved to come and bathe<lb/>
her virgin beauty in the crystal pool.<lb/>

    
After Diana entered with her nymphs,<lb/>
she gave her javelin, quiver and her bow<lb/>
to one accustomed to the care of arms;<lb/>
she gave her mantle to another nymph<lb/>
who stood near by her as she took it off;<lb/>
two others loosed the sandals from her feet;<lb/>
but Crocale, the daughter of Ismenus,<lb/>
more skillful than her sisters, gathered up<lb/>
the goddess' scattered tresses in a knot;—<lb/>
her own were loosely wantoned on the breeze.<lb/>

    
Then in their ample urns dipt up the wave<lb/>
and poured it forth, the cloud-nymph Nephele,<lb/>
the nymph of crystal pools called Hyale,<lb/>
the rain-drop Rhanis, Psecas of the dews,<lb/>
and Phyale the guardian of their urns.<lb/>
And while they bathed Diana in their streams,<lb/>
Actaeon, wandering through the unknown woods,<lb/>
entered the precincts of that sacred grove;<lb/>
with steps uncertain wandered he as fate<lb/>
directed, for his sport must wait till morn.—<lb/>
soon as he entered where the clear springs welled<lb/>
or trickled from the grotto's walls, the nymphs,<lb/>
now ready for the bath, beheld the man,<lb/>
smote on their breasts, and made the woods resound,<lb/>
suddenly shrieking. Quickly gathered they<lb/>
to shield Diana with their naked forms, but she<lb/>
stood head and shoulders taller than her guards.—<lb/>
as clouds bright-tinted by the slanting sun,<lb/>
or purple-dyed Aurora, so appeared<lb/>
Diana's countenance when she was seen.<lb/>

    
Oh, how she wished her arrows were at hand!<lb/>
But only having water, this she took<lb/>
and dashed it on his manly countenance,<lb/>
and sprinkled with the avenging stream his hair,<lb/>
and said these words, presage of future woe;<lb/>
“Go tell it, if your tongue can tell the tale,<lb/>
your bold eyes saw me stripped of all my robes.”<lb/>
No more she threatened, but she fixed the horns<lb/>
of a great stag firm on his sprinkled brows;<lb/>
she lengthened out his neck; she made his ears<lb/>
sharp at the top; she changed his hands and feet;<lb/>
made long legs of his arms, and covered him<lb/>
with dappled hair—his courage turned to fear.<lb/>
The brave son of Autonoe took to flight,<lb/>
and marveled that he sped so swiftly on.—<lb/>

    
he saw his horns reflected in a stream<lb/>
and would have said, “Ah, wretched me!” but now<lb/>
he had no voice, and he could only groan:<lb/>
large tears ran trickling down his face, transformed<lb/>
in every feature.—Yet, as clear remained<lb/>
his understanding, and he wondered what<lb/>
he should attempt to do: should he return<lb/>
to his ancestral palace, or plunge deep<lb/>
in vast vacuities of forest wilds?<lb/>
Fear made him hesitate to trust the woods,<lb/>
and shame deterred him from his homeward way.<lb/>

    
While doubting thus his dogs espied him there:<lb/>
first Blackfoot and the sharp nosed Tracer raised<lb/>
the signal: Tracer of the Gnossian breed,<lb/>
and Blackfoot of the Spartan: swift as wind<lb/>
the others followed. Glutton, Quicksight, Surefoot,<lb/>
three dogs of Arcady; then valiant Killbuck,<lb/>
Tempest, fierce Hunter, and the rapid Wingfoot;<lb/>
sharp-scented Chaser, and Woodranger wounded<lb/>
so lately by a wild boar; savage Wildwood,<lb/>
the wolf-begot with Shepherdess the cow-dog;<lb/>
and ravenous Harpy followed by her twin whelps;<lb/>
and thin-girt Ladon chosen from Sicyonia;<lb/>
racer and Barker, brindled Spot and Tiger;<lb/>
sturdy old Stout and white haired Blanche and black Smut<lb/>
lusty big Lacon, trusty Storm and Quickfoot;<lb/>
active young Wolfet and her Cyprian brother<lb/>
black headed Snap, blazed with a patch of white hair<lb/>
from forehead to his muzzle; swarthy Blackcoat<lb/>
and shaggy Bristle, Towser and Wildtooth,<lb/>
his sire of Dicte and his dam of Lacon;<lb/>
and yelping Babbler: these and others, more<lb/>
than patience leads us to recount or name.<lb/>

    
All eager for their prey the pack surmount<lb/>
rocks, cliffs and crags, precipitous—where paths<lb/>
are steep, where roads are none. He flies by routes<lb/>
so oft pursued but now, alas, his flight<lb/>
is from his own!—He would have cried, “Behold<lb/>
your master!—It is I—Actaeon!” Words<lb/>
refused his will. The yelping pack pressed on.<lb/>
First Blackmane seized and tore his master's back,<lb/>
Savage the next, then Rover's teeth were clinched<lb/>
deep in his shoulder.—These, though tardy out,<lb/>
cut through a by-path and arriving first<lb/>
clung to their master till the pack came up.<lb/>

    
The whole pack fastened on their master's flesh<lb/>
till place was none for others. Groaning he<lb/>
made frightful sounds that not the human voice<lb/>
could utter nor the stag; and filled the hills<lb/>
with dismal moans; and as a suppliant fell<lb/>
down to the ground upon his trembling knees;<lb/>
and turned his stricken eyes on his own dogs,<lb/>
entreating them to spare him from their fangs.<lb/>

    
But his companions, witless of his plight,<lb/>
urged on the swift pack with their hunting cries.<lb/>
They sought Actaeon and they vainly called,<lb/>
“Actaeon! Hi! Actaeon!” just as though<lb/>
he was away from them. Each time they called<lb/>
he turned his head. And when they chided him,<lb/>
whose indolence denied the joys of sport,<lb/>
how much he wished an indolent desire<lb/>
had haply held him from his ravenous pack.<lb/>
Oh, how much;better 'tis to see the hunt,<lb/>
and the fierce dogs, than feel their savage deeds!<lb/>
They gathered round him, and they fixed their snouts<lb/>
deep in his flesh: tore him to pieces, he<lb/>
whose features only as a stag appeared.—<lb/>
'Tis said Diana's fury raged with none<lb/>
abatement till the torn flesh ceased to live.<lb/>


Semele.
SEMELE AND JUPITERTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS

Hapless Actaeon's end in various ways<lb/>
was now regarded; some deplored his doom,<lb/>
but others praised Diana's chastity;<lb/>
and all gave many reasons. But the spouse<lb/>
of Jove, alone remaining silent, gave<lb/>
nor praise nor blame. Whenever calamity<lb/>
befell the race of Cadmus she rejoiced,<lb/>
in secret, for she visited her rage<lb/>
on all Europa's kindred.<lb/>

    
Now a fresh<lb/>
occasion has been added to her grief,<lb/>
and wild with jealousy of Semele,<lb/>
her tongue as ever ready to her rage,<lb/>
lets loose a torrent of abuse;<lb/>

“Away!<lb/>
Away with words! Why should I speak of it?<lb/>
Let me attack her! Let me spoil that jade!<lb/>
Am I not Juno the supreme of Heaven?<lb/>
Queen of the flashing scepter? Am I not<lb/>
sister and wife of Jove omnipotent?<lb/>
She even wishes to be known by him<lb/>
a mother of a Deity, a joy<lb/>
almost denied to me! Great confidence<lb/>
has she in her great beauty—nevertheless,<lb/>
I shall so weave the web the bolt of Jove<lb/>
would fail to save her.—Let the Gods deny<lb/>
that I am Saturn's daughter, if her shade<lb/>
descend not stricken to the Stygian wave.”<lb/>

    
She rose up quickly from her shining throne,<lb/>
and hidden in a cloud of fiery hue<lb/>
descended to the home of Semele;<lb/>
and while encompassed by the cloud, transformed<lb/>
her whole appearance as to counterfeit<lb/>
old Beroe, an Epidaurian nurse,<lb/>
who tended Semele.<lb/>

    
Her tresses changed<lb/>
to grey, her smooth skin wrinkled and her step<lb/>
grown feeble as she moved with trembling limbs;—<lb/>
her voice was quavering as an ancient dame's,<lb/>
as Juno, thus disguised, began to talk<lb/>
to Semele. When presently the name<lb/>
of Jove was mentioned—artful Juno thus;<lb/>
(doubtful that Jupiter could be her love)—<lb/>

“When Jove appears to pledge his love to you,<lb/>
implore him to assume his majesty<lb/>
and all his glory, even as he does<lb/>
in presence of his stately Juno—Yea,<lb/>
implore him to caress you as a God.”<lb/>

    
With artful words as these the goddess worked<lb/>
upon the trusting mind of Semele,<lb/>
daughter of Cadmus, till she begged of Jove<lb/>
a boon, that only hastened her sad death;<lb/>
for Jove not knowing her design replied,<lb/>
“Whatever thy wish, it shall not be denied,<lb/>
and that thy heart shall suffer no distrust,<lb/>
I pledge me by that Deity, the Waves<lb/>
of the deep Stygian Lake,—oath of the Gods.”<lb/>
All overjoyed at her misfortune, proud<lb/>
that she prevailed, and pleased that she secured<lb/>
of him a promise, that could only cause<lb/>
her own disaster, Semele addressed<lb/>
almighty Jove; “Come unto me in all<lb/>
the splendour of thy glory, as thy might<lb/>
is shown to Juno, goddess of the skies.”<lb/>
Fain would he stifle her disastrous tongue;<lb/>
before he knew her quest the words were said;<lb/>
and, knowing that his greatest oath was pledged,<lb/>
he sadly mounted to the lofty skies,<lb/>
and by his potent nod assembled there<lb/>
the deep clouds: and the rain began to pour,<lb/>
and thunder-bolts resounded.<lb/>

    
But he strove<lb/>
to mitigate his power, and armed him not<lb/>
with flames overwhelming as had put to flight<lb/>
his hundred-handed foe Typhoeus—flames<lb/>
too dreadful. Other thunder-bolts he took,<lb/>
forged by the Cyclops of a milder heat,<lb/>
with which insignia of his majesty,<lb/>
sad and reluctant, he appeared to her.—<lb/>
her mortal form could not endure the shock<lb/>
and she was burned to ashes in his sight.<lb/>

    
An unformed babe was rescued from her side,<lb/>
and, nurtured in the thigh of Jupiter,<lb/>
completed Nature's time until his birth.<lb/>
Ino, his aunt, in secret nursed the boy<lb/>
and cradled him. And him Nyseian nymphs<lb/>
concealed in caves and fed with needful milk.<lb/>


Tiresias.
TIRESIASBLINDPROPHECIES

While these events according to the laws<lb/>
of destiny occurred, and while the child,<lb/>
the twice-born Bacchus, in his cradle lay,<lb/>
'Tis told that Jupiter, a careless hour,<lb/>
indulged too freely in the nectar cup;<lb/>
and having laid aside all weighty cares,<lb/>
jested with Juno as she idled by.<lb/>

    
Freely the god began; “Who doubts the truth?<lb/>
The female's pleasure is a great delight,<lb/>
much greater than the pleasure of a male.”<lb/>
Juno denied it; wherefore 'twas agreed<lb/>
to ask Tiresias to declare the truth,<lb/>
than whom none knew both male and female joys:<lb/>
for wandering in a green wood he had seen<lb/>
two serpents coupling; and he took his staff<lb/>
and sharply struck them, till they broke and fled.<lb/>
'Tis marvelous, that instant he became<lb/>
a woman from a man, and so remained<lb/>
while seven autumns passed. When eight were told,<lb/>
again he saw them in their former plight,<lb/>
and thus he spoke; “Since such a power was wrought,<lb/>
by one stroke of a staff my sex was changed—<lb/>
again I strike!” And even as he struck<lb/>
the same two snakes, his former sex returned;<lb/>
his manhood was restored.—<lb/>

    
as both agreed<lb/>
to choose him umpire of the sportive strife,<lb/>
he gave decision in support of Jove;<lb/>
from this the disappointment Juno felt<lb/>
surpassed all reason, and enraged, decreed<lb/>
eternal night should seal Tiresias' eyes.—<lb/>
immortal Deities may never turn<lb/>
decrees and deeds of other Gods to naught,<lb/>
but Jove, to recompense his loss of sight,<lb/>
endowed him with the gift of prophecy.<lb/>


Narcissus. Echo.
NARCISSUS AND ECHOTHE HOUSE OF CADMUS

Tiresias' fame of prophecy was spread<lb/>
through all the cities of Aonia,<lb/>
for his unerring answers unto all<lb/>
who listened to his words. And first of those<lb/>
that harkened to his fateful prophecies,<lb/>
a lovely Nymph, named Liriope, came<lb/>
with her dear son, who then fifteen, might seem<lb/>
a man or boy—he who was born to her<lb/>
upon the green merge of Cephissus' stream—<lb/>
that mighty River-God whom she declared<lb/>
the father of her boy.—<lb/>

    
she questioned him.<lb/>
Imploring him to tell her if her son,<lb/>
unequalled for his beauty, whom she called<lb/>
Narcissus, might attain a ripe old age.<lb/>
To which the blind seer answered in these words,<lb/>
“If he but fail to recognize himself,<lb/>
a long life he may have, beneath the sun,”—<lb/>
so, frivolous the prophet's words appeared;<lb/>
and yet the event, the manner of his death,<lb/>
the strange delusion of his frenzied love, confirmed it.<lb/>

    
Three times five years so were passed.<lb/>
Another five-years, and the lad might seem<lb/>
a young man or a boy. And many a youth,<lb/>
and many a damsel sought to gain his love;<lb/>
but such his mood and spirit and his pride,<lb/>
none gained his favour.<lb/>

    
Once a noisy Nymph,<lb/>
(who never held her tongue when others spoke,<lb/>
who never spoke till others had begun)<lb/>
mocking Echo, spied him as he drove,<lb/>
in his delusive nets, some timid stags.—<lb/>

    
for Echo was a Nymph, in olden time,—<lb/>
and, more than vapid sound,—possessed a form:<lb/>
and she was then deprived the use of speech,<lb/>
except to babble and repeat the words,<lb/>
once spoken, over and over.<lb/>

    
Juno confused<lb/>
her silly tongue, because she often held<lb/>
that glorious goddess with her endless tales,<lb/>
till many a hapless Nymph, from Jove's embrace,<lb/>
had made escape adown a mountain. But<lb/>
for this, the goddess might have caught them. Thus<lb/>
the glorious Juno, when she knew her guile;<lb/>

“Your tongue, so freely wagged at my expense,<lb/>
shall be of little use; your endless voice,<lb/>
much shorter than your tongue.” At once the Nymph<lb/>
was stricken as the goddess had decreed;—<lb/>
and, ever since, she only mocks the sounds<lb/>
of others' voices, or, perchance, returns<lb/>
their final words.<lb/>

    
One day, when she observed<lb/>
Narcissus wandering in the pathless woods,<lb/>
she loved him and she followed him, with soft<lb/>
and stealthy tread.—The more she followed him<lb/>
the hotter did she burn, as when the flame<lb/>
flares upward from the sulphur on the torch.<lb/>

    
Oh, how she longed to make her passion known!<lb/>
To plead in soft entreaty! to implore his love!<lb/>
But now, till others have begun, a mute<lb/>
of Nature she must be. She cannot choose<lb/>
but wait the moment when his voice may give<lb/>
to her an answer.<lb/>

    
Presently the youth,<lb/>
by chance divided from his trusted friends,<lb/>
cries loudly, “Who is here?” and Echo, “Here!”<lb/>
Replies. Amazed, he casts his eyes around,<lb/>
and calls with louder voice, “Come here!” “Come here!”<lb/>
She calls the youth who calls.—He turns to see<lb/>
who calls him and, beholding naught exclaims,<lb/>
“Avoid me not!” “Avoid me not!” returns.<lb/>

    
He tries again, again, and is deceived<lb/>
by this alternate voice, and calls aloud;<lb/>
“Oh let us come together!” Echo cries,<lb/>
“Oh let us come together!” Never sound<lb/>
seemed sweeter to the Nymph, and from the woods<lb/>
she hastens in accordance with her words,<lb/>
and strives to wind her arms around his neck.<lb/>
He flies from her and as he leaves her says,<lb/>
“Take off your hands! you shall not fold your arms<lb/>
around me. Better death than such a one<lb/>
should ever caress me!” Naught she answers save,<lb/>
“Caress me!”<lb/>

    
Thus rejected she lies hid<lb/>
in the deep woods, hiding her blushing face<lb/>
with the green leaves; and ever after lives<lb/>
concealed in lonely caverns in the hills.<lb/>

    
But her great love increases with neglect;<lb/>
her miserable body wastes away,<lb/>
wakeful with sorrows; leanness shrivels up<lb/>
her skin, and all her lovely features melt,<lb/>
as if dissolved upon the wafting winds—<lb/>
nothing remains except her bones and voice—<lb/>
her voice continues, in the wilderness;<lb/>
her bones have turned to stone. She lies concealed<lb/>
in the wild woods, nor is she ever seen<lb/>
on lonely mountain range; for, though we hear<lb/>
her calling in the hills, 'tis but a voice,<lb/>
a voice that lives, that lives among the hills.<lb/>

    
Thus he deceived the Nymph and many more,<lb/>
sprung from the mountains or the sparkling waves;<lb/>
and thus he slighted many an amorous youth.—<lb/>
and therefore, some one whom he once despised,<lb/>
lifting his hands to Heaven, implored the Gods,<lb/>
“If he should love deny him what he loves!”<lb/>
and as the prayer was uttered it was heard<lb/>
by Nemesis, who granted her assent.<lb/>

NARCISSUS

There was a fountain silver-clear and bright,<lb/>
which neither shepherds nor the wild she-goats,<lb/>
that range the hills, nor any cattle's mouth<lb/>
had touched—its waters were unsullied—birds<lb/>
disturbed it not; nor animals, nor boughs<lb/>
that fall so often from the trees. Around<lb/>
sweet grasses nourished by the stream grew; trees<lb/>
that shaded from the sun let balmy airs<lb/>
temper its waters. Here Narcissus, tired<lb/>
of hunting and the heated noon, lay down,<lb/>
attracted by the peaceful solitudes<lb/>
and by the glassy spring. There as he stooped<lb/>
to quench his thirst another thirst increased.<lb/>

    
While he is drinking he beholds himself<lb/>
reflected in the mirrored pool—and loves;<lb/>
loves an imagined body which contains<lb/>
no substance, for he deems the mirrored shade<lb/>
a thing of life to love. He cannot move,<lb/>
for so he marvels at himself, and lies<lb/>
with countenance unchanged, as if indeed<lb/>
a statue carved of Parian marble. Long,<lb/>
supine upon the bank, his gaze is fixed<lb/>
on his own eyes, twin stars; his fingers shaped<lb/>
as Bacchus might desire, his flowing hair<lb/>
as glorious as Apollo's, and his cheeks<lb/>
youthful and smooth; his ivory neck, his mouth<lb/>
dreaming in sweetness, his complexion fair<lb/>
and blushing as the rose in snow-drift white.<lb/>
All that is lovely in himself he loves,<lb/>
and in his witless way he wants himself:—<lb/>
he who approves is equally approved;<lb/>
he seeks, is sought, he burns and he is burnt.<lb/>

    
And how he kisses the deceitful fount;<lb/>
and how he thrusts his arms to catch the neck<lb/>
that's pictured in the middle of the stream!<lb/>
Yet never may he wreathe his arms around<lb/>
that image of himself. He knows not what<lb/>
he there beholds, but what he sees inflames<lb/>
his longing, and the error that deceives<lb/>
allures his eyes. But why, O foolish boy,<lb/>
so vainly catching at this flitting form?<lb/>
The cheat that you are seeking has no place.<lb/>
Avert your gaze and you will lose your love,<lb/>
for this that holds your eyes is nothing save<lb/>
the image of yourself reflected back to you.<lb/>
It comes and waits with you; it has no life;<lb/>
it will depart if you will only go.<lb/>


    
Nor food nor rest can draw him thence—outstretched<lb/>
upon the overshadowed green, his eyes<lb/>
fixed on the mirrored image never may know<lb/>
their longings satisfied, and by their sight<lb/>
he is himself undone. Raising himself<lb/>
a moment, he extends his arms around,<lb/>
and, beckoning to the murmuring forest; “Oh,<lb/>
ye aisled wood was ever man in love<lb/>
more fatally than I? Your silent paths<lb/>
have sheltered many a one whose love was told,<lb/>
and ye have heard their voices. Ages vast<lb/>
have rolled away since your forgotten birth,<lb/>
but who is he through all those weary years<lb/>
that ever pined away as I? Alas,<lb/>
this fatal image wins my love, as I<lb/>
behold it. But I cannot press my arms<lb/>
around the form I see, the form that gives<lb/>
me joy. What strange mistake has intervened<lb/>
betwixt us and our love? It grieves me more<lb/>
that neither lands nor seas nor mountains, no,<lb/>
nor walls with closed gates deny our loves,<lb/>
but only a little water keeps us far<lb/>
asunder. Surely he desires my love<lb/>
and my embraces, for as oft I strive<lb/>
to kiss him, bending to the limpid stream<lb/>
my lips, so often does he hold his face<lb/>
fondly to me, and vainly struggles up.<lb/>
It seems that I could touch him. 'Tis a strange<lb/>
delusion that is keeping us apart.<lb/>

“Whoever thou art, Come up! Deceive me not!<lb/>
Oh, whither when I fain pursue art thou?<lb/>
Ah, surely I am young and fair, the Nymphs<lb/>
have loved me; and when I behold thy smiles<lb/>
I cannot tell thee what sweet hopes arise.<lb/>
When I extend my loving arms to thee<lb/>
thine also are extended me — thy smiles<lb/>
return my own. When I was weeping, I<lb/>
have seen thy tears, and every sign I make<lb/>
thou cost return; and often thy sweet lips<lb/>
have seemed to move, that, peradventure words,<lb/>
which I have never heard, thou hast returned.<lb/>

“No more my shade deceives me, I perceive<lb/>
'Tis I in thee—I love myself—the flame<lb/>
arises in my breast and burns my heart—<lb/>
what shall I do? Shall I at once implore?<lb/>
Or should I linger till my love is sought?<lb/>
What is it I implore? The thing that I<lb/>
desire is mine—abundance makes me poor.<lb/>
Oh, I am tortured by a strange desire<lb/>
unknown to me before, for I would fain<lb/>
put off this mortal form; which only means<lb/>
I wish the object of my love away.<lb/>
Grief saps my strength, the sands of life are run,<lb/>
and in my early youth am I cut off;<lb/>
but death is not my bane—it ends my woe.—<lb/>
I would not death for this that is my love,<lb/>
as two united in a single soul<lb/>
would die as one.”<lb/>

    
He spoke; and crazed with love,<lb/>
returned to view the same face in the pool;<lb/>
and as he grieved his tears disturbed the stream,<lb/>
and ripples on the surface, glassy clear,<lb/>
defaced his mirrored form. And thus the youth,<lb/>
when he beheld that lovely shadow go;<lb/>
“Ah whither cost thou fly? Oh, I entreat<lb/>
thee leave me not. Alas, thou cruel boy<lb/>
thus to forsake thy lover. Stay with me<lb/>
that I may see thy lovely form, for though<lb/>
I may not touch thee I shall feed my eyes<lb/>
and soothe my wretched pains.” And while he spoke<lb/>
he rent his garment from the upper edge,<lb/>
and beating on his naked breast, all white<lb/>
as marble, every stroke produced a tint<lb/>
as lovely as the apple streaked with red,<lb/>
or as the glowing grape when purple bloom<lb/>
touches the ripening clusters.<lb/>

    
When as glass<lb/>
again the rippling waters smoothed, and when<lb/>
such beauty in the stream the youth observed,<lb/>
no more could he endure. As in the flame<lb/>
the yellow wax, or as the hoar-frost melts<lb/>
in early morning 'neath the genial sun;<lb/>
so did he pine away, by love consumed,<lb/>
and slowly wasted by a hidden flame.<lb/>
No vermeil bloom now mingled in the white<lb/>
of his complexion fair; no strength has he,<lb/>
no vigor, nor the comeliness that wrought<lb/>
for love so long: alas, that handsome form<lb/>
by Echo fondly loved may please no more.<lb/>

    
But when she saw him in his hapless plight,<lb/>
though angry at his scorn, she only grieved.<lb/>
As often as the love-lore boy complained,<lb/>
“Alas!” “Alas!” her echoing voice returned;<lb/>
and as he struck his hands against his arms,<lb/>
she ever answered with her echoing sounds.<lb/>
And as he gazed upon the mirrored pool<lb/>
he said at last, “Ah, youth beloved in vain!”<lb/>
“In vain, in vain!” the spot returned his words;<lb/>
and when he breathed a sad “farewell!” “Farewell!”<lb/>
sighed Echo too. He laid his wearied head,<lb/>
and rested on the verdant grass; and those<lb/>
bright eyes, which had so loved to gaze, entranced,<lb/>
on their own master's beauty, sad Night closed.<lb/>
And now although among the nether shades<lb/>
his sad sprite roams, he ever loves to gaze<lb/>
on his reflection in the Stygian wave.<lb/>

    
His Naiad sisters mourned, and having clipped<lb/>
their shining tresses laid them on his corpse:<lb/>
and all the Dryads mourned: and Echo made<lb/>
lament anew. And these would have upraised<lb/>
his funeral pyre, and waved the flaming torch,<lb/>
and made his bier; but as they turned their eyes<lb/>
where he had been, alas he was not there!<lb/>
And in his body's place a sweet flower grew,<lb/>
golden and white, the white around the gold.<lb/>


Pentheus.
PENTHEUS AND BACCHUS

Narcissus' fate, when known throughout the land<lb/>
and cities of Achaia, added fame<lb/>
deserved, to blind Tiresias,—mighty seer.<lb/>
Yet Pentheus, bold despiser of the Gods,<lb/>
son of Echion, scoffed at all his praise,<lb/>
and, sole of man deriding the great seer,<lb/>
upbraided him his hapless loss of sight.<lb/>

    
And shaking his white temples, hoar with age.<lb/>
Tiresias of Pentheus prophesied,<lb/>
“Oh glad the day to thee, if, light denied,<lb/>
thine eyes, most fortunate, should not behold<lb/>
the Bacchanalian rites! The day will come,<lb/>
and soon the light will dawn, when Bacchus, born<lb/>
of Semele, shall make his advent known—<lb/>
all hail the new god Bacchus! Either thou<lb/>
must build a temple to this Deity,<lb/>
or shalt be torn asunder; thy remains,<lb/>
throughout the forest scattered, will pollute<lb/>
the wood with sanguinary streams; and thy<lb/>
life-blood bespatter with corrupting blots<lb/>
thy frenzied mother and her sisters twain.<lb/>
And all shall come to pass, as I have told,<lb/>
because thou wilt not honour the New God.<lb/>
And thou shalt wail and marvel at the sight<lb/>
of blind Tiresias, though veiled in night.”<lb/>

    
And as he spoke, lo, Pentheus drove the seer:<lb/>
but all his words, prophetic, were fulfilled,<lb/>
and confirmation followed in his steps.—<lb/>

    
Bacchus at once appears, and all the fields<lb/>
resound with shouts of everybody there.—<lb/>
men, brides and matrons, and a howling rout—<lb/>
nobles and commons and the most refined—<lb/>
a motley multitude—resistless borne<lb/>
to join those rites of Bacchus, there begun.<lb/>

    
Then Pentheus cries; “What madness, O ye brave<lb/>
descendants of the Dragon! Sons of Mars!<lb/>
What frenzy has confounded you? Can sounds<lb/>
of clanging brass prevail; and pipes and horns,<lb/>
and magical delusions, drunkenness,<lb/>
and yelling women, and obscene displays,<lb/>
and hollow drums, overcome you, whom the sword,<lb/>
nor troops of war, nor trumpet could affright?<lb/>

“How shall I wonder at these ancient men,<lb/>
who, crossing boundless seas from distant Tyre,<lb/>
hither transferred their exiled Household Gods,<lb/>
and founded a new Tyre; but now are shorn,<lb/>
and even as captives would be led away<lb/>
without appeal to Mars? And, O young men,<lb/>
of active prime whose vigor equals mine!<lb/>
Cast down your ivy scepters; take up arms;<lb/>
put on your helmets; strip your brows of leaves;<lb/>
be mindful of the mighty stock you are,<lb/>
and let your souls be animated with<lb/>
the spirit of that dauntless dragon, which,<lb/>
unaided, slew so many, and at last<lb/>
died to defend his fountain and his lake.—<lb/>
so ye may conquer in the hope of fame.<lb/>

“He gave the brave to death, but with your arms<lb/>
ye shall expel the worthless, and enhance<lb/>
the glory of your land. If Fate decree<lb/>
the fall of Thebes, Oh, let the engines<lb/>
of war and men pull down its walls, and let<lb/>
the clash of steel and roaring flames resound.<lb/>
Thus, blameless in great misery, our woes<lb/>
would be the theme of lamentations, known<lb/>
to story; and our tears would shame us not.<lb/>

“But now an unarmed boy will conquer Thebes:<lb/>
a lad whom neither weapons, wars nor steeds<lb/>
delight; whose ringlets reek with myrrh; adorned<lb/>
with chaplets, purple and embroidered robes<lb/>
of interwoven gold. Make way for me!<lb/>
And I will soon compel him to confess<lb/>
his father is assumed and all his rites<lb/>
are frauds.<lb/>

“If in days gone Acrisius<lb/>
so held this vain god in deserved contempt,<lb/>
and shut the Argive gates against his face,<lb/>
why, therefore, should not Pentheus close the gates<lb/>
of Thebes, with equal courage—Hence! Away!<lb/>
Fetch the vile leader of these rioters<lb/>
in chains! Let not my mandate be delayed.”<lb/>

    
Him to restrain his grandsire, Cadmus, strove;<lb/>
and Athamas, and many of his trusted friends<lb/>
united in vain efforts to rebuke<lb/>
his reckless rage; but greater violence<lb/>
was gained from every admonition.—<lb/>
his rage increased the more it was restrained,<lb/>
and injury resulted from his friends.<lb/>
So have I seen a stream in open course,<lb/>
run gently on its way with pleasant noise,<lb/>
but whensoever logs and rocks detained,<lb/>
it foamed, with violence increased, against<lb/>
obstruction.<lb/>

    
Presently returning came<lb/>
his servants stained with blood, to whom he said,<lb/>
“What have ye done with Bacchus?” And to him<lb/>
they made reply; “Not Bacchus have we seen,<lb/>
but we have taken his attendant lad,<lb/>
the chosen servant of his sacred rites.”<lb/>
And they delivered to the noble king,<lb/>
a youth whose hands were lashed behind his back.<lb/>

    
Then Pentheus, terrible in anger, turned<lb/>
his awful gaze upon the lad, and though<lb/>
he scarce deferred his doom, addressed him thus;<lb/>
“Doomed to destruction, thou art soon to give<lb/>
example to my people by thy death:<lb/>
tell me thy name; what are thy parents called;<lb/>
where is thy land; and wherefore art thou found<lb/>
attendant on these Bacchanalian rites.”<lb/>


    
But fearless he replied; “They call my name<lb/>
Acoetes; and Maeonia is the land<lb/>
from whence I came. My parents were so poor,<lb/>
my father left me neither fruitful fields,<lb/>
tilled by the lusty ox, nor fleecy sheep,<lb/>
nor lowing kine; for, he himself was poor,<lb/>
and with his hook and line was wont to catch<lb/>
the leaping fishes, landed by his rod.<lb/>
His skill was all his wealth. And when to me<lb/>
he gave his trade, he said, ‘You are the heir<lb/>
of my employment, therefore unto you<lb/>
all that is mine I give,’ and, at his death,<lb/>
he left me nothing but the running waves. —<lb/>
they are the sum of my inheritance.<lb/>

“And, afterwhile, that I might not be bound<lb/>
forever to my father's rocky shores,<lb/>
I learned to steer the keel with dextrous hand;<lb/>
and marked with watchful gaze the guiding stars;<lb/>
the watery Constellation of the Goat,<lb/>
Olenian, and the Bear, the Hyades,<lb/>
the Pleiades, the houses of the winds,<lb/>
and every harbour suitable for ships.<lb/>

“So chanced it, as I made for Delos, first<lb/>
I veered close to the shores of Chios: there<lb/>
I steered, by plying on the starboard oar,<lb/>
and nimbly leaping gained the sea-wet strand.<lb/>

“Now when the night was past and lovely dawn<lb/>
appeared, I,rose from slumber, and I bade<lb/>
my men to fetch fresh water, and I showed<lb/>
the pathway to the stream. Then did I climb<lb/>
a promontory's height, to learn from there<lb/>
the promise of the winds; which having done,<lb/>
I called the men and sought once more my ship.<lb/>
Opheltes, first of my companions, cried,<lb/>
‘Behold we come!’ And, thinking he had caught<lb/>
a worthy prize in that unfruitful land,<lb/>
he led a boy, of virgin-beauty formed,<lb/>
across the shore.<lb/>

“Heavy with wine and sleep<lb/>
the lad appeared to stagger on his way,—<lb/>
with difficulty moving. When I saw<lb/>
the manner of his dress, his countenance<lb/>
and grace, I knew it was not mortal man,<lb/>
and being well assured, I said to them;<lb/>
‘What Deity abideth in that form<lb/>
I cannot say; but 'tis a god in truth.—<lb/>
O whosoever thou art, vouchsafe to us<lb/>
propitious waters; ease our toils, and grant<lb/>
to these thy grace.’<lb/>

“At this, the one of all<lb/>
my mariners who was the quickest hand,<lb/>
who ever was the nimblest on the yards,<lb/>
and first to slip the ropes, Dictys exclaimed;<lb/>
‘Pray not for us!’ and all approved his words.<lb/>
The golden haired, the guardian of the prow,<lb/>
Melanthus, Libys and Alcimedon<lb/>
approved it; and Epopeus who should urge<lb/>
the flagging spirits, and with rhythmic chants<lb/>
give time and measure to the beating oars,<lb/>
and all the others praised their leader's words,—<lb/>
so blind is greed of gain.—Then I rejoined,<lb/>
‘Mine is the greatest share in this good ship,<lb/>
which I will not permit to be destroyed,<lb/>
nor injured by this sacred freight:’ and I<lb/>
opposed them as they came.<lb/>

“Then Lycabas,<lb/>
the most audacious of that impious crew,<lb/>
began to rage. He was a criminal,<lb/>
who, for a dreadful murder, had been sent<lb/>
in exile from a Tuscan city's gates.<lb/>
Whilst I opposed he gripped me by the throat,<lb/>
and shook me as would cast me in the deep,<lb/>
had I not firmly held a rope, half stunned:<lb/>
and all that wicked crew approved the deed.<lb/>

“Then Bacchus (be assured it was the God)<lb/>
as though the noise disturbed his lethargy<lb/>
from wine, and reason had regained its power,<lb/>
at last bespake the men, ‘What deeds are these?<lb/>
What noise assails my ears? What means decoyed<lb/>
my wandering footsteps? Whither do ye lead?’<lb/>
‘Fear not,’ the steersman said, ‘but tell us fair<lb/>
the haven of your hope, and you shall land<lb/>
whereso your heart desires.’ ‘To Naxos steer,’<lb/>
Quoth Bacchus, ‘for it is indeed my home,<lb/>
and there the mariner finds welcome cheer.’<lb/>
Him to deceive, they pledged themselves, and swore<lb/>
by Gods of seas and skies to do his will:<lb/>
and they commanded me to steer that way.<lb/>

“The Isle of Naxos was upon our right;<lb/>
and when they saw the sails were set that way,<lb/>
they all began to shout at once, ‘What, ho!<lb/>
Thou madman! what insanity is this,<lb/>
Acoetes? Make our passage to the left.’<lb/>
And all the while they made their meaning known<lb/>
by artful signs or whispers in my ears.<lb/>

“I was amazed and answered, ‘Take the helm.’<lb/>
And I refused to execute their will,<lb/>
atrocious, and at once resigned command.<lb/>
Then all began to murmur, and the crew<lb/>
reviled me. Up Aethalion jumped and said,<lb/>
‘As if our only safety is in you!’<lb/>
With this he swaggered up and took command;<lb/>
and leaving Naxos steered for other shores.<lb/>

“Then Bacchus, mocking them,—as if but then<lb/>
he had discovered their deceitful ways,—<lb/>
looked on the ocean from the rounded stern,<lb/>
and seemed to sob as he addressed the men;<lb/>
‘Ah mariners, what alien shores are these?<lb/>
'Tis not the land you promised nor the port<lb/>
my heart desires. For what have I deserved<lb/>
this cruel wrong? What honour can accrue<lb/>
if strong men mock a boy; a lonely youth<lb/>
if many should deceive?’ And as he spoke,<lb/>
I, also, wept to see their wickedness.<lb/>

“The impious gang made merry at our tears,<lb/>
and lashed the billows with their quickening oars.<lb/>
By Bacchus do I swear to you (and naught<lb/>
celestial is more potent) all the things<lb/>
I tell you are as true as they surpass<lb/>
the limit of belief. The ship stood still<lb/>
as if a dry dock held it in the sea.—<lb/>

“The wondering sailors laboured at the oars,<lb/>
and they unfurled the sails, in hopes to gain<lb/>
some headway, with redoubled energies;<lb/>
but twisting ivy tangled in the oars,<lb/>
and interlacing held them by its weight.<lb/>
And Bacchus in the midst of all stood crowned<lb/>
with chaplets of grape-leaves, and shook a lance<lb/>
covered with twisted fronds of leafy vines.<lb/>
Around him crouched the visionary forms<lb/>
of tigers, lynxes, and the mottled shapes<lb/>
of panthers.<lb/>

“Then the mariners leaped out,<lb/>
possessed by fear or madness. Medon first<lb/>
began to turn a swarthy hue, and fins<lb/>
grew outward from his flattened trunk,<lb/>
and with a curving spine his body bent.—<lb/>
then Lycabas to him, ‘What prodigy<lb/>
is this that I behold?’ Even as he spoke,<lb/>
his jaws were broadened and his nose was bent;<lb/>
his hardened skin was covered with bright scales.<lb/>
And Libys, as he tried to pull the oars,<lb/>
could see his own hands shrivel into fins;<lb/>
another of the crew began to grasp<lb/>
the twisted ropes, but even as he strove<lb/>
to lift his arms they fastened to his sides;—<lb/>
with bending body and a crooked back<lb/>
he plunged into the waves, and as he swam<lb/>
displayed a tail, as crescent as the moon.<lb/>

“Now here, now there, they flounce about the ship;<lb/>
they spray her decks with brine; they rise and sink;<lb/>
they rise again, and dive beneath the waves;<lb/>
they seem in sportive dance upon the main;<lb/>
out from their nostrils they spout sprays of brine;<lb/>
they toss their supple sides. And I alone,<lb/>
of twenty mariners that manned that ship,<lb/>
remained. A cold chill seized my limbs,—<lb/>
I was so frightened; but the gracious God<lb/>
now spake me fair, ‘Fear not and steer for Naxos.’<lb/>
And when we landed there I ministered<lb/>
on smoking altars Bacchanalian rites.”<lb/>


    
But Pentheus answered him: “A parlous tale,<lb/>
and we have listened to the dreary end,<lb/>
hoping our anger might consume its rage;—<lb/>
away with him! hence drag him, hurl him out,<lb/>
with dreadful torture, into Stygian night.”<lb/>

    
Quickly they seized and dragged Acoetes forth,<lb/>
and cast him in a dungeon triple-strong.<lb/>
And while they fixed the instruments of death,<lb/>
kindled the fires, and wrought the cruel irons,<lb/>
the legend says, though no one aided him,<lb/>
the chains were loosened and slipped off his arms;<lb/>
the doors flew open of their own accord.<lb/>

    
But Pentheus, long-persisting in his rage,<lb/>
not caring to command his men to go,<lb/>
himself went forth to Mount Cithaeron, where<lb/>
resound with singing and with shrilly note<lb/>
the votaries of Bacchus at their rites.<lb/>
As when with sounding brass the trumpeter<lb/>
alarms of war, the mettled charger neighs<lb/>
and scents the battle; so the clamored skies<lb/>
resounding with the dreadful outcries fret<lb/>
the wrath of Pentheus and his rage enflame.<lb/>

    
About the middle of the mount (with groves<lb/>
around its margin) was a treeless plain,<lb/>
where nothing might conceal. Here as he stood<lb/>
to view the sacred rites with impious eyes,<lb/>
his mother saw him first. She was so wrought<lb/>
with frenzy that she failed to know her son,<lb/>
and cast her thyrsus that it wounded him;<lb/>
and shouted, “Hi! come hither, Ho!<lb/>
Come hither my two sisters! a great boar<lb/>
hath strayed into our fields; come! see me strike<lb/>
and wound him!”<lb/>

    
As he fled from them in fright<lb/>
the raging multitude rushed after him;<lb/>
and, as they gathered round; in cowardice<lb/>
he cried for mercy and condemned himself,<lb/>
confessing he had sinned against a God.<lb/>
And as they wounded him he called his aunt;<lb/>
“Autonoe have mercy! Let the shade<lb/>
of sad Actaeon move thee to relent!”<lb/>
No pity moved her when she heard that name;<lb/>
in a wild frenzy she forgot her son.<lb/>
While Pentheus was imploring her, she tore<lb/>
his right arm out; her sister Ino wrenched<lb/>
the other from his trunk. He could not stretch<lb/>
his arms out to his mother, but he cried,<lb/>
“Behold me, mother!” When Agave saw,<lb/>
his bleeding limbs, torn, scattered on the ground,<lb/>
she howled, and tossed her head, and shook her hair<lb/>
that streamed upon the breeze; and when his head<lb/>
was wrenched out from his mangled corpse,<lb/>
she clutched it with her blood-smeared fingers, while<lb/>
she shouted, “Ho! companions! victory!<lb/>
The victory is ours!” So when the wind<lb/>
strips from a lofty tree its leaves, which touched<lb/>
by autumn's cold are loosely held, they fall<lb/>
not quicker than the wretch's bleeding limbs<lb/>
were torn asunder by their cursed hands.<lb/>

    
Now, frightened by this terrible event,<lb/>
the women of Ismenus celebrate<lb/>
the new Bacchantian rites; and they revere<lb/>
the sacred altars, heaped with frankincense.<lb/>
